<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;वीरराघवः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/vIra-rAghavaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;वीरराघवः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/vIra-rAghavaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>V1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/vIra-rAghavaH/v1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/vIra-rAghavaH/v1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(The Thiruvengadam Temple)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Vol.I&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.K.T. VIRARAGHAVACHARYA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Published By&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIRUMALA TIRUPATI DEVASTHANAMS, TIRUPATI.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1997&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI - VOL.I&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;By&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.K.T. VIRARAGHAVACHARYA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.T.D. Religious Publications Series No. 498&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;All Rights Reserved.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;First Edition&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;1953&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;1997&#xA;Second Edition: 1977&#xA;Re-Print&#xA;Copies: 2,000&#xA;Published By:&#xA;M.K.R. Vinayak, I.A.S.,&#xA;Executive Officer,&#xA;Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanams,&#xA;Tirupati - 517 507.&#xA;F.&#xA;&amp;quot;&#xA;ASWARA&#xA;CEN&#xA;L&#xA;ARY &amp;amp;&#xA;Pr&#xA;H ENTRE&#xA;Printed at:&#xA;Ac&#xA;= 1854&#xA;adsprint&#xA;T.Nagar,&#xA;Dat&#xA;Chennai - 17&#xA;FOREWORD&#xA;From time immemorial, Tirumala, the Holy Abode of Lord Venkateswara has been venerated as one of the most hallowed places The Vedas, ancient Tamil works of the Sangam period, the pasurams of Alwars and the sankirtanas of Tallapaka poets proclaim that the Lord of Seven Hills is the most blissful Archa form of Sriman Narayana Many great dynasties of the South, especially the Pallavas, the Cholas, the Pandyas, and the Vijayanagar emperors liberally patronised the Tirumala temple and the inscriptions found on the walls in the temples at Tirumala and Tirupati give more or less a vivid picture of the Temple and its administration from ninth century to eighteenth century&#xA;Sn 1 KT Viraraghavacharya&amp;rsquo;s History of Tirupati&amp;rsquo; which was first published in 1953 deals with the history of the temple, its layout and general administration After closely studying the available source materials like the inscriptions, ancient records and literary works, late Sn Viraraghavacharya has meticulously brought out a comprehenseve account of the temples of Tirumala and Tirupati The author who was basically an engineer by profession combines his scientific spirit of enquiry with his traditional theistic approach to present a lucid and fairly accurate History of Tirumala Temple&#xA;It is also our endeavour to bring out many more books on sanatana dharma, agamas, temple art and architecture, scriptural texts, besides illustrated books for our young readers Much emphasis is also laid on reprinting some of the popular publications which were not available for several years&#xA;EXECUTIVE OFFICER Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanams&#xA;Tirupati&#xA;INTRODUCTION.&#xA;The History of Tirupati by the late Dr. S. Krishnaswami Ayyangar, published by the TirumalaTirupati Devasthanams Committee, dealt with the setting in which the sacred Temple of Sri Venkateswara existed under the administration of Hindu, Muslim and British rulers. Such mention as was possible was made, therein, of the various costly endowments and gifts to the Temple. In the present work, the author deals, in addition, with the religious, social and economic aspects of the Temple, the evolu tion of the norm of worship and its effect on the worshippers.&#xA;The author traces the changes that have occurred in the norm of worship pari passu with the development of the metaphysical and philosophical ideas of the Upanishads as expounded by Sri Ramanuja. He also traces how the Tamil Prabandhams came to find a place in the ritual, even though worship in all Vaishnavite temples were exclusively governed by the appropriate Agamas. In separate chapters, he deals with how food-offerings came into existence as part of ritual, how endowments for the purpose were made, abused and attempted to be set right; the structural development from a one-room Koyil-Alwar to a huge Temple. the form of the Murti and the authorities therefor; and, when and how other idols were installed there. The temples of Sri Govindaraja and Sri&#xA;V&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Ramaswami and other shrines at Tirupati have been presented to the reader in detail together with the manner and reasons for their affiliation with the main Temple of Sri Venkateswara.&#xA;A separate chapter is devoted to a retrospect of the Temple administration from ancient times setting out lucidly and cogently the manner in which the Temple was managed originally by the Srikaryakarta appointed by the Pallava Kings; then by the Sabhaiyar constituted by the village assembly of Tiruchanur during the period of the later Pallava and Chola Kings; thereafter, by the Sthanattar appointed by the Yadavarayas; and how after the Yadavarayas, the Sthanattar divided themselves into two units, one for the secular and the other for the religious administration of the Temple until it passed into the hands of the Nawab of Arcot.&#xA;The author has devoted four separate chapters to the development and zenith of the Temple, the increase of food offerings and festivals and consolidation of the religious community during the Vijayanagar reign i.e., from the time of Saluva Narasimha to Sadasivaraya and the Aravidu Kings.&#xA;Separate chapters have also been devoted for the Agamas and the Alwars and Acharyas. The author&amp;rsquo;s presentation of the several forgotten portions of the Agamas is original and will dispel the general impression that temple worship is merely pantheistic.&#xA;The work is very original and the author&amp;rsquo;s deep study, of not only the inscriptions but also of the&#xA;vi&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;various sacred texts has resulted in giving a rational explanation of the various, and even minute, details of worship and endowment, the interconnections of which have been forgotten or rendered oblivious through the dim vista of distant centuries. I trust. this will be the first in the line of such thought-provoking works in respect of religious institutions and hope that managements of other such institutions will have all their historic records collected and presented by competent persons to the worshippers.&#xA;The author is eminently fitted to have undertaken this work and he has done it in a way worthy of the great traditions of his family and of his personality. It is his life mission and he has placed the world under great gratitude. At this age that he should have attempted this task and finished so well speaks volumes of his sincerity and devotion to this task.&#xA;MADRAS,&#xA;2-2-1953&#xA;} (Sd.) K. VENKATASWAMI NAIDU&#xA;PREFACE.&#xA;At an age past seventy, while I was compiling a table of latitudes and longitudes for various places in India, the Will of God slowly instilled into me the idea of writing this book on the famous temple of Tirupati or Tiruvengadam. While I was attempting to find out from ancient inscriptions the chronological methods of recording the dates and the changes in such methods from time to time, I referred to the Tirumalai-Tirupati Devasthanam Inscriptions published in six volumes. Going through the first of the volumes, the polished language and the deep piety in which some of them were couched evoked my interest in the higher aspect of the subject matter of the same. Particularly, the imprecation in Inscription No. 8 in Vol. I. caught my imagination. The devout Princess Samavai, in making endowments to the Silver Murti of Bhoga Srinivasa installed by her in 966 A.D., says Both the feet of those who protect this Dharman shall for ever be adornments to my head&amp;quot; and appeals to Sri Vaishnavas in particular to protect the charity. This is very inspiring relief to the other inscriptions relating to later foundations of charity in referring to which the donors invoked curses on those who disturb them saying &amp;ldquo;Those who disturb this charity shall be incurring the sin of having slaughtered a hundred cows in Kasi.&amp;rdquo; The inspiration produced by the love of mankind, the piety and humility of no less than a Princess of the time can only be felt. Such was the height of culture of our mothers and fathers in ancient India much of which has been lost but which, I dare say, could still be revived.&#xA;Thus inspired, in my quest I could not find any work dealing with the structural, religious, ritualistic, economic, administrative and social developments of the temple. I have, therefore, in my humble way traced in this book how from probably an open wooden structure as might be inferred from Kulasekhara Alwar&amp;rsquo;s songs, the temple has developed by stages of a single-room stone structure which was thereafter reinforced by a wall outside into its present size and magnificence, how Samavai installed the silver Murti&#xA;ix&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;of Bhoga Srinivasa with the resultant increase of worshippers; how the Vaikhanasa Agamic form of worship yielded itself to the present form from the time of Ramanuja; how social equality was put into practice and achieved to a great extent by the adoption of Nammalwar&amp;rsquo;s Tiruvoimoli, during religious gatherings and festivals, inculcating the Bhakti form of worship; how the taxation policy of the state was framed from time to time with a view to developing the temple and the cult it stood for with particular reference to the taxes that existed; how food offerings were introduced tackling successfully socio-economic problems; how endowments were conceived, founded and administered by various classes of people at various stages of development with various objects; how the administration passed by stages from state control to popular control, from the Madaptyadar appointed by the King to the Sabhaiyar or committee chosen by the King and later to the Sthanattar chosen by persons interested in the institution and the shape things took up to the present day through the Muslim and British rule.&#xA;In order to set forth the structural and ritualistic significance of the temple, I had to study the Agamas in their original as there is no work dealing with the subject in any of the popular languages. I have endeavoured to present in English, with as much detail as possible, the significance of the Agamic forms in a separate chapter. Likewise, I have devoted separate chapters for the Alwars and Acharyas and their influence on the Temple and on the spread of Srivaishnavism. In separate chapters, I have dealt with the historical connection of the various rulers of the land with this Temple.&#xA;I am grateful to the Lord who enabled me to complete a work which, from its nature and volume, would have been too formidable to attempt at any age, with decaying health and an eye-sight which has almost failed. In writing this work, the one thing I tangibly felt is that, if He wills nothing is impossible. He gave me the steadfastness, energy, eye-sight and the willing and affectionate co-operation of eminent men and good friends who never felt tired to give me suggestions and some of whom sat for hours with me doing tiresome work. I shall be failing in my duty if I do not specially&#xA;XPREFACE&#xA;thank Dr. B. S. Baliga, the Curator, and Sri M. C. Subramanya Iyer, the Assistant Curator, Madras Record Office, for the advice and suggestions they gave me from the time I began this work. I have also to thank the Hon&amp;rsquo;ble Justice Sri P. V. Rajamannar, the Hon&amp;rsquo;ble Justice P. Rajagopalan and Sri V. K. Narasimhan of The Hindu for reading through the first draft of the book and giving me encouraging advice. I feel highly grateful to Sri C. Rajagopalachariar, the Chief Minister of Madras, and Sri K. Venkataswami Naidu Garu, the Minister for Endowments, to the former for the Foreword and the latter for the Introduction to this book. The Members of the T. T. Devasthanam Committee with Sri Venkataswami Naidu Garu as the President have encouraged me by taking it as a Devasthanam publication. The present Board of Trustees and their Chairman, Sri V. S. Thyagaraja Mudaliar, have evinced keen interest in getting the work completed. Sri C. Anna Rao Garu, the very energetic and talented Executive Officer of the Devasthanams, has been continuously taking deep interest in the publication without which it could not have been completed so early. My thanks are also due to Sri Parthasarathy Bhattacharya for reading through the chapter on Temples and Agamas and giving useful suggestions. Sti D. T. Tatacharya, M.O.L., has not only been going through the proofs carefully and giving valuable advice but also has been seeing to my properly interpreting the Siddhantha aspect of temple worship. Sri T. R. Narasimhan, B.A the Superintendent of the T.T.D. Press has been largely responsible for having the work executed in the Press and for getting the blocks of the drawings and pictures carefully prepared. Sri P. Chenchuramiah, the Devasthanam Draftsman, prepared the important drawings and the tracings for making the blocks. My sincere thanks are due to them. Lastly, I have to say that no thanks can adequately express my deep debt to Sri M. Narasimhachariar, Assistant Public Prosecutor, Chittoor, for sparing continuously a portion of his valuable time for correcting my manuscripts, giving instructive suggestions and, in short, for dealing with this work as his own.&#xA;12-1-&amp;lsquo;53.&#xA;T. K. T. VIRARAGHAVACHARI&#xA;XI&#xA;List of Maps, Plans, Charts, etc.&#xA;Map of the Tirumala Hills&#xA;Map of Tirumala&#xA;Tiruvengadam temple as it stood in 1700 A.D.-Plan&#xA;Tirumala temple of Sri Venkateswara as it stood in&#xA;1250 A.D.-Plan&#xA;End elevation on the South of Mukkoti&#xA;Pradakshinam (Tirumalai Temple)-Plan&#xA;Plan of Sri Govindarajaswami Temple, Tirupati&#xA;Pages&#xA;Frontispiece&#xA;106&#xA;.. 113&#xA;.. 132&#xA;138&#xA;.&#xA;248&#xA;Elevation of Garbagriham on the South of Sri&#xA;Govindaraja Shrine Tirupati-Plan&#xA;250&#xA;Ekatala Ekavimana Navashat-Panchamurti Alyayam-Plan.. 314&#xA;Ekatala Ekamurti Alayam&#xA;320&#xA;Chart showing the first three Avaranas and the Devas and&#xA;Devapalas located therein&#xA;Garbha Gara Padavinyasam Sketch a&#xA;Garbha Gara Padavinyasam&#xA;b&#xA;99&#xA;Chart showing the Devas and Devapalas (Dwarapalas)&#xA;etc., in avaranas&#xA;..&#xA;323&#xA;..&#xA;325&#xA;327&#xA;348&#xA;CONTENTS.&#xA;CHAPTER I&#xA;Geography, Topography and Topology&#xA;Geography&#xA;Topography of the Tirumala Temple&#xA;Topology and Topolatry&#xA;CHAPTER II&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1-20&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;10&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;12&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Sanctity of the Vengadam Hills and the antiquity&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;of Tiruvengadamudaiyan&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sanctity of the Hill-Legends&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Legends as to why Sri Vishnu came over here&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Nammāļvār&amp;rsquo;s mystic assertion&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Archavataram as foretold in Sri Mahabharatam,..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Mausala Parvam (Chapter V)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Quotation from Nammālvār&amp;rsquo;s Tiruvoimoli (33)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;21-34&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;21&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;::&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;23&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;28&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;2225&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;31&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;333333&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;30&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER III&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;How the temple became popular and famous:&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(The rivalry between Buddhism, Jainism, Saivism and Vaishnavism; the defects in Saivism and the rise of modern Vaishnavism known as Sri Vaishnavism; the Alvärs as the protagonists of modern Vaishnavism are dealt with in this chapter)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;XV&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;35-55&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER IV&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;History of the Tiruvengadam Temples in Tirumala&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;and Tirupati&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Synopsis (of the information contained in the&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.T. Inscriptions)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;56-71&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER V&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruvengadam and Tiruchchekinur (or Tiruchchuk.com&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Early Account&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER VI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;72-81&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Temple of Sri Parasaresvara in Tiruchchaksour&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER VII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruvengadamudaiyan and the Tiruvengdaam Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The first discovery (of the Idol)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Account of the Temple found in Silappadhikaram Garbhagriham and Sayana mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tiruvilankoyil and the consecration of Manavaja-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;perumal (Bhoga Srinivasa)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;First Purattasi Tirunal&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Date of consecration of Maṇavā lapperumāļ&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Place of consecration&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The necessity for the installation of Maṇavāļapperumā] . Ornaments, or Tiruvabharaṇam of Maṇavāļapperumāļ&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Endowment corpus and the services&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tirukkodi Tirunal (annual festival)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER VIII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;PART (1)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Temple and its environs&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;82-89&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;::::&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;90-105&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;91&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;92&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;93&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;95&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;96&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;98&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;98&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;99&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;100&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;101&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Topography (including particulars of old landmarks)..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;::&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;103&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;196-112&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;106&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CONTENTS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;110&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;111&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Thousand pillared mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Hattiramji Mutt&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;PART (2)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tirumala Temple-Gopurams, Prakarams,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pradakshinams and structures therein&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;113-129&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The outer gopuram&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;113&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Sampangi Pradakshinam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;116&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Ranga Mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;117&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pūla Bhāvi&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tirumalarayan and Unjal mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Dhvajastambha mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Saluva Narasimha&amp;rsquo;s four mantapams in Sampangi&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;118&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;119&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;120&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pradakshinam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Inner Gopuram&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Vimana Pradakshinam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Anga Pradakshinam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;122&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;122&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;124&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;125&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Varadarajaswami Shrine&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Corridor (south)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kalyāņa mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;125&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;126&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;126&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;West Corridor&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;127&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;North Corridor&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s Shrine&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Narasimhaswami Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;128&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;128&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;129&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;PART (3)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tirumala Temple-Sanctum&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Garbhagriham and Mukhamantapam, a double&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;structure (due to renovation)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Sanctum sanctorum-a double structure&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Motive for renovation&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Renovation work of the Garbhagriham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;xvii&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;130-171&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;132&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;134&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;136&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;138&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;North side of the pradakshinam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;First Pradakshinam (Mukkoți Pradakshinam) soon&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;140&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;closed&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;141&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The closure of the Mukkoți Pradakshinam and the&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;formation of the Rāmar-Medai&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;142&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The outer faces of the walls of the First Pradakshinam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(Vimana pradakshinam)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;146&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Why the walls of the Vimana Pradakshinam were left&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;bare without inscriptions for more than a century The Spell broken after 1360 A D&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;148&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;151&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Snapana Mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tirumamani Mantapam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;152&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;154&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Narasimhaswami Shrine&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;157&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s shrine in Tirumala&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;158&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s shrine in Mōkälla metţu hill&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;158&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s shrine in Tirupati&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;159&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Relevant considerations for fixing the date of construction&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;of Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s Shrine&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;162&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRI VARAHASWAMI TEMPLE IN TIRUMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;167&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1957&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;PART (4)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Murti Swarupam of Sri Venkatesa&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;172-204&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Murti Svarupam of Sri Venkatesvara&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;172&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Divine origin of Sri Venkatesvara Mürti&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;173&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Divine sanction for Idol Worship&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;174&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Venkatesvara&amp;rsquo;s Image Svayam Vyakta Murti&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;175&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Murti not a man-made one&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;176&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Types of Dhruva Murtis prescribed in the agamas&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;177&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Venkatesvara&amp;rsquo;s Murti form does not conform to&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;any of those&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;180&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;His Archavatara has direct connection with the avatars of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Rama and Sri Krishna&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;182&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;xviii&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CONTENTS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;BHOGA SRINIVASA, THE KAUTUKA BERAM&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;185&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kautuka Beram&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;187&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Ugra Srinivasa&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;187&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Koluvu Srinivasa&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;187&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Malayappan (Utsava Murti) and his consorts&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;188&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sudarsana&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Raghunatha and Sri Krishna&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;THE TEMPLE ITS PECULIARITIES&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The other Berams (and food offerings)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Some crude and incorrect notions&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;190&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;::::&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;190&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;194&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;196&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;197&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER IX&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Nityarchana (or Daily Worship) in the Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;205&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Benefits conferred by Shat Kala Pujas&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;207&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Routine of Nityarchana&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;209&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Visvarupa Seva&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;210&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tōmala Seva or the Main Puja for the day&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;212&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Puja kramam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;214&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Mantrasanam, Snanāsanam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;214&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Alankarasanam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;216&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Koluvu or Durbar&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;217&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Srinivasa Sahasranamarchana&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;218&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Bhojyasanam (Naivedyam)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;219&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Homam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;220&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;**&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Yatrasanam-Bali offerings&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;220&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sattumurai&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;221&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Dharma Darsanam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;222&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Apărahna Puja&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;223&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Night Puja&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Night Dharma Darsanam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Ardhajama puja&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;223&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;223&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;223&#xA;xix&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Paryankasanam&#xA;Thursday Pulangi Seva&#xA;Friday Tirumanjanam and Pulugukkappu&#xA;Turmeric paste&#xA;Gambūra or Pachchai karpūram&#xA;Pages.&#xA;223&#xA;::&#xA;224&#xA;225&#xA;-227&#xA;228&#xA;Kasturi (Mrga nābhi)&#xA;229&#xA;Civet oil and Rose water&#xA;229&#xA;Food Offerings&#xA;230&#xA;Tirumanjana Tirtham (Friday abhishekam water)&#xA;231&#xA;Sripădarēnu&#xA;231&#xA;Observation&#xA;232&#xA;NOTE ON THE SPICES AND OTHER ARTICLES&#xA;USED IN THE PUJA PATRAMS, OR VESSELS&amp;hellip;&#xA;233&#xA;CHAPTER X&#xA;Tirupati and Sri Govindaraja&amp;rsquo;s Temple&#xA;243-257&#xA;The Founding of Tirupati&#xA;244&#xA;The Building of Sri Govindaraja&amp;rsquo;s Shrine&#xA;247&#xA;Date of Installation of Sri Govindaraja&#xA;250&#xA;Dvårapālas&#xA;252&#xA;Dhvajasthambham (old)&#xA;252&#xA;The Big Gopuram&#xA;Hanuman Shrine&#xA;252&#xA;253&#xA;Vasanta mantapam&#xA;253&#xA;Mantapam in front of temple&#xA;Nirāļi mantapam&#xA;Govinda Pushkarini (Krishnarayan kōnēri)&#xA;Chitrakuta mantapam&#xA;Lakshmidevi mantapam&#xA;Financial status of Sri Govindaraja&amp;rsquo;s temple&#xA;XX&#xA;253&#xA;253&#xA;254&#xA;254&#xA;254&#xA;..&#xA;255CONTENTS&#xA;CHAPTER XI&#xA;Pages&#xA;Shrines attached to Sri Govindaraja&amp;rsquo;s Temple and other&#xA;Temples&#xA;258-287&#xA;Andal Shrine&#xA;258&#xA;Nammålvar Shrine&#xA;259&#xA;Kulasekhara älvar&amp;rsquo;s shrine&#xA;260&#xA;Periya älvar&amp;rsquo;s shrine&#xA;260&#xA;Tirumangai älvai&amp;rsquo;s shrine&#xA;261&#xA;Madhura Kavi älvar&amp;rsquo;s shrine&#xA;262&#xA;Shrines for Alvārs not the work of Sri Ramanuja&#xA;263&#xA;Tirumalai Nambi Shrine&#xA;263&#xA;Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s Shrine (Tirupati)&#xA;264&#xA;Kurattalvar&amp;rsquo;s Shrine&#xA;264&#xA;Vira Narasinga Perumal Temple&#xA;266&#xA;Salai Nachchiyar Temple&#xA;266&#xA;Sri Narasimhasvāmi Temple (Alipırı)&#xA;267&#xA;Periya Raghunatha&amp;rsquo;s (Sri Rama&amp;rsquo;s) Temple&#xA;267&#xA;Another Sri Raghunatha&#xA;269&#xA;Yet another Sri Raghunatha&#xA;269&#xA;Hanuman Shrine (Tirupati Govindaraja&amp;rsquo;s)&#xA;270&#xA;Govinda Krishna Shrine&#xA;271&#xA;Tiruvenkata Gopala Krishna Shrine&#xA;271&#xA;Gopala Krishna&amp;rsquo;s Temple&#xA;272&#xA;Lakshmi Narayann Perumal&#xA;Achyuta Perumal Temple&#xA;272&#xA;273&#xA;Näthamuni Temple&#xA;Tirukkachchinambi Shrine&#xA;273&#xA;273&#xA;Varadaraja Perumal&#xA;Nammalvar Temples (Alvar Tirtham Nammalvar)&#xA;Ramanujakütam Nammalvar&#xA;Tirupati and its suburbs&#xA;ALVAR TIRTHAM, TIRUPATI&#xA;Sri Kapileswara Swami Temple at Alvar Tirtham&#xA;XXI&#xA;274&#xA;274&#xA;277&#xA;278&#xA;279&#xA;284&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;CHAPTER XII&#xA;Pages.&#xA;288-358&#xA;Temples and the Agamas&#xA;SECTION I&#xA;Classification of temples according to their Origin&#xA;288&#xA;Limitations to Agama rules&#xA;289&#xA;Vaikhanasa and Pancharatra Agamas&#xA;289&#xA;FUNDAMENTALS OF TEMPLE WORSHIP&#xA;(POSTULATES) ACCEPTED IN TEMPLE CONSTRUCTION AND WORSHIP&#xA;Vyuha Avatars and Vyuha Lōkas (Vaishnavandam) The Vyüha Theory according to Vaikhanasas The Pancharatra theory of the Vyūhas Cosmogony according to Vishnu Puranam The order of Brahma Srishti&#xA;SECTION II.&#xA;Different types of Agama Temples&#xA;::::::&#xA;290&#xA;294&#xA;296&#xA;299&#xA;304&#xA;306&#xA;310&#xA;Classification of the types of Temples:-&#xA;(a) The Vertical type, one to twelve tiers&#xA;310&#xA;(b) Horizontal type-Trimurti and Dvi Murti&#xA;Temples&amp;ndash;one floor type&#xA;311&#xA;(c) The Eka Murti temple, one to seven āvaranams&#xA;311&#xA;Nava-Shat-Pancha Murti ālayam&#xA;312&#xA;Tritala Nava Murti alayam&#xA;313&#xA;Dvitala alayam&#xA;314&#xA;Dvitala Pancha murti alayam&#xA;314&#xA;Eka tala Eka Vimana Nava Shat Panhca Murti alayam&#xA;314&#xA;Vertical type-The Dvadasa tala alayam&#xA;The Dvi and Trimurti alayams on ground floor The Tri Murti alayam&#xA;:::&#xA;316&#xA;318&#xA;318&#xA;xxii&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;SECTION III.&#xA;The Ekatala Eka murti alayam&#xA;Points of difference between the Ekatala Ekamurti alayam and the Ekatala Eka Vimana Nava-ShatPancha murti alayam&#xA;SECTION IV.&#xA;Garbhagriham, Vimanam and Parivara Devatas&#xA;Garbhāgara Pada Vinyasam&#xA;The Dhruva Murti (Standing Sitting and Reposing) postures; also Yoga, Rhoga, Vira and Abhicharika&#xA;states&#xA;Distinguishing features of the Yoga, Bhoga. Vira and Abhicharika forms of the Uttama, Madhyama and Adhama classes&#xA;Parivara Devas within the Garbhagriham, the Vimanam and the first avaranams including Brahma, Sankara, Markandeya, Bhrigu, the Dvara devas, Dvarapalas, Vimanapalas, the Anapayins&#xA;SECTION V.&#xA;The Devas in the seven avaranams&#xA;Mahat pitham&#xA;Ganas (Uttama. Madhyama and Adhama)&#xA;Pages.&#xA;320&#xA;322&#xA;325&#xA;325&#xA;328&#xA;330&#xA;337&#xA;345&#xA;350&#xA;350&#xA;SECTION VI.&#xA;Main Purpose of Temple worship-Universal Co-operation&#xA;351&#xA;CHAPTER XIII.&#xA;Retrospect&#xA;Original simplicity&#xA;Changes after the influx of the Southern Tamils&#xA;Bhakti form of worship&#xA;xxiii&#xA;359-376&#xA;360&#xA;361&#xA;363&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;The Vijayanagar Period&#xA;THE ADMINISTRATIVE MACHINERY&#xA;The Sthanattår&#xA;Mullai Tiruvenkata Jiyar&#xA;CHAPTER XIV.&#xA;Expansion of Sri Vaishnava Activities&#xA;Sthanattar and Sthānikās&#xA;Separation of secular administration from religious&#xA;propaganda&#xA;How the scheme worked&#xA;Local support and Royal benefactions&#xA;Appendix I-Reprint of an article which appeared in the&#xA;Asi tic quarterly of 1831 A.D.&#xA;Pages.&#xA;366&#xA;368&#xA;. 370&#xA;375&#xA;377-386&#xA;377&#xA;378&#xA;379&#xA;382&#xA;1&#xA;Appendix II-The Four ancient inscriptions which were&#xA;originally on the Koyil alvãr walls&#xA;Appendix III-Extract from Silappadhikaram&#xA;20&#xA;10&#xA;26&#xA;Appendix IV-Note on the probable date of birth of&#xA;Vijayāditya Bānaraya&#xA;28&#xA;28&#xA;Appendix V-English translation of an extract from&#xA;Mausala parva (Chapter V) of Sri Mahabharata&#xA;xxiv&#xA;29&#xA;WILE&#xA;TAL&#xA;On&#xA;STOMACHALAN LITH.RF 115&#xA;SESENCRALLANT RESERVED FOREM&#xA;281&#xA;MAP&#xA;OF THE&#xA;TIRUMALAI HILLS&#xA;2&#xA;www&#xA;W&#xA;WOW!&#xA;MARKETIN&#xA;AL&#xA;P&#xA;MANA&#xA;MARY PALAGAY&#xA;DIN&#xA;3NTES PRAGE SITES&#xA;of MS &amp;amp; SPALAND&#xA;FOOT PAINS LANY TRICKS scav&#xA;PEREST BOUNDARY N TEMPLES&#xA;THE BRAK&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;(The Tirumala, Tirupati Temples)&#xA;CHAPTER I&#xA;TIRUMALA, TIRUPATI AND TIRUCHANUR.&#xA;Geography, Topography and Topology.&#xA;TIRUMALA has always been known by its ancient name Vengadam (Tiruvengadam); and the Hill on which the Temple stands was known as the Vengadam Hills. Tirupati owes its importance to having been, from the date of its founding, a necessary adjunct to Tirumala. Sri Ramanuja is said to have done this about the beginning of the twelfth century A.D. But the precise date cannot now be ascertained directly with any degree of accuracy. There was obviously a very petty village with a small shrine of Sri Parthasarathy Swami even before Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s advent. There is, however, neither inscriptional evidence nor tradition about this. Tiruchanur, known in ancient days as Tiruchchokinur and Tiruchchukanur, is more ancient than Tirupati, although it cannot claim the same antiquity as Vengadam. Chandragiri is another place about 7 miles West of Tirupati and about 5 miles South of the Hill; and the road from Chandragiri affords a second access to the Tirumala Temple.&#xA;A glance at the map usually attached to the 1 M. &amp;amp; S.M. Railway guide will show that a Metre gauge chord line from Katpadi junction to Renigunta junction and thence to the Gudur junction connects Tirupati with the Broad gauge S.W., N.W. and N.E. lines of that railway system, all converging towards Madras. To follow the modern practice of locating places, we may state that&#xA;Tirumala is in Lat.&#xA;Tirupati is in Lat.&#xA;13° 41&amp;rsquo; N&#xA;Long. 79°-21&amp;rsquo; E.&#xA;13°-38&amp;rsquo; N&#xA;Long. 79°-25&amp;rsquo; E.&#xA;Long. 79°-27&amp;rsquo; E.&#xA;Long. 79°-19&amp;rsquo; E.&#xA;Tiruchchukanur in Lat. 13-36&amp;rsquo;&#xA;Chandragiri is in Lat. 13°-35&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>V2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/vIra-rAghavaH/v2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/vIra-rAghavaH/v2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(THE THIRUVENGADAM TEMPLES)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;BY&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.K.T. VIRARAGHAVA CHARYA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Q22:38.4416.7&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;-роз&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;71855&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;00&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Published by&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIRUMALA TIRUPATI DEVASTHANAMS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Vol.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;II&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(The Thiruvengadam Temples)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Vol.II&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.K.T. VIRARAGHAVACHARYA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIRUMAL&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;THANAMS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;DEVASTH&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;भीनिवासी विजयते&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Published By&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIRUMALA TIRUPATI DEVASTHANAMS, TIRUPATI.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;2003&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI - VOL.II&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;By&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.K.T. VIRARAGHAVACHARYA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;T.T.D. Religious Publications Series No. 499&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;All Rights Reserved.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;བད་&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;First Edition&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;1954&#xA;Second Edition : 1982&#xA;Re-Print&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;2003&#xA;SRI VENKATESWARA! CLITPAL LIBRAMY X&#xA;RESEARCH CENTRE&#xA;ALD No. 7.1885&#xA;Copies:2,000&#xA;Date.&#xA;TIRUPATI&#xA;Published By:&#xA;Ajay Kallam, I.A.S&#xA;Executive Officer,&#xA;Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanams,&#xA;Tirupati - 517 507.&#xA;Printed at:&#xA;adsprint:&#xA;T. Nagar, Chennai - 17.&#xA;FOREWORD&#xA;The period from the fifteenth century to the ninteenth century, till the entry of the East India Company was a tumultous period in the History of South India. There were bitter wars waged by one dynasty against the another. It was also the period when the Muslim rulers and the Mahrattas entered the fray to get a firm foothold in this part beyond the Vindhyas and take maximum advantage from the internecine wars. We also find the arrival of the foreign companies ostensibly for trade and their gradual involvement in the political intrigues of the country which tilted the balance of power in their favour.&#xA;The period, however witnessed great Hindu revival under the dynamic rule of the Vijayanagar kings. The rulers of the Sangama, Saluva, Thuluva, and Aravidu dynasties of this empire considered Lord Venkateswara as their tutelary deity and the liberal grants and endowments, they made are a measure of their piety to Lord Srinivasa. The temple of Tirumala - Hill reached its zenith of glory during the period of the illustrious king Krishnadevaraya, the scion of the Thuluva dynasty. He not only gave fabulous gifts to Thiruvengadamudaiyan but also undertook major renovation to the temple and personally supervised its dayto-day administration.&#xA;In this volume, the author deals with the History of Tirupati from the last phase of the Sangama dynasty to the early years of the 19th century. The History of the recitation of Alvars&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;Divya prabandham&amp;rsquo; also finds a place in this book. The Alvars&amp;rsquo; concept of the Archa form of Sri Venkateswara is also dealt with at length in this volume.&#xA;EXECUTIVE OFFICER Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanams&#xA;Tirupati&#xA;T.T.D. Religious Publications Series No.: 499&#xA;Price: Rs. Rs. 40/-&#xA;Venkatadri samam sthānam&#xA;brahmāṇḍe nästi kincana&#xA;Venkatesa samo devo&#xA;na bhūto na bhaviṣyati II&#xA;&amp;ldquo;There is no place equal to Venkatadri in the whole universe. A god equal to Venkatesa, there never has&#xA;been and there never will be&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Published by the Executive Officer, T.T. Devasthanams, Tirupati and Printed at Ads Printers, T.Nagar, Chennai&#xA;on behalf of T.T.D.&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;(TO THE FIRST EDITION)&#xA;This volume deals with the history of the temple from about the closing years of the Sangama dynasty of the Vijayanagar Empire, say from 1450 A.D. to the early years of the nineteenth century when the English East India Company at Fort St. George, Madras, after dispossessing the Nawab of Arcot in 1801 A.D., assumed direct management of the temple and carried out a systematic investigation into its affairs till about 1830 A.D. It is only for the period from 1450 to 1638 A.D., that sufficient materials of historic value are available from the inscriptions on the walls of the temple. Although the last king of the Vijayanagar Empire continued to retain the title till 1665 A.D., the Carnatic country and our temple passed into the hands of Mir Jumla, former commander of the Golkonda forces, in July 1656 as his personal Jagir granted by the Moghul Emperor Shah Jehan. The temple continued since then to be under the control of the Nawab of the Carnatic till 1801 A.D., except for a short period in 1758-59 as the French captured the temple in October 1758.&#xA;Materials for writing the history during the period of Muslim overlordship have not been obtained from inscriptions but from contemporary records of the English and the Dutch Factories in India and the East which came into existence in the early years of the seventeenth century. Foster&amp;rsquo;s Book on English Factories in India throws some indirect light on our temple affairs also. After the building of Fort St.&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;George in Madras in 1641 our position improves. The Diary and consultations Book, Military and country correspondence and Reports of secret committees. throw more light on the political game in which our temple became a pawn.&#xA;The Marattas entered the South as the comrades of the Bijapur muslim king in his invasions and established a principality in Tanjore. Sivaji a little later came in as the ally of the Golkonda King in 1677. The net result of the ambitions of the Marattas was a treaty with the Moghul Emperor which secured for them one fourth of the revenues technically known as the chauth. For the annual assessment of the chauth amount, all the accounts and connected records, including land registers, came to be maintained in the Modi script of the Maratta language. This is of interest to us because all the important old records of our temple, whether in the Devasthanam office or in the Madras Records office, are in that language and script. Until they are translated into English or Telugu an authentic history of the temple during the Muslim and the East India Company rule could not be written. Chapter XXII deals with this period. There is not much to learn therein about the internal affairs of the temple, its festivals, the changes in religious practices and so on. All that we learn is that for the first time in its history the temple and its properties were farmed out annually by bid to a renter who managed to secure all votive offerings into his hands and pay the Nawab the bid amount. He seems to have devised the method of collecting the bid amount by such exactions as-poll tax, kanukas, varttanas,&#xA;vi&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;ārjitams, etc. These have continued to be levied as a permanent source of income. We are loath to believe that Hindu pilgrims who are deeply religious would not voluntarily give large donations for charitable purposes connected with temple administration without exactions made.&#xA;Chapters XV to XXI register only such voluntary offerings and endowments from the days of Saluva Narasimhadeva Udaiyar to the end of the Vijayanagar Empire in 1665 A.D. Saluva Narasimha laid the foundation for the fame and popularity of the temple. It assumed superb proportions during the days of Sri Krishnadevaraya, Achyutaraya and Sadasivaraya. The decline commenced with the battle of Talikota in 1565. But even during the dacadent period the services in the temple retained their grandeur, those connected with Sri Ramanuja in particular.&#xA;One hundred and sixty eight inscriptions relate to the period of Saluya Narasimha and his son Immaḍi Narasimha (1445-1505 A.D.). Out of these only 136 are complete ones useful for writing a history. The others are either incomplete, fragmentary or undatable. The period of Sri Krishnadevaraya and his elder brother (1505 to 1530 )gets two hundred and twenty nine inscriptions, out of which only 165 are complete ones. Achyutaraya&amp;rsquo;s period (1530 to 1542) has two hundred and fifty one inscriptions, but only 176 are complete ones. Sadasivaraya&amp;rsquo;s period has one hundred and seventy six inscriptions, but only 134 are complete ones. It will be seen that there are too many fragmentary and incomplete inscriptions. They testify to our national defect of not realising the historical value&#xA;vii&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;of inscriptions. A workman would mercilessly break to pieces a valuable inscription if only he could get one broken piece to fit into his new masonry.&#xA;The Aravidu kings of the Vijayanagar Empire ruled after the battle of Talikota for ninety years from 1575 to 1665 A.D. Although there are one hundred and eighty five inscriptions classed by the epigraphist as relating to this period, only thirty three complete ones can be used for historical purposes. The remaining 152 inscriptions are either fragmentary, incomplete or undatable. Very many of these may well be ascribed to any period of our history.&#xA;Throughout the Vijayanagar period the management of the temple was in the hands of the Sthanattar who as we know (Chap. XIII, p. 374) formed a selfconstituted autonomous body of twelve members. After 1600 A.D. their strength got reduced to six. They were completely extinguished and along with them Tamil as the language of the temple, presumably when the temple passed into the hands of the Golkonda Muslims about 1656 A.D. An inscription of the year 1684 A.D. confirms their disappearance and the appearance of a body of Telugu Sthānālavāru of four members who however had not the power to receive endowments. There is in fact no Tamil inscription after 1638 A.D.&#xA;All the endowments made during the long period of rule of the Saluva and the Vijayanagar kings are marked by three distinct features. They are in a sense different from the endowments made during the Pallava, the Chola and the Pandyan sovereignty. The&#xA;viiiPREFACE&#xA;latter devoted more attention to the burning of perpetual lights or Nandavilakku while the provision for food offering was limited to the requirements of the temple establishment in ordinary days and for any additional members taking part in festival celebrations. The feeding of the pilgrims who turned up on such occasions was catered to by private charities. The Saluva period made a distinct departure. It was recognised that temple worship provided a course of self-discipline and attuned the body and the mind of the worshippers for concentrated meditation. It was also recognised that managers of temples have a responsibility for providing amenities for the accommodation and feeding of the devotees. The Taittiriopanishad starts with statement that food is Brahmam. Therefore, in Sri Vaishnava temples consecrated water or Tirtham and consecrated food or Prasadam were made essential features of temple worship. The herbs used for the cold infusion of the Tirtham have health giving and curative properties. The menu for Prasadāms has a wholesome body building value. Annadanam or free distribution of food in the name of God worshipped in a temple engenders in the donor the spirit of self-surrender or non-egotism. In a place like Tirumala which pilgrims approach after trekking over long distances and after negotiating on foot with an empty stomach several steep ascents and descents of the hill, wholesome tirtham and prasadam have great physical and psychic value. Endowments therefore became phenominally numerous. The festivals and calender days with which many of the endowments were associated appealed to the higher aesthetic sense of the pilgrims. The recitation of the Vedas and the&#xA;ix&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Tamil Prabandhams and the discourses which were conducted in the temple as well as in the homes and mutts of the religious preceptors served to awaken the desire for spiritual education. Thus tirtham and Prasadam, festivals and calender days, the recitation of the Vedas by Brahmins and of the Prabandhams by the Brahmin and the non-Brahmin Srivaishnavas on a footing of equality formed the three distinguishing features of the endowments made during the Vijayanagar period. Abuses did creep in the administration of these, but endeavours were being made from time to time for finding suitable remedies.&#xA;In this volume these aspects have been dealt with at length. The names of the donors, who came from all classes and all castes, have been given in annexures to the chapters wherein the purpose and nature of the endowments have also been described. They illustrate how in India those who amassed wealth in the material field applied their surplus wealth to encourage the activities of the spiritual workers who for that very purpose have to work in material poverty.&#xA;The recitation of the Prabandhams of the Alvārs has taken a deep root in the liturgy of Sri Vaishnava temples, although the Agamās did not contemplate it The Prabandhams are also of special importance to the Tirumalai Temple as they alone bear the most authentic testimony for the Vishnu swarupam of Sri Venka tesvara. In Chapter XXIII, the history of the &amp;lsquo;recitatior of the Prabandhams in the Tirumalai-Tirupati Temples is given in Sec. 2. In Sec. 3 the authorities from the alvārs&amp;rsquo; songs have been profusely quoted for proving beyond doubt that even in days which the alvar&#xA;X&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;speak of as ancient Sri Venkatesvara has been considered to be Sriman Narayana, Self-Manifest as an Image for the furtherance of the archa form of worship.&#xA;The numbering of the chapters and pages of this volume are in continuation of those of Vol. I.&#xA;As there are a few more chapters of collective interest to print, the Index for Volumes II and III together will, soon be published if Sri Venkatesvara so wills and grants me a modicum of eye-sight and health.&#xA;I am thankful to Sri C. Anna Rao Garu, Executive Officer and to the staff of the T.T.D. Press, for their kind co-operation and interest in bringing out this volume.&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;23&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;xi&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;THE AUTHOR&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Saluva Narasimha.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CONTENTS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XV&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;389-405&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Saluva Narasimha and Kandaḍai Rāmānuja Ayyangar 389-391&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Periya Raghunatha&amp;rsquo;s Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Yugadi and Dīpāvali&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Adhyayanōtsavam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;392&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;392&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;392&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pavitrōtsavam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;393&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pāḍiya Veṭṭai&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;393&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kōdai Tirunal and Tiruppalli-ödam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;394&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Food offerings increase&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;394&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruvandu Eluttiḍal, or writing the New Year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Accounts&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;396&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruvenkata Mahatmyam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;397&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pulugukkāppu Murai&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;398&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Van Sathakōpan Matham (Ahobila Mutt) Endowments and offerings mainly Kāmyārtha&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;398&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;400&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Names of villages endowed during Saluva Narasimha&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;. period&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;402&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XVI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kandadai Ramanuja Ayyangar and Saluva Narasimha&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;406-419&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kandadai Ramanuja Ayyangar&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;408&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kandadai Ramanuja took full advantage of his influence The attitude of other donors&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;410&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;413&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Kandaḍai Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s activities after the death of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Säluva Narasimha&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;416&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Note on the disposal of the donor&amp;rsquo;s share of prasadams&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;by members of the Saluva family&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;418&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;XIII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XVII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Period from about 1492 to 1511 A.D. (Immadi&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Narasimharaya and Vira Narasimha Maharaya)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;420-426&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Acharyapurushas&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XVIII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;425&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Nandavanams and Sattāda Srivaishnavas ignored&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Tiruvengadam Temple and Sri Virapratapa Vira&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Krishnadeva Maharaya (1509 to 1530 A.D.)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Krishnadevaraya&amp;rsquo;s Religious Beliefs&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Krishnadevaraya&amp;rsquo;s attitude towards the Sthanattār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temple structures received no attention&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Krishnadevaraya&amp;rsquo;s gifts to Tiruvenkatanatha&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;427-466&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;429&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;436&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;439&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;440&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;440&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Endowments and gifts by the generals and officers of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Krishnadeva and others&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;444&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Jiyars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;453&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Van Sathakopan Matham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;456&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Vyasaraya Matham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;458&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Ekākis&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;460&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Scholars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Yagna Narayana Bhattar Doddaiyyangar Appai Udaiyavarkoyil Anna&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Merchants&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XIX&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;461&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;461&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;462&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;463&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;463&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Achyutaraya Maharaya and the Tirumalai Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Appointment of Muddu Kuppayi for doing dancing&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;467-505&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;service in the temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;470&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Alvar Tīrtham, construction of cutstone steps and&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sandhyavandana mantapams&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;474&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;XIV&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CONTENTS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Achyutaraya performed Srinivasa Sahasranāmāärchana&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;with his own hands&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Lakshmidevi Mahotsavam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Achyuta Perumal and Achyutarayapuram Achyutarayar Kōnēri in Tirumala&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Probable date of construction of Achyutaraya Kōnēri&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Palace influence&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Transfer by sale in perpetuity of donor&amp;rsquo;s share of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;prasadams made by Saluva Timmarasa to Tallapakkam Tirumalai Ayyangar&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Prasadams-article of trade&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temple worship, Acharya purushãs and other ächäryäs Agreement among cloth merchants and lessees&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Annexure to Chapter XIX&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Other donors-Adaippan Baiyyappa Nayakar, Periya Timmappan and Chinna Ramappan, Dalavay Timmarasayyar, Lepakshi Virapparungal, Angaraja Nagappayyar, Salakayyadeva Singaraja&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;477&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;479&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;482&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;483&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;484&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;485&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;489&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;496&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;499&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;502&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;506-512&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;506&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Villages endowed in Krishnadeva&amp;rsquo;s and in Achyutaraya&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;reign compared&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;508&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XX&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sadasivaraya Maharaya&amp;rsquo;s Period&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;513-546&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Sthanattar and the succession dispute&amp;ndash;The Salaka-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;raja and the Aravidu family as donors compared Prasadam Lessees-Prasadakkarar Mahamedangal&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;513&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;522&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;List of Prasadakkārar&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;522&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temple palanquin and portion of daily prasadams gifted&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;away to Tiruvenkata Manickam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;524&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;New Minor temples and shrines&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;525&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;New Festivals&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;528&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tabular statements of endowments made from time to&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;time (explained)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;534&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;XV&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Statement I&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;538&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Statement II-(a)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;540&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Statement II-(b)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;542&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Income and Expenditure from Endowments discussed..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;545&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Annexure to Chapter XX-Donors and their endowments&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;during Sadasiva Maharaya&amp;rsquo;s period&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Endowments by military and other officers&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;547-576&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;553&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Endowments by persons connected with temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;557&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Archakas or Nambimars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;558&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Jiyars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Acharyapurushas&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;558&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;559&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tallapakkam Tirumalai Ayyangar, Tallapakkam Tiru-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;vengada Ayyangar:&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;562&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruninra-ur-udaiyars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Emperumānaḍiyars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;566&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;567&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temple door-keepers (koyilaḍis).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Viņņappam seyvar; Lessees of Temple Prasadams&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(Prasadakkara Mahamedangal) and Temple astrologers Endowments by persons unconnected with the temple .. Classified list of donors and their endowments..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XXI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;567&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;568&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;571&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;574&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Aravidu Emperors of Vijayanagar and the Tiru-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;vengadam Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;577-608&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Venkatapatideva Maharaya (Venkata I)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Vira Rama Ravudēva Maharaya (Rama IV)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Virapratapa Sri Rangarayadeva Maharaya&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(Ranga VI)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;587&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;592&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;599&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XXII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Post-Vijayanagar Period&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The temple passes into the hands of the Golkonda&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Muslim King&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;xvi&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;609-650&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;609&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CONTENTS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Cessation of Endowments explained&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Maratta invasion in 1677 aggravated the situation Sivaji Maharaja-His antecedents and aims in life Sivaji&amp;rsquo;s conquest of the Carnatic and premature death&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;in 1680&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Aurangazeb&amp;rsquo;s conquest of the Deccan down to&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Trichinopoly&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Economic chaos in the Carnatic country&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;A solitary inscription in Telugu in 1684 by a Maratta&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;officer&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;610&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;611&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;612&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;615&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;616&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;617&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;618&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Surmise as to the disappearance of most of the endowed&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;lands&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;621&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The office of the Kanungōs&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;621&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temple lands how treated&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;623&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;How the protracted Moghul-Maratta War ravaged and&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;impoverished the country&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;623&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sadet-ulla-khan and Toḍar Mullji&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;625&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The sudden incursion of the Marattas in 1740 A.D.;&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Dost Ali killed in Damalcheruvu battle&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;626&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Bāji Rao&amp;rsquo;s mother and wife worship Sri Venkatesvara..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;628&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Subsequent political events&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;629&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Duplix and Clive&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;630-650&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tirumalai Temple income goes to further succour&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Robert Clive&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;633&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The motive for resumption of temple lands and the&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;grant of tasdik allowances&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;643&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Minor Temples&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;648&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;CHAPTER XXIII&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Alvars&amp;rsquo; Prabandhams and the Tirumalai Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;651-713&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SECTION I&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temples and the Prabandhams of the Alvars ..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Portions of the Prabandham culled out for daily&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;recitation, called Nityānusandhänam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;652&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;653&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;xvii&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Prabandham of the Alvars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Recitation of the Tiruvaymoli is attributed to Sri&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Näthamuni&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The superiority of Tiruvaymoli over the other three works of Sri Nammalvar and the works of all the other Alvars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;655&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;656&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;659&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Commentaries on the Tiruvaymoļi&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;663&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The other three thousand verses of the Prabandham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;667&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Other works comprising the Prabandham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;670&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pantheon of the Alvars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;678&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Why the Tiruväymoli is recited along side of the Vedas&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;during the Adhyayanotsavam..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;680&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Temple visited and, or sung by the Alvars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;683-694&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Shrines in the Vaḍa nāḍu&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;695&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Shrines in Tonḍamandalam or Tondai nāḍu..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;696&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Shrines in Chōla nāḍu and Shrines in Nādu nādu&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;696&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Shrines in Pandi nāḍu&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;697&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Shrines in Malai nāḍu&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;697&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Birth dates of the Alvars&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;700-706&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The order of succession as gleaned from the&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Prabandhams&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;703-713&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SECTION II.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Recitals in Tirumalai Temple&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;714-767&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruppavai recital in Tirumala (about 1250-1255 A.D.)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;715&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruvaymoli recital in Tirumala 1360 A.D.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;718&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tiruppavai recital during Margali month in Tirumala&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;and next in Tirupati, 1390 A.D.;&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;719&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Srivaishnava terms used in connection with the Alvārs&amp;rsquo;&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;songs&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;721&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Anusandhanam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;724&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Adhyayanam, Sevai, Anusandhigal, Anusandhanam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;725&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;xviiiCONTENTS&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pages&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Iyal&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Shrines for the Alvārs&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tirumangai Alvar&amp;rsquo;s Tiruvadhyayanam in Tirupati&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1475 A.D.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Uḍaiyavar Emperumānar&amp;rsquo;s Tiruvadhyayanam in&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tirupati 1475 A.D.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s twelve days Tiruvadhyayanam festival&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;in Tirumala&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Adhyayanōtsavam explained&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Adhyayanōtsavam of Sri Govindarajaswam, 1485 A.D. Adhyayanōtsavam in Tirumalai, 1491 A.D&amp;hellip; Circumstances which helped Prabandham recital to gain&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ground&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;726&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;727&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;728&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;728&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;729&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;730&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;731&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;732&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;735&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The beginnings of the Anusandhānam office and how&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;it was viewed by some famous acharyas&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;736&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Change in the relationship between the Koyil-kelvi and&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;the Van Saṭhakōpan Jiyar&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;743&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Iyal Sattumurai done at the Balipīṭham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;746&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Lakshmidēvi Mahotsavam;-no recital of Prabandham&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;746&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Attitude of Achyutaraya&amp;rsquo;s generals and chief officers&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;towards Prabandham recital ..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;748&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Instances when Prabandham reciters were not remu-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;nerated&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;748&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Payment for Anusandhānam&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;749&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Post-Talikota Period&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;756&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SECTION III.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Venkatesvara-Self-Manifest Archa Form of Narayana&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;and Vengadam Hill, His Hallowed Spot&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;768-820.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Preamble-Alvars&amp;rsquo; Devotion to Vishnu&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;768&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;References by the Early Alvars to Vengadam and to&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;other places of public worship &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;783&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Xix&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sanctity of the Vengaḍam Hill and the Self-Manifes-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;tation of Vishnu thereon&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Poygai aļvār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Bhūdattāļvār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Pey āļvār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tirumalisai Alvār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Tiruppänälvär&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Kulasekhara ālvār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Sri Nammālvār&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Pages&#xA;785&#xA;785&#xA;789&#xA;792&#xA;801&#xA;804&#xA;805&#xA;805&#xA;APPENDICES.&#xA;Appendix VI Copy of Firmans granted by Damarla Venkatappa (1639 A.D.) and Emperor Srirangaraya Maharaya (1645 A.D.)&#xA;Appendix VII Copy of inscription No. 237 T.T. (Vol. I, No. 179 of T.T.D. Inscriptions) in Telugu language and script (1359 A.D.)&#xA;Appendix VIII Edict of the Vijayanagar Emperor Devaraya Maharaya II, (1429 A.D.) in Kannada language and Telugu Script, Inscription No. 188. T.T. (Vol. I No. 192)&#xA;Appendix IX Elict of Saluva Narasingayyadeva Maharaya (Inscription No. 8, G.T.) Vol. II, No. 30 in Kannada language and Telugu Script&#xA;Appendix X Extract from Devasthanam Tasdik Book, abstract of receipts and charges, Fasli 1233 (1823-24 A.D.)&#xA;35-38&#xA;39&#xA;40-43&#xA;44-48&#xA;XX&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;(The Tirumala Tirupati Temples)&#xA;CHAPTER XV.&#xA;IT&#xA;SALUVA NARASIMHA.&#xA;was left to Saluva Narasingayadeva Maharaya to open a new chapter in the history of the Tirumala and Tirupati Temples. His devotion to this God may, to some exent, be explained by the fact that he was the great grand-son of Mahamandalesvara Misaraganda Mangideva Maharaja, who however, had not the agnomen or birudu &amp;ldquo;Saluva&amp;rdquo; prefixed to his name. It was he that gold gilt the Vimanam and the Sikharam of the Tirumala Temple in 1359 A.D. The inscription being in Telugu with a Kannada tinge in the language we may infer that he was in touch with the people of both countries. The capital of his ancestral territory was known to be Kalyanapuram (in Nizam&amp;rsquo;s Dominions). We are aware that Yadavaraya Sri Ranganatha built a palace for himself in Tirumala in 1352 a short time before his death and that no Yadavaraya appears to have stepped into his place. Mangideva played the most prominent part in the military campaign against the Sultan of Madura under the command of Prince Kumāra Kempanna. We found that he was in Tirumala just about the time of Sri Ranganatha Yadava&amp;rsquo;s death and the return of the God of Srirangam towards Srirangam; and he also did the unique service of making the Vimanam and Kalasam lustrous. It may reasonably be presumed that he was given the governorship of the erstwhile Yadavaraya country by the Vijayanagar King Bukkaraya I. But there is nothing to show that he transferred his capital to Chandragiri. His great grand-son, Mahamandalēsvara Mēdini Misaraganda Kaṭṭāri Saluva Narasingayyadeva Maharaja, is said to have done so, and to have kept the Mulabalam&#xA;·&#xA;389&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;or the strongest and best tried section of his army at Chandragiri. He would have inherited his great grand father&amp;rsquo;s piety and a special reverence to the God of Tiruvengadam. This seems to have been a characteristic of all the members of the Saluva family. The word Saluva seems to be the name for hawk.&amp;rsquo; If so, he must have been regarded as swooping down on his enemies as a hawk does on its prey. There is an edict of his (II. 30) issued in December 1467 making a grant of three villages, Mupaḍuvēta, Mangoḍuvelada and Mananuru for making sumptuous daily offerings to Sri Govindaraja in Tirupati. This edict also permitted the Sthānikas in Tirupati to appropriate to themselves daily a quantity of prasadams similar to the practice in Tirumala; to have the donor&amp;rsquo;s share of the Prasadams sent to his Rāmānujakūtam to be distributed there to pilgrims by his agent Kandaḍai Rāmānuja Ayyangar and above all to have a certain daily service of supplying parimalam (refined camphor, musk and saffron) carried out in the Tirumala temple by the non-brahmin Sättāda Sri Vaishnavas who were shown in return certain honours. The inscription is in Kannada showing that he wanted this important edict to be in his native language and not Tamil. This unique privilege which he gave to the Sattada Sri Vaishnavas shows the catholicity of his religion. The inscription also shows how ready he was to see that men doing service in the temple should be recompensed adequately.&#xA;In his political career, he withstood the temptation of making undue use of the power and influence which was his more than that of his overlord in Vijayanagar. He was able to keep himself above exciting the jealousy or envy of his numerous cousins and nephews, all of whom were powerful. He appropriated to himself no higher titles than they enjoyed. This self-control and consideration for others he seems to have evinced even in religious matters.&#xA;He was lucky in having as his co-workers in temple affairs a gentleman of wide understanding and experience in Sri Kandaḍai Ramanuja Ayyangar. He seems to have had implicit faith in his honesty, capacity and application to work. But it is too much o say that he was his spiritual teacher or guide. The terms in&#xA;390&#xA;SALUVA NARASIMHA&#xA;which the Ayyangar is referred to in the inscriptions do not admit of that status being given. A separate chapter is devoted to considering in detail Sri Ayyangar and Saluva Narasimha.&#xA;He describes himself as the disciple of Alagiya Manavāla Jiyar of Kanchipuram. H life period is said to be from 1430 to 1496 A.D. and Saluva Narasimha&amp;rsquo;s rule from 1445 to 1492 A.D. They worked together in the prime of life. For the Ramanujakūtams which Narasimha started in Tirumala and Tirupati, Ramanuja Ayyangar was the unfettered manager. Appreciating his cconomical management of these institutions and the savings effected, he was made by Saluva Narasinga&amp;rsquo;s son the Officerin-charge of the Por-Bhandaram for jewellery and the silver and gold vessels in the temple (Por-Bhandaram Kāniākshi&amp;quot;QUADU Lis SGT) so that they may be kept in good repair. For the festivals which Saluva Narasimha instituted the budget was drawn up by Sri Ayyangar. The Sättāda Sri Vaishnavas were the exclusive disciples of Sri Ayyangar. They cultivated flower gardens and supplied parimalam everyday for the Alagappiranar Tiruman&amp;rsquo;anam of the God. Above all this, he made them share in the daily routine of temple service, the privilege of reciting Tiruvoymoli in company with the Brahmins and to receive their share of the embluments. The credit for all these must be given to Saluva Narasimha and Ramanuja jointly. A very large part of Vol. II of the T.T.D. Inscriptions represents their joint. work. Another instance of laying stress on social justice based on personal purity irrespective of the distinctions of caste created by the accident of birth is the importance attached to the reading of the Kaisikapuranam on the Utthana Dvadasi Day before day-break by a member of the first Acharya purusha&amp;rsquo;s family. Although the celebration of the Kaisika Dvadasi is mentioned as early as in the year 1308 A.D., it became a regular festival only in 1494 (II. 115) as is seen from an endowment made by Tiruninra-ur-udaiyan Māru Nayinar Perumakkal and Govindar. These are outstanding developments in the administration of the temple in which the secular as well as the religious side seems to have heartily co-operated.&#xA;391&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Periya Raghunatha&amp;rsquo;s Temple.&#xA;Until Saluva Narasimha entered the scene there was very little improvement in Tirupati and its Govindaraja&amp;rsquo;s temple. During his reign of about half-a-century the festivals and food offerings increased in number. There was also a new temple for Sri Raghunatha-called Periya Raghunatha to distinguish the deity from the other Raghunatha installed in Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s1 Shrine-constructed in 1480 (II. 73) by one Narasimharaya Mudaliar for the merit of Saluva Narasimharayar. An endowment for a supplemental food offering was also made on 29-10-1481 (II. 74).&#xA;Kandadai Ramanuja Ayyangar constructed a temple for Kulasekhara Alwar in November 1468 A.D. for which the Sthanattar endowed as Sarvamanya the lands in Ilamanḍaiyam Kūraikkal.&#xA;Yugadi and Dipavali.&#xA;From Samavai&amp;rsquo;s days all festivals were being timed according to the solar calendar. It was only in 1&amp;hellip; 1 A.D. (II. 914, 27-6-1491), that there is the first mention of the Yugadi and Dipavali festivals being celebrated with food offerings in an endowment by Sriman Mahamandalesvara Baichchraja Timmaya deva Maharaja. This shows that to suit the customs of the ruler of the land, the ChandraSaura-māna Panchanga was being brought into use. The Yugadi and the Dipavali were ultimately to throw the Chittirai and the Tula Vishus into the shade. They were to be classed among the principal Asthanam Festivals.&#xA;Adhyayanotsavam.&#xA;From the Sri Vaishnava point of view the most important festival introduced in Tirumala is the Adhyayanotsavam, although portions of the Alvārs&amp;rsquo; Prabandhams were being repeated on occasions from about 1360 A.D. Tiruvadhyayanam in the month&#xA;II. 88; 12-8-1488.&#xA;392&#xA;SALUVA NARASIMHA&#xA;of Margali as a festival celebrated in Tirumala occurs only (and even that incidentally) in 1468 (II. 31) in an endowment by Saluva Narasimharaja Udaiyar. It reads, LD LOIT&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;யேனத்தில் பிற்பத்தில் திருத்துவாதசியில் &amp;lsquo;&amp;rsquo;(&amp;lsquo;on the Tirudvadasi - day occuring in the latter ten days of the Tiruvadhyayanam in the Margali month&amp;quot;). An endowment by Sathakōpadāsar Narasimharaya Mudaliar in the year 1476 (168) distinctly mentions that in the month of Chittirai Udaiyavar Emperumānār hears on the 12 days of his festival the Tiruvadhyayanam.1 In both cases the donor&amp;rsquo;s share of the offered prasadams went to the Ramanujakutam for distribution to Sri Vaishnavas by Kandadai Ramanuja Ayyangar. The Adhyayanotsavam is a festival repeated on two occasions in the year, that is, in the month of December as well as in April both being celebrated only in front of Udaiyavar (Sri Ramanuja) in his Tirumala Shrine. The festival in Tirupati is not being referred to here. The prasadams are first to be offered to Tiruvengadamuḍaiyan and then to Uḍaiyavar.&#xA;Pavitrotsavam.&#xA;Pavitrotsavam was another festival newly introduced during this period in an endowment by Kaṭṭāri Sāluva Mallayyadeva Maharaja in 1464 (II. 18) being a five day&amp;rsquo;s festival in the month of Avani. It has a ritualistic form.&#xA;Padiya. Vettai.&#xA;Padiya Vettai (Hunting) festival (ur qu CLL) first commenced in 1456 although one would expect it to have been a very old festival seeing that the God is on a thickly forested hill of which the original owner is believed to be Sri Varaha Swami (the Boar Avataram of Vishnu).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
