<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 9th to 17th CE on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 9th to 17th CE on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>12 INSCRIPTIONS ON THE TEMPLES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/12_INSCRIPTIONS_ON_THE_TEMPLES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/12_INSCRIPTIONS_ON_THE_TEMPLES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Tirumala Temple like others bears several inscriptions of considerable interest giving us full details about the temple. These along with others from neighbouring temples in lower Tirupati and Tiruchanur making a total of well over 1,000 furnish a continuous and authentic record of the transactions of the temple and its neighbourhood for the last seven or eight centuries. For example, we have full and complete information on the buildings and endowments and the numerous visits to the temple by the Vijayanagar rulers, especially, the emperors Krishnadevaraya and Achyutaraya. Amongst the great rulers of South India, Raja Raja Chola, from a late and incorrect copy of the inscription of the 16th year of his reign, is known to have been directly connected with the shrine of Tirumala. From earlier records found in the neighbourhood, like those of Dantivarman in Tiruchanur, it is possible to surmise that many of the more ancient inscriptions have disappeared beyond recovery, as a result of the restorations undertaken in the 13th century and later. However, the present inscriptions which number over 1000 if properly analysed give us a fairly continuous account of the history of the temple, and an attempt in this direction is made below.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 EARLIEST EPIGRAPHICAL EVIDENCE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/13_EARLIEST_EPIGRAPHICAL_EVIDENCE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/13_EARLIEST_EPIGRAPHICAL_EVIDENCE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The earliest inscription found in the Tirumala temple mentions the birth of the Bana prince, named Vijayaditya, who flourished in the early half of the ninth century (429-T.T.). This prince is said to have made a gift to Lord Venkatesvara at Tiruchanur. (229-G.T.).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;57&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 TIRUMALA AND THE PALLAVAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/14_TIRUMALA_AND_THE_PALLAVAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/14_TIRUMALA_AND_THE_PALLAVAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Among the Pallavas only one later king, viz., Ko-Vijaya-Dantivikrama-Varman is represented by two epigraphs from Tiruchanur, which give his regnal year 51 which approximates to 830 A.D. (219-T.T. and 223-G.T.). In the later inscriptions the date is missing. But both the inscriptions register the record of a gift of gold for a perpetual lamp in the temple.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The contemporary of Parantaka II, Sundara Chola, Ko-Parthivendra-varman, who probably belonged to the family of the Pallavas who were dispossessed of their kingdom of Tondamandalam by Aditya I, had a certain Kadava subordinate under him, by name Sakti-Vitankan. His queen Samavai was the donor of two records of the temple. The queen is said to be the daughter of a Pallavappergadaiyar. The Kadava chief Sakti-Vitankan had some sort of relationship to Danti-Saktı-Vitanki ahas Lokamahadevi one of the queens of Rajaraja I.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 TIRUMALA UNDER THE CHOLAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/15_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_CHOLAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/15_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_CHOLAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest Chola inscriptions of the temple is Madiraikonda Ko-Parakesarivarman alias Parantaka I, who ruled from 905 to 953 A.D. (232 and 234-G.T.). Both these register the gift of a lamp apiece in the 20th and 29th of the regnal year of the King. 232-G.T. also refers to an assembly or Sabhai in Tiruchchokunar (modern. Tiruchanur) which shows that the divisions of the country were the same as those that existed in the time of the Pallavas. The Cholas on the conquest of Tondamandalam seemed to have maintained the administrative system of the Pallavas which was readily available to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 TIRUMALA UNDER THE PANDYAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/16_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_PANDYAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/16_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_PANDYAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Only one Pandya king is represented by few inscriptions recorded in prasasti in Sanskrit which pertain to Jatavarman Sundara-Pandya I.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;His prasasti as given in No. 175-T.T. represents him as the ornament of the lunar-race (Somakula-tilaka), the ruler of the town of Madhura (Madhurapuri Madhava), the destroyer of the family of the Keralas (Keralavamsa-nirmulana), the second Rama in shattering Lankapuri (Lankapuri-luthana-dvitiya-Rama), the thunderbolt to the mountain which is the Chola family (Cholakulasailakulisa), one who put to flight the Karnata king (Karnataraja-vidravana), the destroyer of the forts of the several enemy kings(Vividharipu-durga-mardana,) , the kindler of the fire to the forest which is Vira-Gandagopala (Vira-Gandagopala-vipina-davadahana), the lord of Kanchi the best of cities (Kanchipuravaradhisvara), the tiger to the deer which is Ganapati (Ganapati-harina-sardula), the establisher of the suppliant kings (Pranata-raja-pratishthapaka), the lord paramount over the maharajas and adhirajas (Maharajadhiraja-paramesvara) and the sovereign over the three worlds (Tribhuvanachakravarti). He is therein called Sri Sundara-Pandyadevapperumal. There are several other records of this king in Tirumala Temple (127, 140, 164, 172, 175, 230, 241 T.T. and 11 G.T.) though they have no other useful information.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 TIRUMALA UNDER PANDYA SUBORDINATES THE YADAVARAYAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/17_TIRUMALA_UNDER_PANDYA_SUBORDINATES_TH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/17_TIRUMALA_UNDER_PANDYA_SUBORDINATES_TH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The chieftains of this family, who governed part of Tondamandalam first as Chola subordinates, then as Pandya feudatories and subsequently as independent rulers, were ardent devotees and patrons of Sri Venkatesvara. ViraNarasingadeva is the earliest member of this family to be connected with the temple of Tirumala. This Chieftain gifted a village to the temple for the supply of rice, vegetables and ghee every day (164-TT). Tirukalattideva, another member, assigned some land in the village of Avilala to the temple (170-TT). Virarakshasa Yadavaraya also granted some land (293-TT). The queen of Viranarasinga presented 64 cows and two bulls for setting up two perpetual lamps (381-TT). In the 40th year of the rule of Viranarasinga, a certain Tiruppullanidasar, a visiting pilgrim, obtained the ruler&amp;rsquo;s permission and renovated the shrine of Sri Venkatesvara (17-TT). This chieftain performed the Tulabhara ceremony at Tirumala and made Venkatagiri equal to mount Meru (371-TT), Another chieftain of this family, Tiruvenkatanatha, gifted a village as sarvamanya for conducting the Adi-tirunal for the god (189-TT). His father-in-law and mahapradhani Singaya-dannayaka, instituted an offering named Sitakara-sandhi in the temple (195-TT). A record dated in the third year of the rule of another member of this family, Sriranganatha, refers to flower gardens, mathams etc., on the hill and mentions the Hunting festival of Sri Venkatesvara (354-TT). Another record dated sixteen years later, mentions the metallic image, Malaikuniyaninra-perumal and his Nachimar (I-106). One more record mentions of Vasanta festival (1-113). Hobala Yadavaraya presented to the god an ornament for his band, obviously to the lower right hand which is in the varada pose (56,A-TT).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 TIRUMALA UNDER VIJAYANAGAR EMPERORS,</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/18_TIRUMALA_UNDER_VIJAYANAGAR_EMPERORS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/18_TIRUMALA_UNDER_VIJAYANAGAR_EMPERORS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The establishment of the Vijayanagara empire in 1336 A.D. was a turning point in the religious and cultural history of South India. The temples and gods of this region passed through critical days during the first three decades of the fourteenth century on account of frequent Muslim invasions. The new Hindu empire offered them all the needed protection and extended to them zealous patronage. The Sri Venkatesvara temple of Tirumala received the devoted attention of the various royal families that ruled over the empire and entered upon a phase of unprecedented glory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 TIRUMALA UNDER THE SANGAMA DYNASTY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/19_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_SANGAMA_DYNASTY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/19_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_SANGAMA_DYNASTY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first ruler of the First or Sangama dynasty who can be easily recognised in the temple epigraphs is Harihara II, mentioned in No. 103-TT. dated in Saka 1309, Prabhava. But there are three earlier records belonging to the reign of Bukka I (Nos. 487, 237 and 238, and 485-TT.) though the king is not mentioned in any of them, No. 487-TT. which is undated and fragmentary, registers the grant of a village to the temple for a sandhi (offerings) twice a day in the name of Bukkarayan and this Bukkarayan-Sandhi is again referred to in No.44 TT. dated in Saka 1379.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 TIRUMALA UNDER THE SALUVA DYNASTY OF VIJAYANAGAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/20_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_SALUVA_DYNASTY_OF/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/20_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_SALUVA_DYNASTY_OF/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even during the last years of Devaraya II, the Saluvas appear to have been rising to power. Saluva Peri-Mallayadeva Maharaja, son of Errakampayadeva Maharaja, comes to notice from No. 13-TT. dated in Saka 1368, Kshaya (10-10-1446 A.D.).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;No. 100-TT. dated in Saka 1364, Dundubhi, registers the payment of 3000 honnu as kanike for the God by Tippada Nageya-Nayakkar, son of Muddiya-Nayara. Probably he was a general (Nayaka) under Devaraya II and belonged to the Vijayanagara forces stationed at Chandragiri.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 TIRUMALA UNDER THE TULUVA DYNASTY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/21_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_TULUVA_DYNASTY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/21_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_TULUVA_DYNASTY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Temples of Tirumala received royal patronage during the period of the rule of this dynasty. The most famous rulers of this line, namely, Sri Krishnadevaraya and Sri Achutaraya were ardent devotees of Sri Venkatesvara and gave the Lord many presents and offerings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;tirumala-under-krishnadevaraya&#34;&gt;TIRUMALA UNDER KRISHNADEVARAYA.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Krishnaraya is represented by nearly fifty inscriptions in the temple belonging to himself and his two queens Chinnajidevi and Tirumaladevi. They range in date between Saka 1434 (1513-A.D.) and Saka 1445 (1524 A.D.) and register personal offerings and direct gifts made during their frequent visits to the temple of Sri Venkatesvara on Tirumala, whom he venerated as his Patron-God, as well as the edicts of grants issued by him from his capital city of Vijayanagara. As in the case of his charities elsewhere, Krishnaraya&amp;rsquo;s gifts in the Tirumala temple also are generally recorded in the three South Indian languages Telugu, Tamil and Kanarese, as if indicating his sway over the entire Southern India in which they were spoken.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 Tirumala under SadasIVARAYA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/22_Tirumala_under_SadasIVARAYA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/22_Tirumala_under_SadasIVARAYA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sadasivaraya the next king has in the walls of Tirumala temple engraved nearly a hundred and fifty inscriptions most of which begin with his introduction A peculiar feature of this prasasti is that to the king is ascribed not only the lordship of the eastern, southern and western oceans which fringe the Peninsula, but also that of the northern ocean that is non-existent in the case of India itself. The earliest date that is available for him in these epigraphs viz., Thursday combined with the star Punarvasu, the 12th day of the dark fortnight of the Karkataka month in the cyclic year Plava, current with the Saka year 1463, corresponding to the 21st July 1541 A.D., which occurs in 659 - T.T. Registering the gift of Muttur and another village to the temple by SriramaBhattar, son of Yandalur Tirumalai-Josyar, is about eight months anterior to the latest date furnished for his predecessor Achyutaraya in No. 504-T.T. viz., Thursday combined with the Star Ardra, being the 7th day of the bright fortnight of the Mina month in Plava, current with Saka 1463, corresponding to the 23rd March 1542 A.D. It has been stated that Sadasivaraya had been chosen crown prince already in Saka 1459, Hevilambi (1537 A.D.), nearly five years earlier (Ar. Sur. Sept. for 1908-09, page 193), and this statement seems to be supported by the surname “Sadasivapura &amp;quot; found to have been&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 TirumalA UNDER ÁRAVIDU</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/23_TirumalA_UNDER_RAVIDU/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/02_9th_to_17th_CE/23_TirumalA_UNDER_RAVIDU/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ruling line of the Aravidu family commenced with Tirumala, who acquired power as the chief minister of Sadasivaraya in 1565 A.D. after the death of his elder brother Aliya-Ramaraya in the battle of Talikota, ascended the Vijayanagara throne ten years later in about 1575 A.D. having at the same time changed his capital to Penugonda. His was a brief reign lasting for two or three years during which his second son Srirangaraya or Ranga II ruled as co-regent with him. His Unjal-mantapam, generally called the Tirumalaraya-mantapam, with its exquisitely sculptured high pillars bearing the figures of a warrior riding a horse standing erect over an elephant with&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
