<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;वेङ्कटाचलः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;वेङ्कटाचलः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>ItihAsa-mAlA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/itihAsa-mAlA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/itihAsa-mAlA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;रविलोचनाभिप्रायः (द्रष्टुं नोद्यम्)&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Venkatachala itihasa mala is later day fraud- not written by anandanpillai. It claims that ramanuja installed Govindaraja in 1077 itself - which is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Tirumalai-Tirupati Devastanam Series.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्रीवेङ्कटेश इतिहासमाला&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ASK SOM&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;EDITED BY&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Rajasevasakta&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;WAN BAHADUR DR. S. KRISHNASWAMI AIYANGAR, M.A., PH.D.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Published under the authority of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;A. RANGANATHA MUDALIAR AVL., B.A., B.L.,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Commissioner&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;i-Tirupati Devasthanam Committee, Tirupati.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1937.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;yright reserved.)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Price Re. 1.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;तिरुमलै तिरुपदि देवस्थान ग्रन्थावलिः&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्रीः&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्रीवेंकटाचलेतिहासमाला श्रीमदनन्तार्यगुम्भिता ॥&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;राजसेवासक्तैः दिवान्बहदूर् डाक्टर&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;शाखोट्टै कृष्णस्वाम्यय्यङ्गायैः&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;परिशोधिता&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;देवस्थानसभाध्यक्षैः रङ्गनाथमुदलिवर्यैः&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;प्रकाशिता&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;१९३७ (संवत्सरे)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRIVENKATACH ** A A ITIHASAMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Garland of Historical Tales of the Hill of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Venkata (Tirupati)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;This is a work which professes to be a historical account of the various arrangements that were made from time to time for the conduct of worship in the temple on the hill at Vengadam. It is not a regular history of the temple in the sense that it gives an account of the temple from its origin down to the time of writing of this account, but is more or less a record of certain important incidents in its history. The whole account consists of seven chapters dealing with the topics connected with the contesting claims of Saivas and Vaishnavas to the temple, the settlement arrived at as a result of the discussion between the contesting claimants, the arrangements ordered in consequence thereof by the Vaishnava teacher Rāmānuja through the local ruler Yadava Raja. This is followed by the further arrangements that were called for and made subsequent to this, but all of them more or less during the life and under the commands of Rāmānuja. It may therefore be taken to be an account of what was done to the temple by Ramanuja and does not purport to give the history of the shrine either in the period previous to Rămâ- nuja regarding which some allusions could be found here and there, and naturally nothing for the subsequent period. The work therefore deals as it were with one particular period of its history, which is comprised perhaps in the century after Christ, 1050 to 1150.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;2&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;First Stabaka&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Our Lord God residing in immeasurable happiness in Vaikuntham, the Lord of the Goddess Sri and surrounded by those who had obtained eternal release, in his infinite. mercy decided to come down upon earth in order to save those struggling in the sea of life without knowing how to get out of it. He regarded it as his mission to come on to the earth in a visible form to provide the means of saving themselves for those struggling in great suffering in worldly life. He there- fore assumed the form of an image at Tirupati, and placed himself there as the saviour of mankind. His right hand is held in a position inviting all beings to come to him as the highest protector, and the left placed on the corresponding thigh in such a position as if to indicate that, to those devoted to him, the sea of life (samsara) is only knee deep. This gives indication to the people that to those who devote themselves to the worship of God manifesting Himself in Tirupati, worldly life need have none of the fears generally associated with it. That he came to the earth on this merciful mission is a fact known to all.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;In the second section of the current Brahmakalpa (the age of Brahma), in the second section in the ruling period of the 7th Manu and at the commencement of the age of the 8th Mahakali, there was a large assemblage of Rishis and others in a great sacrifice that was celebrated in the forest of Naimiša. In that assembly the great Sūta well versed in all the Puranas and the Itihāsas related the holy history of the hill Vengadam and all that was likely to happen after that time.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Among these future occurrences is the story of a Tondaman Chakravarti who was going to be born after the commencement of the era of Vikrama, and before the com- mencement of the current Sälivahana era. He was, among those devoted to the God at Vengaḍam, the most prominent.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;In order that the devotee of Venkatēśvara might become victorious over his enemies, the God gave him his own conch and the discus. From that time onwards the God at Tirupati remained without these two characteristic weapons, as if to exhibit his great generosity to this devotee of His.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;3&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;During this period the world was suffering from the evils of the Kali age, and people went about without any regard to the regulations of Varṇāśrama (the differences of groups and the progressive order of life constituting the essen- tial feature of the Hindu Dharma or rule of life). The ruling princes adopted other religious persuasions. Temples were neglected and even destroyed, and there was loss of Dharma the world over. Large numbers of people became Pashandis&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;(ascetics of the heretical sects).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Having seen these, God in his infinite mercy ordered Ananta Alvān (the great serpant Sesha who forms his bed generally), to go into the world and re-establish the orthodox Hindu order by destroying heretics.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Ananta in due submission to the order thus delivered, came down on earth and was born in Bhutapuri (Śrī Perum Pūdur) near Madras in the Tondamandalam division of the Tamil country as the son of a Kesava Sōmayāji of the Harita Götra in the year of Kali 4118, Salivahana Saka 938 past, the year Pingala, month Chaitra and the nakshatra Ardra.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;This was Rāmānuja. He acquired expert acknowledge in all the Sastras in course of time and mastered the Veda of Sanskrit and Tamil completely, and, having defeated all the teachers of the heretical sects, he re-established the orthodox teaching of Vaishnavism and had settled down in the holiest of the holy Vaishnava temples, Srirangam.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;3&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;In this state of affairs it happened that in Vengaḍam the Vaikhānasas (followers of the Vaikhanasa agama) who were entrusted with the conduct of the worship in the temple there, failed in their duty, and, having been punished by the local ruler, Yadavarāja of Nārāyaṇavaram, quitted the place and emigrated elsewhere.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;While in this manner the more elderly Vaikhānasa Vaishnavas had left the place, and as there were not, among those that stayed behind, people sufficiently learned in the Vaikhanasa way of life (Dharma), some of the Saivas near about took the opportunity to prejudice the Yadava Rāja peainet, the Vaikhanasa Vaishnavas gradually.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;5&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Therefore they urged that in this temple everything would have to be conducted according to the prescription for worship laid down in the Saiva Āgamaṣ.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Having heard this, the Yadavarāja began to ponder seriously over the matter, and, having known that for some considerable period of time the place was regarded as a Vaish- nava holy place and that worship was being conducted by the Vaishnavas according to the Vaikhanasa Agama, he thought he should not commit himself to any course of action without proper investigation, notwithstanding what the Saivas urged.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Vaishnavas that were left in Tirupati feeling themselves not competent to discuss with the Saivas on equal terms gave a detailed report of what took place to Rāmānuja then in residence in Srirangam.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;On receipt of this information Rāmānuja set forward immediately from Srirangam. Having reached Tirupati, he intimated the Yadavarāja of his arrival and offered to explain satisfactorily all the objections that the Saivas put forward against Tirupati being regarded a Vaishnava shrine, and prove to the satisfaction of the Yadavarāja, on the autho- rity of the Sastras, that Venkatachala was the hill of Vishnu, and remove his doubt in regard to the matter. He informed the Raja he undertook the journey from Srirangam specially with a view to this.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Having been thus assured, the Yadavarāja brought together a great assembly of learned men both from among the Saivas and from the Vaishnavas, and having brought them together proposed the subject for their discussion in the proper form.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The Saivas stated that Kumārasvami obtained his father&amp;rsquo;s (Siva&amp;rsquo;s permission and arrived at Venkatagiri (Tirupati) and set up to perform his penance on the bank of a holy tank, according to Vamana Purāņa. There standing, with his feet touching the ground, on the south bank of the Svāmi Pushkariņi wearing a coiffure of matted locks and keeping aside the warlike weapons as unsuitable to an ascetic, Skanda shows himself in the form of an image to enable people to offer him worship and thus fulfil their cherished&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;4&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;THE SAIVA CLAIM&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;They said that the God who manifested himself in the temple on the south bank of the tank of Svami Pushkariņi was no other than the worshipful Skanda. They gave as a reason for this that the name Svāmi is peculiarly applicable to him. as forming part of Kumārasvāmi which is the acknowledged name of Subrahmanya. The holy tank near the temple goes also by his name as belonging to him. There is nothing strange about it, they urged, as other names are similarly attributed in use, such as Bhimasēna being generally called Bhima and Satyabhama being generally called Bhama.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;They quoted for authority the Vamana Purāņa which contains a section illustrative of the holiness of Venkatachalā. Skanda is said to have consulted his father in regard to a place peculiarly holy to Vishnu, for performing a penance and getting rid of the sin of killing the Asura Taraka. The father, Śiva, advised the son to go to Venkatachala as the holiest of the holy places of Vishnu. Skanda went to Venkatachala and per- formed his penance on the bank of a tank, according to Vāmana Purana, part ii. He there found Vayu (god of the air) also similarly performing penance, and, having paid his respects to him, he also set up there to do likewise. Therefore they urged that the God there ought to be regarded as God Kumārasvāmi. Being in the position of one performing a penance, they said, the God is there exhibited without his extra hands and characteristic weapons, For these and for many other good reasons they urged the place is really a holy place of Skanda, not Vishnu.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;They pointed out further that for some time past some Vaishnavas took possession of the place and having there set up some of the Vaishnava images which did not exist in the temple before, took possession of the temple and conducted worship there as though it were a Vaishnava shrine, thus making people believe that it was a Vishnu temple; but in actual truth that was a Saiva holy place without a doubt owing to the merits of the penance that Skanda had perfor there.6&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;wishes. Therefore they stated that the place where Skanda performed penance in the hill Vengaḍam must be regarded as a Saiva holy place.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;They further asserted that this image of God can- not be said to be Vishnu. The weapons characteristic of Vishnu, such as the conch and the discus were not seen in the image; while the matted locks and naga (serpent) orna- ments characteristic of other Gods are seen on the image. Therefore the image cannot be regarded as that of Vishnu.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s Answer: Before God Śrīnivāsa appeared on this hill, Brahma, Rudra and the other gods besides several Rishis are stated to have already begun performing penance there. If so, would it not be madness to state that one of those performing penance should be singled out as being exclusively associated with this hill and as giving it sanctity? Further than this, in the self-same Vamana Purana, in chapter 14, Venkatachalam is held up as a very holy place dedicated to Vishnu, whose temple was on the south bank of the Svāmi Pushkarni. In the same Vamana Purana, in seve- ral other contexts, the place is described as the residence of Vishnu in the form of Varaha, and in the form of Srinivasa. It is further stated to be a place fit for the residence of those devoted to Vishnu. Therefore it is clear that it was regarded as a place holy to Vishnu and not to any other.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;In the same manner, the Varaha Purāņa states that Venkatachalam was the temple of Varäha-Vasudeva in the colloquy between Dharani (the earth) and Varaha in the first chapter of the Venkatachala Mahatmya section. There is an equally clear statement to this effect in the Padma Purana in chapter 24.1, and in the Garuda Purana in the colloquy between Arundati and Vasishța, in chapter 63. Simi- larly this hill is stated to be a Vishnu-kshetra in the Brah- 、mānḍapurāņa in the colloquy between Bhrigu and Närada.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;So also other Purāņas make similar statements.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;In addition to these clear statements, all the Purāņas state that this hill was the Krida-parvata, (sporting hill) in Vaikuntha wherefrom it was brought down by Garuda. In consequence, this hill is called the Vaikuntha-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;7&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;giri, Garudachalam and by other similar names. These would make it clear that the hill was sacred to Vishnu. More than this Vaidika Brahmans on occasions of the performance of ceremonies prescribed in the Śrutis and Smritis indicate this place as Varaha Kshētra. There is not much use in repeating the statement again and again. Even the Veda which is acknowledged to have no beginning, speaks of this hill as a hill holy to Vishnu in the Rig-Veda (Eighth Ashtaka, eighth chapter and section 13).&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;On this clear exposition by Rāmānuja that the hill Venkatachala was a hill dedicated to Vishnu, the Yadava Rāja became quite clear in his mind that there was no reason for regarding the Saiva contention as deserving of any serious consideration.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Second Stabaka&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Rāmānuja: &amp;ldquo;The Saivas assert that the name Svămi Pushkariņi indicates clear association with Kumārasvāmi.&amp;rdquo; This name was given to it because Kumārasvāmi performed his penance on the bank of this tank. The statement that, for this reason, the tank belongs to Skanda is not worthy of acceptance.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;The meaning of the term Svāmi Pushkariņi is that this tank is the lord of all similar tanks in the world. It is a term indicative of leadership or excellence. It is so explained in the Purāņas, and the Sanskrit compound is so explained. There- fore the term Svāmi cannot be held to apply to Kumārasvāmi as an abbreviation.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Moreover the term Svāmi can convey Śrīman Nārāyaṇa as he is the creator, protector and destroyer of all the worlds. Association with such an unparallelled leader&amp;rsquo;s name might as well be connoted by the term, if we make the first part of the compound a word in the genitive case which would not offend against Sanskrit grammar.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;On the bank of that tank there are several beings engaged in the performance of penance Kumarasvami is just one of them. The tank therefore cannot be the holy tank of Kumāra. Among the authorities quoted by my rivals in support of&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;TIKUFAT..&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;10&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Garuda from Vaikuntha, it follows that the tank of divine holiness was also the same God&amp;rsquo;s sporting tank. If so, it cannot follow that the name Svami Pushkariņi was given to the tank because of Skanda performing his penance on the bank of this tank. &amp;ldquo;Therefore it is clear&amp;rdquo;, he said, &amp;ldquo;that you are in no position to give an effective reply to the arguments adduced by Rāmānuja Muni to establish that there was no manner of a connection between this tank and any other God, and there- fore what Rāmānuja Muni had actually proved seemed quite adequate to establish his contention. What remains to be done therefore is only whether the God represented by the image on the south bank of the tank is Vishnu or Skanda. Even in regard to that, I shall ask Rāmānuja Muni to state what he may have to adduce as satisfactory reason.&amp;rdquo; So saying he addressed Rāmānuja with much attention and respect.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Yadava Rāja: Addressing sage Ramanuja, the Yadava Rāja said: &amp;ldquo;It was clearly demonstrated, by what the sage had already urged as evidence, that the shrine on the south bank of the Svāmi Pushkariņi was a Vaishnava holy place, and that the tank itself was a Vaishnava holy tank. He said that he was prepared to accept that position; but wanted that Rāmānuja should put it beyond a doubt by evidence that the deity on the south bank was Mahavishnu, and no other god.&amp;rdquo; Thus addressed by the Rāja, Rāmānuja put forward his argu- ments as follows-&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-puraṭṭāsi-september-october-festival&#34;&gt;Rāmānuja Bespeaking the Raja&amp;rsquo;s attention, Rama- nuja said &amp;ldquo;It was well recognised by all that the deity on the south bank of the tank was Vishnu and no other, and there was little in it that required to be proved by him. That the lord on the hill Venkata was only Madhusudana without an equal, and there is not the slightest reason to sus- pect that the deity there is any other god. To say that he is Skanda is to assert that the light emitted by the fire-fly is sun- light. Proceeding to evidence, the Puranas which are accepted and read as authoritative holy books, all of them declare with- out a doubt that the deity on the south bank is no other than Nārāyaṇa, the lord of Sri (goddess Lakshmi). In the first chapter of the second part of the Varäha Purana God Varaha himself is made to say that Srinivasa appeared on the south&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;7&#xA;giri, Garudachalam and by other similar names. These would make it clear that the hill was sacred to Vishnu. More than this Vaidika Brahmans on occasions of the performance of ceremonies prescribed in the Śrutis and Smritis indicate this place as Varaha Kshetra. There is not much use in repeating the statement again and again. Even the Veda which is acknowledged to have no beginning, speaks of this hill as a hill holy to Vishnu in the Rig-Veda (Eighth Ashtaka, eighth chapter and section 13).&#xA;On this clear exposition by Ramanuja that the hill Venkatachala was a hill dedicated to Vishnu, the Yadava Raja became quite clear in his mind that there was no reason for regarding the Saiva contention as deserving of any serious consideration.&#xA;Second Stabaka&#xA;Ramanuja: &amp;ldquo;The Saivas assert that the name Svāmi Pushkariņi indicates clear association with Kumārasvāmi.&amp;rdquo; This name was given to it because Kumārasvāmi performed his penance on the bank of this tank. The statement that, for this reason, the tank belongs to Skanda is not worthy of_ acceptance.&#xA;The meaning of the term Svāmi Pushkarini is that this tank is the lord of all similar tanks in the world. It is a term indicative of leadership or excellence. It is so explained in the Purāņas, and the Sanskrit compound is so explained. There- fore the term Svami cannot be held to apply to Kumārasvāmi as an abbreviation.&#xA;Moreover the term Svami can convey Śrīman Nārāyaṇa as he is the creator, protector and destroyer of all the worlds. Association with such an unparallelled leader&amp;rsquo;s name might as well be connoted by the term, if we make the first part of the compound a word in the genitive case which would not offend against Sanskrit grammar.&#xA;On the bank of that tank there are several beings engaged in the performance of penance. Kumāraşvāmi is just one of them. The tank therefore cannot be the holy tank of Kumāra. Among the authorities quoted by my rivals in support of&#xA;2&#xA;10&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;Garuda from Vaikuntha, it follows that the tank of divine. holiness was also the same God&amp;rsquo;s sporting tank. If so, it cannot follow that the name Svämi Pushkariņi was given to the tank because of Skanda performing his penance on the bank of this tank. &amp;ldquo;Therefore it is clear &amp;ldquo;, he said, &amp;ldquo;that you are in no position to give an effective reply to the arguments adduced by Rāmānuja Muni to establish that there was no manner of a connection between this tank and any other God, and there- fore what Rămănuja Muni had actually proved seemed quite adequate to establish his contention. What remains to be done therefore is only whether the God represented by the image on the south bank of the tank is Vishnu or Skanda. Even in regard to that, I shall ask Rāmānuja Muni to state what he may have to adduce as satisfactory reason.&amp;rdquo; So saying he addressed Ramanuja with much attention and respect.&#xA;Yadava Rāja: Addressing sage Rāmānuja, the Yadava Rāja said: &amp;ldquo;It was clearly demonstrated, by what the sage had already urged as evidence, that the shrine on the south bank of the Svāmi Pushkariņi was a Vaishnava holy place, and that the tank itself was a Vaishnava holy tank. He said that he was prepared to accept that position; but wanted that Rāmānuja should put it beyond a doubt by evidence that the deity on the south bank was Mahavishnu, and no other god.&amp;rdquo; Thus addressed by the Rāja, Rāmānuja put forward his argu- ments as follows-&#xA;Rāmānuja: Bespeaking the Raja&amp;rsquo;s attention, Rama- nuja said &amp;ldquo;It was well recognised by all that the deity on the south bank of the tank was Vishnu and no other, and there was little in it that required to be proved by him. That the lord on the hill Venkata was only Madhusudana without an equal, and there is not the slightest reason to sus- pect that the deity there is any other god. To say that he is Skanda is to assert that the light emitted by the fire-fly is sun- light. Proceeding to evidence, the Puranas which are accepted and read as authoritative holy books, all of them declare with- out a doubt that the deity on the south bank is no other than Nārāyaṇa, the lord of Sri (goddess Lakshmi). In the first chapter of the second part of the Varaha Purana God Varaha himself is made to say that Srinivasa appeared on the south&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;11&#xA;bank of the tank to grant the boon prayed for by Vayu (god of the air) who was in penance for the purpose. He also stated that Śrīnivāsa was going to remain there to the end of the kalpa (one of the greater periods of time) and was going to be worshipped by Kumārasvami (Skanda or Subrahmanya). In the face of the statement, it cannot be argued that the Śrīnivāsa is Skanda. Further it is stated that Skanda per- formed a penance in the presence of Śrīnivāsa with a view to get rid of the evil attaching to him by his killing the Asura Taraka. How then can Skanda the worshipper be transformed into Skanda the object of worship. It is not only in this Purāņa, but in several of the Puranas describing the great merits of Venkatachala, it is clearly stated that Srinivasa and Varaha, both of them forms of Vishnu, were respectively on the south and west banks of the holy tank under reference. More than this the Bhavishyottarapurāņa recounts a colloquy which took place between Srinivasa and Varaha. When Śrīnivāsa married Padmavati, the daughter of Akāśa Rāja, it is stated in the Puranas that both Varaha and his consort Bhumi (the goddess of earth) were invited. Thus there are many stories in the Purānas which state that both Śrīni- vāsa and Varaha were separately enshrined on the south and west banks of the tank. Much more than this, as we stated already in the first stabaka, the term sirimbiḍasya used in the Rig Veda, Eighth Ashtaka, eighth chapter, 13th Varga (sec- tion) is explained as referring to Srinivasa. The deity in this shrine has a single face and four arms, while it is stated that Skanda at birth had only one head and two hands; and that when it came to a question of being nursed by the Pleides (Krittikä) he is said to have acquired six faces and twelve hands. Further than this when Skanda resolved to go to Venkatachala for performing penance, he is said, by the Saivas, to have given up all his weapons. This is obviously an error, as others who went on a similar purpose, such as Raghava (Vishņu as Rama) and the Pandavas when they went to perform penance carried their weapons with them. The Vamana Purana in chapters 22 and 23 states clearly that when Skanda went to perform penance he carried all his weapons with him. It is not stated elsewhere in the work that he laid&#xA;14&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;acceptable to god Srinivāsa. Even in the Sastras, bilra (marmelos) is included among the articles with which puja (worship) is to be performed on an equal footing with tulasi (basil). That bilva is acceptable to Lakshmi is stated clearly in the Śrīsūkta (prayer addressed to Lakshmi). The Harita- smrti mentions bilva as one of the principal objects of use for worship. Coming down to evidence, the Varaha Purana, in part i, chapter 45/13, describes the appearance of Srinivasa on Venkatachalam to Dasaratha, and it is stated there that the rishis who were living on the south bank of the Svämi Push- kariņi performing penance worshipped him on occasions with bilva. In the second part of the same Purāņa, chapter 9, it is stated that Mahalakshmi generally resides in gardens where bilva is cultivated. Thus it is clear from the statements in the Śruti, Smrti, Itihāsa and Purāņa that worship with bilra is appropriate to Vishnu.&#xA;Vishnu is stated to have allowed his hair to grow into matted locks in several of his avatars. The existence of the matted locks therefore need not be held to detract from the Vaishnava character of the image. In the Sri Bhagavata, book ii, chapter 5, in the colloquy between emperor Nimi and the sage Navayōgiśvara, it is laid down clearly that on special occasions worship may be offered to Vishnu wearing a coiffure of matted locks. Similarly in the 12th chapter of the Pancha- rātra, the Satvata Samhita, one is advised to contemplate Vishnu as having a coiffure of matted locks and a beard, carry- ing in his one hand the danda (a stick of palāsa or aścaka carried by Sanyasis and Brahmacharis) and kamandala in an- other and as wearing a garland of lotus seeds. Similarly Vishnu is described to have worn matted locks in severa avataras. It cannot therefore be held that the wearing of matted locks is the characteristic of other gods only. More than this the Skanda Purana in part I, chapter 10, states that Śrīnivāsa wore the matted locks when he appeared in Ven katachala. A similar statement is made in Vämana Purāņa chapter 34/15.&#xA;It is stated in Skanda, Vamana, Varäha, Padma and other Purāņas that, at the request of Brahma and of other Gods&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;11&#xA;bank of the tank to grant the boon prayed for by Vayu (god of the air) who was in penance for the purpose. He also stated that Śrīniväsa was going to remain there to the end of the kalpa (one of the greater periods of time) and was going to be worshipped by Kumārasvāmi (Skanda or Subrahmanya). In the face of the statement, it cannot be argued that the Śrinivasa is Skanda. Further it is stated that Skanda per- formed a penance in the presence of Srinivasa with a view to get rid of the evil attaching to him by his killing the Asura Taraka. How then can Skanda the worshipper be transformed into Skanda the object of worship. It is not only in this Purāņa, but in several of the Puranas describing the great merits of Venkaṭāchala, it is clearly stated that Srinivāsa and Varaha, both of them forms of Vishnu, were respectively on the south and west banks of the holy tank under reference. More than this the Bhavishyottarapurāņa recounts a colloquy which took place between Śrīnivāsa and Varaha. When Śrīnivāsa married Padmavati, the daughter of Akāśa Rāja, it is stated in the Puranas that both Varaha and his consort Bhumi (the goddess of earth) were invited.&#xA;were invited. Thus there are many stories in the Purāņas which state that both Śrīni- vāsa and Varaha were separately enshrined on the south and west banks of the tank. Much more than this, as we stated already in the first stabaka, the term sirimbiḍasya used in the Rig Veda, Eighth Ashtaka, eighth chapter, 13th Varga (sec- tion) is explained as referring to Śrīnivāsa. The deity in this shrine has a single face and four arms, while it is stated that Skanda at birth had only one head and two hands; and that when it came to a question of being nursed by the Pleides (Krittika) he is said to have acquired six faces and twelve hands. Further than this when Skanda resolved to go to Venkatachala for performing penance, he is said, by the Saivas, to have given up all his weapons. This is obviously an error, as others who went on a similar purpose, such as Raghava (Vishnu as Rama) and the Pandavas when they went to perform penance carried their weapons with them. Vamana Purana in chapters 22 and 23 states clearly that when Skanda went to perform penance he carried all his weapons with him. It is not stated elsewhere in the work that he laid&#xA;The&#xA;14&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;acceptable to god Srinivāsa. Even in the Sastras, bilva (marmelos) is included among the articles with which puja (worship) is to be performed on an equal footing with tulasi (basil). That bilva is acceptable to Lakshmi is stated clearly in the Śrīsūkta (prayer addressed to Lakshmi). The Harita- smrti mentions bilva as one of the principal objects of use for worship. Coming down to evidence, the Varaha Purāņa, in part i, chapter 45, 13, describes the appearance of Śrinivasa on Venkatachalam to Dasaratha, and it is stated there that the rishis who were living on the south bank of the Svami Push- kariņi performing penance worshipped him on occasions with bilva. In the second part of the same Purana, chapter 9, it is stated that Mahalakshmi generally resides in gardens where bilva is cultivated. Thus it is clear from the statements in the Śruti, Smrti, Itihasa and Purana that worship with bilva is appropriate to Vishnu.&#xA;Vishnu is stated to have allowed his hair to grow into matted locks in several of his avatars. The existence of the matted locks therefore need not be held to detract from the Vaishnava character of the image. In the Sri Bhagavata, book ii, chapter 5, in the colloquy between emperor Nimi and the sage Navayõgiśvara, it is laid down clearly that on special occasions worship may be offered to Vishnu wearing a coiffure of matted locks. Similarly in the 12th chapter of the Pancha- rātra, the Satvata Samhita, one is advised to contemplate Vishnu as having a coiffure of matted locks and a beard, carry- ing in his one hand the danda (a stick of palasa or asvaka carried by Sanyasis and Brahmacharis) and kamandala in an- other and as wearing a garland of lotus seeds. Similarly Vishnu is described to have worn matted locks in several avataras. It cannot therefore be held that the wearing of matted locks is the characteristic of other gods only. More than this the Skanda Purana in part I, chapter 10, states that Śrīnivāsa wore the matted locks when he appeared in Vên- kaṭāchala. A similar statement is made in Vamana Purāņa, chapter 34/15.&#xA;It is stated in Skanda, Vämana, Varaha, Padma and other Purāņas that, at the request of Brahma and of other Gods,&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;15&#xA;Vishnu suppressed his fearsome form and assumed a pleasant looking shape. In the Padma Purana, chapter 26/3, Vishnu is said to have been dressed up in cloth carrying figures of naga. In chapter 27/4 of the same work he is said to be wearing matted locks. In chapter 33/10 a fearsome form and a pleasant form are both described as forms alike of Vishnu. In the Bhavishyottara Purāṇa, chapter 11, it is stated that Akāśa Rāja presented jewels made in the form of cobras to Śrīnivāsa on the occasion of his marriage with the Raja&amp;rsquo;s daughter Padmavati. In the esoteric sections of the Bhavish- yottara Purāņa, Śrīnivāsa is said to have worn jewels in the form of Nagas, where Paramēśvara expounds Śrīnivāsa to Parvati. The Brahmanda Purana, chapter 2, states that the great Naga Adisesha serves as all kinds of dress and decorat- ive ornaments. In Padma Purāņa, chapter 34/11, Śrīnivāsa is said to reside along with Lakshmi on the hill which was an incarnation of Adiśēsha. In the Brahmanda Purāņa, in the chapter containing Venkaṭēśa Sahasranama, Vishnu is stated to have matted locks, the conch and the weapon sakti (a javelin or short double sword used as a throw weapon), and jewels in the form of cobras. It is further stated that God there appeared in both the forms. It is therefore clear that jewels in the shape of Naga were always worn by Śrīnivāsa. It cannot therefore be said that that form of jewel is peculiar only to other gods. Further, since we have now offered proof, it is wrong to regard these features, the use of bilva, the absence of the conch and discus and the wearing of the matted locks and någa jewels as necessarily peculiar to other gods. It would be equally clear that, if these are peculiar to Śiva as our opponents say, they could hardly be appropriate to Skanda. These contentions are therefore clearly baseless.&#xA;The image of god that appears before us has the mark of Śrīvatsa, and carries Lakshmi on his chest. These make it clear that He is God Nārāyaṇa and nobody else. Nārāyaṇa is stated to be the only primeval being. Brahma and Śiva and other gods sprang from him. Nārāyaṇa is again stated to be the creator of the universe, its protector and ultimate des- troyer. That it is from this primeval Supreme that Brahma, Śiva and others arose is stated clearly in the Upanishads. If&#xA;316&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;Nārāyaṇa is the cause of creation, protection and destruction, and, as the cause can contain features that appear in the con- sequence, the wearing of the matted locks and the naga jewel is but an indication that Brahma and Śiva emanated from him. This form of Vishnu is described with the same features in the Satvata Samhita. In the Padma Puraṇa, chapters 27/3, these powers are ascribed to Vishnu, and he is also stated to be surrounded by the various powers to carry out these func- tions. It therefore becomes clear that the features pointed out by our opponents as peculiar to other gods become as much features of Vishnu.&#xA;The next point for consideration is what the quotation from the Padma Purāņa above conveys, namely, that Nārā- yana is the primary cause of all that exists. Vämana Purāṇa, chapter 24 (end of the chapter) states that the form of Śrīnivāsa is the primal form of Nārāyaṇa himself. It is in conformity with this that Pēy Alvar describes him as exhi- biting the two forms, namely, that of Vishnu and Siva. In chapter 21/2 of the same work, it is stated that Vayu made an incantation of the saving mantra Rama, and that Skanda did so also, having obtained the mantra from his father Śiva. The Brahmanda Purana, chapter 2, and Brahma Purāņa chapter 2 alike, state that it was Adiśēsha that became the sporting hill of God and thus gained the enjoyment of God&amp;rsquo;s perpetual presence on him. Both Varaha Purana, part II, chapter 3, and Padma Purana, chapter 32/10 state clearly that Srinivasa came down to the earth at the commencement of Kritayuga. Therefore the god whose image is on the southern bank of the Svami Pushkarini with all the features, such as the wearing of the matted locks, the cobra ornaments, worship with bilva, etc., is no other than Srinivasa, the con- sort of Lakshmi, the lord of Vaikuntha, who came to reside in Venkatachalam, worshipped by Skanda, Mahādēva and others. It is thus clear that He is Śrīman Nārāyaṇa and no other like Skanda or Siva.&#xA;When Rāmānuja thus concluded his arguments, the Yadava Rāja told the Saivas that he felt convinced that their arguments were all satisfactorily met by Rāmānuja, and that,&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;17&#xA;if they had anything further to urge, they might do so the next day, and requested Rāmānuja that further arguments will continue on the following day. When again they as- sembled, the Saivas urged that the deity on the south bank of Svāmi Pushkarini is either Skanda or Mahādēva, and if not, it must be Harihara; but it never could be Vishnu. They urged in support that the emblems of Vishnu were not in- compatible with the deity being Skanda, as the Vamana Purāņa, chapter 21/2 where the origin of Skanda is recounted by Brhaspati, it is stated clearly that Skanda had a part of Vishnu in him. Since Skanda is said to have one head and two arms, or six heads and twelve arms, it may not be in- appropriate if sometimes he had one head and four arms. If, however, this is objected to, we claim the image to be that of Mahādēva on the same argument as the Vaishnavas who claim these peculiar features as not unsuitable to Vishnu, the primal cause of the universe, as we claim Mahādēva to be the primal cause. Even otherwise since the Vaishnavas claim that the god is Vishnu, because of some of the Vaish- ṇava Āgamas, so we call him Siva because of the Saiva signs in the image. Again if it is inappropriate to regard him as Mahādēva, he is certainly Harihara, since the signs of both Vishnu and Śiva are found in the image, and even Vaishnava saints have so described them. Therefore in Skanda Purāņa chapter 8, Srinivasa is described as Mahādēva, as also in several other places, where the two terms are used together. Therefore we may be certain that it is Harihara and nobody else. Similarly in the Padma Purana, chapter 27/4 des- cribing the coming down of the God, he is said to have worn face mark resting upon a base resembling that of the eighth day moon. This part moon is a characteristic of Śiva, and is generally associated with him. Therefore the image must be regarded as that of Harihara. Any other contention beyond the three seems to us unacceptable.&#xA;The Yadava Rāja replied that he could not agree with the Saivas in respect of the image being regarded as either Skanda or Mahādēva, but whether it could be Harihara, he would ascertain from Rāmānuja himself. Rāmānuja replied that all that was urged by the Saivas was wrong. In chapter&#xA;18&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;10 of the Bhagavat Gita, Krishna says everything that exists has a part of Vishnu in it, and therefore even Skanda and Mahādēva must necessarily contain a part of Vishnu. It does not require much further argument. In the Vamana Purāṇa, chapter 21/2, it is stated that Skanda is said to have had his three baths daily and worshipped Nārāyaṇa in the presence of Vayu who was also there performing his penance. Since he is said to be contemplating upon Nārāyaṇa to get rid of the sin of killing Tarakāsura, and since, in chapter 24/5 of the same work, Vayu is said to be performing penance long since to God Srinivasa in the same place, and since Skanda is said to have been worshipping Srinivasa ever since, it would be absurd to say that the worshipping Skanda and the worshipped Śrīnivāsa are one and the same.&#xA;Further, another question arises. It is admitted that on the south bank of the tank, there is an image of a god en- shrined in a temple. It is stated equally clearly in the same Purānas that Skanda came there to perform penance to Vishnu to get rid of the sin of his having killed Tarakāsura in battle. These Purāņas again say that in the same place God Śrīnivāsa appeared for the benefit of Brahma and the other Devas, the Brahmarishis and Rajarishis and others who were performing penance there with the same object. The question therefore airses whether the God referred to as being on the south bank of the tank is, in the circumstances, Skanda or Śrīnivāsa. It can hardly be Subrahmanya because he is said to have come there to get rid of his sin by penance, attracted towards the place for gaining the grace of Vishnu, and therefore one among the many like Brahma and others who were similarly engaged. How can Skanda then be regarded as the object of worship to the others? More than this, the same Purāņas assert that Skanda came daily from the Kumāra Dhārikā to offer worship to Srinivasa, and there- fore it cannot be said, on their authority, that Skanda&amp;rsquo;s habi- tual residence was on the south bank of the Svami Pushkariņi. Nor is this fact of the establishment of Skanda in a shrine stated in any of our authorities. Moreover the same Pură- nas state that Sankarāja and Tondaman Chakravarti built a shrine to Vishnu who appeared in response to the penance of&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;19&#xA;the Devas and the Rishis. Therefore their contention has no evidence to rest on. It is thus clear that the deity there is not Skanda.&#xA;.&#xA;Since even the Śrutis state it clearly that Vishnu came down from Vaikuntham to show himself to Brahma, Indra and the Rishis performing penance on the south bank of the tank, therefore it is impossible that the deity there is Skanda; nor is it any more possible that it is Mahādēva, who it has already been stated was there to worship Vishnu, and since it is clearly stated that it is Nārāyaṇa who appeared there in response to the penance of these, there is no room for the inference it could be Mahādēva. As was already stated Mahādēva was already there at the foot of the hill even before Skanda appeared. It is also stated clearly in the Vamana Purāņa that, after offering worship along with others when Śrīnivāsa appeared on the hill, Mahādēva returned to Kailasa as the others returned to their own places, and that Śrīnivāsa alone was in residence on the hill. Therefore it cannot be said that Mahādēva is in residence where Srinivasa actually is. More than this, it is well-known that the prescribed image for the worship of Mahādēva is a linga. It is not usual to worship Śiva in the form of an image with all organs. That that is the accepted form of worship is stated in the Bhavishyōttara Purāṇa, chapter 2. In the Varaha Purāņa chapter 29 containing the Śrīnivāsa Ashtottara, it is stated that he was being meditated upon by Sankara residing at the foot of the hill, and in the Brahmanḍa Purāņa, Śrīnivasa is called .Kalagamya, worshipped by Kalakantha. The image on the south bank therefore can only be Nārāyaṇa and not Mahādēva. The matted locks and the nāga jewels cannot be said to be peculiar to Mahādēva since the god there is given the peculiar name of Nārāyaṇa. It is not unusual that among the avataras of this Nārāyaṇa some are exhibited as wearing matted locks, etc. It is not correct, as the Saivas contend, to say that Mahādēva is the cause of all on the analogy of the Vaishnavas claiming that Vishnu is the cause of all. Because in the Śrutis, it is only Nārā- yana that is declared to be the cause of all. It is thus clear that this God is not Mahādēva (Śiva). He cannot be des-&#xA;20&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;cribed as Harihara because the weapons peculiar to Vishnu alone, such as the conch and the discus, are worn by Śrī- nivāsa. He is further described to have come from Vai- kuntha specifically. Even the Alvārs who mention the Saiva features in the Prabandhas speak of the God as Nārāyaṇa notwithstanding these features. Further than that it is stated. that on the occasion when Srinivasa appeared, the gods in- cluding Brahma and Rudra are said to have come there and offered worship. It cannot be said that Brahma offered wor- ship to Siva, his son. Further it is stated in the Vamana Purāņa that Mahādēva himself stated it clearly in the Vamana Purana that it was not appropriate he should touch the un- created (apprākṛtam) image of Bhagavan. It is thus clear that the image cannot be described as Harihara. The fact that the image of Vishnu wears the upright face mark resting on a base like the moon grown eight digits cannot be held to mean the carrying of the crescent moon on the head of Śiva, as it is clearly stated that the mark was worn on the face. Further in regard to the various avataras of Vishnu, such as the fish, the tortoise, the boar, etc., these are determined on the evidence of the words in the Śruti, not by the marks or other signs on the face and arms. Therefore since it is clearly stated that God Nārāyaṇa came from Vaikuntham as Śrīnivāsa on the Venkatachala hill, the appearance of features like the matted locks, and the Naga jewels cannot be held to indicate the Saiva character of the god.&#xA;Seeing that Rāmānuja had successfully met all the arguments urged by the Saivas in their support, the Yadava Rāja inquired whether the Saivas had anything else to urge in support of their contention. They said in reply that they had become dumbfounded by the power of incantation of Rāmānuja, and further if, as the ruler of the locality, he carried out the wishes of Ramanuja by force, they were in no position to do anything against him. We would be satis- fied however completely if Ramanuja could show us that his contention is acceptable to the god himself. The Yadava Rāja said in reply that, having once diverted his mind from the truth by false arguments, they were still attempting to persist, and warned them that if they so persisted; he would&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;21&#xA;be compelled to punish them, and, turning to Rāmānuja, asked him to demonstrate to the Saivas that his contention has the approval of the god himself.&#xA;Rāmānuja resolved within himself to put the question beyond doubt by making the god wear the conch and the discus, as he is described in chapter 11 of the Brahmānḍa Purāṇa. Then addressing the king, he said that, if the king would be pleased to make a conch and a discus, the special symbols of Vishnu, and the rope, the goad and other weapons characteristic of other gods, and place them in the sanctum of the temple, the weapons that the god assumes would put it beyond a doubt whether he is Vishnu or any other god.&#xA;This was agreed to, and each party got the weapons characteristic of Vishnu and other gods made, and proceeding with the king to Venkatachala placed these in front of the god, and locking the door kept watch all round. Rămānuja on his part approaching the God by means of his Yoga prac- tices prayed that he might assume his own weapons as before, and put the question beyond a doubt. After daybreak the Yadava Rāja took both the parties along with him and got the door opened, when to his surprise, he saw the image of Śrīnivāsa wearing the conch and the discus. Thereafter he became a devotee of Rāmānuja and punished those who set up this mischievous contest. He became thenceforward Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s disciple, accepting from him the Vaishnava initia- tion of the holy branding and other ceremonies, and con- tinued to be his devoted disciple. Thereafter Rāmānuja satisfied with what had been done, got the king&amp;rsquo;s judgment published and restored the old form of puja according to the practice of Vaikhanasa Agama, having duly performed the great ablution as an initial purificatory ceremony to the god &amp;ldquo;and the temple. Further he took steps to restore the damaged Vimana Anandanilaya in accordance with the pres- cription of the Vaikhanasa Agama, and put round the neck of the Bhagavan a garland of gold containing an image of Pad- mavati, and re-established the deity as before. Having thus got rid of the danger from the Saivas to the Vishnu temple, and, making Yadava Rāja who was his disciple do everything&#xA;•&#xA;22&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;required to conduct the regular worship in the temple, Rāmā- nuja retired to Lower Tirupati (Govindarajapattana) and remained there for sometime.&#xA;Fourth Stabaka&#xA;Rāmānuja while himself residing in Tirupati (Lower Tirupati) saw that the Friday ablution (abhisheka) was performed every week as prescribed in the Ananda Samhita of the Vaikhānasa Agama. He also arranged that that for Śrīnivāsa the upright face mark should be of pacchaik- karpuram (preparation of camphor) as prescribed in the 27/41st chapter of the Padmapurāņa, and Bhavishyottara Purāņa 7/11. It was laid down by him that thenceforward this ought to be the upright face mark for three days begin- ning Friday, and for the following three days beginning Monday, this mark should be of white earth. He also prescribed the application of collyrium to the eye over and above this. On Thursdays the jewellery worn by the God should be removed completely, and the image should be dressed all over in flowers as prescribed by him. This flower dress should be removed on the following Friday, and the upright face mark should be made on the forehead of the image with the sacred earth (tiruman). The image should also be made to wear the under cloth and the upper cloth. Then the morning worship ought to be performed. Afterwards the image should be given ablution, and then decorated with all the jewels with the upright face mark of camphor as before. He further prescribed that on Fridays the Näcchiyar Tirumoli of the Prabandham sung by Godā, an incarnation of Bhudevi should be sung, as in the removal of the jewels worn by the image, the golden representation of Padmavati would also be removed to the regret of the god. He further arranged for the celebration of the festivals to the god. As there were no streets laid down for taking out the god, he made arrangements for the laying out of the streets for the purpose. He also arranged for the continu- ance of the worship in the temple by making it the duty of those descended from one Bimbădhara who was peculiarly attached to the god, was an expert in the Vaikhanasa Agama,&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;23&#xA;and who received the Vaishnava initiation of Panchasam- skāra from himself. Having got all these arrangements made through the Yadavarāja who had become his disciple, Rāmā- nuja set about, and arranged for the installation of the images of the Alvārs in the Govindarāja temple at Tirupati at the foot of the hill. This he did, as they themselves in their works thought it polluting the hill to go up even for worship, and therefore worshipped God on the hill from a distance, because it is stated in the Vamana Purāṇa, chapter 21/2, that great rishis like Šuka, Bhṛgu, and devotees like Prahlada, and kings like Ambarisha, all regarded the hill Venkatachala as abode of Vishnu, and therefore too sacred to be trodden&#xA;upon.&#xA;an&#xA;Sometime before this, it happened that a Chola ruler by name Krmikantha destroyed several Vishnu temples and carried his destructive work even into the holy place of Govinda Rāja at Chitrakūta (Chidambaram). Some of the Vaishnavas of the locality carried the Utsava image (move- able festival image) from there, and removed themselves for safety to Tirupati at the foot of the hill, the larger image of the sanctum having been thrown into the sea by order of the Chola. Having heard of this calamity with great sorrow, Rāmānuja set up another image in the sanctum, and with the utsava image brought by the Vaishnavas instituted a regular system of worship in the temple of Govinda Raja in Lower Tirupati. All this Ramanuja did through the Yadava Rāja, resident at Nārāyaṇapura, who fixed a spot on the bank of a tank to the south of the town of Tirupati, and there in- stalled the images of Govinda Rāja. He then built the temple and a town round it by name Rāmānujapura, and in- stituted a course of worship as in Tirupati on the hill. Having carried all these out through the Yadava Rāja by exhibiting to him the great devotion that he himself felt for Srinivasa, Rāmānuja returned to Srirangam. He made three or four visits afterwards on occasions and instituted various services in the temple as occasion demanded. The Yadava Rāja carried out everything as arranged by Rāmānuja.&#xA;of these occasions Rāmānuja instituted in the temple of Govinda Raja the shrine for the goddess Gōda, who as a&#xA;4&#xA;24&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALÁ&#xA;vyuha (manifest form) of Lakshmi, was found in his garden of basil and brought up by Bhatṭanātha. Thereafter the Yadava Rāja arranged for the conduct of the worship of Govinda Rāja in the month of Ani (August-September) as also the bathing festival in the month of Margali (December- January). The Yadava Raja then constructed houses in the four streets of Ramanujapura, and granted them as a free gift to devotees of Vishnu like Tirumalai Nambi, Ananta Alvān, and others. He also built the bazaar streets to the north-west of the temple and a granery for paddy to the east of the town.&#xA;Fifth Stabaka&#xA;Relating to the story of the step well and the golden well.&#xA;As has been related in the 2nd part of the Varaha Purana, chapter 10, Tonḍaman Chakravarti was ruling the locality at the beginning of the Kali age. He used to visit the temple of Srinivasa by the underground passage called the Nrisimha cavern. On one occasion this Chakravarti having been driven out by enemies went through the secret passage to the temple at dead of night. In consequence of this intrusion, it is said that Śrī Dēvi hid herself in the chest of Srinivasa, while Bhu- dēvi sheltered herself in the well dug by Ranga Dasa for watering the flower garden. Hearing these stories from the old people in the locality, Rāmānuja arranged to set up images of Śrīnivāsa with Bhūdēvi on the bank of the step well con- structed by Ranga Dasa, and arranged for their daily worship. He also asked that flowers, basil, etc., used in wor- ship of Śrīnivāsa may be dropped into that well for the sake of Bhūdēvi. On one occasion when Alavandar undertook a visit to Tirupati, he found that Tirumalai Nambi, who used to bring water from the Pāpanāśa tank and bathe the images in it, on that particular day, was not able to do so owing to illness. Alavandar took the occasion to address a prayer to God Srinivasa that he might accept the water from the well formerly constructed by Ranga Dasa, as the equivalent of water from Pāpanāśa, and ordained that thereafter the water from that well should be regarded as of equal holiness with&#xA;6&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;25&#xA;that of either Pāpanāśa or Akāśa Ganga. It has therefore be- come the habit in consequence that the water of that well was being used for all holy purposes in the temple. Having heard of this, Rāmānuja ordained that the water of Pāpanāśa, Ākāśa Ganga, and this well called Sundarasvami well were all of equal holiness, and the water of any of these should be used for all purposes in the temple. The two wells referred to above, the step well of Ranga Dasa, and the Sundarasvāmi well were stated to have been originally constructed for the kitchen convenience of Sri Devi and Bhuūdēvi. Having fallen into neglect for sometime, it is stated that the gardener Ranga Dāsa repaired them and made them fit for use. This is stated in the 9th chapter of the Varāha Purāņa, part ii.&#xA;In the Bhavishyottara Purana, chapter 13, it is stated that this was done by Tondaman Chakravarti in his previous birth. Chapter 7 of the Brahma Purāņa, however, contains a state- ment that the well was actually constructed by Bhudēvi, and that the flower garden was made by the Sudra (probably Ranga Dāsa). In the Bhavishyottara Purana, it is stated that the devotee Ranga Dasa met the Vaikhanasa temple priest Gopinatha on the way, and discovered the god at the foot of the tamarind tree. Therefore, in constructing the temple, he took care that the tree was not affected by the structure. In chapter 9 of the Varaha Purana in the section bearing on Ranga Dasa, Ranga Dasa is said to have constructed the tem- ple. In the story of Tondaman Chakravarti in chapter 10, it is stated that God commanded the Chakravarti to construct the shrine, which he attempted to do between the tamarind tree and the champaka tree without hurting either, and when the Chakravarti was actually exercised as to how to bring in a temple of the size within the narrow limits, it is also stated. that the trees of themselves moved out of their place to make room for the temple. On the basis of these stories Rāmānuja recognised that these trees were fit for being worshipped and ordained daily worship of these as well.&#xA;The explanation for the Naga jewels on the image.&#xA;On a previous occasion, a Gajapati king by name Vira Narasimha was on a pilgrimage to Rāmēśvaram (Sētu). He26&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;came to Venkatachala in the course of his journey, and having had his bath at the Svami Pushkarini offered worship at the temple of Śrīnivāsa. Having done so, he ordered the con- struction of a tower for the temple to complete the structure. Having gone forward on his pilgrimage taking Srirangam and other holy places on the way, he returned to Venkatachalam after his visit to Rāmēśvaram and remained there to complete the structure of the tower. During his stay he dreamt one night that a serpant came to him and addressed him as follows: &amp;ldquo;O Gajapati. I am this Venkatachala. Your con- structing this big tower on the hill gives me great pain. I had therefore to proceed to the God and twine myself round his arm in carrying my appeal to him.&amp;rdquo; Having heard this, the king consulted elderly folk in the place. They told him in reply that it was a fact on the authority of the Purāņus, that the hill undoubtedly was the great serpant, Sesha, or Ananta, and that the construction of a great tower for the temple was likely to be painful to the serpant Ananta. They advised him therefore to desist. Having heard this, the Gajapati completed the tower without carrying through the whole of his project, and, as an expitiation for the pain that he gave to Ananta; he made a golden jewel in the shape of Ananta and asked it to be put on the god as a jewel. The orthodox folk round about objected to this as the jewel was characteristic of other gods, but he was assured by the god himself, assuring them through one possessed of his spirit, that the jewel was acceptable to the God. It was thus made clear to Rāmānuja that, from the days of Vira Narasimha, this Nāga jewel was worn on one of the arms of the god. On further enquiry, Rāmānuja found, from the accounts in the Bhavishyottara Purāņa and in chapter 2 of the Brahma Purāņa, that the God was presented with this Nāga jewel for both the hands by Akāśa Raja on the occasion of the marriage of Padmavati to the God. Having ascertained this he ordained that the Naga jewel ought to be placed on both the hands of the image.&#xA;Next follows the story of Nrisimha: In the Skanda Purāṇa, in the section dealing with the river Svarnamukhari, it is stated that God Sankara performed a penance for some- time on the west bank of the Svami Pushkariņi in contempla-&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;27&#xA;tion of God Nrisimha, and that, in this place, Nrisimha ap- peared before the penitent Śiva. It is also stated in the 61/29th chapter of the first part of the Varāha Purāņa, in the Ashtottara Sata Nāmāvaļi (a string of 108 names) some of the Saivas who lived about that time wanted to build a temple on the west bank of the tank for both Sankara and Nrisimha who appeared in response to his penance. The Vaishnavas oppos- ing it pointed out that according to the Purāņas Śiva who wished to reside there with Vishnu was asked by the latter to reside below the hill in the south-eastern direction. They also pointed out that the hill Venkatachalam is a divine hill sacred to Vishnu, and therefore any representation of Śiva should not be installed therein. So saying they succeeded in stopping the building of the temple. Afterwards when Rāmānuja was there, seeing that God Nrisimha was of a very austere form, and since a separate shrine for this God would lead to trouble with the Saivas, found authority in the Varaha Purana, first part, chapter 61/29, to regard God Srinivasa himself as Nri- simha in form, and therefore set up a separate shrine in the temple of Srinivasa with the tower called Ananda-Nilayam in front of Srinivasa himself and ordained the conduct of the worship of this form of Vishnu there.&#xA;The image of Nrisimha half way up the hill.&#xA;The Markandēya Purāṇa, chapter 2, states that a disciple of Agastya by name Suddha along with the Rishi Märkandeya once went up the hill of Venkatachalam. On the way, near the cavern sacred to Nrisimha, it is stated that Märkandeya had a vision of Nrisimha. On the basis of this Rāmānuja set up a Nrisimha image on the spot where God Nrisimha appeared before Markandeya, and arranged for the worship of this deity also.&#xA;Application of the camphor preparation on the chin of Srinivāsa and the hanging of the shovel.on the temple tower.&#xA;Rāmānuja had directed one of his disciples Anantārya, a great devotee of Vishnu, to maintain the flower garden for the service of Śrīnivāsa. Anantārya took great interest in this work and was doing all the work of the garden himself without seeking assistance of others, and when-&#xA;28 -&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;ever earth had to be dug and removed, he drew upon the assistance of his pregnant wife to carry the earth for him. On this, God Srinivasa was moved to pity for the woman, and, assuming the form of a young bachelor (vatu), took the basket of earth from the lady and was carry- ing it himself. Anantarya was wild with the young bachelor for doing what he regarded as an impertinent act. All this warning fell on deaf ears. Getting angry once, he struck the bachelor with his shovel, which struck him at the chin and left a depression there. When he went to worship Srinivasa that day, he found blood dripping from the God&amp;rsquo;s chin. Guessing that it was no other than Srinivasa himself that appeared as the offending bachelor, he collected the pollen from the flowers of Vishamacchada and pressed it on the wound to stop the blood, and begged the God to excuse him for the offence of hurting him. Pleased with his devotion Śrīnivāsa thought it but right that the wound should remain as it was, and asked him to place the shovel with which he hit him at a prominent place in the temple, so that it may be seen by all. This was carried out and ever since that time, on the occasion of the daily worship, Śrīnivāsa is anointed with the camphor mixture on the mark of the wound at the chin.&#xA;The Puraṭṭāsi (September-October) Festival.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As directed by Rāmānuja, Anantarya (Ananta Alvār) had set himself up in Venkatachalam, having made a big flower garden, and a large tank to irrigate it. He was engaged in the daily service of supplying flowers to the temple from this gar- den. God Śrīnivāsa demonstrated this devotion of Antärya to the public by a miracle. He assumed the form of a prince and made Padmavati take the form of a princess. They both of them engaged themselves in the pleasant occupation of collect- ing flowers every night in Anantārya&amp;rsquo;s flower garden. Having found that somebody was depriving the garden of its best flowers so sedulously cultivated for God&amp;rsquo;s service, Anantārya kept watch for eight days, and at dead of night on the eighth day discovered the pair moving about in the garden. He tried to capture both of them, but God Srinivasa managed to dodge him and enter the temple. But Padmavati, in the form of the&#xA;·&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;29&#xA;princess, could not run as fast, and was actually caught and tied up to the champaka tree in the garden. Padmavatī with great deference prayed to Anantārya that he might capture the husband, but might let her off, treating her as his own. daughter. In the course of this colloquy day dawned, when the temple establishment entered the temple and opened the sanctum. God Srinivasa let them know, through one of them, that what took place in the garden was his own doing and com- manded that Anantarya might be brought down together with Padmavati. On hearing this Anantārya was transported with joy. He came over with his basket of flowers, carrying Padmavati on his head, and set her down at the feet of Sri- nivāsa. Having heard of this occurrence, Rāmānuja directed that, in memory of this miracle, the God may be taken in pro- cession, on the seventh day of the Puraṭṭāśi festival, round the town, and on the eighth, the day of the car festival, Anantārya may be presented with a garland of flowers and other gifts from the God himself.&#xA;The story of the God at the foot of the Tamarind Tree.&#xA;Tirumalai Nambi (the maternal uncle of Ramanuja and a grandson of Alavandar) was commanded by Alavandaār to go and settle down at Tirupati and perform regularly the duty of bringing water for the ablution of the image in the temple there. He had settled down at Tirupati for this purpose, and, when Alavandar had passed away, Ramanuja went over to him to have the Ramayana expounded to him. Well pleased with this, Tirumalai Nambi expounded to Rāmānuja the Ramayana with all its esoteric explanation. Rāmānuja arranged to live in the town of Tirupati at the foot of the hill as he thought it would be desecration that he resided on the hill. Tirumalai Nambi on the contrary, engaged in the temple service, had necessarily to live there and the two had arranged to meet half way up the hill. They fixed upon a tamarind tree far down the hill as their meeting place where the Ramayana was being expounded regularly. Having gone through this course of instruction for a year, Tirumalai Nambi one evening felt some contrition that because of this Ramayana work, he had to forego the midday worship of Srinivasa. Having expressed&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;31&#xA;came possessed of him, to be taken over to Venkatachala. They therefore removed the image from there, and, carrying it to Tirupati, set it down in front of Tirumalai Nambi at the foot of the tamarind tree, as he was expounding to Rāmānuja Vibhishana seeking refuge of Rama. Being quite surprised at the coincidence, both Nambi and Rāmānuja took the image of Rāma from there with Janaki his consort and other attendants, and set these up according to the Vaikhānasa Agama, and ordained the daily worship of these along with the worship of Śrīnivāsa as has been stated in the Tiruchanda Viruttam of Tirumaliśai Alvār (87).&#xA;The Story of Varaha.&#xA;Rāmānuja also ordained that the God Varaha on the west bank of the Svami Pushkariņi should be worshipped first by those going to worship Śrīnivāsa. This was laid down in several Purāņas describing the merits of Venkatachala such as the Padmapurāṇa, as they state it clearly that Varaha was there even before Srinivasa; that he should be wor- shipped before Śrīnvasa is laid down in the 8th chapter of the Brahma Purana, and in the 5th chapter of the Bhavish- yottara Purāna.&#xA;When Rāmānuja had set up the image of Govinda Raja in his shrine in Lower Tirupati and ordained that worship should be conducted as if Venkatachalam and Tirupati were one place of worship, he arranged it that when the final evening ceremony of sending God to sleep was performed, these people engaged in temple service should be presented with garland in the shrine of Visvakṣēna (an attendant god answering to the controller of the household), before locking up the temple for the night.&#xA;Sixth Stabaka&#xA;The account of Tirumalai Nambi&amp;rsquo;s Association with Tirupati. Tirumalai Nambi (who, by the way, was according to the Guru Paramparas a grandson of Alavandar), was one among the younger men in Srirangam, who was in the habit of attending at Alavandar&amp;rsquo;s exposition of Vaishnavaism. Āļa- vāndār whose name was Yamunacharya was among the&#xA;5&#xA;30&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;this feeling before God Srinivasa that evening, he went to bed as usual. God appeared before Tirumalai Nambi in a dream and promised to show himself to him at midday thereafter. Tirumalai Nambi went about his work as usual with the re- collection of this dream. One midday, Nambi felt the smell of civet, musk, the camphor mixture, etc., associated with the worship of God as when the temple worship was going on, and suddenly he saw before him a pair of foot impressions of the God with the leaves of basil offered in worship. Surprised at this sudden appearance both Nambi and Rāmānuja built up a shrine for the foot-mark at the foot of the tamarind tree, and, consecrating it, properly arranged for its daily worship. As several Purāņas have stated that in the age of Kali, God Venkaṭanatha was the God complete, Nambi and Rāmānuja arranged that all people without distinction of caste, including the Chandalas, might come and worship there at the foot of the tamarind tree. They were to take their bath at a tank called Chanḍāla Tirtha near about, and then come and circum- ambulate and offer worship at the foot marks of the god under the tamarind tree. As prescribed in chapter 62 of part i of Varaha Purāņa, every one that wished to worship Śrīnivāsa had to come to the spot, and, crying out the name of Govinda, should offer worship at the foot and then proceed higher up the hill to the temple.&#xA;The story of the image of Śrī Rāma in the temple of&#xA;Śrīnivāsa.&#xA;Once upon a time, as it is stated in the Vasishta Rāmā- yaṇa, there lived on the banks of the Kritamālā (Vaigai) to the south-west of Madura of the south, there was a Rishi by name Viśvambara in the town of Kalavingam (sparrow). Having recollected the offer of protection by Rama to Vibhishana, he set himself up in penance to realise this particular act of grace. on the part of Rama. Śrī Rāma was gracious enough to give him a view of his offer of protection to Vibhishana. That Rishi made an image of what he saw and set it up there in a shrine and worshipped it daily. Some time after, there was a great disturbance in the town, and the image of Ramachandra there directed the Vaishnavas there, through one of them, who be-&#xA;32&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;teachers (Acharyas) of Vaishnavism coming really two gene- rations after, but almost as the next important successor of the first Acharya Nathamuni. One of the main functions of these teachers is to expound the cardinal texts of Vaishnavism. On one occasion he was expounding the Tiruvaymoli, the prin- cipal work of Nammālvār regarded as an exposition in Tamil of the essence of the Veda. In the course of exposition of the third ten of the third Tiruvaymoli, he expatiated upon the great religious merit of the holy place Tiruvengaḍam and pointed out that, in such a holy place, it would be very desir- able indeed for one to render service to the God by providing water for his ablution and flower for worship and decoration. He wound up by expressing his great regret that at his age, he could not undertake the important and meritorious service. Young Tirumalai Nambi immediately got up from the audi- ence and volunteered to go to Tirupati and render this service to the God by residing there. To demonstrate the great devotion of Tirumalai Nambi, the God at Vengaḍam assumed the form of a hunter as Tirumalai Nambi carrying the water pot on his head was going towards the temple from the holy water of Papanasśa. The hunter begged of him for a little of the water that he was carrying, as he was very thirsty. Naturally Tirumalai Nambi declined to desecrate the water for the holy service by using a part of it for the purpose of drink, and so walked along quietly. The hunter kept follow- ing him as he thought. As the Nambi was repeating the Pra- bandha verses of Kaliyan (Tirumangai Alvar) and moving on, the hunter made a small hole in the pot by the arrow that he was carrying in his hand and gradually drank off the whole water. Having gone some considerable distance absorbed in his recital of the Prabandha, Tirumalai Nambi felt that the burden on his head had become very light, and discovered what had happened, as the hunter was still drinking the water. To his angry question whether it was proper for him to have done what he did with the water that he was taking to the temple for God&amp;rsquo;s service, the hunter coolly answered &amp;quot; O, Grandfather, do not be distressed about the water. Here a little way down is a holy pool of water from which you can take water for the temple service instead &amp;ldquo;. He led the Nambi&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;33&#xA;some little way and pointed to the holy water of Akāśa Ganga, and said that &amp;ldquo;This is the holy Ganges water itself, and you might bring this daily for our service&amp;rdquo;. Having said this to indicate that he was no other than God himself, he dis- appeared. Struck with wonder at this exhibition of grace by God to his devotees, he became the more devoted, and was serving God with water taken from the Akāśa Ganga instead of from the distant Pāpanāśa. Since the God himself address- ed him Tata (grandfather), he was thenceforward known Śrīśaila Natha Tätacharya or in Tamil, Tirumalai Tātācharya). Tirumalai Nambi had a son by name Rāmānuja. When he died early, he had adopted a son, who was known as Kumāra Tirumalai Nambi. Tirumalai Nambi often used to call him Tāta, and he came to be known thenceforward as Tatacharya. Since he was friendly to everybody in the locality, he became popular and was designated Tolappa Tatacharya or Tātārya, the friend. Having spent some time longer in this service, Tiru- malai Nambi ultimately passed away. Rāmānuja arranged in memory of Tirumalai Nambi the annual celebration of a fes- tival in which the God is given an ablution on the day follow- ing the Adhyayana Utsava (festival of the recital of Pra- bandhas). The image of the God is to be seated in the hall Mangalagiri. A number of Sri Vaishnava Brahmans used to go to the Akāśa Ganga and bring water from there chanting all the way the Prabandha of Tirumangai Alvar, and carry- ing the water in procession through the four streets running round the temple, bring it into the temple and with the water perform the ablution of the image and satagopa (sin-destroyer; this is of the shape of the head gear made of metal covered with gold, carrying on the top of it a pair of sandals symboli- cal of the feet of God).&#xA;The Account of Anantarya.&#xA;Anantarya belonged to the West country and was born at Lughunütanapura on the banks of the Kaveri (Sirupudu- paṭṭanam or Siruputtur). His father was à Kesavacharya of the Bharadvaja gotra. The date of his birth is given as Kali 4154 or Saka 975 expired, the year Vijaya, the month of Chaitra and nakshatra Chittra.. Having received his early&#xA;34&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;education and attained to much competency, he went down to Śrirangam, along with a number of others including Yegñesa, to Rāmānuja, who then was teaching in Srirangam. Rāmā- nuja welcomed them among his pupils and was giving them instruction in the Vedanta. One day Rāmānuja enquired. who among the number of his disciples was willing to vol- unteer service at Venkatachala to supply flowers, etc., to God Venkaṭanatha there. Most of them shrank from it as the place was cold and otherwise uncomfortable for a permanent residence, while Anantārya bravely got up and offered his services. Rāmānuja applauded his courage and sent him there. It is this that gave him the later name Ananta-purushārya, purusha being the equivalent of a manly man. He went to Vēnkaṭāchalam and laid out a big garden and even construct- ed a tank for the purpose of watering it. He took the flowers from this garden and offered them for the daily service in the temple. Having heard that at one time Yamunacharya had a little cottage put up near the temple and from there was doing the flower service, he built up a Mantapa on the same spot, and set up an image of Yamunacharya and arranged for con- ducting the worship of Yamunacharya in that pavilion. He generally strung the flowers together into garlands in that pavilion and took them over for service to the temple at the time of worship, carrying them on his head. Anantārya went on doing this service with his son who was called Ramanuja.&#xA;Seventh Stabaka&#xA;The organising of some other festivals as a result of a careful investigation of Venkatachala Mahatmyam.&#xA;The first point discovered was that the hill Venkatachala was Vishnu himself. This is stated in the following Purāņas; -Märkandeya Purāṇa, Part ii, Varāha Purāņa, part i, chap- ter 34/2, Vamana Purāņa, chapter 21/2, which state clearly that sages like Suka, great devotees like Prahlada and royal saints like Ambarisha all regarded the hill itself as a form of Vishnu, and therefore always remained at the foot of the hill. not to desecrate it by walking up the hill. Having known this, Rāmānuja himself followed the example by remaining&#xA;36&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;worship him daily which was not granted, and the fact that he was asked to make his abode at the foot of the hill to the south-west of it on the bank of the Kapila Tīrtha. Therefore all the distance between Svāmi Pushkariņi and Kapila Tirtha is marked out as holy for Vishnu. Therefore through a radius of one yojana (7 to 8 miles) round the Svāmi Pushkariņi is regarded holy because of the presence of God; and all that is laid down above, will apply to that whole area. Within this area no temple to any other god should or could be erected. Whatever people do in accordance with these regulations does not make them liable for any desecration. Tirumalai Nambi and Anantārya laid down these regulations of Rāmā- nuja before the God in the sanctum and prayed for his appro- val, which was expressed through one of the worshipping priests becoming possessed and giving divine assent. This was accepted by all those associated with the temple and in resi- dene on the hill.&#xA;The appointment of a bachelor (Ekangi) for taking care of whatever belongs to Srinivāsa.&#xA;Rāmānuja wanted someone to see that these regulations were carried out and that the worship itself was conducted according to regulations after the death of Tirumalai Nambi and Anantārya. Someone was also required to see that there was no quarrel about these matters. He was to be a man of learning, capable of instructing the local ruler, and of sufficient renunciation to have any desire for himself. So Rāmānuja arranged it that an unmarried man (Brahma- chari), such as is prescribed in the Paramēśvara Samhita be chosen and given the coloured robes of a sanyasin, and that he carry on the administration of the temple under the orders of Tirumalai Nambi and Anantārya. He also entrusted him with the image of Chakravarti Kumāra (Rama) and a seal with the mark of Hanuman for him to seal up the treasury, and a key with which to lock up the temple for the night.&#xA;The Installation of a Sanyasin (Yati) called Venkaṭanātha Satagōpa Yati by Ramanuja.&#xA;Rāmānuja during his first visit to Tirupati arranged to secure the gift of a village called Balamandyam irrigated byINTRODUCTION&#xA;37&#xA;a canal from the river by one Viṭṭala Dēva Raya, his disciple. He then asked a few families of Sri Vaishnavas to go and settle down in Tirupati. It was also at this time that he learnt the Rāmāyaṇa from Tirumalai Nambi. When after a year&amp;rsquo;s stay he wanted to return to Srirangam, he gave to Anantārya, who was disconsolate at parting, an image of his own likeness. He then left for Srirangam taking with him his cousin Govinda Nambi.&#xA;On the second occasion&amp;rsquo; of his visit to Tirupati, he had to settle the question whether the God there was Vishnu or any other. He established successfully and to the satisfaction of the Yadava Raja that it was Vishnu and, through the good offices of the Raja, he got the Vimäna tower, pavilion and such other structures for the temples built. It was also on this occa- sion that he took up the image of Govinda Raja from Chitra- kūta cast out by the Chola Krimikantha and got him estab- lished in a temple along with Godā Dēvi. He also got constructed through Tirumalai Nambi and Anantārya a shrine to Hanuman, and set up there the image of Chakra- varti Kumāra (Rama) given to him by Tirumalai Nambi. He ordained the bachelor who was a disciple of Anantārya and installed him there as described in the Paramēśvara Samhita, giving him the red robes and appointing him guardian of the shrine, Senapati. He also gave him the seal bearing the mark of Hanuman, a seal-ring, a pennon with the mark of the bell on it, and the key of the temple. He got the Yadava Rāja to pass an order that all those residing in Venkatachalam should act according to his commands. He then left for Srirangam. When again he visited Tirupati at the ripe old age of 102 in the year Kali 4220, Salivahana Saka 1041, he entrusted, in view to his own great age, the whole management to Anantarya who was then 66 years old to supe- rintend the management of the temple. Since the whole management could not be conducted by the&#xA;one&#xA;bachelor sanyasin, he also ordered he might be made a full sanyäsin, and given two or three assistants by appointing brahmacharis (bachelors) to these offices as in his own case. Seeing that a special kind of service should be instituted in the temple as described in the Tiruvaymoli of&#xA;38&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;Nammālvār, the third ten, third section, he appointed a spe- cial devotee for this purpose under the name Saṭagōpa Yati. He entrusted him with the worship of the image of Rāma. Then he chose from among the disciples of Anantārya four and made them bachelor sanyasins to assist him. He then told Yadava Rāja to conduct the management of the temple with the assistance of Anantārya, on account of his old age, owing to which it was not possible for him to be visiting Tirupati often. Under the direction of Anantārya, Saṭagopa Yati and the four Brahmacharins should actually carry on the services to the temple. These four bachelors took over the work of the one bachelor before, and put themselves under the direction of Saṭagopa Yati. He commended Anantārya as the most capable among his students, and bespoke the Ya- dava Raja&amp;rsquo;s consideration for him. He also informed the Ya- dava Raja that similar arrangements were required in all the Vaishnava shrines and that he had instituted 74 sim- hasanas (throne) for his disciples, and enthroned them on the acharyapitha and made them Acharyas.&#xA;What these āchāryapurushottamas should be is laid down in the Padmōttara, Chapter I. These Āchār- yapurushas as a body were to keep an eye upon the proper conduct of worship in all the temples dedicated to Vishnu. When a number of these came together, they must be treated with respect and rewarded as prescribed in the San- dilya Śruti. Having made these arrangements Rāmānuja pointed out to the Yadava Rāja that Anantārya was the senior- most among those present at the time, and that he might do everything with his advice. This person Anantārya, with some of your descendants, Saṭagopa Yati representing him, and a certain number representing Tirumalai Nambi should be ap- pointed for the future as such are not at the moment here present, and asked him to carry this out. He further instruct- ed that one belonging to the Satamarshana gōtra should be appointed for this service as Nathamuni, Kurukai Kāvalappan, Yamuna-muni and other great teachers belonged to this gotra. Having made these regulations, he got down the hill, for Govindarajapattinam wherefrom he left for Srirangam, after instructing the Yadava Rāja to see to it that the trouble created&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;39&#xA;by the Saivas was not repeated either in the one place or in the other.&#xA;The setting up of the image of Ramanuja in Venkatachalam.&#xA;Sometime after, Anantărya having heard of Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s nirvāņa (giving up of his body) prayed to God Śrī- nivāsa, with great sorrow, and put forward a request that, in recognition of the great services of Rāmā- nuja to humanity generally, he might condescend to permit of the recital of the centum Rāmānuja Nürṛandadi composed in praise of Ramanuja by one of his disciples, Amudan of Srirangam, during the Adhyayana Utsava, and that he might permit of the setting up of an image of Rāmānuja within the precincts of the temple and the arranging for the conduct of daily worship to that image with a view to the promotion of his teaching and the perpetuation of the arrangements that he had made. The God expressed his assent through one of those present.&#xA;On another occasion a certain Saṭagōpa who was appoint- ed to carry out the wishes of Srirangarāja (Śrī Rangaraja Vigñapti Karya) who instructed Rāmānuja himself in the Prabandhas of the Alvars took the opportunity, during the festival in the month of Karttika to appeal to Ranganatha for permission to go to Tirupati. Having worshipped the God Ranganatha, he proceeded to&#xA;proceeded to the Ramanuja mantapa (pavilion) in Srirangam and obtained the approval of Rāmā- nuja for his proceeding to Tirupati with a view to singing the Prabandhas in the Devagana on the hill. Having received Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s approval, he started on his journey. Having broken his journey at Conjivaram to worship Varadarāja, he proceeded onward to Lower Tirupati at the foot of the hill. Having offered his worship at the Govinda Rāja shrine, he walked up to the foot of the hill, and, worshipping again the foot-marks under the tamarind tree, and the Nrisimha image enshrined in the forest near about, he went up the hill to where Tirumalai Nambi and Anantārya were. Having ex- changed courtesies with them, he took his bath at the Svāmi Pushkarini, and, having completed his daily services, went and offered worship at the Varaha shrine as instructed in the&#xA;6&#xA;40&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;Tiruvōymoli of Parānkuśa, and then proceeded to the temple of Venkatanatha (Śrīnivāsa). There he offered his worship to the God in prescribed form, and having accepted his tīrtha (holy water) from the kaṭāha (the vessel in which the water used in ablution of the image is preserved), he also offered worship at the shrine of Visvaksēna, Nrisimha at Venkaṭā- chala, Garuda and other attendant deities in the temple. Then having got round the temple rightwise, he went into the pre- cincts of the God, and, as directed in the Periya Tirumoli, he sang the Tirumoli of the Alvar. Then, praying for the inter- cession of Lakshmi, he made his self-surrender to the God and had a complete view from head to foot of the image there. He was then commanded by God in the usual fashion to sing a few verses from the Prabandha of the first Alvārs. He did as he was commanded and pleased God immensely. Having been rewarded by God with the gift of the holy water and other things usual, in reward for his services, he went up to Tiru- malai Nambi and Anantārya. Having been requested by them to begin the Adhyayana Utsava daily by chanting the first ten of Periya Alvar&amp;rsquo;s Tirumoli. He rendered it musically first, and then the rest of the Prabandhas during the festival. He took leave and left for Srirangam and reported all that had taken place to Rāmānuja..&#xA;Well pleased with what had been done, Rāmānuja ordained that the Prabandha of the first Alvärs may be sung first, and then the other Prabandhas, all of them being alike set to music and musically chanted. In order that this may be done regularly he appointed one from among the descend- ants of Nathamuni for this particular task and gave him the designation Srisaila Vigñaptikarya, and sent him to Tirupati with a letter to Anantārya. Having reached Tirupati with the letter, this Śrīśaila Vigñaptikarya handed the letter over to Anantārya and went to the sanctum of Srinivasa along with Anantārya. Anantārya intimated to Srinivasa the wish of Rāmānuja in regard to Srisaila Vigñaptikārya, and, having received God&amp;rsquo;s approval, asked him to reside in Tirupati and keep conducting his services as directed by Ramanuja.&#xA;The above resume of the work Sri Venkatachala Itihasa Mālā gives more or less a clear idea of the contents of the&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;41&#xA;work. A critical evaluation of the material contained in it would be necessary before it can well be used for purposes of reconstructing a history of Tirupati so far as that important epoch is concerned. The epoch is of particular importance as practically the whole organisation of worship in the temple seems based upon the arrangements that Rāmānuja is believed to have made there.&#xA;The work claims to have been compiled by Anantārya. If he was the disciple of Rāmānuja deputed to carry out Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s directions and see to it that the affairs of the temple were managed satisfactorily thereafter is doubtful. From the details given in the work itself, he was Rāmā- nuja&amp;rsquo;s junior by about 36 years, and had been contem- porary not only with Rāmānuja but even with his uncle Tirumalai Nambi, so that Tirumalai Nambi, Rāmānuja and Anantārya between them would perhaps have covered about a century of time. The precise date given for the birth of Rāmānuja is Saka 939, equivalent to A.D. 1017, and, by all accounts, he is said to have lived for a period of 120 years, which would take him to A.D. 1137 for his last year. He must have passed away either that year or the year following. In the course of the narrative contained in this work, he is made to say to the Yadava Raja that he was too old to be able to make other visits to Tirupati as he was 102 years at the time. That would mean he had just about 18 years of life left, and that again would mean the actual date under reference is A.D. 1118 or 1119 when Anantārya is said to have been 66 years. That is the date for Rāmānuja so far as the Guru- parampara accounts and the account of the Itihāsa Māla are concerned. We have no means of checking this by any other direct sources of information, as we have none. But then this can be checked in a way by the traditional account of the life of Ramanuja which brings him into contact with rulers who lived at the time and rendered him assistance in various ways, such as for instance the Yadava Rāja who figures so largely in this narrative. There are three rulers that come into view in the account of his life, a Krimikantha Chola, a Chola sovereign who died from an abcess in the neck which was so bad and severe an attack that worms appeared in the&#xA;42&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;abcess. Hence the name. Of course if the Vaishnava accounts are to be believed in their entirety, he is supposed to have suffered from this fell disease because of the dessecration pur- posefully carried out in regard to the Vishnu temple of Govinda Rāja in Chidambaram. In regard to this particular matter we come upon what seems to be a very serious discrepancy. Assuming for the moment that the date as given for Rāmānuja in these works is correct, Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s life would be covered by the whole of the 11th century practically and the first 38 years of the 12th. If for our purposes we neglect the first 25 years or even 30 years of Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s life as uneventful and anterior to his having become anything prominent, it would bring us to the second half of the 11th century for his active life, and almost the following 40 years of the next century. During the former period, and a very considerable part of the latter, the Chola ruler happened to be the great Chola, Kulottunga Chola I, A.D. 1070 to 1118; his last year may have been a few years later.&#xA;He was followed by a professed Vaishnava Vikrama Chola who ruled from A.D. 1118 to 1136. He was in turn succeeded by Kulottunga Chola II, a comparatively young man and a devout Saiva. The unsettling of the arrangements in Chidambaram, and the throwing out of the main image of Govinda Rāja into the sea were acts of desecration said to have been brought about under the orders of this ruler, and the circumstances are described to us in literature, contemporary literature, that has come down to us. The Cholas were in the habit of confirming their accession to the throne by having themselves anointed in the coronation hall on the east bank of the tank in the temple at Chidambaram. The story is that when the anointing was over and the procession was formed to start from the hall to go round the town, the elephants, the horse and the foot soldiers of the court that had been drawn up, along with the contingents brought by the subordinate rulers, found too little room to move about, and finding that there was such a crush in front of the Nataraja shrine on account of this, the prince enquired what buildings they were that obstructed the front yard of the court so badly. Being told that it was the shrine of Govinda Raja lying there, he replied smartly that the place for the lying of Vishnu was not the&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;43&#xA;front yard of the temple of Naṭarāja, his favourite deity, but the sea, and ordered therefore that the Vishnu image might be cast into the sea. The order was probably carried out literally. This could have been only somewhere about A.D. 1135 or 1136, the year of accession of Kulottunga II. Kulottunga I was not fanatical enough to do that for one thing; and he made actual grants and even detailed arrange- ments regulating worship in respect of Srirangam about the year A.D. 1084, even providing for the recital of the Pra- bandhas of Kulasekara Alvar and Tirumangai Alvar. It would be difficult to imagine that he was responsible for this desecra- tion; the more particularly in the face of the definite state- ment in the works of Oṭṭa Küttan, the poet who was the tutor to Kulottunga Chola II as prince. This is one difficulty which it seems almost impossible to get over. From certain incidents related in the Itihāsa Mālā, it seems to be clear that Rāmānuja had already returned from the Mysore country where he had to reside for over a quarter of a century because of the offence that his principal disciple Kurattu Alvān gave to the Chola ruler, and of Rāmānuja having to go into exile as a result thereof to save himself from being molested by the Chola ruler for the time being. It is a well known fact, borne out by dated inscriptions, that he was responsible for the adoption of Vaishnavism by the Hoysala ruler Bitți Deva, who ever afterwards adopted the style Vishnu Vardhana, although the Kannada word Bitti is an actual Kannada form of the Sanskrit Vishnu. But this Vishnu Vardhana did not come to the throne till almost the end of the first decade of the 12th century. The third ruler under reference is a Yadava Rāja whose invitation it was that brought Ramanuja to Tirupati for the second time and who afterwards rendered so much service by assisting Rāmānuja in carrying out his instructions with respect to the temple at Tirupati as a local ruler responsible for the ordering of the worship in the temple. There is so far no inscriptional evidence for the existence of a Yadava Rāja so early, the earliest Yadava Rāja figuring in inscriptions coming almost about the end of the 12th century. But that is not a very great bar and cannot constitute a vital objection as there might have been Yadava Rājas ruling in the locality&#xA;44&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;who might not have done anything which would ordinarily be recorded in the inscriptions. The local rulers were known Yadava Rājas as a family name, and we know of Yadava Rājas who played important parts later. They must have had their ancestors as local rulers without having achieved any distinc-. tion to come down to us in inscriptions. It may be that the traditional date for Rāmānuja is pitched a little too early, and a readjustment of the dates may be necessary. But that is a question that cannot be definitely settled here and now.&#xA;Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s connection with Tirupati, however, need not be rejected on that account. The territory dependent upon Tirupati, as an important centre, had been brought under Chola rule when the second Chola Aditya of the new dynasty conquered the Tonḍamandalam and annexed it to the Chola empire. Later inscriptions record that that Chola died at 2 place called Tondaman Arṛür, a place now in ruins on the banks of the Svarṇamukhi not far from Kalahasti, called now Tondaman Nadu. There are inscriptions which name this place Tondaman Perur or Tondaman Pērāṛṛūr even. Therefore the Chola power must have extended in reality to this region pretty early on the establishment of the dynasty. This Chola Aditya&amp;rsquo;s dates would be the end of the 9th and the initial years of the 10th century, as his successor Parantaka came to the throne in A.D. 906. Aditya is said to have built 300 temples to Śiva on the banks of the Kaveri, clearly indicating his enthusiasm for Siva worship and his personal devotion to the promotion of Saivism. It would not be very difficult to imagine that since then there had been a certain amount of religious ferment, and if the Saivas made an effort to gain the upper hand to set up Saivism as perhaps the domi- nant religion, it would be nothing strange or even unnatural. The period of the great Chola rulers culminating in that of Rājarāja the Great, the builder of the temple at Tanjore, must have been a period of Saiva propaganda, that is the. whole of the 10th century with perhaps a decade or more of the previ- ous century being included in it. It is not unlikely that at some period, it must be in the latter half of the tenth century, there was a squabble over the character of the temple at Ven- kaṭāchalam, and a dispute between the Saivas and the&#xA;INTRODUCTION&#xA;45&#xA;Vaishnavas might have come to a head calling for the inter- vention of the Yadava Raja of Nārāyaṇavaram. Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s intervention might have been sought by the Vaishnavas even with the countenance of the Yadava Rāja to settle the question. The disputation that took place between Rāmānuja and the Saivas is given in full detail, and there is nothing in it that could be cavilled at in respect of the sources quoted in au- thority. Therefore Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s intervention in the affairs of Tirupati seems natural enough, and all the arguments that he adduced are arguments that are available for examination today. Without going into unnecessary detail in regard to this question Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s answers must be considered con- clusive for the believing people. But for the more critical, and to some extent unbelieving audience, the authorities quoted may not be acceptable in their entirety. But the following should ordinarily suffice. Be the form of the image what it may, some peculiar features of the image are certainly noted by the early Alvars themselves, these early Alvars and their followers subsequently, none of them had the slightest doubt that the shrine was a holy shrine of Vishnu, the peculiar fea- tures notwithstanding. It is not merely the Alvārs who have held that view. The author of the Silappadhikāram, Ilangō Adigal, who was certainly not a Vaishnava, he was probably a Buddhist, has simply no doubt that it was a Vishnu god in the shrine there, and describes it in the most graphic language so as to leave absolutely no doubt in regard to the matter. Coming further down in point of time, the place was a well recognised Vishnu shrine in the days of the later Pallavas, as the Tamil Mahabharata by Perumdēvanar, a contemporary of Nandivarman of Tellāru refers, in one stanza in the part of the work that is available to us, that Vengadam was a Vishnu shrine. Therefore there is a continuous tradition from the early centuries of the Christian era down to almost the 10th century A.D. that the shrine was a Vishņu shrine notwith- standing the peculiar features. The third stabaka of the work most effectively disposes of the contention successively that the figure may be that of Subrahmanya, or Siva Mahadeva, or even Harihara. A Rig Veda verse is quoted in authority for the contention that the hill tops were sacred to Vishnu. The verse&#xA;46&#xA;SRIVENKATACHALA ITIHASAMALA&#xA;as interpreted by Ramanuja makes it refer to Tirupati itself. But this need hardly be the case with Tirupati in particular, the vedic verse meaning it generally in respect of hill tops. That verse in the Rig Veda is reinforced by a passage in the Yajur Veda which puts it in more unmistakable terms that the governing deity of the hill region is Vishnu. It is probably this Vedic idea that was at the root of the statement conveyed in the Sutra of the Tolkäppiyam that the mountain region of land was a region sacred to Mayōn (Krishna-Vishnu).&#xA;In regard to the rest of the work the details of organisa- tion are probably correct as they do continue down to the present times. A suspicion has been cast upon the work, that it may be a modern composition foisted of course upon the name of Anandālvăr, the contemporary of Ramanuja. This is quite possible; but the work itself does not make the claim. A careful reading of the work does not show any- thing in it that should make the work a modern composition foisted upon an old name. There is nothing on the face of it to cast a suspicion upon the character of the work, and it would be safer to hold the work genuine till we came upon something precise which militates against that position. We are content to leave it there for the moment and leave it to our readers to judge for themselves whether the work is genuine or spurious.&#xA;EDITOR.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SavAl javAb</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/savAl-javAb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/savAl-javAb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE&#xA;HOLY SHRINE&#xA;OF&#xA;LORD SRI VENKATESVARA&#xA;(TIRUPATI)&#xA;An English Translation of&#xA;SAWAL-E-JAWAB&#xA;An authoritative, unique and hitherto unpublished&#xA;f 1800 A.D. in the form of&#xA;juestions and answers&#xA;BY&#xA;V. N. SRINIVASA RAO&#xA;1950&#xA;more detailed and fuller account of the Origin,&#xA;Significance and History of the Temple please read the author&amp;rsquo;s book&#xA;TIRUPATI&#xA;SRI VENKATESVARA-BALAJI&#xA;Price Rs 3-12-0&#xA;(Copies can be had from: Umadevan &amp;amp; Co., 16, Sembudoss Street, Madras 1, Higginbotham&amp;rsquo;s and Swadesamitran&amp;rsquo;s Book Stalls.)&#xA;OPINIONS&#xA;Not the least important service that the author has rendered to the cause of religious catholicity is the reproduction of questions and answers collected by the East India Company under the title &amp;lsquo;Sawal-e- Jawab&amp;rsquo; which were furnished by the Sthanikas in charge of the temple in the year 1800. Mr. Srinivasa Rao has earnt the lively gratitude of all those who are interested in the preservation of ancient traditions and the spirit that underlay our religious institutions and which has been obscured, if not forgotten, in the course of recent and purposeless controversies.&amp;quot;&#xA;-Sir C. P. Ramaswami Aiyar.&#xA;This well documented and attractive book with nine plates and a map is a geographical, ritualistic and spiritual aid to the pilgrim. Historical matters are discussed with learning and dispassion&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.&#xA;&amp;ldquo;The author&amp;rsquo;s purpose is not to pursue any pole- mics with Dr. S. Krishnaswami Aiyengar but to empha- size that &amp;ldquo;the shrine has always had a universal appeal by its non-sectarian tradition and the message it proclaims of the Oneness of the Atman and the Para- matman and of self-realisation by annihilation of Ahamkara&amp;rsquo; (P. 151). He expounds the other side of the medal in order to strike a true balance&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&#xA;(Continued on cover page 3)&#xA;THE&#xA;HOLY SHRINE&#xA;OF&#xA;LORD SRI VENKATESVARA&#xA;(TIRUPATI)&#xA;An English Translation of&#xA;SAWAL-E-JAWAB&#xA;An authoritative, unique and hitherto unpublished record of 1800 A.D in the form of&#xA;questions and answers&#xA;BY&#xA;V. N. SRINIVASA RAO&#xA;(All Rights Reserved by the Author)&#xA;REPRINTED FROM THE QUARTERLY JOURNAL OF THE MYTHIC SOCIETY, BANGALORE-2.&#xA;Price Annas Eight.&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;THE celebrated shrine of Sri Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara ot Vengadam-Tiru. malai-Tirupati, in Chittoor District, is one of great antiquity and unequalled sanctity. Inscriptions on the temple walls disclose that the Yadava Kings, and their Cola and Vijayanagara overlords, vied with each other in munificent gifts to the shrine contributing to the splendour of its festivals and providing amenities for the pilgrims visiting the shrine from all parts of India. After the final dissolution of the Vijayanagara Empire, the country round the shrine was acquired by the Sultans of Golconda who endeared themselves to their Hindu subjects by their toler- ance and liberal gifts to Hindu temples. Aurangazeb broke up these Kingdoms and on the ruins of the Sultans arose the Nizams of Hyderabad and the Nawabs of Carnatic and this temple came under the protection of the latter. These Nawabs allowed the institution to go on as usual contenting themselves with the surplus income from the temple which they farmed out to Hindu renters. They were receiving an aunual income of about two lakhs of rupees.&#xA;Muhammad Ali, the patron and protege of the East India Company assigned the revenues of this temple to the East India Company for restoring his authority in the Carnatic as a sure source of discharging his dues to the Company. (This was between 1744 and 1750 A.D.) The East India Company continued the practice of farming out the revenues and contented itself with protecting the shrine from the attacks of adventurers, who swarmed in this part of the country during the unsettled conditions pre- vailing after the break up of the Mughal Empire. This was also the period of weakness which afforded opportunities to the foreign merchants to acquire dominion in India. Muhammad Ali assigned the country round the temple, which was then included in the North Arcot district to the East India Company on 31 July 1801 when the direct management of the temple was taken over by the Company. The first Collector of North Arcot was Mr. Stratton&#xA;il&#xA;who was then styled the Collector, Western Polians. He made very careful and exhaustive enquiries not only about the territory. entrusted to him but also about the history, tradition and resources of this temple. He asked a series of questions on all aspects of its administration and answers were furnished by those in actual management of the affairs of the temple and the information gathered from these questions and answers is locally known as Sawal-e-Jawab&amp;rdquo; account. The arrangements he made for the management of the temple were mostly based on these reports. He constituted the country round Tirupati into a Taluk and the Tahsildar of Tirupati was in direct management of the temple which was expressed by the term &amp;ldquo;Amani&amp;rdquo; as against the previous practice of farming out the revenues to renters annually. The following account is a translation of a Telugu manuscript contain- ing questions and answers relating to the Stalapurana of the temple. There are several other sections relating to the internal administration of the temple, its resources, land, etc. but these are owned by private persons and mutts and guarded secretly and produced in sections before law courts in support of claims for or against the temple. So far, no authorised version of the &amp;ldquo;Sawal-e- Jawab&amp;rdquo; account containing the entire material has been made available to the public by the Devastanam authorities. The Gov- ernment have been equally reticent about the publication of the wealth of material that should be available with them, not only this, they have been refusing access to these records even to research scholars. The manuscript under translation is in the official style of the early nineteenth century and is undoubtedly genuine. The internal evidence in it shows that it was prepared in Fasli 1213, i.e. 1801-2 A.D. and it should be of considerable interest as showing the great veneration in which the temple has been held even so lately as about two centuries ago and the respect which the ruling powers have all along shown in preserving its ancient custoins and traditions without interference.&#xA;Further details about the temple and its administration will&#xA;be furnished in a separate sketch.&#xA;V. N. SRINIVASA RAO.&#xA;SAWAL-E-JAWAB&#xA;Question 1. How many Yugas (ages) have passed since Sri Venkatesvara took up his abode on these bills?&#xA;Answer. Sri Venkatesvara first manifested Himself before Brahma and other Gods, Rsis and Kings in the twenty-eigth Yuga before the present Kaliyuga. (Chapter 43 Vamana Purana.)&#xA;Question 2. After appearing on Tirumalai what induced Him to continue to stay here till now and give darsan to people?&#xA;Answer. Knowing that people in Kaliyuga will be of feeble faith and wanting in capacity to engage themselves in severe austerities, Brahma entreated the Lord to continue his stay here and give them the darsan which is sufficient to redeem them. To show His great mercy to mankind the Lord has been staying here to save and bless. (Chapter 2 of Brahmandapurana and chapter 1 of Brahmavaivartapuraņa.)&#xA;Question 3. Which is the mountain going by the name of Tirumalai-Tirupati and S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;acalam?&#xA;Answer. In the middle of the earth, which is (Panchasat. koti) five hundred crores of miles in extent, there is a great moun- tain called the Mahāmēru which is golden in colour. One of the peaks of this King of mountains is known as S&amp;rsquo;os&amp;rsquo;acalam, also as the son of Méru. (Chapter 26 of Vamana Purana.)&#xA;Question 1. When and by whom was S&amp;rsquo;as&amp;rsquo;acalam brought here from Mahāmōru?&#xA;Answer. Many years ago in Sri Vaikunta in the presence of the Lord a dispute arose between Vayu and the thousand-headed&#xA;2&#xA;Adi S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;a as to who was more powerful. In the contest, Adi S&amp;rsquo;ēs&amp;rsquo;a opened his thousand hoods and grasped tightly one of the peaks of Mount Meru. In his attempt to blow Adi S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;a away together with the peak, Vayu raised a terrible tempest which shook the heavens. Indra and the other Devas prayed to Adi S&amp;rsquo;ēsa (Ananta), who is the embodiment of satvaguna, to concede victory to the rude Vayu by releasing his hold of one of his hoods on the peak. On his doing so, a portion of the peak was blown away and fall- ing here became S&amp;rsquo;ēs&amp;rsquo;acalam.&#xA;Question 5. What is the extent of this range, north to south&#xA;and east to west?&#xA;Answer. According to Brahmandapurāņa, this range extends five thousand miles north to south and five hundred miles east to&#xA;west.&#xA;Question 6. Why is this mountain range called S&amp;rsquo;äs&amp;rsquo;acalam?&#xA;Answer. The Lord intending to reside here sent Adi S&amp;rsquo;us&amp;rsquo;a in advance and he was asked to remain here in the form of a mountain range. As Adi S&amp;rsquo;os&amp;rsquo;a himself is here in the form of a nountain, the range is called S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;acalam. (Chapter 3 of Brahmāndapurāṇa.)&#xA;Question 7. How did it aquire the name of Venkatacalam?&#xA;Answer. Once a Brahmin guilty of incest with a Candala woman consulted Rsi Vasista as to the best mode of getting rid of the sin. On his advice he came here on a pilgrimage. No sooner than he reached the top of the hill, his body burst into flame like a cracker. Soon he was found standing uninjured but with a brighter and more handsome form than before. Only his sins had been consumed away in flames. The Devas and Rşis who witnessed this miracle, named the hill Venkatadri or the extinguisher of sins. This is stated in chapter 1 of the Varāha- purana.&#xA;Question 8. What are the various names applied to this range and under what circumstances was each of them aquired?&#xA;Answer. Several names are given to this range in Brahma- purana and in chapter 4 and 5 of Brahmandapurana. Some&#xA;3&#xA;among them are (1) S&amp;rsquo;ès&amp;rsquo;acalam, (2) Vrisadri, (3) Vrisabadri, (4) Ven- katicalam, (5) Nārāyaṇadri, (6) Garudadri, (7) Anjan@dri and (8) Svarṇādri.&#xA;Nārāyaṇādri. An old Brahmin, named Naιāyaṇa, who was disgusted with life on account of his abject poverty and old age, deciding to end his life, got up the hill intending to throw himself down from its summit, but as soon as he had reached the top, the Lord appeared before him and blessed him with youth and unlimited wealth. On his prayer that the hill should be known thereafter by his name, the Lord granted the boon. (Chapter 3 of Brahmandapurāna.)&#xA;Vrisabadri. When Lord Venkatesvara killed Vriśabasura. He granted his wish that the hill should be called after his name. Hence it is known as Vrisabadri. (Chapter 4 of Brah- mandapuraṇa).&#xA;Vrisüdri. As there are many sacred thirthams on this range it is called Vrisādri.&#xA;Garudadri. As Garuda brought this hill from Sri Vaikunta for the sport of the Lord it is called Garudādri,&#xA;Narasimhadri. As there is the shrine of Narasimha in the centre of this range it is known as Narasimhaādri.&#xA;Anjanadri. As Anjana Devi begot Anjaneya, the great general of Sri Rama, by performing penance here, it is called Anjanadri.&#xA;(Note: Explanation for Svarnadri not furnished. This peak is a part of the&#xA;Golden Mountain-Mount Meru.)&#xA;Question 9. What sacred that has are there on this range and how have they acquied their names?&#xA;Answer. It is said in the puranas that there are three and a half crores of thirthas in various parts of these hills. The chief among them are: (1) Kumāradhara, (2) Tumburukona, (3) Kataha thirtha, (4) Akasa Ganga, (5) Papavinasam, (6) S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;a thirtha, (7) Cakra thirtha, (8) Pandava thirtha, (9) Svāmi Puskarani, (10) Gogarhham, (11) Bharadvaja thirtha, (12) Vai- kunta thirtha, (13) Aști thirtha, (14) Sanakādi thirtha,&#xA;4&#xA;(15) Yuddanirasta Rasayana thirtha, (16) Brahma thirtha, (17) Visvaksena thirtha, (18) Indra thirtha, (19) Kapiladhāra thirtha, (20) Vajra thirtha, (21) S&amp;rsquo;anka cakrādi pancha thir- tha, (22) Agneya thirtha, (23) Vamana thirtha and (24) Brahma Ksatriya-Vaisya-S&amp;rsquo;udra thirtha, etc.&#xA;Kumaradhāra. God Subramania killed Tarakasura in the wars between Devas and Asuras. At the suggestion of his father, God S&amp;rsquo;iva, he took bath in Kumāradhāra and he was freed from the sin. Again Nārāyaṇa, who was contemplating suicide on account of infirmity and poverty was advised by the Lord to take a bath in this thirtha and on doing so, he was blessed with youth and wealth. (Chapters 3, 4 and 5 Markandeya Purāṇa.)&#xA;cars.&#xA;Tumburu Kōņa. In some previous Yuga, two Rsis Nārada and Thumburu were travelling all over the world in their celestial Thumburu indulged in the praise of mortals. Suddenly he was dropped down to the earth from the celestical car. He bathed in this thirtha as a result of which his sin was washed away. The celestial car reappeared and took him back to heaven. (Garuda purana and chapter 51 of Brahmōttara purana.)&#xA;Kataha thirtha. This is otherwise called Thotti thirtha which is inside the prakāra of the temple. A sip of this water removes all evil influences and secures success in all undertakings. Though all castes are allowed to touch this thirtha, it is not con- sidered polluted. (27 Chapter, Skandapurāṇa.)&#xA;Akusa Gunga. The Lord sent an arrow into the ground and brought the Ganges here. A bath in it removes all sins and secures fulfilment of all desires.&#xA;Svāmi Puşkarani. It is not possible to describe adequately the greatness of this sacred thirtha. It is believed that in Dhanurmasa (Dec.-Jan.) Suklapaksa-dvadasi, early in the morning all the sacred waters of all the sacred places on earth and in heaven including the waters of the rivers, Ganga, Yamuna, Sarasvati, Kaveri, Godavari, Tungabhadra enter Svami Puskaraņi and bathe in it in order to purify themselves. The efficacy of a bath in this Puşkaraņi at such a time can easily be imagined. (Vamana Purana, chapter 30.)5&#xA;Papavinasam. All sins drop off at the very sight of this thirtha. A bath in it confers great merit. (Chapter 3, Brah. manda Purāṇa.)&#xA;Rasayana Thirtha.-Old persons, even those who have attained the age of hundred years, when they bathe in this thirtha become young and do not suffer from old age again. They will attain the strength of several elephants.&#xA;About four hundred years ago, an old woman, who had come to the hills on a pilgrimage, was returning from a bath in Kumāra- dhara; feeling very thirsty on the way she plunged her drinking vessel in this thirtha to get some water. On removing it from the water, she found the vessel was changed into gold. The pilgrims who witnessed the miracle were struck with awe and when they attempted to take a bath in it, the waters went under- ground. Hence it was named Rasayana Thirtha. (Rasayana = Alchemy.)&#xA;Kapiladhara Thirtha. This is situated at the foot of the hills to the south of them and to the north of Tirupati Town. Kapila Mahaṛşi installed a Siva Linga here and was doing penance calling the God, Kapilesvara, after his own name. To the west of this thirtha, there is the shrine of God Narasimha. In this temple there is a cave. Thondaman used to visit the temple on the hills through a passage from this cave. (Brahmanda Purana, chapter 7.)&#xA;Question 10. Who are the Rsis that performed Tapas (penance) on these hills and where are their Asramās situated?&#xA;Answer. Several Yugas ago, King Dasaratha did penance at the foot of the Pipal tree (Aivatha) on the banks of Svāmi Pūska- rani for obtaining children. Kumarasvami did penance at Kumāra. dhara Thirtha. It is said in the puranas that Rsis like Agastya and others obtained their final siddhis only after performing tapas on the hills. (Markandeya Purana, chapter 2; Vamana Purana, chapter 22; Varahapuraua, chapter 43.) The Pipal tree under which King Das&amp;rsquo;aratha performed his penance is still found on the banks of Svami Puskarāņi. Kumirasvami Asrama can be seen at Kumaradhāra Thirtha. Agastyasrama is located on the top of&#xA;6&#xA;Chandragiri hill to the south of S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;acalam. The asramas of Sanaka and Sanandana are within a mile of Papavinasam. The as&amp;rsquo;ramas of Sapta Rsis (seven rṣis) are situated to the north-east, at a distance of about ten miles from the temple. Besides those mentioned several other asramas of Rsis are found, scattered here and there on the range.&#xA;Question 11. Are there any special characteristics also in the animals, birds, trees and plants found on this sacred range?&#xA;Answer. Everything that takes birth on these hills men, animals, plants, insects or anything else attains Mukti. It is recorded in the puranas that many Devas, Rsis and spiritually advanced men prefer to be reborn in this range as animals and inanimate objects to secure a surer and quicker means of salvation. This is the difference between the objects found existing on these hills and those found in other places of pilgrimage and hence their claim for being treated with veneration. (Markaudoya Purāṇa, chapter 4, Varahapurana, chapter 6, Vanana Purana, chapter 12.)&#xA;Question 12. What Gods have manifested themselves on this range and at which places?&#xA;Answer. This range being in the form of Adi Ses&amp;rsquo;a, Sri Venkatesvara manifests himself on the portion representing the hood. At the centre of the body of the serpent, represented by Ahobilam, God Narasimha manifested himself; at the tail repre- sented by Srisailam, God Mabesvara manifested himself. (Brah- mandapurana chapter 2; Padmapurana chapters 28 to 31.) The three Gods confer earthly prosperity and ensure salvation for their votaries by the mere darsan of their glorious divine forms.&#xA;Question 13. Why are Mlecchas and Candalas forbidden from climbing the hills?&#xA;Answer. Many Puranas declare that this hill is the personi- fication of Adi S&amp;rsquo;os&amp;rsquo;a. Many wise men and sages, therefore, con- sidered it profanation to set foot thereon and that the mere sight of the hill will confer the same merit as the actual darian and worship of God himself on the hill and built their as&amp;rsquo;rams at the foot of the hills and offered their prayers. This prohibition against&#xA;climbing the hill does not apply to all. Those who had work to do in the temple were allowed to go up the hill after making them- selves absolutely clean. The bar as to Mlecchas and Candalas goes back to an antiquity (which is said to have come into vogue by the desire of Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo; vara himself). From actual experience it has been found that if Mllecchas either by accident or design attempted to climb the hill, they met with some obstruction or obstacles. This is so well-known that to this day Mlecchias do not attempt to ascend the hill. This belief is universally known and&#xA;followed implicitly.&#xA;Question 14. Why do dweliers on the hill suffer from fevers such as Malaria during Pulguna, Caitra, Vaisakha and Jyesta inonths? (March, April, May and June).&#xA;Answer. As the hill is said to be Adis&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;a himself, great sages say that dis&amp;rsquo;ōs&amp;rsquo;a exhales poisonous air during these four months.&#xA;But a few observers attribute the unhealthiness during these four months to the blasts blowing over flowers of poisonous creepers and shrubs on the hill, which blossom during this period.&#xA;Question 15. What rivers rise from these hills? What special sanctity is attached to each one of them? Are they associated with any great sages and if so what particular spots on the banks are considered specially holy on account of their residence?&#xA;Answer. A big river, the Svarnamnkhi, springs from this hill. According to Skanda Purana, seventh chapter, the Ganges is said to have come down here in this shape. The Svarpamukhi is so called, because, this hill, from which it rises is considered to be the golden peak of Mount Meru. Five miles from this hill is Agastyas&amp;rsquo;rama on the bank of the Svarnamukhi. Agastya wor- shipped Rudra and installed a Linga and called it Agastes&amp;rsquo;vara, after his own name. In the middle of the river, a representation of the feet of Rucha is installed. The puranas declare that ceremonies performed here, have as much potency as those per- formed at the &amp;ldquo;Visupadas&amp;rdquo; on the banks of the Ganges in Gaya.&#xA;About five miles from this hill, on the bank of this sacred river, sage Paras&amp;rsquo;ara established an as&amp;rsquo;rama, installed a Linga,&#xA;B&#xA;8&#xA;calling it Paras&amp;rsquo;arōs&amp;rsquo;vara after his own name and was doing pen- ance. On account of this, several other sages had settled them- selves round about the as&amp;rsquo;rama for penance; therefore, the appel- lation of Yogimallapuram. These details are found not only in Skanda but also in the second chapter of Markandeya Purāņa; again, within a couple of leagues from this hill to the south of it, on the banks of the Svarṇamukhi was the hermitage of the great yogi S&amp;rsquo;ri S&amp;rsquo;uka, the inspirer of the Bhagavatapurana. He installed here the images of Balarama and Krsna and was doing penance. Since then the place was known as S&amp;rsquo;ukapuram. By usage it has now acquired the name of Chiratünür or Tirucanur (Tiru-S&amp;rsquo;uka- nir). Even now the same Balarama and Krsna are fulfilling the desires of the devotees and blessing them with their darsan which is obtained easily.&#xA;Question 16. What is the name of the sacred lake on the bank of the Svarṇamukhi and who is its presiding deity?&#xA;and&#xA;Answer. The lake is known as &amp;ldquo;Padmasarōvaram it is situated in the centre of S&amp;rsquo;ukapuram otherwise known as Tirucanur, on the banks of the Svarṇamukhi.&#xA;Question. Why is the lake called Padmasarovaram?&#xA;Answer.-S&amp;rsquo;ri Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara after his incarnation at Ven- katācala performed a great penance in order to obtain Laksmi. He dug up a lake here and placed in it a celestial creeper bearing golden lotuses. He also installed Suryanarayana on the eastern side of the lake so that the lotuses may bloom both day and night without fading. In deference to his penance, Laksmi manifested herself before him in a lotus in the centre of the lake. The lake goes by the naine Padmasarovaram since then.&#xA;Shrines of Balarama and Krsna are to the north of this pond; Padmavathi (Lakṣmi) was installed to the south-east of this lake. (Further details will be given later under questions and answers relating to Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara Mahatmyam.)&#xA;Question 17. It is stated in the Puranas that Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara took up his abode in S&amp;rsquo;esacalam several yugas ago. So far, only the greatness of the hill and the sanctity of the river Svarṇamukhi&#xA;9&#xA;have been described but little has been said about the God himself. The question is, which aspect among the several manifestations of God, does Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara represent?&#xA;Answer. Sri Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara is declared to be the superme God-S&amp;rsquo;ri Maha Visnu in the following Purāņas: Markandeya, Garuda, Brahma, Brahmanda, Varaha, Bhugola Varaha, Padma, Vamana, Skanda, Bhavis&amp;rsquo;yottara, Mahabharata and in the Ascarya- parvan of Harivamṣa.&#xA;Question 18. Which is the real form of Sri Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara?&#xA;Answer. Sri Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara is the embodiment of the Absolute Effulgence. Further details about this will be found in the purāņas mentioned previously.&#xA;Question 19. With the changes in time were there any changes in the form of Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo; vara?&#xA;&amp;ldquo;C&#xA;Answer. Actually Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara is in the form of a mass of Self-Effulgence.&amp;rdquo; To Brahma and others who meditated on him in certain ages the Lord appeared in the form hearing S&amp;rsquo;aikha and Cakra. Moreover, the Lord is always changing. His grace is such that He appeares to His devotees in the form in which they adore Him. He assumes various shapes and forms suited to his mysterious purposes of creation. He manifests Himself in diverse formis aud in one form.&#xA;Question 20. Where did Venkatōs&amp;rsquo;vara hail from? Was Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara brought over here from some other place or did he manifest himself here directly or was he installed here with any special object?&#xA;Answer. Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara came down from Vaikunta to sport on the hills and to fulfil the desires of Brahma and other Gods and great sages, like Vas&amp;rsquo;ista and to give salvation to man- kind. That is why this place is known as a Svayamvyakta- stala&amp;rdquo; (ie. a place where God manifested himself directly as distinguished from places having man-made sculptured images of&#xA;Him. These details are found in the puranas mentioned supra).&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Question 21. When did this Lord arrive here and to whom did He appear in His divine form?&#xA;10&#xA;Answer. This Lord came over here in the twenty-eighth Mahayuga itself and appeared to Brahma and others. In the Kaliyuga, as people&amp;rsquo;s minds are steeped in ignorance he draws them to himself by force and receives various offerings from them by ful- filling their desires. To some he appears in &amp;ldquo;Arcarupa&amp;rdquo; (the present idol form) and to several others in several forms convincing them of His grace and His sportive mood. This is mentioned in the Varaha, Vamana, Bhavis&amp;rsquo;yottara, Brahma, Brahmanda and Padma purāņas.&#xA;Question 22. What are the various sacred names of this Lord? Who all worshipped the Lord and what objects had been attained by them?&#xA;Answer. The most current names of this Lord are Sri Venkates&amp;rsquo; vara and Srinivasa. But His names are inuumerable. Gods such as Brahma and sages such as Agastya, did great penance to Him and achieved their hearts&amp;rsquo; desires. King Das&amp;rsquo;ara- tha did penance for about ten thousand years and obtained sons. Anjanadevi worshipped Him and begot Anjaneya. Many Brah. mins and Kings worshipped Him and attained their objects.&#xA;Question 23. After his appearance here what are the various diversions in which He had sported?&#xA;Answer. Once upon a time there was a king named Akasa. raja who had his capital at Nārāyaṇavanam twenty miles from Tirupati. He was desirous of getting children. One day while ploughing a field he found a lotus in the middle of which was a baby, girl. He was overjoyed and adopted her and named her as Padmavati. In due course Padmavathi attained the marriageable&#xA;She was divinely beautiful. Lord Venkatesvara desired to marry her. He took the form of a handsome young man, grace- fully attired, mounted a fine horse and entered the grove where Padmavati was amusing herself with her maids, on the pretext. of chasing an elephant. He contrived to present hintself before Padmavati and by his artfulness made her fall madly in love with Him. Then He started negotiations, for narrying her through Vakula, Sri S&amp;rsquo;uka and others. After his marriage, he performed many wonderful deeds. This information is contained in Bhavis&amp;rsquo;- yottara purăņa, Varaha and other purapas. In Nārāyaṇavanam,&#xA;11&#xA;in proof of this episode, there still exists a shrine dedicated to Kalyana Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara who exactly resembles the Lord here (on the hills), in the splendour of His divine beauty and grace. During the time of Thondaman Cakravarti, the brother of Akaşa- rāja, the Lord had worked many amazing wonders.&#xA;Question 24. In olden days who all had built mantapas and prakāras for the shrine and who all had improved or renovated them?&#xA;Answer. In the twenty-eighth Mahayuga, in the Kaliyuga a King named S&amp;rsquo;ankha Mahārāja built the Garbha Gṛha, Gopura, mantapams and prakaras. This is stated in 33, 34, 35 and 36th chapters of Vamana purana and referred to in Skanda and other puraņas also.&#xA;Later on Thondaman, built the main shrine, with Vimana, gopuras, mantapas and prakaras, with the assistance of Brahma and other Gods. In this Kaliyuga the Cōla and the Pandya Kings have reconstructed the gopuras, mantapas and prakaras. This information is found in Bhavis&amp;rsquo;yotara and others.&#xA;puriņas.&#xA;Question 25. Who is the person who first instituted a festival in the temple, what is the festival and how has it been continued since then?&#xA;Answer, When the Lord appeared first to Brahma on this hill, the latter, initiated the festival of Brahmotsava in Kanya- masa for a period of nine days, from Dvajharohana (flag hoisting) onwards, himself, officiating as the priest. Since then, by his command celebrations are being conducted according to the rites prescribed by him to date, without any break. He further ordained that devotees who arrange for the performance of Brah- motsava on ordinary days also would acquire great merit. Accordingly several people pay the prescribed fees and celebrate. this Utsava. But during such festivals, except Dvajharōhaṇa and Avarahana, every other detail, such as procession of the God on the appointed vehicles (Vahanas) is gone through, as in the regular Brahmotsava. Complimentary presents are given to those devotees who celebrate this festival. Many bhaktās (devotees) celebrate Brahmotsava. As Brahma initiated this&#xA;12&#xA;form of festival, it is called Brahmotsava. Those who cannot afford to celebrate the Brahmotsava perform Garudōtsava, Kalyanotsava and other Utsavas according to their means, paying the fees prescribed and enjoy the benefits accruing from such services to the Lord.&#xA;Question 26. Did Sri Rama at any time visit this shrine?&#xA;Answer. In Kritayuga Sri Rama camped on this Hill for a night along with his monkey horde on his march to Ravana&amp;rsquo;s kingdom. Then, Hanuman and other monkeys roaming about in the neighbourhood entered the Vaikunta cave and seeing the splendour of a vision of Lord Srinivasa, came out in wonder and narrated their adventure to S&amp;rsquo;ri Rama. Sri Rama, thinking that it did not behove him to admit that it was all due to his own power of maya, explained to the monkeys that the wonder was all due to the mountain itself. While returning along with Sita and Lakṣmaṇa, after killing Ravana, Rāma dwelt at Tirupati for sometime. The temple of Kodandaramasvamy at Tirupati comme- morates this visit. In this temple S&amp;rsquo;ri Rama, Sita and Lakṣmaṇa stay in the form of idols and bless their devotecs fulfilling their desires. This account is found here and there in several puriņas and also in Varahapurāņa.&#xA;Question 27. Which of the various services in the temple initiated by Brahma or the ancient kings are still continued in the manner prescribed by them?&#xA;Answer. Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo;varn lived in the forest before he appeared to S&amp;rsquo;ankha Maharaja. Then, the fourheaded Bralna used to bathe the God in milk every Friday, himself taking the form of a cow and then worship him performing the various rites. Thereafter, S&amp;rsquo;ankha Mahārāja and other performed these services. regularly. So also even today this abhiseka (bath) with nilk is offered every Friday. Other services are, a service called Pulakapu in which a paste made of civet, sandal, saffron and paccakarpuram (refined camphor) is smeared over the Lord; every year Brahmotsava is performed in Kanyamāsa. Besides these, Brahmotsava, Garudõtsava and Kalyanotsava and other Ulsavas are celebrated whenever devotees arrange for such festivals,&#xA;13&#xA;Question 28. What is the reason for the Lord wearing a Nāgābharaṇa, (serpent ornament) and the rule for worship with Bilva leaves?&#xA;Answer. In olden days Agastya and other sages worshipped this Lord as S&amp;rsquo;iva using the special forms of worship prescribed for S&amp;rsquo;iva. This is stated in the sixtieth chapter of Bhavis&amp;rsquo;yōtara purāņa. Later on, when Thondaman prayed to this Lord to give him victory over his rival in war, it is said, that this Lord lent him his s&amp;rsquo;anka and cakra, and was withont these emblems. He was then worshipped as God Subramanya; Arcana (worship) with bilva leaves and adornment of the Lord with the nagabharaṇa came into vogue since then. Latterly Sri Ramanuja who was a follower of Vaisnavism invested the God with gold emblems denot- ing s&amp;rsquo;anka and cakra and arranged for worship of the God according to the rites of Vaikhäuasa agama. It was, then ordained by the Lord himself that nagabharana should continue as before and that he should be worshipped with bilva leaves during the month of Margazhi. Moreover, from time immemorial, it has been declared that as the shrine is equally sacred to all the three religious sects there is sanction for all form of worship on the hill.&#xA;Question 29. Leaving out of account the ornaments offered by Brahma and other Gods, who are the kings, in this age, who endowed the shrine with gifts of ornaments etc. and where have they been seen secured now?&#xA;Answer. After the s&amp;rsquo;äka year 1074, from Projotpathi, King Prataparudra of Warangal, reigned for fifty-eight years. He was a famous king. Nine lakhs of bowmen guarded his palace. He ruled from the Narmada to cape Comorin. Prataparudra offered a ratnakavaca (armour studded with rubies) worth eighteen lakhs of gold mohurs and also performed Kanakabhiseka with eighteen lakhs of gold mohurs. This is inscribed on the walls of the second prakära of the temple. Innumerable ornaments offered by several kings must be available. That is why there is the tradition that Lord is the possessor of a crore of ornaments.&amp;quot; As the present era is Kaliyuga when most people are likely to be impious and also on account of certain insurrections within the&#xA;&amp;ldquo;C&#xA;14&#xA;temple, the treasures are hidden on the path of Pradaksiņa (circumambulation) which is three hundred yards long and forty yards broad; It is closed by doors and rivetted with stones and is not open to public like other places of worship in the temple. Hearing this account, a Tahsildar named Srinivasacarya, attempt. ed to investigate the truth of this tradition. He, however, could not proceed with the work owing to the sudden illness of the men employed for the purpose. He gave it up thinking that it was useless to attempt the task untill the Lord himself directed them to do so. Elders say that several other attempts were made to locate the treasure but on every occasion they met with some obstacle or the other.&#xA;Question 30. There are ever so many temples in the world. but why is it that so many offerings are made to this Lord only?&#xA;Answer. It is said in the Brahmanda purana that the Lord blesses such devotees as propitiate him with votive offerings, with prosperity, children, good health, victory over enemies and the many good things of life. The Lord through &amp;ldquo;Avesa&amp;rdquo; convinces the devotees of His presence and enforces compliance with the vows taken by them. There is a tradition handed down by elders, that once upon a time, when Sri Sankarācārya visited the shrine he installed a Yantra&amp;rsquo; and an Akarsana Cakra&amp;rdquo; near the Padmapitam of the God; on that account valuable gifts are being offered to the shrine.&#xA;Question 31. What is there in the idol of Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara which is not present in other idols? What are the miraculous happenings within the past one thousand years?&#xA;Answer. About eight hundred years ago, a great man, Tirumala Nambi by name, though very old, due to his great devotion to the Lord, used to go to Papavinäsa thirtha daily and bring a potful of water for the worship of the Lord. Days passed when one day when he was bringing water for the worship, the Lord intending to test him, appeared before him in disguise and begged him to give a little water pleading great thirst. But the old man declined to give him any. The Lord then drank up all the water in the pot unknown to Nambi, by causing a hole in15&#xA;the pot with an arrow, and then disappeared. Finding that the pot he was bringing was empty Nambi once again proceeded to Papavinasam thirtha to fill it. But he had fainted on the way. Then the Lord appeared before him, comforted him and instructed him that in future he may get water from Akäṣaganga (which is nearer) and then disappeared. Thenceforward water for the wor- ship of the Lord is being got from Akaṣaganga. The descendants of Nambi are continuing this service to this day. One member of this family was the famous Tirumala Tatacarya.&#xA;Tirumala Nambi built a mantapam at the spot where the Lord appeared to him and installed the footprints of the Lord in it. There is an inscription near the spot recording this episode. By the grace of the Lord, there has been plentiful and perennial supply of water in Aküṣganga and it has not been known to shrink in volume even during the worst drought.&#xA;About eight hundred or one thousand years ago a devotee named Änandalvar was showing his piety by supplying flowers for worship. He wanted to have a good supply of water for the flower garden he had raised and was digging a tank after vowing to take no assistance excepting that of his wife. The Lord could not endure the sight of their labouring without help. Disguising himself as a brahmacari (bachelor) he was helping them in removing the excavated mud and putting up the bund. Anandāl- var when he noticed this, could not tolerate a third party helping in his chosen task for the Lord and threw stones at the braluna- cări. One of them caught the bachelor on the chin and he immedi. ately disappeared. In the temple, the arcakas who were worship- ping the Lord, noticed blood dropping from the chin of the Lord. All were amazed. The Lord through the medium of one of those present (Avesa), narrated how he had sustained the injury. Immediately the arcakis applied gambura powder. (refined camphor) to that part. Even to this day gambura powder is applied to the chin of the image during the daily worship. The tank too exists to this day and is known as Anandalvar tank.&#xA;About eight hundred years ago another devotee named Kuruka Nambi, born in the potter&amp;rsquo;s caste, was engaged in his traditional&#xA;C&#xA;16&#xA;work of making pots. He set up a picture of the Lord in a portion of his hut and was offering worship to it with lotuses made of mud. The arcakis of the Lord at the Tirumalai at the time of worship noticed some lotuses made of mud at the feet of the Lord and were very much amazed. As usual the Lord announced through Aves&amp;rsquo;a that he had accepted these mud lotuses from a devotee named Kuruka Nambi. This Nambi built a gopuram on the path to the Tirumalai hill and this story is recorded in the inscriptions on the gopuram. It is said that his potter&amp;rsquo;s wheel too was seen exhibited on the pathway to the hill for a long time.&#xA;About five hundred years ago a great bairagi-chief named Hattiram Bavaji, belonging to Northern India, learning from his guru that he would be blessed with a vision of the Lord on the Tirumalai hills, came over here at the direction of his guru and built himself an as&amp;rsquo;ram to the north of the shrine on the pathway to Papanasanam and Äkās&amp;rsquo;aganga at a distance of about twenty- five minutes walk from the shrine. He kept up a dhuni&amp;quot; (a permanent flame burning uncessingly) in front of his as&amp;rsquo;ram. He supplied voluntarily the firewood required for preparing naivedyams for the Lord taking in return a very small quantity of the prasādam of the God just to keep himself alive. Thus he spent twelve years doing penance. The Lord disguising himself variously now as Yenadi, now as a Yerukvila, and then as a Chenchu tried to frighten him to test whether he had acquired steadiness of mind of the true path. Hattiramji was steadfast in his devotion. The great bhakta piqued at the Lord not favouring him with his darsan despite his hard penance for twelve years was getting down the hill determined to leave the place for good. In the guise of a brahmin Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara followed him and entreated him to remain on the hills but Bavāji would not hear him. The brahmin accompanied him trying to urge him to stay till they came down the hill as far as Avvaccarikona. Then the Lord out of mercy to his devotee appeared before him in his divine form with both s&amp;rsquo;ankha and cakra. Bavāji then prostrated himself before Him and firmly caught hold of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s feet, placing his head on the Lord&amp;rsquo;s feet. Though the Lord requested him to&#xA;17&#xA;release his hold he continued to pray appealingly that he should be blessed with the sight of His divine form eternally. The Lord blessed him accordingly and offered to unite him with himself after his death. Bavāji then went back to the hill with the Lord and remained there ever afterwards as a great devotee of the Lord. It is said that he often played chess with the Lord.&#xA;A certain chief of the Devaraya dynasty seeing Hattiram Bavaji told him that his name Hattiram meant an elephant and asked him to prove that he merited the name. The bhakta, Hattiram, met the taunt by placing his faith in the Lord. He offered to prove to the king that he was an elephant. He caused an enclosure to be made to accommodate an elephant and such articles as are consumed by elephants to be placed within. Bavaji entered the enclosure in the night and with the blessings of the Lord assumed the form of an elephant. At midnight he made the same noise as an elephant at its feed and consumed all articles kept in the enclosure to feed the elephant. In proof, of the stay of the animal there was the excreta of the elephant in the enclosure. At the break of the day he came out of the enclosure in his human form. The chief who saw this miracle appealed in great consternation for mercy and forgiveness. He became ever after a great devotee of the saint. He spent many years playing dice with the Lord. The Lord advised him to establish a mutt and train a disciple but he did not do so, saying that he did not want anything beyond the service of the Lord. As the advice was repeated several times, he took it as a command, selected a disciple named Giridhara Doss and built a mutt on the elevated ground to the south-east of the temple. He then reported the fact to the Lord and prayed to him that the hierarchy of disciples who would live in the mutt may be provided with a simple fare consisting of the curry of Sama leaves and rotis (chapathis). The Lord was very much pleased at the establishment of the mutt and blessed that ample food and clothes would be provided to the disciples, so long as bells ring in his temple (i.e. so long as worship endures in his own temple). When the devotee asked for meagre fare the Lord duly blessed him with abundance such is the love of the Lord to his devotees. One day&#xA;18&#xA;when Hattiram Bavāji was doing the pradakṣinam of the temple, the Lord united the spirit of Bavāji with himself. Bavaji&amp;rsquo;s disciple Giridhara Doss Mahant, according to the custom of his community. laid the remains of his guru in the dhuni kept by him. Even now, the place is known as the &amp;ldquo;Samadhi&amp;rdquo; and daily worship is offered there. In virtue of the boon of the Lord the two mutts, the one on the hill and the other in Tirupati, have gradually grown in impor- tance and are in a flourishing condition today. Food and provisions. are distributed to all sadhus and brahmins. The miracles worked by the Lord are innumerable and none can adequately describe them. Books containing accounts of Tirumala Nambi and others written four hundred or five hundred years ago are still extant. With the rapid advance of Kaliyuga the Lord has stopped direct conversations with devotees but still gives proof of His presence through dreams and through mediums who are temporarily inspired (Avesam).&#xA;Question 32. How many full naivedyams (food offerings) are being hitherto made to the God daily? How many villages and lands have been endowed for the purpose or are the charges being met from cash collections?&#xA;Answer. This Lord is offered full naivedyams sixty times in the course of the day with the attendant Karpoora huratis and Akhanda Diparādhanas. Forty two villages in this neighbour- hood, in the Tirupati taluk, have been assigned for this purpose. In addition to this, the then kings used to make munificent contri- butions for special festivals and celebrations. Moreover, every item of worship without any omission is being done with the amounts contributed by the pilgrims coming here. As a statement of the full details of the villages and the gifts made by the kings and pilgrims will swell this account considerably only a brief abstract is furnished. These details are recorded in the inscriptions on the temple walls.&#xA;Question 33. This Lord has ceased to talk to persons directly but He communicates through dreams and aves&amp;rsquo;ams (mediums). Again, it is said that the people should not wear the flowers which have been used for decorating the Lord and also&#xA;19&#xA;that except the Lord no one while on the hills, should wear flowers and actually this is found in practice now. Are there any reasons&#xA;for these?&#xA;Answer.&#xA;Long ago, a certain devotee, Rangadass by name, was supplying flowers to the Lord. He detected a lock of hair in them and was hesitating to offer them to the Loid. Then through aves am the Lord directed that from that date nc one should wear tulasi and flowers on the hills, not even those worn by the Lord and thrown away as nirmalyam and that the latter should be put into a well situated in the north-east corner of the Sampangi Pradakṣina. Accordingly, flowers and tulasi are not worn by any one while on the hills and also the nirmalyam of the Lord is put into the well which has hence acquired the name Poola bhavi (the well of flowers).&#xA;Question 34. There are ever so many shrines in the land. Why do all people look on this Lord with such unique devotion. and awe?&#xA;Answer. Local people or those belonging to other places when they put their trust on this Lord and pray to him fervently, He unfailingly grants their wishes; besides, when they make vows to him and inadvertently forget them, He immediately reminds them by appearing in their dreams or through avesam and exacts the fulfilment of the vows; If however, in spite of such warnings the vows remain unfulfilled, the person gets some un- expected trouble, which is relieved immediately on the vow being fulfilled and their faith in the Lord is thus reinforced. By such and various other leelas (plays) with His devotees He keeps their faith in Him strong and abiding. Such experiences are not had in other shrines. Hence this shrine enjoys pre-eminence in the esti- mation of the people.&#xA;Question 35. What is the reason for paying an amount equal in value to presents made to the Lord such as ornaments, garments, vahanas, cows, etc.?&#xA;Answer. As the Lord is the fulfiller of the desires of all persons, it has been directed by the Lord himself. There is the precedent of King Prat@parudra paying a fee of eighteen lakhs of&#xA;20&#xA;mohurs along with his presents of equal value.&#xA;Recent govern- ments have followed the precedent and levied taxes in order to pay the temple the fees. So great is the sanctity of the shine that such levies are being paid to this day without question.&#xA;C&#xA;Question 36. What are the original sources for the Venkatā. cala Mahatmyam ?&#xA;Answer. It is said in the Upanisads that this Lord is the all pervading Visņu present in Vaikunta, on the earth and every- where. In the Taittiriyōpanisad, in the fifth parva called Narayanam&amp;rsquo;, it is stated that the Lord shines at the farther end of the water, in the middle of this earthly region, and that He makes the other elements shine through His own light. This is quoted from the conimentary of Vidyaranya on the said Upanisad. In the eighteen puranas, including the Mahabharata, the sanctity of this shrine has been recorded. It is said that the inscriptions on the temple walls also give such details.&#xA;Question 37. When and by whom was S&amp;rsquo;ri Gō vindarājasvāmi installed at Tirupati and who built the temple and compound walls?&#xA;Answer. S&amp;rsquo;ri Govindarajasvami originally manifested Him- self at Chitrakuta (Chidambaram), a place of puranic fame. Later on owing to some local disturbances the place was deserted. About five hundred or six hundred years ago, S&amp;rsquo;ri Ramanujacārya (the famous advocate of Vaisnavism) brought the idol to Tirupati. and installed it in the present place. He also provided the pro- cessional images and consecrated them. The kings of the Yadava dynasty, who held sway over this country from S&amp;rsquo;aka 756 (834 A.D.) constructed the temple, gopurams and prakārams (com- pound walls). Subsequently, about three hundred years ago, Anantha, a chief of Matla family, built the big entrance gopuram and excavated the two &amp;ldquo;Buggas&amp;rdquo; (artesian wells or fountains), within and outside the walls of this gopuram. Later, another chief of the same dynasty, Appayaraju and his Dewan, Musalayya Naidu, renovated the old car but after some time the condition of the car deteriorated. The estate of the Matla chief was also annexed by the Company (East India Company).&#xA;21&#xA;Question 38. Who installed Kodandaramas vami at Tirupati at first and who built the temple, the towers and the compound walls?&#xA;Answer. The traditional account is that in the sixty-fourth year of this Kaliyuga, King Janamejaya, who was ruling the country, found the temple in ruins and renovated it, building the main shrine, the tower and the compound walls reinstalling the images of the Gods. The kings of the Yadava dynasty who came into power from the S&amp;rsquo;aka year 756, reconstructed the temple with mantapams, prakaras and gopurams.&#xA;Question 39. When and by whom was the Goddess installed at S&amp;rsquo;ukapuri, otherwise called Chirtanüru or Tirucanür?&#xA;Answer. Once, the great sage Bhrgu, intending to test the Trimurtis, went to Vaikunta and S&amp;rsquo;ri Visnu was reclining on his serpent coach with Lakṣmi by his side. Bhrgu kicked at the chest of the Lord with his foot. Visņu got up, showed great humility and expressed regret for the pain caused to the sage by his foot coming into contact with the hard surface of his chest. On the pretext of relieving the pain by massaging the foot He (Lord) put out the eye which the sage possessed in his foot. Goddess Laksmi noticing that the Lord was humbling himself and rendering service to a man who had the effrontery to kick at the place of her abode, got enraged and parted from Visņu and hid herself at Kolhapur. The Lord unable to endure the pangs of separation went in search of her and reached Kolhapur, which is situated at a distance of about five hundred miles from S&amp;rsquo;es&amp;rsquo;acalam. He could not find her there and was in consequence very much distressed. Then, a voice from the sky directed him that five miles to the south of the S&amp;rsquo;ōs&amp;rsquo;acalam (which was to the north of Kolhapur) there was a village S&amp;rsquo;uka- puri, on the hauks of the Svarṇamukhi river, and that He should go there, excavate a lake with His Gadayudha, obtain and nurse in the lake the lotus creeper of the celestial regions which yields golden lotuses and instal the Sun God to the east of the lake so as to keep the lotuses always in bloom and then enga penance when, the voice declared, Goddess Laksmu appter before Him. Lord Visņu accordingly proceeded me place, dug&#xA;22&#xA;a lake, introduced the divine lotus creeper into it, installed Surya- nārāyaṇa on the bank and engaged himself in penance. To the intense joy of the Lord Goddess Laksmi appeared before Him in a lotus in the middle of the lake. He then built a shrine for her to the north of the temple where S&amp;rsquo;ri S&amp;rsquo;uka had installed Balarama and Kṛṣṇa for his worship and settled the Goddess in it under the name of Padmavati. He instituted an annual festival called Avabhyatottsavam on a Pancami day, the Lord Himself paying her a State visit in due form from the hills bringing with Him presents of garlands, sarees, blouses, pan, turmeric, kunkum and panniyarams, (articles priced by married women as auspicious gifts). Since then a Brahmotsavam festival is being conducted annually in the month of Karthigai, the Dvajarohanam com- mencing eight days prior to Pancami and ending with Avabhridot- savam. The festival is widely known as the Cirtanur Pancami festival. About two hundred years ago, the Rajahs of Karvetnagar, reconstructed the lake and arranged for some special services. About one hundred years ago, one S&amp;rsquo;ri Nārāyaṇa Pillai of Madras and a few others constructed stone steps leading to the lake.&#xA;Details regarding the origin of the image of the Goddess and other matters connected with the shrine are found in the thirty- fourth chapter of S&amp;rsquo;ri Padmapurana. By the grace of the Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara since then the temple of the Goddess has been con- siderably enlarged by the construction of additional mantapams, etc. and the services to her are being performed with ever increas- ing magnificence and splendour by her own devotees and of Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara.&#xA;Question 40. Are there any remarkable features in the Goddess, such as those of Lord Venkates&amp;rsquo; vala? Do pilgrims who visit S&amp;rsquo;ri. Venkates&amp;rsquo;vara on the hills visit this temple also and offer similar kinds of services and gifts?&#xA;Answer. By virtue of Divine grace abiding in the Goddess great powers are manifested by Padmavati also. As evidence of this, it is seen that large crowds of people both men and women, throng to this shrine. on Fridays and offer special worship. and&#xA;23&#xA;taligais (food offerings) in order to obtain their objects. Those who pray for children are blessed with children. Persons possessed by evil spirits and grahūs, such as sākini and dakini pray for release from them and obtain relief. Those who have lost their sight and even the lame put absolute faith in the Goddess and do pradakși- nams and namaskārams to her for some period. They get back their sight and limbs. Her grace shines in proportion to the intensity. of the faith and devotion of each worshipper. All pilgrims who visit the hills of the Lord invariably visit the Goddess also and make presents of garments, jewels, taligais and also contribute according to their means for special utsavas such as Garudavāha- nam, (elephant) gajavāhanam, etc. Further, people from Tirupati and surrounding localities take vows and visit the shrine on Fridays, bathe in the lake do pradakṣiņam and make offerings of food, lights, clothes and jewels. Several people from various places pay the prescribed fees and arrange for burning daily akhandams before the Goddess and for daily performance of tulasi and kunkum arcanas according to the prescribed rites. Therefore there is basis for thinking that great powers abide also in Goddess S&amp;rsquo;ri Padmavati.&#xA;APPENDIX&#xA;Question 1. How many years have passed from the begin- ning of the Kali Yuga up to date, i.e. up to saka 1724-Roudr year-Fasli 1210?&#xA;Answer. The Kali Yuga commenced in the Pramadi year- The total period of the Yuga is 43,200 years. 4,908 years have elapsed up to saka 1724-Rondri; 1210-Fusli.&#xA;Question 2. What are the various dynasties of kings that have ruled the country and who are the kings and their periods of their reigns?&#xA;Answer. After the great Mahabharata War, Dharmarāja reigned for thirty-six years and in the Pramadi year, comunencing with the Kali Yuga, he crowned his grandson Parikṣit and left this world. The following is a list of kings who had reigned from that date.&#xA;KINGS.&#xA;Total period of roign in years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>अष्टोत्तर-शतनामावलिः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/venkaTeshvarAShTottara-shata-nAmAvaliH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/venkaTeshvarAShTottara-shata-nAmAvaliH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;श्रीवेङ्कटेश अष्टोत्तर-शतनामावलिः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वेङ्कटेशायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ शेषाद्रिनिलयायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वृषदृग्गोचरायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ विष्णवेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ सदञ्जनगिरीशायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वृषाद्रिपतयेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ मेरुपुत्रगिरीशायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ सरस्स्वामितटीजुषेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ कुमाराकल्पसेव्यायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वज्रिदृग्विषयायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ सुवर्चलासुतन्यस्तसैनापत्यभरायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ रामायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ पद्मनाभायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ सदा वायुस्तुतायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ त्यक्तवैकुण्ठलोकायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ गिरिकुञ्जविहारिणेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ हरिचन्दनगोत्रेन्द्रस्वामिनेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ शङ्खराजन्य नेत्राब्जविषयायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वसूपरिचरित्रात्रेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ कृष्णायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ अब्धिकन्यापरिष्वक्तवक्षसेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वेङ्कटायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ सनकादिमहायोगिपूजितायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ देवजित्प्रमुखानन्तदैत्य सङ्घप्रणाशिनेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्वेतद्वीपवसन्मुक्तपूजिताम्फ्रिुयुगायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ शेषपर्वतरूपत्व प्रकाशनपरायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ सानुस्थापिततार्क्ष्यायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ तार्क्ष्याचलनिवासिनेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ मायागूढविमानायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ गरुडस्कन्धवासिनेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ अनन्तशिरसेश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ अनन्ताक्षायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ अनन्तचरणायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीशैलनिलयायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ दामोदरायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ नीलमेघनिभायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ ब्रह्मादिदेवदुर्दर्शविश्वरूपायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ वैकुण्ठागत सद्धेमविमानान्तर्गतायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ अगस्त्याभ्यर्थिताशेषजनदृग्गोचरायश्री वेङ्कटेशाय नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;[[602603]]&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अष्टोत्तर शतनामावलिः&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>पद्मावती-चतुर्विंशति-नामावलिः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/padmAvatI-chaturviMshati-nAmAvaliH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/gadyam/sthala-mahimA/venkaTAchalaH/padmAvatI-chaturviMshati-nAmAvaliH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[608]]&lt;br&gt;&#xA;श्री पद्मावती चतुर्विंशति नामावलिः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं श्रियै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं लोकधात्त्र्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं ब्रह्ममात्रे नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं पद्मनेत्रायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं पद्ममुख्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं प्रसन्नमुख पद्मायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं पद्मकान्त्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं बिल्ववनस्थायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं विष्णुपत्न्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं विचित्रक्षौमधारिण्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं पृथुश्रोण्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं पक्वबिल्वफलापीनतुङ्गस्तन्यै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं सुरक्त पद्मपत्राभकरपादतलायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं शुभायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं सरत्नाङ्गद केयूरकाञ्चीनूपुरशोभितायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं यक्षकर्दमसंलिप्तसर्वाङ्गायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं कटकोज्ज्वलायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं माङ्गल्याभरणैश्चित्रैर्मुक्ताहारैर्विभूषितायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं ताटङ्कैरवतंसैश्च शोभमानमुखाम्बुजायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं पद्महस्तायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं हरिवल्लभायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं ऋग्यजुस्सामरूपायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं विद्यायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ॐ श्रीं अभ्धिजायै नमः&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;ठ्&amp;mdash;&amp;ndash;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;[[609]]&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
