<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 DHRUVABERA on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 DHRUVABERA on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>25 Self-manifested</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/01_Self-manifested/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/01_Self-manifested/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tradition of a self-manifested idol:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Dhruvabera of Lord Venkatesvara and the complementary bronzes, with the Utsava murtis of Sri Rama and Sri Krishna make up the pantheon of Tirumala. Tradition has it that the Dhruvabera of Lord Venkatesvara was not wrought by the hand of man and that the supreme Lord manifested himself in a form which could easily be comprehended by human beings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thus we have Nammalvar&amp;rsquo;s assurances that param has come down to Tirumala from his Divya Loka out of his own choice for our spiritual benefit. All the earlier alvars have also stated that the devas headed by Brahma daily worship Sri Venkatesvara on this hill as we do even now. Sri Ramanuja the great Vaishnava teacher in his mangalasloka of his great work “Sribhashya &amp;quot; lays stress on the great solace of the Lord for the salvation of mankind, and equals Brahma with Srinivasa. Hence traditional belief is that, Sri Venkatesvara is the self-manifested Brahman who came to Tirumala for our salvation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 Agamic rule</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/02_Agamic_rule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/02_Agamic_rule/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Agamic rule for making a deity&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The agamas like vaikhanasa agama, the pancharatra agama, the tantras, and vishnu dharmottara, are the basic texts which lay down in precise detail the rules regarding the construction of a temple and the installation of murtis therein. In agamas the relative proportions of the idol, the posture of the body, the hands, the weapons to be borne by it, the jewellery to be adorned on it, are all laid down. If there is the slightest defect in execution or even a minute variation from the prescribed rule, that image would be considered unsuitable for consecration or worship and not used.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 General features</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/03_General_features/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/03_General_features/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;General features of an idol of Vishnu&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vishnu images usually have four arms, the ayudhas or weapons held in the hands usually being the Chakra, Sankha or conch, the Bow and arrows and the Gada or club. The other weapons of Vishnu include the khetaka or the shield, the katari or the sword, the parasu or the battle-axe, hala or the plough, and sometimes the whip (for Gopi-Krishna) images. The hands are usually in the abhaya, varada or katyavalambita poses. It is however relevant to note here that the Yogasastra recognises twenty five kinds of mudras in images. The Abhaya pose is the one in which the Lord holds his hand aloft, with the right palm facing the devotee with all the fingers of the hand pointing upwards. This is a pose in which the Lord assures his protection to the devotee-relieving him from fear i.e., Bhaya. The Varada hasta is the pose in which the Lord holds his hand with the palm facing the devotee with all the fingers of the hand pointing downwards. This pose signifies that the Lord is a giver of boons. According to the Mayasastram however, &amp;ldquo;when the tip of the thumb is placed at the end of the breast, it is the attitude of abhaya or protection of God. If the hand is on the waist, it is said to be the attitude of giving vara or boon.&amp;rdquo; The Katyavalambita hasta pose is the one in which the Lord keeps his hand (left hand) on the kati or waist. This is a pose that indicates that the Lord&amp;rsquo;s protection and grace is available to those worshipping him with constant devotion. According to another interpretation, it indicates that Samsara is knee-deep only to those devoted to the Lord&amp;rsquo;s feet. Vishnu images are shown to carry several ornaments such as the Padma or the lotus, Kirita or the crown, Makara Kundalas or crocodile ear ornaments, Keyura or armlets, Kankanas or wristlets, Udarabandhas or ornaments around the waist, Katibandhas or ornaments around the waist and the hips, the sacred thread etc. There is usually a mole on the right chest called the Srivatsa, and a garland reaching up to the knees called the Vaijayantimala. Sri Kaustubam is a gemstudded jewel on the chest which is sacred to Lakshmi. The consort of the Lord is usually carved or exhibited near the Srivatsa and the Sri Kousthubam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 Type of idol</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/04_Type_of_idol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/04_Type_of_idol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The type of idol of Lord Venkatesvara as per Vaikhanasá agama:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The idol of Lord Venkatesvara at Tirumala is clearly seen to be a standing one which makes it fall only under the sthanaka type. Hence a sthanaka image, according to the agamas, can be of the Yoga, Bhoga, Vira or Abhicharika type, each of which would have three sub-types namely Uttama, Madhyama and Adhama murtis. Hence the image of the Lord of Tirumala could fall only under one of the above twelve divisions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Description</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/05_Description/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/05_Description/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A description of the idol of Lord Venkatesvara&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The idol of the Lord is a majestic, beautiful and superbly executed one. The full majesty, divine grace and unbounded compassion of the Lord is clearly manifest even to the uninitiated either when the Lord gives darshan draped in all his clothes and ornaments, or on Friday the abisheka day, when these are removed when the Lord&amp;rsquo;s full glory is revealed in all its pristine purity. The most arresting feature of the Lord is the permeating aura of an overpowering sense of divinity, that is so utterly compassionate, that pours out love and desire to help if only one turns to Him. His facial expression with long and dark eyes in ‘ sama drishti,&amp;rsquo; and with an eternal smile is extraordinarily tranquil and beautiful, reflecting a sense of complete love and serenity, that envelops all living creatures in its benevolence. People who can rise above mere sectarian difference, and respond to the Divine wherever he is, will be struck with the same divine concordance which one has in the Sistine Chapel or in the presence of the blessed saints, who have adorned the Christian Church during the middle ages, and whose smile as in the case of the Lord of Tirumala, transforms their faces into that of a child, and enchants us with its bewitching vibrant potent power. The Lord of Tirumala, is a supreme pontiff, who cares not for worldly power, and because he is in all, all are part of him, and if we surrender to Him, our cares are His. And when the eternal takes care of our cares, whom should we fear, and what should we worry about. He asks only one price for it viz., our love, and how easy is it to pay!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 Vaishnavaite or Saivaite?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/06_Vaishnavaite_or_Saivaite/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/02_DHRUVABERA/06_Vaishnavaite_or_Saivaite/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The idol of the Lord, a Vaishnavaite or Saivaite one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There has been a persistent controversy going on, whether the image of the Lord at Tirumala is a manifestation of Vishnu or Siva. There is also a view that it represents Subramanya and another extreme view that the idol represents Shakti. These are questions which time and again agitate the minds of devotees and pilgrims who intensely believe in the sanctity of this great temple. It is therefore necessary that this should be examined in detail and settled once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
