<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Lies on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Lies on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Buddhist jamnAdAs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/buddhist-jamnAdAs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/buddhist-jamnAdAs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;contents&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Foreword&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Preface&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 2&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 6&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 8&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 9&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 10&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 11&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 12&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 13&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 14&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 15&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 16&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 17&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 18&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 19&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 20&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 21&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 22&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 23&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 24&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 25&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 26&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 27&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 28&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 29&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Chapter 30&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Bibliography&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tirupati Balaji was a Buddhist Shrine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;table-of-contents&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TABLE OF CONTENTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOREWORD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;by Prof. Dr. M. D. Nalawade, M.A., B.Ed., LL. B., Ph. D.,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JagannAthaH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/jagannAthaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/jagannAthaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;within-three-miles-from-tirupati-dialectal-form-of-the-sanskrit-term-the-transformation-is-as-follows&#34;&gt;The author reserves for himself al&amp;rsquo; rights.&#xA;Copies can be had from:&#xA;TRILINGA GRANTHAMALA,&#xA;Jagannadhapuram,&#xA;TIRUPATI. (CHITTOOR DST.)&#xA;Donated by&#xA;Pinnapati Narasimhaiah &amp;amp; Savitramma&#xA;to&#xA;C. P. Brown Memorial Trust&#xA;CUDDAPAH&#xA;A&#xA;SYMPOSIUM&#xA;ON&#xA;TIRUPATI VENKATESWARA&#xA;AUTHOR :&#xA;Dr. P. T. JAGANNADHA RAO, L.I.M.&#xA;TIRUPATI.&#xA;Published under the patronage of 18 Holiness Sri Sri Mahant Narayandossji Varu&#xA;of Sri Hathiramji Mutt,&#xA;TIRUPATI.&#xA;1952&#xA;Rights reserved)&#xA;(Price R-12-0&#xA;PRINTED AT&#xA;RATHNA PRESS,&#xA;TIRUPATI.&#xA;July 1952.C. 1000.&#xA;PREFACE.&#xA;I was brought by my father in my fifth year to Tirupati to have a Darshan of Lord Venkate&#xA;ever since I had an admiration and appretwo decades, resulting in Tirupati permanantly in&#xA;ciation for Him for over my settling down here at the year 1932. I wanted to guess what He stands for and what His message is in terms of Hindu philosophy. I came to a conclusion after twenty years. I felt it my duty to give out what 1 conceived and this booklet is its manifestation. I thank His Holi ness Sri Sri Mahant Narayanadossji Varu of Sr Hathiramji Mutt, Tirupati, who encouraged me in writing this booklet and patronised me in getting this published for the benefit of the public.&#xA;Publications under the title of &amp;lsquo;History of Tirupati&amp;rsquo; by sectarian authors gave an impetus to my quest and the latest publication &amp;ldquo;Tirupati Sri Venkateswara&amp;ndash;Balaji&amp;rsquo; by Sri V. N. Srinivasa Rao was appeasing. I feel it my duty to offer my thank: to Sri V. N. Srinivasa Rao, who has dealt with the subject in detail in an impartial and nonsectarian way. My pen recorded only original views and failed to make mention of the history, chronologi-&#xA;2&#xA;cal sovereignty, religious endowments and the mode of administration relating to the shrine. I am a disciple of Ahobila Mutt and I believe in Vaishnavism but I do not belong to the fanatic school. I am of view that every Hindu has an equal claim to Lord Venkateswara and that even non-Hindus would someday or other devote themselves to Lord Venkateswara, who is an exponent of universal oneness of religion.&#xA;May Lord Venkateswara bless us all.&#xA;P. T. Jagannadha Rao&#xA;Dedicated to&#xA;Lord Venkateswara - Balaji.&#xA;य: न : धिय: प्रचोदयात्.&#xA;TRADITIONAL TERMINOLOGY&#xA;:&#xA;TIRUPATI Tirupati is the name of the preent municipal town down the holy hill, on which Lord Venkateswara resides. The word Tirupati appears to be a dialectal form of some original Sanskrit word with some significance. In the English translation of some Malayalam manuscripts made at Chandragiri on 11-6-1802, with reference to the chronological account of sovereigns, references to this town were made as Tirupati and Teeroopaty, the latter also having the same pronunciation. But, in the report of Stratton, district collector, Chittoor, dated 31-1-1803, the hill proper was mentioned to be Tripatty Hill and Tripatty Pagoda and the village down was mentioned to be Tripatty village in all references of the report. In the Mackenzie collections, manuscript translations and reports, translated from Marati by Baboo Rao in 1804, Tripetty was the name given to this town. It is therefore to be inferred that the early part of the nineteenth century was the time for the recogni. tion of the transformation of &amp;ldquo;Tri&amp;rdquo; into &amp;ldquo;Tiru This is often the case with Sanskrit terms in South India. The cause is simplicity and facility in pronunciation, as it appeals to masses. For instance, Trichinopoly or the present day Tiruchchirapalle&#xA;2&#xA;is the transformed dialect of the Sanskrit term. &amp;ldquo;Tri Sirah Palle&amp;rdquo;. So also Trinçumoly, which stands for Trikonagiri of Sanskrit or the present day Tirukkonamalai. In these cases the Sanskrit prefix &amp;ldquo;Tri&amp;rdquo; is transformed into &amp;ldquo;Tiru&amp;rdquo; to facilitate pronunciation. Similarly in the case of the word Tirupati also the prefix &amp;ldquo;Tiru&amp;rdquo; is the transformation of &amp;ldquo;Tri&amp;rdquo; of Sanskrit origin. The original word is &amp;ldquo;TRIPATI&amp;rdquo;. In the .details of Sri Venkatesa Ashta kshari Manthram, which is adopted in the routine worship of Lord Venkateswara. its Gayathri Manthram is given as below:&amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;Venkatesaya Vidmahe, Tripati Nadhaya Dhimahi Thannah Srinivasah Prachodayath&amp;rdquo;. This Ashtakshari Manthram is in vogue in the family of the author hereditarily. Lord Venkateswara is referred therein to be the Lord of Tripati. Tripati is the name of the hill. on which Lord Venkateswara resides.&#xA;Two centuries back this town Tirupati, down the hill was a small village. Fifteen centuries back there was no village at all down the hill, but a huge forest existed, extending all round the hill upto the Bay of Bengal in the east, upto the river Pinakini or Penna in the north, and a long distance in west and south, as per the Kaifiats of Kota, Chittivel, Chowdeswari Nandavanam and Talpagiri. Gradually with the growing importance of&#xA;3&#xA;Tirupati hill, a village down the hill emanated and developed into a town. The name of the hill extended to the village or town below, which mainly depended on the former&amp;rsquo;s prosperity. Even today the public of Tirupati call the hill, UpTirupati, and the town, Down-Tirupati, the Telugu terms in vogue being &amp;ldquo;Eguva&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Eguva Tirupati &amp;quot; and &amp;ldquo;Diguva Tirupati &amp;ldquo;. This has also reference to Stratton&amp;rsquo;s report, which mentions the names of Tripatty Hill and Tripatty Village seperately.&#xA;The word Tirupati cannot be a dialectal form of Triputi❞ as interpreted by certain authors. There is no significance at all connected with the history of the place or the presiding deity. Nor is it derived from Sripati in a similar manner. The word Tirupati is a Telugu dialectal form and cannot be a Tamil one. In Tamil it should have been &amp;ldquo;Tirubadi&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Tiruppadi &amp;ldquo;. These two forms are not at all found in any part of the history of Tirupati nor in any of the inscriptions in Tamil. The hill is mentioned to be &amp;ldquo;Vengadam&amp;rdquo; in all Tamil inscriptions. It is a dialectal form of &amp;ldquo;Venkata&amp;rdquo; of Sanskrit. Tirumala of Telugu and Tirumalai of Tamil are cognates, derived from the Sanskrit word &amp;ldquo;Sri Saila&amp;rdquo; which has reference in the concerned Puranas and the history of Tirupati. But these words are of a very recent origin, coined to create difference between the hill proper and the&#xA;4&#xA;town below it. It would not be even a century since these words were used. We do not find them&#xA;in ancient literature.&#xA;TIRUCHANUR: Tiruchanur is a small village&#xA;within three miles from Tirupati. dialectal form of the Sanskrit term The transformation is as follows:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sri-suka-puri--&#34;&gt;Tiruchanur is a &amp;ldquo;Sri Suka Puri&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Sri Suka Puri -&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;वकरऽमत-बजसत-कटमशवरय-मचयत--अमतशवरय-सघतव-कटदर-रत-समत-&#34;&gt;Tiru Chugan Uru - Tiruchchuganur Tiruchchuhanur Tiruchanur. The railway station of this village is named &amp;ldquo;Chiratanur&amp;rdquo;. This is a result of metathesis according to philology. The word Tiruchchuganur is found in certain, inscriptionfrom Yogula Mallavaramu, an adjoining village of ancient repute. Sri Suka Puri is the place, where the famous saint Suka did penance and the two adjoining villages on either side of the river Swarnamukhi, namely Yogulamallavaramu and Munulapudi are pure unadulterated Telugu words with historic reference in vogue from time immemorial. By the side of Munulapudi is another village called Padipeta, renowned for its cattle wealth and Telugu origin.&#xA;A brief of this place, Tiruchanur, may not be out of place to an interested reader. Tiruchanui is now called Alamelumangapuram also. Alamelumanga Thayar or Padmavathi, alleged to be the consort of Lord Venkateswara, was installed in an&#xA;5&#xA;already existing temple at the time of Vaishnava (lomination. References from inscriptions denote an ancient temple. going by the name of &amp;ldquo;Illan Koil at Tiruchanur. Illan Koil means the temple of the younger. Vaishnavaites interpret Illan to be Bala Krishna and Saivaites interpret Illan to be Bala Subrahmanya, as sung by ancient devotees. Illan Koil is not existing now at Tiruchanur. The present temple at Tiruchanur has a presiding deity. Lord Krishna, directly opposite to the main entrance and Alamelumanga is to a side. This is an evidence to prove that the installation of Alamc lumanga is very recent. Some inscribed stones referring to Illan Koil are found in the construction of the present temple. Some other such stones with inscriptions are found at the basement of resident houses. There was an Illan Koil of Saivaite importance at Tiruchanur before the seventh century, when Saivism thrived. But sub. sequently with the downfall of Saivism during the seventh century this temple was deserted and pulled down and the stones from it were used in the construction of the present temple. Such stones, bearing inscriptions, are noted by the iconographists. To attribute the antique repute of Illan Koil to Vaishnavism the present day temple was built with Krishna as the presiding deity to represent Illan. The worship at this temple is according to Pancha Ratra Agama and by Vaishnavas, whereas the6&#xA;worship at hill to Lord Venkateswara is according to Vaikhanasa Agama and by Vaikhanasas only.&#xA;Many Alwars referred to Krishna or Manavala Perumal of Tiruchanur in their songs, which do not offer any clue to the date and place of the deity. The deities at Tiruchanur are referred to in inscriptions as Tiruvilonkoil Perumanadigal, Tirumantrasalai Perumanadigal and Tiruvengatattu Perumanadigal.&#xA;The main deity was Tiruvegatattu Perumanadigal, which was very much mistaken by many authors to be Lord Venkateswara on the hill These deities date back to the last quarter of the eighth century as per inscriptional authority. The Saivaite Illan Koil should have disappeared in the seventh century and the Vaishnavaite Illan Koil or Tiruvengatattu Perumanadigal should have come into existence early in the eighth century before the period of Sri Ramanuja itself. Inscriptional evidence of grants and endowments for the Akhandam to be maintained in this newly built temple is available. Even today an author interprets Illan Koil to be Snapana Mantapa of Lord Venkateswara&#xA;on the hill with a motive.&#xA;Very early Alwars did not visit Lord Venkateswara, but described him in their prayers to be a blend of Hari and Hara. In the tenth century Nammalwar ascended the hill and prayed Lord&#xA;7&#xA;Venkateswara to be the embodiment of the Omni.&#xA;present Vishnu. He consecrated a silver image at about 966 A.D. in the temple on the hill and called it Manavala Perumal. There is a difference of about two centuries between the consecration of a Vaishnava temple at Tiruchanur and the first Alwar to ascend the hill to consecrate a Vaishnava image on the hill. Many Alwars abstained from ascending the hill to worship Lord Venkateswara for fear that the deity was a Siva with Saivaite. paraphernalia. Customarily some turmeric and Kumkum is used to be sent from the hill to Tiruchanur during the annual festival at the latter. But there is no inscriptional evidence to prove it to be an ancient one. Silappadikaram, an oft quoted authority, the antiquity of which was dated back to about 756 A.D. by Dr. Swamikannu, does not tell. us that the hill was sacred nor does it say when the god manifested himself there. But the same authority corroborates the facts given above in respect of the deities consecrated at Tiruchanur.&#xA;ALIPIRI: This is the name, by which the foot of the hill, from where the route to the hill commences, is called. Alipiri is a pure Telugu word, meaning miniature. It means that Lord Venkateswara in his miniature form dwells there to give Darshan to his non-caste-hindu devotees, who were forbidden in those days to ascend the hill. Mala-&#xA;8&#xA;vani Gundam is a pure Telugu term. It is close to Alipiti.&#xA;That portion of&#xA;GOVINDARAJA PATTANA: Tirupati, where Lord Govindaraja is consecrated, Is called Govindaraja Pattana. Inspite of its existence from the year 1050 A.D., when Tiruverenda Yadavarayalu reigned and got Govindaraja consecrated, the whole town Tirupati is universally called Tirupati only.&#xA;CHANDRAGIRI: This is a village six miles off from Tirupati. It is of historic importance with an old fort and remnants of scientific materials, which conduct the gong sound from the Venkatadri hill to Chandragiri fort. Archaelogical findings of Jain importance are also found there. The original name is traditionally maintained in its Telugu form. In Tamil it should have been called Sandira Malai, but such a term is absent. This is supposed to have come into existence at about 1330 A.D. from the time of Saluva Mangi Deva.&#xA;THEERTHAMS: All the Theerthams of Puranic importance on and around the hill, connected with the shrme of Lord Venkateswara, have retained heir original names in Sanskrit, such as Kapila Theertham, Bheema Theertham, Gogarbham, Pandava Theertham, Akasa Ganga, Papanasanam.&#xA;9&#xA;Sesha Theertham, Ramakrishna Theertham, Thumburu Theertham, etc. There are some Theerthams, which bear pure Telugu names, such as Pasupu Theertham and Seethamma Theertham. All the names, connected with the different parts of the hill and forest around this hill, are of pure Telugu language, as inferred from any map of this hill. The words Vagu, Vanka and Kona are widely used in such terminology.&#xA;TRADITIONAL TELUGU WORDS IN USE: The following pure Telugu words were used in the time of Mackenzie in 1803 A.D.:Kuruvá Dova (Hill path), Padikavali (Gateman), Bangaru Vakili (Gold entrance), Koppera (Hundi), Gudi (Temple), Thotti Theertham (Holy water of the tub), Koluvu (Durbar), Alavattam (Fan), Parasa (Pilgrim), Kanuka (Offering), Cherupu (Food - derived from the word Cherava, meaning a wide-mouthed vessel in which food is made to offer to god), Laddu (A round pudding), Sukiya (A sweet preparation), Thena Thola (Another sweet preparation), Ookaya Pachchadi (A dish made with Ookaya), Mudupu (Money bag), Duggani (Duga+Kani=Two pies), Pavada (An offering as Bali), Etc. In the report of Stratton the following Telugu words were used :&amp;ndash; Ookaya, Kanukalu, Varthana (Maintenance), Mangala Katta (Barbers&amp;rsquo; bund), Mancham Seva or Panupu Seva (Repose worship), Addala Ara (Hall&#xA;10&#xA;of mirrors), Namala Angadi (Market of marking mud), Poola Bavi (Well used to deposit flowers), Nambi (One who worships god. This term was very widely used by both Mackenzie and Stratton). In both the above reports the following South Indian cognates were observed: Thiruvaradhana (Worship), Thomala Seva (A variety of worship). Vada (A hot cake), Poli (A sweet cake), Dosa (A flat pudding), Appam (A sweet flat pudding), Padi (A measure), Kani (A measure of land), etc. In Cox&amp;rsquo;s gazette the following words were used:Addakonda (The name of a hill), Muggu Bavi (A well or tank in the middle of the ascent of the hill), Gangalam (A wide-mouthed vessel), Poolangi (Flower decoration), Namala Guha (A cave, where white and red earth is found), etc, Zunnu Padi was endowed by Muru Raja Rama Raja Sripathi Obaleswara at about 1546 A.D. Zunnu is a Telugu term. All the traditional terms are Telugu terms but for a few Vaishnava technical terms of worship, introduced during the era of Sri Ramanuja.&#xA;VENKATESWARA : The name of the deity on He is also called Venka-&#xA;the hill is Venkateswara.&#xA;tesa, Venkatachalapati.&#xA;Venkataramana.&#xA;Tiru-&#xA;vengadaththan, etc. He is the Lord of the hill Venkata. The word Venkata is interpreted thus in Venkatachala Mahathmyam :&#xA;11&#xA;वेंकारोऽमृत बीजस्तु कटमैश्वर्य मुच्यते । अमृतैश्वर्य संघत्वा कटाद्रि रिति स्मृतः ॥&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;वरह-परण-अधय-३६---ल-३२&#34;&gt;वराह पुराणे अध्या. ३६ - लो. ३२.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vem = Eternal; Kata Bliss; Venkata = Eternal Bliss; the hill that conduces Eternal Bliss is called Venkatadri or Venkatachala and the Lord of such a hill is called Venkateswara. In another version, Vem Sin; Kata= Destroy or burn; Venkata= That which destroys or burns sins or purifier. Many authors are of opinion that these are not etymological. Sanskrit is so tightly knit that not a single word in it is left behind without an etymological origin. These interpretations are of Puranic origin only. They intend to support the supremacy of a particular deity in an idealistic way to convince the masses. The word Vengada is used by both the Andhras and Tamilians in common for Tirupati, but the etymological version is different. In the Andhra version it is Vengi Kada Vengada. ie. the boundary or limit of the territory called Vengi and ruled by the Andhra kings. In Tamil it is Ven+Gadam Vengadam, meaning a white hill. Venkatachala is said to be of a molten gold&#xA;colour and hence named Kanakachala.&#xA;It was praised as such by many devotees of Andhra and Tamil culture. It is not mentioned to be white in&#xA;12&#xA;colour by any body anywhere. Therefore the word Vengadam is only a dialectal form of the Sanskrit term, Venkata, and not an independant Tamil word. Chandramana of Hindu calendar is observed by Andhras and the Souramana by Tamilians. Here on this hill in the shrine of Lord Venkateswara Chandramana is observed. New year&amp;rsquo;s Asthanam takes place on the Telugu new year&amp;rsquo;s day. Chandramana is in use upto and includnig Sesha. chala and Souraniana beyond and south of it, as per Jyothisha Siddhantha.&#xA;SESHACHALA: SESHAGIRI: SESHADRI: SESHASAILA: These are all synonyms indicating the name of the hill, bearing reference to Sesha or the Adi Sesha. In Venkatachala Mahatınyam it is said. that Adi Sesha, in a conflict with Vayu, was blown off and deposited here. This Sesha is connected with Meru and Meru Puthra in the same Purana. This has a philosophical meaning, with special reference to the science of Yoga, which will be explained in the last chapter. BUSA NAGAPPADU is a pure Telugu term relating to Lord Venkateswara, indicating his origin to be that of a serpent, in virtue of his residence and identity with Seshadri and his emanating from an ant-hill. He is called Vyala Rupa in his one thousand names and it confirms this view.&#xA;13&#xA;SRISAILA: Srisaila and Venkatachala are synonyms. Srisaila is the original name of the hill, as illustrated in Venkatachala Mahatmya :&#xA;श्रीपदत्वात् श्रियोवासात् शब्दशक्त्याच योगतः । रूढ्या श्रीशैल इत्येवं नामचास्य गिरेरभूत् ॥&#xA;वराह पुराणे अध्या. ३६ - श्लो. ३४.&#xA;Many authors quote a verse from Rigveda and attribute it to this Venkatachala. The early commentators Sayana and Yaska completely ignored this Venkatachala. Later authors commented Vikate Girim to be Venkatachala, attributing the word Sirim Bittasya to it. Sirim Bittasya is said to be Sree Peettasya. It means that the hill is an abode of Sree, which means Sree Chakra or the supreme Chakra, the Sahasrara. This version is in common vogue both in the Andhra and Tamil countries. We hear an Andhra call this deity &amp;ldquo;Edu Kondala Vadu&amp;rdquo; and a Tamilian call this deity &amp;ldquo;Elu Malai Appan&amp;rdquo;. This is not an outcome of or a translation of or a dialectal form of any original Sanskrit term, but an original South Indian term representing this hill to be seven in number in anology to the six Chakras and the seventh SahaThe establishment of the importance of this hill connected with the Sri Chakra is not limited&#xA;srara.&#xA;14&#xA;only to South India, but extends to the whole of North India. Sri Chakra is a form of worship of Bala Tripura Sundari. Hence the North Indians call the hill and the deity &amp;ldquo;Balaji&amp;rdquo;. The Vaishnava commentary interpreted Sri to be the goddess Lakshmi, and the abode of which is Sri Nivasam. The latter term, when compounded means Vishnu, the lord of Lakshmi. But the term Sri Saila is in reference to a hill but not a deity thereupon. The derivative explanation of the term, relating to the deity, Venkata, is given quite seperately. If Sri is considered to be Lakshmi, Lakshmi-in some form or other should be the presiding deity there on the hill, irrespective of Vishnu. It is not so. There is no place seperately for either Lakshmi or any other Sree. A recent devotet connected with the management of the temple introduced &amp;ldquo;Lakshmi Devi Mahotsavam&amp;rdquo;, which did not gain any importance nor achieve the aim with which it was introduced. One should try to understand the principle on which the consort is omitted to this Lord Venkateswara. This is explained by Yoga science in the last chapter.&#xA;CONCLUSION: From a survey of traditional terminology, it is evident that all the terms are of Telugu origin. The area of the hill with its surrounding villages is purely Andhra, There are inscriptional evidences to show that many endow-&#xA;15&#xA;ments were made by Andhra kings, but it is a freak to note that such inscriptions are in Tamil. Inscriptions dating back to sixteenth century, ie. 1509. 1530 the reign of Sri Krishna Deva Raya and 1565-1684: the reign of Aravidu Rajas, appear in Tamil. It is believed that the heads of temple department then were Tamil Vaishnavaites, who took to inscriptional work in Tamil. There is no evidence to prove that Sri Krishna Deva Raya ever paid a visit to the temple of Govindaraja or that of Alamelumanga, nor that he endowed any thing to those temples.&#xA;DEVOTEES OF REPUTE.&#xA;Gopinatha is said to be the first Vaikhanasa, that worshipped Lord Venkateswara. He did penance on the hill and dedicated his life to Him. Ranga Doss was another devotee from Rangampeta. a village ten miles off from Tirupati, who dedicated his life to Lord Venkateswara. Both of them it is alleged were together doing service to god. They were supposed to be in the reign of King Sakhana of Kambhoja Desa. But historical evidences are not available. Ranga Doss was supplying flowers to god and Gopinath was worshipping god in very early days.&#xA;Thallapaka Annamacharyulu was a devotee well known to all Andhra. He was born on a full16&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SItApatiH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/sItApatiH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/sItApatiH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Book University Series&#xA;SRI VENKATESWARA&#xA;The Lord of The Seven Hills, Tirupati&#xA;P. SITAPATI&#xA;BHARATIYA VIDYA BHAVAN&#xA;आ नो भद्राः क्रतवो यन्तु विश्वतः ।&#xA;Let noble thoughts come to us from every side&#xA;-Rigveda, I-89-i&#xA;BHAVAN&amp;rsquo;S BOOK UNIVERSITY&#xA;General Editors&#xA;R. R. DIWAKAR S. RAMAKRISHNAN&#xA;156&#xA;SRI VENKATESWARA&#xA;THE LORD OF THE SEVEN HILLS, TIRUPATI&#xA;By&#xA;PIDATALA SITAPATI&#xA;93&#xA;A&#xA;BHAVAN&amp;rsquo;S BOOK UNIVERSITY&#xA;Organising Committee:&#xA;LILAVATI MUNSHI-Chairman&#xA;K. K. BIRLA&#xA;S. G. NEVATIA&#xA;J. H. DAVE&#xA;S. RAMAKRISHNAN&#xA;BHAVAN&amp;rsquo;S BOOK UNIVERSITY&#xA;SRI VENKATESWARA&#xA;THE LORD OF THE SEVEN HILLS,&#xA;TIRUPATI&#xA;By&#xA;PIDATALA SITAPATI&#xA;ரீ ராம ஜயம்&#xA;இந்தது பிரபுதம் Anjana sty. பிரமா சதெ&#xA;भारतीय&#xA;555&#xA;fara&#xA;भवन&#xA;55&#xA;21 1972&#xA;BHARATIYA VIDYA BHAVAN&#xA;CHOWPATTY: BOMBAY 7&#xA;YTB&#xA;All Rights Reserved&#xA;AЯAW&#xA;First Edition : 1968&#xA;2. Second Edition : 1972&#xA;ITATUHIT&#xA;ITAHAT&#xA;Aple&#xA;TAQUE&#xA;Price: Rs. 4.00&#xA;182&#xA;PRINTED IN INDIA&#xA;By P. H. Raman at Associated Advertisers &amp;amp; Printers, 505, Tardeo Arthur Road, Bombay-34, and Published by S. Ramakrishnan, Executive Secretary, Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan,&#xA;Kulapati K. M. Munshi Marg, Bombay-7.&#xA;GENERAL EDITOR&amp;rsquo;S PREFACE&#xA;THE Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan-that Institute of Indian Culture in Bombay-needed a Book University, a series of books which, if read, would serve the purpose of providing higher education. Particular emphasis, however, was to be put on such literature as revealed the deeper impulsions of India. As a first step, it was decided to bring out in English 100 books, 50 of which were to be taken in hand almost at once. Each book was to contain from 200 to 250 pages.&#xA;It is our intention to publish the books we select, not only in English, but also in the following Indian languages: Hindi, Bengali, Gujarati, Marathi, Tamil, Telugu, Kannada and Malayalam.&#xA;This scheme, involving the publication of 900 volumes, requires ample funds and an all-India organisation. The Bhavan is exerting its utmost to supply them.&#xA;The objectives for which the Bhavan stands are the reintegration of the Indian culture in the light of modern knowledge and to suit our present-day needs and the resuscitation of its fundamental values in their pristine vigour.&#xA;Let me make our goal more explicit :&#xA;We seek the dignity of man, which necessarily implies the creation of social conditions which would allow him freedom to evolve along the lines of his own temperament and capacities; we seek the harmony of individual efforts and social relations, not in any makeshift way, but within the framework of the Moral Order: we seek the creative art of life, by the alchemy of which human limitations are progressively transmuted, so that man may become the instrument of God, and is able to see Him in all and all in Him.&#xA;The world, we feel, is too much with us. Nothing would uplift or inspire us so much as the beauty and aspiration which such books can teach.&#xA;vi&#xA;GENERAL EDITOR&amp;rsquo;S PREFACE&#xA;In this series, therefore, the literature of India, ancient and modern, will be published in a form easily accessible to all. Books in other literatures of the world, if they illustrate the principles we stand for, will also be included.&#xA;This common pool of literature, it is hoped, will enable the reader, eastern or western, to understand and appreciate currents of world thought, as also the movements of the mind in India, which, though they flow through different linguistic channels, have a common urge and aspiration.&#xA;Fittingly, the Book University&amp;rsquo;s first venture is the Mahabharata, summarised by one of the greatest living Indians, C. Rajagopalachari; the second work is on a section of it, the Gita by H. V. Divatia, an eminent jurist and a student of philosophy. Centuries ago, it was proclaimed of the Mahabharata: &amp;ldquo;What is not in it, is nowhere&amp;rdquo;. After twenty-five centuries, we can use the same words about it. He who knows it not, knows not the heights and depths of the soul; he misses the trials and tragedy and the beauty and grandeur of life.&#xA;The Mahabharata is not a mere epic; it is a romance, telling the tale of heroic men and women and of some who were divine; it is a whole literature in itself, containing a code of life, a philosophy of social and ethical relations, and speculative thought on human problems that is hard to rival; but, above all, it has for its core the Gita, which is, as the world is beginning to find out, the noblest of scriptures and the grandest of sagas in which the climax is reached in the wondrous Apocalypse in the Eleventh Canto.&#xA;Through such books alone the harmonies underlying true culture, I am convinced, will one day reconcile the disorders of modern life.&#xA;I thank all those who have helped to make this new branch of the Bhavan&amp;rsquo;s activity successful.&#xA;1, QUEEN VICTORIA ROAD,&#xA;NEW DELHI:&#xA;3rd October, 1951.&#xA;K. M. MUNSHI&#xA;AUTHOR&amp;rsquo;S PREFACE&#xA;LORD Sri Venkateswara of the Seven Hills of Tirupati is worshipped throughout India. No comprehensive temple Monograph giving all particulars of this temple is available at present. An attempt has therefore been made in this book to prepare a temple Monograph and give authentic information about the temple and the Lord in a very comprehensive manner, studying the temple and the Lord from the historical, literary, sculptural, religious and other points of view. This book is dedicated to the twin feet of Sri Venkateswara, the Lord of the Seven Hills.&#xA;I have to acknowledge with thanks the kind encouragement given to me in the writing of this book by Sri P. V. Narasimha Rao, Minister for Education, who was previously Minister for Law and Endowments in the Government of Andhra Pradesh. This book could not have been written but for the able stenographic assistance of Shri R. Thippanna, Anantapur. I am also grateful to my Sanskrit Guru, Sri Subramanyam Sastri of Anantapur and to Mrs. Rama Devi Sitapati for valuable assistance in the preparation of this book. Thanks are also due to the T. T. Devasthanam authorities, for assistance and facilities given, in particular to Sri K. Vasudeva Rao, I.A.S., Endowments Commissioner, Govt. of Andhra Pradesh. I acknowledge with thanks the excellent photographs of Tirupati presented to me for use in this book by Sri Raju of Raju Photographic Studios, Anantapur.&#xA;I also take this opportunity to give my respectful pranams and obeisance to Jagadguru Sri Sankaracharya Swamiji of Kanchi Kamakotipeetam.&#xA;I am grateful to Dr. K. M. Munshi in particular, and the Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan, Bombay for undertaking the publication of this work in their Book-University series.&#xA;HYDERABAD, 2-10-1968.&#xA;PIDATALA SITAPATIAUTHOR&amp;rsquo;S PREFACE TO THE SECOND EDITION&#xA;The first edition of the book Sri Venkateswara, the Lord of the Seven Hills, Tirupati, was well received both by the public and the press and was sold out quickly, with the result that a second edition is now being brought out by Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan, Bombay. I am grateful to late Dr. K.M. Munshi in particular, and the Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan, Bombay, for undertaking the publication of this work in their Book University series. Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan has played, and is continuing to play, a major role in the Cultural Renaissance of this country and the credit for visualising, motivating and organising all this creative activity should go to Dr. K.M. Munshi, Kulapati of the Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan.&#xA;Lord Sri Venkateswara of the Seven Hills, Tirupati, is worshipped in India and abroad. He is the Eternal Cosmic One that is manifested at Tirupati and pervades the entire Universe. This book is dedicated to this Eternal One.&#xA;The writing of this monograph on the ancient temple of Tirupati was taken up and completed by me while I was at Anantapur, and as District Collector of Chittoor. Sahitya Ratna Sri P.V. Narasimharao, the scholar-statesman of Andhra Pradesh, was then the Minister for Law and Endowments of the Government of Andhra Pradesh. Sri Narasimharao is the architect of the model statute for religious and charitable endowments i.e., the Andhra Pradesh Charitable and Hindu Religious Institutions and Endowments Act of 1966. It was primarily his encouragement which helped me in bringing out this book and it gives me great pleasure to record my heart-felt gratitude to him. The Telugu translation of this book is on the anvil, the work having been taken up by Mrs. P. Ramadevi Sitapati conjointly with me, and I hope the Telugu version will see the light of the day as soon as possible.&#xA;This temple monograph has been revised, and it is hoped, gives authentic information about the temple and the Lord in a comprehensive manner, studying the temple&#xA;X&#xA;AUTHOR&amp;rsquo;S PREFACE TO THE SECOND EDITION&#xA;and the Deity from the historical, literary, sculptural, and other points of view.&#xA;I acknowledge with thanks the stenographic assistance of Sri R. Tippanna of Anantapur in the preparation of the book and Sri Raju of Raju Photographic Studios, Anantapur, for the excellent photographs of Tirupati presented to I am thankful to my colleague, Sri M. Chandramouli Reddy, I.A.S., Executive Officer, at present at Tirupati, for facilities afforded. The assistance of Sri M. Srinivasulu Naidu, Peshkar of the Tirupati temple, is gratefully acknowledged. I acknowledge the assistance given to me in the compilation of the book by Mrs. P. Rama Devi Sitapati and my daughter Chir. P. Jyothirlakshmi.&#xA;Several suggestions made in the first edition of the book as well as suggestions made by me as District Collector, Chittoor, have been or are in the process of being accepted by the temple authorities. It is hoped that a day will soon dawn when every devotee, whatever be his religion or nationality, will have the blessing and a &amp;lsquo;Happy Darshan&amp;rsquo; of the Lord at all times with facilities for meditation and prayer without botheration of payment of fees.&#xA;Sarve Janah Sukhino Bhavantu&#xA;VISAKHAPATNAM,&#xA;3-7-1972&#xA;P. SITAPATI&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;PAGE&#xA;I. INTRODUCTION&#xA;1&#xA;II. THE LORD IN THE TEMPLE&#xA;7&#xA;III. THE DEITIES OF THE GARBHA GRIHA&#xA;30&#xA;IV. THE TEMPLE AND ITS SCULPTURES&#xA;41&#xA;V. THE VENGADAM HILL AND THE TEMPLE THEREON&#xA;84&#xA;VI. ANANDA NILAYA VIMANAM&#xA;101&#xA;VII. SRI VENKATESWARA SUPRABHATAM&#xA;109&#xA;VIII. LEGENDS OF THE LORD OF TIRUMALAI&#xA;.. 118&#xA;IX. FESTIVALS, DAILY WORSHIP AND SOME PECULIAR&#xA;CUSTOMS IN THE TEMPLE&#xA;X. THE ADMINISTRATION OF THE TEMPLE&#xA;CONCLUSION-THE KATYAVALAMBITA MURTHI&#xA;XI.&#xA;ART PLATES AND PLAN&#xA;&amp;hellip;.AT THE END&#xA;139&#xA;..&#xA;160&#xA;198&#xA;LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS&#xA;LORD VENKATESWARA &amp;amp;&#xA;GODDESS PADMAVATI&#xA;FRONTISPIECE&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vn shrInivAsaH</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/vn_shrInivAsaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/lies/vn_shrInivAsaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;majestic-setting-of-the-shrine-to-probe-into-its-past-and-interpret-its-message-which-the-seven-sacred-hills-silently-whisper-if-these-pages-help-the-pilgrim-to-beguile-an-idle-hour-while-sojourning-on-the-hills-i-shall-be-content-if-however-they-are-able-to-convince-scholars-better-fitted-for-the-task-that-there-is-still-a-rich-field-for-research-here-and-induce-them-to-further-effort-and-succeed-also-in-awakening-the-interest-of-the-busy-politicians-in-the-temple-and-guide-them-to-correct-lines-of-approach-in-framing-the-new-administrative-set-up-i-shall-feel-amply-rewarded-for-the-labour&#34;&gt;TIRUPATI&#xA;SRI VENKATESVARA - BALAJI&#xA;(Origin, Significance &amp;amp; History of the Shrine)&#xA;TIRUPATI&#xA;SRI VENKATESVARA-BALAJI&#xA;(Origin, Significance &amp;amp; History of the Shrine)&#xA;By&#xA;V. N. SRINIVASA RAO&#xA;Tahsildar, Chittoor Dt. and&#xA;Asst. Commissioner, Hindu Religious Endowments (Retired)&#xA;With a Foreword by&#xA;Rao Bahadur Sri N. CHANDRASEKHARA AIYAR, B.A., B. L. (Retd.) Judge, High Court of Judicature, Madras.&#xA;(Copyright reserved by the Author)&#xA;Published by UMADEVAN &amp;amp; CO&#xA;MADRAS&#xA;1949&#xA;For the statements made&#xA;and the views expressed the author alone is responsible.&#xA;Printed at The Jupiter Press Ltd., 16, Sembudoss Street, G. T., Madras.&#xA;Kalyana Venkatesvara, (Mangapuram) Chandragiri&#xA;[Photo by: Mr. A. Balasubramanyam, Chittoor.]&#xA;DEDICATED&#xA;TO&#xA;LORD SRI VENKATESVARA&#xA;८८&#xA;यत्तत्परमनिर्देश्यमचिन्त्यमजमक्षरम् ।&#xA;अव्यक्तमजरं नित्यमव्ययं धाम शाश्वतम् ॥ अरूपममलं ब्रह्म सर्वेशमचलं विभुम् । यद् ब्रह्म तत् परं धाम भवानेव न चापरः ॥ तन्न विद्मः परं रूपं तव यत्तु पुरातनम् । एतच्चापि न जानीमां यदेतद्दर्शितं त्वया ॥&#xA;प्रसीद विश्वेश्वर विश्वतोमुख&#xA;प्रसीद विश्वक्षयपालनेश ।&#xA;प्रसीद विश्वालय विश्वमूर्ते&#xA;विश्वस्य योने भगवन् प्रसीद || ”&#xA;&amp;ndash; Vamana Purana, Kshetra Kanda, Venkatachala&#xA;Mahatmya, Adhyaya 35.&#xA;FOREWORD&#xA;This is a very readable book well-written and full of information about Tirupati, and the sacred hill called Tirumalai, over which presides the Lord Sri Venkatesvara. The author Mr. V. N. Srinivasa Rao deserves to be congratulated on the scholarship and powers of research he has brought to bear on this work.&#xA;In dealing with the question whether the deity.was Vishnu or Siva originally, we are on debatable ground. Mr. Srinivasa Rao controverts vigorously the theory propounded by Dr. S. Krishnaswami Aiyangar in his history of Tirupati to the effect that the image was a Vaishnavite one right through. The correct identification of Ghattideva, in whose time it is alleged that the Siva-Vishnu controversy about the Tirumalai shrine was finally settled, receives much attention at the author&amp;rsquo;s hands who is convinced that he was not a Yadava Chief who had any sway over the Tirupati region as Dr. Krishnaswami Aiyangar holds, but that he was a minor chieftain in the Nellore District. Mr. Srinivasa Rao gives several reasons why the idol was probably a Saivite one at the commencement when the shrine was founded. Some of them are at least as convincing as those advanced to support the opposite view. One can add two more also. From time immemorial, the deity has been famous throughout India as Sri Balaji, which is the special name of God Subrahmanya. The sacred tank on the hill is known as the Svami Pushkarini and by the word &amp;lsquo;Svami&amp;rsquo; is generally meant Kumarasvami.&#xA;Of what avail are all these controversies. The Kularnava Tantra furnishes a definite negative answer to the question. Sectarian bigots may revel in them but not they who think of God as One, with several names and forms. God Venkatesvara on the Tirumalai Hill is common to all worshippers of the Hindu faith, be they Vaishnavites or Saivites. He sheds His grace on all His devotees equally and impartially. He is the are in this Kali Age, and in His presence, all differences and controversies of faith and ritual lose their significance altogether and are hushed. True devotion transcends barriers of creed, sect, and class. It has been well said that while it is good to be bornVI&#xA;in a church, it is bad to die in it. As introspection increases, as bhakti progresses, and as the realisation of Truth comes over a man gradually, he feels amused at the bitterness which even well-read people display in the discussion of sectarian subjects, often losing balance of mind and a sense of true proportion of real values. If God has a form-but mystics and sages of all religions say he has none-does it matter really if He appears to you with astrident namam in his forehead, or three parallel and horizontal lines of viboothi, or without any mark whatsoever?&#xA;To say all this is not to belittle the commendable efforts of Mr. Srinivasa Rao, whose theme is exactly the same&amp;ndash;namely that Lord Venkatesvara represents the Absolute and is the God of all Hindus equally irrespective of divisions and sects and castes and creeds. The chapters of the work dealing with the puranic stories about Lord Sri Venkatesvara and Sri Padmavati and the esoteric significance of the sacred hill and the shrine are of special interest and those who read them will undoubtedly increase their stock of knowledge. What is known as the SawalE-Jawab, a memoir of questions put to the sthanikas of the temple in 1801 by Mr. Stratton, the then Collector of the Western Palayams, and the answers given by them concerning the origin, history and administration of the temple, has been fully extracted in this work and contains valuable information, throwing a flood of light on many of the questions discussed. The author has laid the public under a deep debt of obligation to him by bringing out a book of this kind, carefully prepared and well-documented. It is a book that must find a place in the library of every student of Hindu theology and every sincere bhakta of God.&#xA;Madras,&#xA;221da948.}&#xA;N. CHANDRASEKHARA AIYAR.&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;There are few families in South India with a history of sickness or grave anxiety who have not made vows to Tirupati Venkatachalapati and have not had thrilling experiences of relief and help or awe-inspiring and exacting reminders of unfulfilled vows. Among the few families that do not visit the temple are those who are known as &amp;ldquo;Tirupati Dongalu&amp;rdquo; or Tirupati thieves, so called, because their ancestors, having made vows to the God and not having fulfilled them, have for ever been debarred from visiting the temple.&#xA;An enterprising Parapatyadar could easily benefit himself and also serve the public, by collecting true stories of the miracles worked by the God, from the pilgrims who daily pour their offerings into the temple Hundi. If the West had anything equal to it which could draw such immense crowds from all parts of the country, day-in and day-out, in fair weather and foul, in times of war as in peace, regardless of distance and discomforts of travel, through all the long centuries, it is inconceivable to what wonderful use they would have put the wealth of the emotional appeal contributed by such an ancient shrine. At least, a special library of literature would have sprung round it and the holy precincts would have been converted into a very heaven on earth. Unfortunately we cannot even claim to possess an authoritative and impartial history of the shrine and the surroundings of the temple are now anything but holy.&#xA;We do lip service to our cultural heritage and talk of our mission of spiritualising the materialistic West, but have very little to show concretely that we actually practise the truths that we profess to believe in. The West with true humility admits that its civilisation is materialistic but practises the divine virtue of reverence for all forms of life and judges its ascent in the scale of civilisation by the amount of happiness it is able to ensure for the common man, though within the narrow limits of its own nationality.&#xA;Even our temples, designed by our sages to proclaim the truths realized by them personally and to promote the development of God-Consciousness, have been left in sole charge of priests who&#xA;V111&#xA;have forgotten the fundamental tenets of the institutions which they guard and make a fetish of the idols which are only symbols intended to aid worship. Their contribution to the shrines, where they preside, is a crop of civil suits regarding the length, breadth and shape of the face-mark that should adorn the image. and such other trivial matters, which render the task of the apologist for our, so called, religious practices greatly embarrassing. Hereditary office, intended to ensure a succession of Gurus (Gurukkals) trained and disciplined in Yoga and God-Consciousness from early childhood, has, by the security of office it ensures, produced a breed of priests with vested interests, who befoul the sacred atmosphere of the temples with intolerance, bigotry, hatred, sectarianism, and hypocrisy. Our present Governments cast greedy eyes on the rich income of temples, like Tirupati, as resources to be tapped for miscellaneous objects which they cannot conveniently provide for in the usual budgets. They show no imagination to utilise the immense power of shrines like Tirupati for the moral re-armament of the Hindu society. The last two wars have rudely shaken the ethical foundations of our society and the old codes of moral values and personal conduct, do not govern the present trends of thought among the masses. A National Government should take stock of the situation and urgently endeavour to arrest this degeneration, and to restore faith in God and pride in our spiritual heritage by canalising the immense power which our temples still wield on the public mind.&#xA;As the Vedanta satisfies the needs of a Universal Religion, Sri Venkatesvara is a concrete representation of the one God, Supreme Brahman or the Absolute, without name or form or sect or creed. This temple is unique in the whole of India and has been a place of worship common to all sects and creeds of Hindus for centuries together and has been a powerful unifying force by its non-sectarian appeal to us to cast out Ahankara or &amp;lsquo;I am-ness&amp;rsquo; and discarding desire and fear to lead our lives as free men in fellowship with God. The world has still a good future, if it would but listen to the message of Sri Venkatesvara.&#xA;The name Venkatesvara merely means the Lord of Vengada, which denotes the hill and also the human body, which is con-&#xA;1X&#xA;tinuously scorched by animal heat. Thus the God has no name. He has no specific form, but all manifested forms, such as Shakti, Siva, Vishnu and Brahma are His forms. The whole range of the Eastern Ghats from Tirupati to Guntur was known to the ancients as Sri Parvata but the portion of the range within the limits of the present Kurnool and Guntur Districts was called by the Telugu speaking people of the locality as &amp;lsquo;Nallamalais&amp;rsquo; or Black Mountains&amp;rsquo;, while the portion within the limits of a part of the present Cuddapah District and the entire Chittoor District was called by the local Tamil residents as Vengadam or White mountain, on account of the buff colouring of its cliff-faces, to distinguish it from Nallamalais. Venkatachalamahatmyam also refers to the Tirupati range as &amp;lsquo;Srisailam&amp;rsquo; or Sri Parvata, the mountain of the Divine Mother. She has, in Her ample bosom, room enough for all. It is on record that even Europeans and Muhammadans, though prohibited from ascending the hills, felt no repugnance in making vows and sending offerings to the shrine.&#xA;The following studies on the origin, significance, early history and administration of the temple, undertaken as a hobby were intended to accompany iny translation of a Telugu account of the temple, in the form of questions and answers, Sawal-EJawab, contributed to the Quarterly Journal of the Mythic Society; but as it would take a long time for the entire matter to appear in a quarterly, I was prevailed upon by my friend Sri Ponneri Sriramulu Chettiar of Madras, a philanthropist well known for his liberal patronage of Education and Religion and who is a great devotee of Sri Venkatesvara, to publish them in book form and he has kindly undertaken to meet the cost of printing and publication. I cannot adequately express my indebtedness to him for encouraging my humble effort and for enabling me to place the materials gathered by me before a wider circle of readers. Personally, I class this offer, among the minor miracles worked by Sri Venkatesvara, to confirm my faith in His grace to bless any correct endeavour of even the humblest of His devotees, regardless of the merits of the performance.&#xA;I claim no originality for the views stated in the book. My approach to the subject has been that of a pilgrim visiting the shrine, whose curiosity is impelled by the serene beauty and the&#xA;X&#xA;majestic setting of the shrine, to probe into its past and interpret its message which the seven sacred hills silently whisper. If these pages help the pilgrim to beguile an idle hour while sojourning on the hills, I shall be content. If, however, they are able to convince scholars, better fitted for the task, that there is still a rich field for research here and induce them to further effort and succeed also in awakening the interest of the busy politicians in the temple and guide them to correct lines of approach in framing the new administrative set up, I shall feel amply rewarded for the labour.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is true that the Devasthanam Committee had commissioned Dr. Krishnaswami Aiyangar to write a history of the temple, giving expression to certain views regarding the origin and institutions of the temple, but by stating that there is also room for other points of view, no disrespect to the memory of the learned Doctor is meant. Valuable as it is, Dr. Krishnaswami Aiyangar&amp;rsquo;s work has not rendered further research on the subjects superfluous. It is not however claimed that the present study exhausts the subject. It may be taken as one more attempt to study a rich subject from a fresh angle; moreover, it is attempted here to bring the history of the temple up to date and naturally it covers fresh ground. The book falls into four natural divisions.&#xA;Part Iis a guide to the temple, its daily routine, darshanams,&#xA;utsavams and fees; it also suggests the spiritual significance of the Seven Hills and interprets the message of the shrine, as embedded in the sthalapurana; extracts from the Mackenzie collections, regarding the routes, daily routine etc., as they were in 1800 A.D., are also given.&#xA;Part II-sketches the early history of the Shrine basing mainly on unpublished local records contained in the Mackenzie collection, Archaeological reports, and inscriptions. In view of the fresh light thrown by some records a few suggestions are offered regarding the identification of Vengadam of the Alvars&amp;rsquo; songs; some space has been devoted to the Siva-Vishnu controversy, not on account of itc intrinsic worth, but as Dr. Krishnaswami Aiyangar has &amp;lsquo;dealt with nothing else, in his two volumes of the History of Tirupati and has actively revived the controversy, it&#xA;XI&#xA;was not found possible to omit mention of it altogether, in a work dealing with the history of the shrine.&#xA;Part III-sketches the administrative history of the temple from 1800 A. D. up to date. It is based on Manuscript Transla. tions of Mackenzie Collections, Reports, Parliamentary papers, court exhibits and contemporary history; the origin of the several fees levied at the temple for darshanams, utsavams etc. is traced. It will be found to be of topical interest in the context of the proposed amendment of the present Devasthanam Act; further,. this part contains several interesting extracts from Reports in the Mackenzie collection, regarding the condition of Tirumalai and the state of worship in the temple at the close of the Eighteenth Century.&#xA;Part IV-is a translation of an account of the temple, furnished by the Stanikas in charge of the temple in a. D. 1800, in the form of questions and answers, Sawal-E-Jawab, to Mr. Stratton, the first Collector of the District, on the assumption of the direct management of the temple by the East India Company. It is of special interest as showing the honesty and the liberal spirit that pervaded the temple administration at the close of the eighteenth century. The Stanikas were not shy to admit that the God was worshipped as Siva according to the forms of Saiva-Agama for sometime and then as Subrahmanya up to the date of the transfer of the temple to the custody of the Vaishnavas, due to the efforts of Sri Ramanuja. This effectively clinches the arguments of Dr. S. Krishnaswami Aiyangar&amp;rsquo;s school of writers, that the temple has always been that of Vishnu.&#xA;The book is thus intended to appeal to the Pilgrim, to the Scholar and to the Politician.&#xA;I have, mostly, allowed my authorities to speak for themselves and I believe that this arrangement leaves the reader free to draw his own conclusions from the material placed before him.&#xA;I regret that a few errors have crept into the book in the spelling of proper names like Padmavati and names&#xA;X11&#xA;ending with Svami and special terms like Shanka, Navaneetham, Devasthanam, Mahatmyam, Ashtotra, Thirtham, Sthala, Maharata, Sawal-E-Jawab etc.&#xA;The manuscript of the book was sent to the Press in January 1948 but owing to a variety of unforeseen circumstances the printing could not be completed before the end of the year.&#xA;My obeisance to Lord Sri Venkatesvara, to whom the work is dedicated, for His grace in permitting my humble effort at understanding His mystery, to see the light of the day.&#xA;May His grace abide with you all!&#xA;Madras,&#xA;1st January 1949.}&#xA;V. N. SRINIVASA RAO.&#xA;ACKNOWLEDGMENTS&#xA;I have great pleasure in acknowledging my indebtedness to several friends who have helped me with manuscripts, records and quotations from ancient literature, relating to the temple, without which the work could not have been undertaken. It would be invidious to mention only a few names but I cannot omit mention of Sri D. Kalyana Rao of Chittoor, who had kindly presented me with the manuscript of Sawal-E-Jawab, which really started me on these studies, nor can I fail to acknowledge my obligations to my brother Mr. V. N. Shama Rao, B.A., B.L., Advocate, T. Nagar, who not only encouraged me to write the history but kindly perused the manuscript and took several photos of the temple and its surroundings, some of which appear as illustrations in this book. My thanks are due to Mr. T. R. Ramakrishna Sastriar, M.A., B.L, an erudite Sanskrit scholar, for kindly looking through the manuscript, for checking the Sanskrit quotations, for furnishing correct translations of them and for generally checking up the portions relating to the esoteric significance of the shrine and suggesting improvements. I am also indebted to Mr. V. Venkatasubba Aiyar, B.A., Retired Epigraphist, Madras, for not only helping me to get at the original transcripts of the inscriptions referred to in the book and furnishing me with true translations of them, but also for perusing the manuscript and checking up the chapters on the early history and suggesting corrections and improvements. I greatly appreciate the help rendered by my nephew Mr. V. N. Srinivasa Rao, M. A. (Oxon.), Bar-at-Law, Madras, in closely checking up the manuscript, suggesting improvements, preparing the manuscript for the Press and in correcting the proofs.&#xA;I had the singular good fortune of receiving invaluable help from the India Office Library, London, now designated Commonwealth Relations Office Library, through&#xA;through its distinguished Librarian, Dr. H. N. Randle, C. I. E., M. A., D. Phil. I had applied to him after sending the manuscript to the Press. He was kind enough to loan to me, first, the original detailed critical catalogue of the Mackenzie Manuscript Transla-&#xA;X1V&#xA;tions and Reports, to guide me to select the volumes relevant to the subject and then, arranged to send urgently, three heavy volumes, in hermetically sealed cases, at the cost of the library, for my perusal at Madras. As the printing of the book had been delayed for want of paper, opportunity was taken to introduce several selections from these volumes, some in the body of the book and some as notes under the relevant chapters, thus richly contributing to the research value of the book. This instance is sufficient to give an insight into the efficiency and organization of British Libraries and their spirit of service in the cause of knowledge. I am very grateful to Dr. H. N. Randle. as he had enabled me, within a very short time, to obtain a general idea of the historical material contained in the Mackenzie manuscripts, which I could not get by months of wading through the mass of moth-eaten original manuscripts in the local library, which has not even got a detailed catalogue showing their contents. How much we wish the Doctor were in India to infuse the true library spirit and order, at least in our larger libraries in the City! I am greatly beholden to Rao Bahadur Sri N. Chandrasekhara Aiyar, B.A., B.L., Retired Judge of the Madras High Court, who is properly a native of Tirupati, for not only perusing the manuscript and suggesting valuable corrections, but for kindly writing a Foreword for this book. I acknowledge the help rendered to me by Sri P. Balakrishnamurti, B.O.L., Tirupati, in translating the Sawal-E-Jawab account.&#xA;My thanks are due to the Mythic Society, Bangalore, for kindly permitting me to reprint the Sawal-E-Jawab, and for also lending me four blocks, which were used for illustrating my article&#xA;on Chandragiri, previously contributed to the Journal.&#xA;I thank the Proprietor, Luz Studio, Mylapore, for taking the photos for the illustrations in the book and I thank also the Directors, The Jupiter Press, Ltd., Madras, for the uniform courtesy and accommodation shown to me during the course of the printing and publication of the book.&#xA;Mudras, 1st January 1949. [&#xA;V. N. SRINIVASA RAO.&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;Part I. Guide to the Temple, The Daily Routine of Worship, Fees etc. and The Significance of the Symbology of the Seven Hills.&#xA;Chapter&amp;rsquo;&#xA;I. General Description&#xA;Page&#xA;II. Routes to the Hill Shrine&#xA;III. The Temple-Daily Routine&#xA;7&#xA;IV. The Puranic Story of the Origin of the Shrine&#xA;and its Spiritual Significance&#xA;39&#xA;51&#xA;59&#xA;V. Sri Sankaracharya and the Tirumalai Shrine VI. The Message of the Shrine&#xA;Part 11. Early History and Transfer of the Temple to&#xA;Sri Vaishnavas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
