<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;0 on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;0 on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 DEDICATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/1_DEDICATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/1_DEDICATION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Invoking the Blessings of Lord Varadaraja and His Consort, this work is dedicated to our eminent Acharya Sri Lakshmi Kumara Tatadesika, the Sri Karya-durandara of Temples and the Royal-preceptor of the Vijayanagar monarchs, who is deified in the Temple along with his Consort.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 CONTENTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/2_CONTENTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/2_CONTENTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-preface-by-r-varada-tatacharya&#34;&gt;Foreword &amp;quot; by Dr. V. Varadacharya&#xA;4&#xA;1.&#xA;2.&#xA;Publisher&amp;rsquo;s Note&#xA;Sri Tatadesika Tiruvamsastar,&#xA;3. Preface by R. Varada Tatacharya&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Introductory&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Chapter&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I (Part I)&#xA;II&#xA;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;III&#xA;IV&#xA;99&#xA;Page&#xA;i&#xA;Saba, Kanchi&#xA;xiv&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;XV&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;1&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4&#xA;12&#xA;23&#xA;404&#xA;8.&#xA;30&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;33&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;9.&#xA;V&#xA;33&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;10.&#xA;1&#xA;99&#xA;(Part II)&#xA;42&#xA;11.&#xA;II&#xA;49&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;12.&#xA;III&#xA;53&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;99&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;13.&#xA;IV&#xA;65&#xA;37&#xA;14.&#xA;V&#xA;89&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;15.&#xA;VI&#xA;96&#xA;99&#xA;99&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;16.&#xA;VII&#xA;104&#xA;99&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;17.&#xA;VIII&#xA;107&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;18.&#xA;IX&#xA;111&#xA;&amp;ldquo;3&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;19.&#xA;X&#xA;116&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;39&#xA;97&#xA;20.&#xA;2323&#xA;23.&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;rdquo;&#xA;24.&#xA;25.&#xA;Conclusion&#xA;21. Appendix-A-1 to A-5 (Bibliography)&#xA;22. Appendix-B&#xA;26.&#xA;27.&#xA;29&#xA;(Inscriptions)&#xA;C-1 to C-16 (Historical Extracts)&#xA;D-A&#xA;E&#xA;F&#xA;Abbreviations&#xA;28. Index&#xA;delineation of Sri Tuppul Desika&amp;rsquo;s Mangalasasanam The services of Tatacharyas in the Temple with their significance&#xA;192&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;The genealogy of Tatacharyas 195&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;196&#xA;197&#xA;120&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;124&#xA;131&#xA;159&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;188&#xA;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 FOREWORD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/3_FOREWORD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/3_FOREWORD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have great pleasure in writing the Foreword&#xA;to the &amp;ldquo;Critical Survey&amp;rdquo; written by my esteemed friend Sri R. Varada Tatacharya who undertakes a critical study of Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Sri Varadarajaswami Temple, Kanchi&amp;rdquo;. The author throws much light on the crucial issues raised and discussed by Dr. K. V. Raman.&#xA;Dr. K. V. Raman has made an orginal contribution on the history and management of this temple. He deserves credit for collecting the required data from various sources and presenting them in this book. Among the ten chapters, which this con- tains, special mention must be made of Ch. II VIII, IX &amp;amp; X for the valuable information they contain. At the same time, it must be said that the book abounds in conclusions arrived at hypo- thetically, assumptions based on predilections and hastily drawn observations. As a diligent and hard worker in the field of re- search, he could have avoided much of these. His purpose in writing the Thesis on the subject treated in this book, is not merely to provide relevant information as found in the four chapters noted above but also, or rather to suggest, on the basis of available evidence, that the Tenkalai traits are predominantly noticed in this temple.&#xA;In this book &amp;ldquo;Critical Survey&amp;rdquo;, Sri R. Varada Tatacharya has ably brought to light the shortcomings and defects found in Dr. K.V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s book and after a critical examination of them, has advanced sound arguments while refuting them. In this, he proves himself to be free from bias and has pinned his faith on authentic evidence for drawing his conclusions. He has avoided the narratives and anecdotes that are irrelevant and so his work is mainly a Critical Survey of Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s book.&#xA;Of the several ways adopted by man to convey his feelings and intentions to another, writing occupies a more prominent position than others. The written records endure as long as the materials in which they are presented last. They are to serve&#xA;viii&#xA;their purpose by educating the people and guiding them on- right lines. The historian has a significant role to play as a writer. He has to present the past occurrences as they happened then without idealising them with his personal views and avoid- ing speculations. Loose statements and expressions that serve no purpose shall not find room in his writings. Otherwise, he will be arousing confusion among the unlearned who have more faith in it than in their understanding of it. The Lord&amp;rsquo;s utterance &amp;ldquo;na buddhibhedam janayet&amp;rdquo; (Gita 3.26) &amp;ldquo;The wise man shall not disturb the minds, (of the unlearned)&amp;rdquo; must be respected. Posterity shall not be drawn astray to wrong thinking developed by careless writing.&#xA;Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s writing is uniformly good but expres- sions like &amp;lsquo;probably&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;it appears&amp;rsquo;, &amp;lsquo;it seems&amp;rsquo; and others are found used without adequate justification. The word &amp;lsquo;probably&amp;rsquo; shall be used when something could not be affirmed as &amp;lsquo;is&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;is not&amp;rsquo;. There is room for indecision here. If there is scope here for taking a position in between &amp;lsquo;is&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;is not&amp;rsquo; and if this position has a leaning on probability without detriment to improbability, then expressions like these could be used. Predilection for a dogma and intentional advocacy for a creed shall not be the ground for using them particularly when their use could not be substantiated. Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s use of them is likely to lead casual readers to treating his writing as having veracity which it does not possess.&#xA;The second point that requires consideration here is the author&amp;rsquo;s attempt to prove Alakiya Manavala Jiyar as responsible for the building of some structures in the temple and that he wielded influence over the administration of the temple. This is far from true. In the present case, the Jiyar is mentioned in two inscriptions as doing Srikaryam service in the temple. He is not mentioned there with any honorific such as Srimadvedamargapratishtapanacarya indicating his status as Guru of the then rulers, who were the Kings at Vijayanagaram. On whose authority, did he take up the work of building the structures in the temple? What was he before the dates of these inscriptions and what happened to him after this period, when&#xA;ix&#xA;according to the inscriptions, there were others doing the Sri- karyam work? He had no hand in the building of the hundred- pillared mandapam and the figure of the ascetic carved there is certainly not his. Besides, the inscription in the temple of Sri Dipaprakasa mention one Alakiya Manavala Jiyar as well studied in both the Vedantas and as an authority in the Sri- bashya. As the dates are not mentioned here, it is not possible to identify the ascetic. In one other respect, the author has erred. Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyangar is stated by him as the first person to hold the post of Srikaryam in this temple.&#xA;Nextly, it must be said that there is no substance in using the word Prabandhaic predominance with reference to this temple. To whichever sect the temple could belong, every shrine of the major kind has smaller shrines for the Alvars and Acharyas. Annual. birthday festivals for these are performed with the recitation of the Vedas and Divyaprabandham. Likewise, the rituals in the temple are conducted in strict accordance to the Vaikhanasa or Pancharatra Agama. The recitation of the Vedas or the Prabandhams do not form part of the ritual. Where then does the question arise about the relative importance of the Prabandham ?&#xA;It is idle to argue that the character of the sub-shrines should determine the original nature of the main shrine. It must also be borne in mind that the deities of the central shrines alone get daily puja elaborately. This is proof to admit that the nature of the sub-shrines should be in accordance with that of the central shrines and not vice-versa.&#xA;Sri R. Varada Tatacharya has done well by drawing atten- tion to many of these shortcomings such as non-mention of the Vedaparayana and its attractiveness, Tatadesikan&amp;rsquo;s Tiruna- ksatra festival and of the Vadakalai marks which are promi- nently displayed in the temple. Again, it will be appropriate to refer to Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s remarks on the Tatacharyas and their position in this temple. In his view, there is no evidence from the inscriptions that they were at Kanchi before the middle of the 16th century. With the downfall of the Vijaya- nagaram rule, they left Kanchi to&#xA;left Kanchi to seek their fortunes elsewhere. They returned to Kanchi about the beginning of&#xA;K&#xA;X&#xA;the 18th Century. That these are mere assumptions for which evidences are not available in well argued by Sri R. Varada Tatacharya.&#xA;Some observations may be made here for clarifying the issues. It is known to everybody that Ramanuja received instructions of the Ramayana from Srisailapurna and taught them to his pupils. Pillan his spiritual son inherited this traditional doctrine from his Guru and taught them to his pupils and descendants. The Ettur brothers had inherited the secret doctrines of the Ramayana from their ancestors who descended from Srisaila Purna and Pillan. With their abiding faith in the efficacy in the immortal epic, they were able to drive away the evil spirits from the palace of the Vijayanagaram Rulers, as a result of which Virupaksha, the then Ruler displayed his leanings on Vaishnavism. The successive rulers became Vaishnavas. The descendants of Virupaksha became the disciples of the members of the family of the Ettur brothers and their descendants. It is the members of this family that were responsible for the spread of Vaishnavism in the Vijayanagaram Empire and took keen interest in the maintenance of the Varadarajaswami Temple at Kanchipuram. Achyutaraya and Krishnadevaraya, in particular, paid visits to the Kanchipuram Temple and worshipped the Lord, making several endowments to the temple. It is not therefore surprising to note that Lakshmi Kumara Tatadesikan was much devoted to Sri Rama whose name he uttered repeatedly, as a result of which he was saved from robbers by Hanuman. Out of gratitude and in commemoration of the help rendered by Hanuman, Lakshmi Kumara Tatadesika composed a poem Hanumadvimsati in 24 slokas which are engraved in the walls of the temple built by him on the banks of the tank Tatasamudra, which It is also engraved in the main gopura&#xA;he calls in this poem as Ramatataka. on the outer walls in the Hastigiri, and in the shrine of Perundevi Tayar. It is published by Sri Harihara Sastri and Dr. V. Raghavan in the journal of Oriental Research Vol. XVIII Part I 1950. The Ramayana tradition was thus unbroken in the family.&#xA;xi&#xA;If the Ettur brothers had been along with their family enjoying royal patronage at Vijayanagaram it does not follow that the cousins and kinsmen of these brothers had left Kanchi once for all. Those who remained behind were also the members of the Tatacharya family..&#xA;Inscriptions are really invaluable for the information they contain on the events and donations recorded during that period. They have value only for that period. Non- mention of these in the inscriptions of other period does not prove that such events did not occur at other times and donations of the same or other kinds were not made, and the persons of the families to which they belonged did not live there. Inscriptions are not diaries to offer day-to- day reports of the occurrences. The Tatacharyas, who were the Rajagurus, did guide their patrons in matters spiritual and also secular in nature. They were guiding the administra- tion of the temple through the persons whom, their patrons appointed, at their direction, to attend to the work of the Srikaryam in the temple. Alakiya Manavala Jiyar was one such person.&#xA;Perfect amity that prevailed then did not restrain the Tatacharyas from choosing him for this post. It will be wrong to suggest that the Tatacharyas changed the Srikaryams out of spite. They had to be replaced because of the need to pay personal attention to the work then undertaken in the temple. This should be sufficient to explain why the Tatacharyas are mentioned in the inscriptions made after the middle of the 16th century. The inscriptions, which were issued occasionally did not therefore refer to the presence of the Tatacharyas at Kanchi before 16th century. Besides, building of the portions, and additions made to the structures in the temple were undertaken only in the 16th century. The Tatacharyas were then at Vellore and Chandragiri nearer to Kanchi. Panchamathabhanjanam Tatadesikan and his illustrious son Lakshmikumara Tatadesikan played a notable part in guiding these constructions. It is worth noting here that the building of the hundred pillared mandapam was begun at the instance of the father and completed during the glorious period of the son. This is not a conjecture.&#xA;xii&#xA;It is also worth noting here that the Tatacharyas had their agents to look after their work in the temple. Ettur Tirumala Kumara Tatacharya is often mentioned in the inscriptions as attending to the work of Srikaryam himself and at times through his agents. There is also mention of one Tiruppani pillai who attended to the construction work in the temple and also to Srikaryam. as the agent of the Tatacharyas.&#xA;Coming to, the contribution made by Sri R. Varada Tata- charya, it must be said that he has wisely divided his work into two parts. In the first part, he prepares the ground for a proper understanding of what he intends to prove and maintain. What is outstanding in this part is the historicity of the positions held by the Tatacharyas in the court of the Vijaya- nagaram rulers. The second part is devoted to a critical examination of the theories, arguments based on them and the conclusions drawn on them by Dr. K. V. Raman. The latter&amp;rsquo;s findings are shown to be unacceptable on the strength of evidence, employing cogent reasonings. Mention must be made here to his well reasoned arguments levelled against Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s treatment of the History of Management in the Post Vijayanagaram period. Why did the Collector ignore the petitions of the Tenkalais and the Stalattars and prefer the Tatacharyas to them? Dr. K. V. Raman does not provide the answer to this question. Sri Varada Tatacharya does offer an explanation to this. In support of this explanation, he brings the entire records comprising correspondences, legal documents and the like which shows that he is guided in these matters by authority and is not swayed, by partisanship and the consequent appeals to emotion. His contribution is indeed admirable.&#xA;The value of Sri Varada Tatacharya&amp;rsquo;s book is high and is made further to rise by the appendage in the form of nearly fourty illustrations all taken from this temple and all of them prominently displaying the Vadakalai sectarian marks. All these are obtained at present in the temple. To one who entertains misgivings about the genuineness of these illustra- tions, the only answer that could be given is to ask him to pay a visit to this temple and verify the true nature of them.&#xA;xiii&#xA;Those who are interested in knowing the way in which the temple developed and how and why the Tatacharya families have been holding it dear to their heart have only to read this book of Sri R. Varada Tatacharya. It will not be an exaggera- tion if this book is said to serve as the source book for further writings on this theme. The author&amp;rsquo;s zeal and enthusiasm in safeguarding the original form, nature and character of this temple have prompted him to devote all his life for the cause of this temple, without ever seeking to get a job for which he is adequately qualified. The Vaishnava community is bound to be grateful to him for making this worthy contribution.&#xA;Dr. V. VARADACHARYA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 PUBLISHER&#39;S NOTE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/4_PUBLISHERS_NOTE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/4_PUBLISHERS_NOTE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We the members of Sri Tatadesika Tiruvamsastar Sabha and ancient adherents to Sri Varadarajaswami Temple, Kanchi entrusted this noble service of compiling this book to our esteemed brother Sri R. Varada Tatacharya, experienced as he is as a Trustee of the Temple for well nigh three decades. Our sole object in this venture is to provide a true and unbiased history of the Temple, its character and management based on archaeological, inscriptional and irrebuttable evidence, documentary and intrinsic. One of the main aims in starting the Sabha more than a decade ago, is also to serve such a purpose viz to bring out a historical treatise of our Temple and the contribution of our forebears towards its improvement and maintenance.&#xA;True to his life as an ardent devotee of the Lord and our eminent Acharya, the author readily acceeded to our request with an inspiring sense of duty and has fulfilled the task with all thoroughness. Needless to say that he has taken great pains to project without any predilection whatsoever a vivid account of the subject-matter in its proper perspective, tracing the same from the days of Sri Vedanta Desika, with emphasis on the role of the Tatacharyas in the development, management and upkeep of the Temple. We are grateful to him for having refuted effectively the biased and distorted versions introduced with ulterior motives, in several portions of the publication &amp;ldquo;Varadarajaswami Temple&amp;rdquo; by Dr. K. V. Raman.&#xA;We are also bound to express our deep sense of gratitude to Dr. V. Varadacharya for the contribution of his excellent &amp;lsquo;Foreword&amp;rsquo;, which may, without exaggeration, be described as the &amp;ldquo;crest-Jewel&amp;rdquo; of this book.&#xA;SRI TATADESIKA TIRUVAMSASTAR SABHA,&#xA;KANCHI.PREFACE&#xA;The Lord aloft the twenty four steps alone gave me the necessary strength and inspiration to undertake this responsible work under the behests of Sri Tatadesika Tiruvamsastar Sabha, Kanchi. When I started writing this book, I never thought or hoped, I could gather so much material of historical and inscriptional importance. I had the rare fortune of serving our Lord for quite some time as a trustee of the Temple. This experience also gave me somewhat the courage and impetus to take upon myself the task of refuting the several wrong state- ments and distortions and countering the various sectarian versions contained in the Treatise&amp;rsquo; by Dr. K. V. Raman, about our Temple.&#xA;&amp;lt;&#xA;I have arranged to divide the subject matter of my &amp;lsquo;Critical Survey&amp;rsquo; into two parts. The first part. I have devoted for presenting the positive side of the picture viz., a brief history of our Temple, dating back to the fifteenth century A. D., particularly with reference to the important role played by the Tatacharyas who in their capacity as the custodians of the Temple as well as the royal preceptors of the Vijayanagar monarchs and Mysore Kings were able to effect the several major improvements in the Temple like the huge construction of Towers, Rampart walls, Mantapas, Vimanas etc., securing substantial properties for the maintenance and upkeep of the institution and making the several vehicles and precious jewels to the God, from the fifteenth century onwards.&#xA;The Critical Survey&amp;rsquo; proper is dealt with in the second part. For this purpose, I have taken Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Treatise&amp;rsquo; chapter by chapter with the headings with which they are found there and dealt with them in their order so that the readers may follow them easily in the absence of the original in their hands. This has also facilitated my meeting the contro- versial points found therein squarely, in their order.&#xA;There is some unavoidable delay for this publication. Firstly we came to know about Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s book long after its publication. The Treatise&amp;rsquo; could not be secured&#xA;€&#xA;&amp;lt;&#xA;xvi&#xA;easily locally. Nextly, the Saba&amp;rsquo; which was made aware of it, had to resolve and sanction the publication by me in its general body. Naturally, all these took sometime.&#xA;I sincerely hope not only our present generation but posterity will be benefited by this dissertation since this has, as its basis, purely historical and inscriptional facts and figures. I hope also, our younger generation may take up the threads from this and utilise them for further developing the thesis and bringing out treatises, if and when circumstances warrant it.&#xA;Sri Tatadesika Tiruvamsastar Saba deserves all the credit and praise for this undertaking.&#xA;Next to our Saba, Sri V. Sundararajan, B.E., was immensely helpful in bringing this work to a successful conclusion in several respects including the procuring of Dr. K. V. Raman&amp;rsquo;s book with great difficulty. I cannot thank him adequately for all this.&#xA;Dr. V. Varadacharya with his rich experience and erudition gave me very useful suggestions and guidance apart from his inestimable &amp;ldquo;Foreword&amp;rdquo;. It will be an exercise in futility to express my feelings of gratitude to him.&#xA;I will be failing in my duty if I do not place on record my sense of appreciation and thanks for the unstinted co-operation and assistance I received throughout from my brothers and friends Messers R. N., R. T., T. L. K., A. L. S., Tatacharyas, R. Krishnaswamy Tatachari, R. S. Kannan, T. R. Ragunandan, K. R. Rajagopalan, S. Krishnamachari and P. V. Seshadri for the fulfilment of this task.&#xA;I have to thank also the Archaeological survey of India, Southern Circle-Madras-9, who, kindly responding to my application, have furnished the bulk of the photos, which, are their copy right and appear in this book. Finally I cannot afford to omit to congratulate and thank M/s. Super Power Press, Madras-1, for bringing out this publication attractively.&#xA;R. VARADA TATACHARYA.&#xA;SRI&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 INTRODUCTORY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/5_INTRODUCTORY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/0/5_INTRODUCTORY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sri&#xA;The author Dr. K. V. Raman in his Treatise Varadarajaswami Temple - Kanchi&amp;rdquo; for a study of its History, Art &amp;amp; Architecture&amp;rsquo; has taken enormous pains in collecting data both inscriptional and historical as well as traditional for impressing upon his readers, his theory about the religious and historical aspects of this great Vaishnavite Temple. Being a Vaishnavite of the Tenkalai sect, it is no wonder. he gives prominence only to certain Tenkalai features and stories in connection with the Temple, leaving aside the more and most important Vadakalai characteristics of the same. His account of the Temple can be very well described as what they call in legal parlance &amp;ldquo;Suppressio Veri and Suggestio Falsi&amp;rdquo;. The glaring omissions of certain Vadakalai Shrines festivals and features, while describing all others and the emphasis on certain Tenkalai features and festivals will go to show his bias and sectarian approach. His stories regarding the Tenkalai predominance and theories of their influence are exaggerated and far-fetched. He gives a clever twist to certain inscriptions, and builds a story of Tenkalai domination in the Temple over them. The object of the author in this Treatise seems to be therefore to establish a theory that the Temple of Sri Varadaraja- swami is Tenkalai in character.&#xA;As a true and devout Tenkalai he starts the subject, with a sloka said to have been composed by Sri Manavalamamuni in praise of Lord Varadaraja and throughout the Treatise he gives full prominence to his Acharya by depicting his anecdotes and photos as also that of a stone inscription with a Tenkalai mark. But these illustrations which are intended to highlight the Tenkalai predominance in the Temple will pale into insignificance when compared with the innumerable Vadakalai marks and features in the most prominent and frontal portions, all over the fabric of the Temple. These Vadakalai features and marks will be dealt with in detail with illustrations and photos, in this book at the appropriate places and contexts.&#xA;2&#xA;The object of this book is to counter in detail all the fallacious theories and accounts set forth by Dr. K. V. Raman in his Treatise, chapter by chapter. A correct version of the history of the Temple, based on inscriptions, history and tradition handed down to us by our forebears, is given in Part I of this Book.&#xA;The author has also exhibited his lack of personal knowledge in the course of his description and narration of certain items like postures of Alwars, location, festivals, names etc., which will go to show that he is tutored and guided by the staunch leaders of his sect. These fallacies will be also dealt with, in the appropriate contexts.&#xA;The author, in this dissertation, has started propounding the tenets of the Tenkalai-Vadakalai sects based on our Vaishnavite religion and philosophy. We do not know about his qualifications and competence with regard to our religion&amp;rsquo;s scriptures. It is possible that in this also he had had his tuition from the members of his sect who are more qualified and competent. But even here, we are able to see the slant and the sectarian bias in abundance.&#xA;We have based our survey and theories mostly on the puranic and traditional version as found in our religious scriptures handed down to us by our forebears, as far as the general religious themes are concerned. But, for the history of the Tatacharyas and their connection, influence and services in the Temple we have relied purely on history, inscriptions and ancient unassailable records and texts.&#xA;Though we are not presumptuous to claim&amp;quot; perfect know- ledge in our religious literature we shall try to counter the disputable points, the author has raised in his book, to the best of our ability, in our own way, even though both these do not have any relevance to the subject-matter of the &amp;ldquo;Treatise&amp;rdquo; in the ultimate analysis.&#xA;It is surprising to see the author&amp;rsquo;s references to certain controversial and sectarian documents and books which he&#xA;3&#xA;has evidently taken as the basis for his version. These docu- ments filed in the courts as exhibits by his sect (Tenkalais) during the litigation that raged over our Temple for the last two centuries or more and books written with a bias, should not be brought in, in as much as they present the picture of only one side. Much reliance shall not be placed on them attributing undisputed authenticity to them. At any rate they should not form part of a thesis submitted for the award of the Ph.D. Degree. To a reader who has no correct knowledge of the origin and basis of these documents, the author&amp;rsquo;s references to them would evidently create an impression that these documents and exhibits are genuine. It becomes therefore incumbent on our part to meet the points raised in these documents and exhibits by citing documents which are not only unassailable on the strength of evidences they contain but also because most of them are judicial pronouncements.&#xA;We crave our readers&amp;rsquo; pardon for certain repetitions which may occur during the course of this &amp;ldquo;Critical Survey&amp;rdquo; caused solely on account of similar repetitions occurring in many of the chapters of the &amp;ldquo;Treatise &amp;ldquo;.&#xA;Wherever the word &amp;ldquo;author&amp;rdquo; occurs in this book, it means Dr. K. V. Raman and wherever the word &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; occurs it is the author of this &amp;ldquo;Critical Survey&#xA;Critical Survey&amp;rdquo; and his associates. Wherever the words &amp;ldquo;Our Temple &amp;quot; or &amp;quot; The Temple&amp;rdquo; occur, it is Sri Varadarajaswami Temple, and the word &amp;ldquo;Treatise&amp;rsquo; occurs, it is the book by the author with the title, &amp;ldquo;Sri Varadarajaswami Temple - Kanchi&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
