<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;३ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;३ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>001 Sūta Romaharṣaṇa Agrees to Narrate Padma Purāṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1. Om, salutation to (Gaṇeśa) the remover of obstacles. Salutation to the glorious one. I salute the lotus-like feet of Govinda (i.e. Viṣṇu), which are always saluted by Indirā (i.e. Lakṣmī), which are called ‘the best’, which are fixed in the hearts of people, and which are the only, absolutely excellent abode of the great people.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. Once all the sages resembling blazing fire, all the sages living on the Himalaya mountain and masters of the Vedas, knowing(events) of (all) the three times (viz. past, present and future), magnanimous ones, resorting to (i.e. doing) many meritorious (acts), those who lived on the Mahendra mountain, the Vindhya mountain, in the Arbuda forest, in the Puṣkara forest, on the Śrīśaila mountain, in Kurukṣetra, in Dharmāraṇya, in Daṇḍakāraṇya. Jambumārga, in Satya(-loka)—these and many other spotless sages came along with their disciples, as they were eager to see Śaunaka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>002 The Creation of the Elements, Prakṛti etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O best brāhmaṇas, I shall first tell you about the first creation, by which the eternal lord, the highest soul, is known.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O best brāhmaṇas, in the creations there was nothing (left) after the universal destruction. There was only one lustre called Brahman, the cause of everything. It was the ocean of joy, it was pure, and that which those longing for salvation, desire. It was omniscient because it was of the form of knowledge; it was unlimited, immutable. It was indestructible, always very clear, fixed, great and pervasive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>003 Various Mountains and Regions of the Earth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O best one, tell us fully the names of the rivers, mountains of the countries, and of those who have resorted to (i.e. are living on) the earth, O you who know the measures, the full measure of the earth, and about the forests also.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-10. O very wise one, the gross elements in the universe are five in all; and the wise say that they are equal. (They are:) earth, water, and air, fire and ether. All of them are attended with attributes. Earth is the chief of them. The sages knowing the essential nature (of things) have said that the attributes of earth are sound, touch, colour, taste and smell. O brāhmaṇas, four attributes are (found) in water. It does not have smell. Fire (or light) has three attributes: sound, touch and colour. Air has (two attributes, viz.) sound and touch. Ether has (the attribute of) sound only. O brāhmaṇas, in the five elements these five attributes (are found), and (depending) on them the creatures in all the worlds exist. There is homogeneity when they do not overcome one another; but when they, becoming uneven, enter one another, then the beings spring up (into life) with bodies. This is not otherwise. They are destroyed in order. They come into existence in order (i.e. they are destroyed in the same order as they come into existence). All of them are immeasurable. Their form is the lord (himself).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>004 Uttarakuru, Bhadrāśva, Mālyavat</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, O you very intelligent one, tell us in full (about the countries) to the north, west and east of Meru, so also about the Mālyavat mountain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O brāhmaṇas, on the south of Nīla, and the northern side of Meru there is the auspicious land called Uttarakuru, where siddhas have resided.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. The trees there have sweet fruits and always have flowers and fruits. The flowers are very fragrant and the fruits are tasty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>005 Ramaṇaka, Hiraṇmaya, Airāvata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O best one, tell us duly the names of countries and mountains, so also (about) those that live on those mountains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. On the south of Śveta and on the north of Niṣadha there is the country named Ramaṇaka. The men there are born in pure noble families, and all of them are handsome; and all the men that are born there are without enemies. O glorious ones, they being always cheerful, live for eleven thousand and five hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>006 Bhāratavarṣa: Its Rivers and Regions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Tell us about the auspicious Bharata country which endows merit, (since) you are intelligent in our opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. I shall now describe to you the excellent country Bharata of the god dear to his friends, of Manu the son of Vivasvān, of Pṛthu, of the wise Vainya; also of the high-souled Ikṣvāku, of Yayāti, Ambarīṣa, Māndhātṛ and Nahuṣa; also of Mucakunda, Kuberośīnara, Ṛṣabha; also of Aila, and king Nṛga; of Kuśika, of the royal sage Gādhi the magnanimous one, also of Soma, and of the royal sage Dilīpa; also, O glorious ones, of other powerful kṣatriyas and is dear to all beings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>007 Span of Life in the Four Yugas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Tell us, in detail, of the measure (i.e. span) of life, strength, the auspicious and inauspicious, the future, past and present (of the residents) of Bhāratavarṣa, Himavat, and also Harivarṣa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. There are four yugas in Bhāratavarṣa. The first yuga was Kṛta; then there was Tretāyuga, O brāhmaṇas. After that Dvāpara sets in; then comes Kali. The span of life, O best sages, was known to be four thousand years, in Kṛtayuga. O ascetics, similarly they know that the span of life in Tretāyuga is three thousand years. The span of life at present in Dvāpara is two thousand years; for that much period men live on the earth. However, in Tiṣya (i.e. Kali)-yuga, men die while in womb, and also they die as soon as they are born.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>008 Śākadvīpa: Mountains, Rivers and Countries</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. O best one, you have duly described (to us) Jambukhaṇḍa. Tell us correctly the extent of its dimensions. You who see the whole, tell us properly about the extent of the ocean, as well as about Śākadvīpa and the sacred Kuśadvīpa: also tell us properly about Śālmala and about Krauñca-dvīpa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-6. O brāhmaṇas, there are many islands which have covered the earth. I shall describe the seven islands: Listen, O best brāhmaṇas. The measure of the mountain Jambu is full eighteen thousand and six hundred yojanas. The extent of the salt sea is said to be double this. It is crowded with many countries, and is beautified with gems and corals. It is also adorned with mountains variegated with many minerals. Crowded with siddhas and cāraṇas, the ocean is circular in form.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>009 Śālmalika, Krauñca, Kuśa and Puṣkara Dvīpas and Their Mountains</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O illustrious ones, now listen to the account of the northern islands from me who am telling it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. There is an ocean having the water of clarified butter; another has the water of curds; then there is an ocean having the water of wine; and one more is an ocean of milk.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O best brāhmaṇas, these islands have double the size of one another (as they proceed northwards). O highly intelligent ones, there are also mountains surrounded by oceans.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>010 Dialogue between Nārada and Yudhiṣṭhira</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Having heard the measure and the position of the earth, so also (having heard) about the rivers from you, we have just drunk nectar. We have heard that there are holy places on the earth. Describe them to us and also how they are fruitful. O very wise one, we desire to hear about them in detail from you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. O you ascetics, you have asked about an excellent, meritorious, great account. I shall narrate it to the best of my knowledge, suitably and as I have heard it. I shall tell you the ancient conversation of the celestial sage Nārada with Yudhiṣṭhira. O best brāhmaṇas, listen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>011 Puṣkara, the Holiest of Holy Places</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vasiṣṭha-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vasiṣṭha said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you knowing what is right, O you illustrious one, I am fully pleased with you due to this your civility, restraint and truthfulness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. You who have such piety have emancipated your forefathers. Therefore, O son, you (are able to) see me; and O descendant of Manu, you are fit to be a sacrificer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. My affection for you increases; tell me today what I should do for you. O you sinless and best among men, I shall give you what you will ask for.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>012 Visit to Some Holy Places and Its Merit</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vasiṣṭha-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vasiṣṭha said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. Turning round and moving to the right, he would approach the way to Jambu. Approaching the path of Jambu, adored by manes, gods and sages, he obtains (the fruit of) Aśvamedha and goes to Viṣṇu’s world. A man going (from there) after having stayed there for five or six nights, does not meet with ill luck, but obtains best success. Returning from Jambumārga, he should go to Dulikāśrama. He does not meet with indigence and is honoured in heaven. O king, he who engaged in worshipping the forefathers and gods observes a fast for three nights after reaching the hermitage of Agastya, would obtain the fruit of (having performed) an Agniṣṭoma sacrifice. By subsisting on vegetables or fruits he obtains the fruit of youthfulness; after reaching Kanyāśrama nourished with glory and revered by people, he is free from his sins the moment he enters it, since, O king, it is a meritorious and the best sacred grove. Being controlled and having limited food, he, after having worshipped his forefathers and deities, gets the fruit of a sacrifice full of (i.e. that satisfies) all desires. Having turned to the right, he would then go to Yayātipatana.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>013 The Greatness of Narmadā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O Nārada, I desire to hear again about the best, well-known holy place called Narmada, that rends the mountains of sins, which Vasiṣṭha described to Dilīpa. (O Nārada,) describe it to me. O best brāhmaṇa, also (tell me about) the greatness of Narmadā as described by Vasiṣṭha. O Nārada, tell me how this very pious river, known as Narmadā, is famous everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. Narmadā is the best of rivers; she destroys all sins; she would liberate all beings—immobile and mobile. I have heard the greatness of Narmada as told by Visiṣṭha. O great king, know (i.e. listen to) it; I (shall) tell you the whole (of it).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>014 Sages Pray to God Śiva for Protection from Demon Bāṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The greatest river Narmadā, that is holy and most auspi-[?]-strands is divided into three (streams) by the glorious sages, longing for piety.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O Pāṇḍava, the (three) divisions are just like (the three strands of) a sacred thread. O lord of kings, a man bathing in (any of) them is free from all sins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O son of Pāṇḍu, listen to me who am telling you about the origin of the sacred place Jaleśvara which is well-known in the three worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>015 The Greatness of Amarakaṇṭaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7a. O son of Kuntī, listen to (me telling you) and understand what you ask me about. In the meanwhile Rudra remained on the bank of Narmadā. The place is called Hareśvara, and is well-known in the three worlds. At that place Mahādeva, thinking about Tripura’s murder, (stayed,) making Mandara the bow, making Vāsuki the bow-string, standing with his feet a span apart, making Viṣṇu the best arrow, putting fire in the fore; Vāyu was put at the mouth; (making) the four Vedas the horses, (he made) the chariot full of all gods. The two gods, Aśvins, were on the wheels; the disc-holder himself was the axle; Indra himself was at the end of the bow; Vaiśravaṇa remained on the arrow. Yama was on the right hand and the terrible Kāla on the left. Gandharvas, well-known in the worlds, were placed on the radius of the wheels. Of this best chariot Prajāpati Brahmā was the charioteer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>016 Kāverī Saṃgama Tīrtha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sage-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sage said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. All those magnanimous multitudes of people with Yudhiṣṭhira as the chief, and the sages, the abodes of penance, asked Nārada: “O revered one, tell us for the good of the people and for our prosperity, the great truth about the confluence of Kāverī, that wicked men who are always engaged in sinful activities, become free from all sins and go to the highest place (on bathing there). We desire to know this. O revered one, please tell it.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>017 Narmadā and the Holy Places on Her Northern Bank</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. On the northern bank of Narmadā, there is an extensive holy place. It is known as Patreśvara, and is great and removes all sins. O king, having bathed there, a man rejoices with deities. Taking any form he likes, he sports for five thousand years.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Then a man should go to Garjana where Megha is present. By the power of that holy place, it has attained the name Indrajit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>018 More Tīrthas on the Bank of Narmadā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Since then Brahmā and others, as well as the sages rich in penance, being free from lust and anger, resort to Narmadā, O king. Seeing the trident of the lord fallen at that place on the earth, the magnanimous Śiva narrated its importance. It came to be known as the great, most meritorious holy place Śūlabheda. He, who, having bathed there, would worship the god (Śiva), would obtain the fruit (of the gift) of a thousand cows. O king, he, who would pass three nights there, and would worship Mahādeva, would not be reborn. Then a man should go to Maheśvara, (then) to the excellent Narmadeśvara. (Then he should visit) the very meritorious Ādityeśvara. Then on worshipping Mallikeśvara with ghee and honey, be obtains the fruit of his existence. Then he should see (i.e. visit) Varuṇeśvara, the excellent Nirajeśvara. He gets the fruit of (visiting) all the holy places by seeing (i.e. visiting) these five. O lord of kings, he should go to the place where the battle was fought.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>019 Śuklatīrtha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Thence he should devoutly go to Bhārgaveśa where the demons were destroyed by god Viṣṇu with his huṃkāra sound. O lord of kings, having bathed there, he is free from all sins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-6. O son of Pāṇḍu, also listen to the (description of) Śuklatīrtha. Mārkaṇḍa, seeing god (Mahādeva) with Umā, who was seated on the peak of Himālaya which was charming, variegated with various minerals, which resembled the young sun and heated gold, which had the staircase of strong crystals, which had a slab of stone with a variegated strap, which was golden, which was divine and adorned with many lotuses, asked (Mahādeva) who was omniscient, who was the immutable lord, who favoured the worlds, who was surrounded by the hosts of attendants and by Skanda, Nandi, Mahākāla, and attendants like Vīrabhadra:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>020 Naraka, Kapilātīrtha, Ṛṣitīrtha, Gaṇeśvara, Bhṛgutīrtha, Somatīrtha etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-12. Then he should go to (the holy place called) Naraka. He should bathe there. Merely by bathing there a man does not see (i.e. go to) hell. O you son of Pāṇḍu, listen to the greatness of this holy place. O lord of kings, all the bones which he would drop there, are dissolved, and the man becomes handsome. O lord of kings, thence a man should go to the excellent (holy place called) Kapilātīrtha. O king, having bathed there, he would obtain the fruit of (having given away) a thousand cows. The man, who, when the month of Jyeṣṭha has come and especially on the fourteenth day, observes a fast devoutly, gives a tawny cow, and burning a lamp with ghee, bathes Śiva with ghee, and offers a coconut along with ghee, and in the end goes round, and gives a tawny cow with a bell and (other) ornaments (to a brāhmaṇa), becomes like Śiva, and is not born again. When Tuesday has come, especially on the fourth day (falling on Tuesday), a man should devoutly bathe (the image of) Śiva and give food to brāhmaṇas. When the ninth or the new moon day falls on a Tuesday, he should carefully bathe (the image of) Śiva. (Thereby) he would be handsome and fortunate. He should bathe the Phallus with ghee and devoutly honour brāhmaṇas. Surrounded by thousands, he (going in) Puṣpaka aeroplane, obtains the position of Śiva. He would not come here (i.e. to this world) again. He rejoices for an eternal time, and he becomes like Rudra. When the most righteous one comes to the mortal world due to his contact with (the fruits of) his deeds, he becomes a king, and becomes handsome and strong.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>021 Vīhageśvara, Narmadeśvara, Aśvatīrtha, Pitāmaha, Sāvitrītīrtha, Mānasa etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O lord of kings, from there he should go to the excellent (holy place called) Vihageśvara.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O lord of kings, by seeing it, he is free from all sins. Thence, O lord of kings, he should go to the excellent (holy place called) Narmadeśvara. O king, having bathed there he is honoured in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. From there a man should go to Aśvatīrtha and should bathe there. He becomes prosperous, handsome and happy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>022 The Story of Five Gandharva Maidens</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O king, I have thus described to you the excellent Narmadātīrtha. Formerly the fire of the drops of the water of Revā destroyed the excessive fear due to the curse of the daughters of gandharvas. A man is liberated by the touch of the drops of the water of Revā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6. O revered one, wherefrom did the many daughters get a curse? Whose children were they? What were their names and their ages? How did they get free from the fruit of the curse by the contact of the water? Where did they bathe? O lord, tell me all this. The greatness of the Narmadātīrtha would be surprising. It is said to destroy sins even by listening to it. He who utters the word ‘Narmadā, Narmadā’, gets eternal liberation as long as the moon and stars exist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>023 The Sage Lomaśa Comes to the Help of the Goblins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. After a long time the magnanimous, best sage Lomaśa who wandered as he liked, came there. Seeing the brāhmaṇa all the goblins living in a group and being overpowered by hunger and desiring to eat him, ran to him. Being burnt by the sharp lustre of Lomaśa, unable to stand before him, they remained away from him. Then, that brāhmaṇa, who had become a goblin as a result of his former deeds, seeing Lomaśa, saluted him by prostrating himself before him, and putting his folded palms on his head spoke true and pleasant words, O king:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>024 Piṅgatīrtha, Narmadā, Dvārāvatī, Timi etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Now tell me about other holy places described by Vasiṣṭha, on hearing about which sins perish, O Nārada.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6a. O king, now hear about the holy places described by Vasiṣṭha. A self-restrained man, with his senses controlled, obtains (the fruit of) the Agniṣṭoma sacrifice on reaching the southern sea and gets into an aeroplane. A restrained man, having controlled his diet, having reached Carmaṇvatī, and being allowed by Rantideva, would obtain the fruit of (having performed) the Agniṣṭoma sacrifice. Then, O righteous one, he should go to Arbuda (i.e. mountain Abu), the son of Himālaya, where, O Yudhiṣṭhira, there was formerly a fissure in the earth. There is the hermitage of Vasiṣṭha, well-known in the three worlds. Having lived there for a night, he would obtain the fruit of (having given away) a thousand cows (to a brāhmaṇa).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>025 Vitastā, Malada, Maṇimanta, Brahmavālaka etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O descendant of Bharata, a man after having reached Vitastā, and after having offered oblations to the manes and deities, gets the fruit of (having performed) a Vājapeya sacrifice. In Kāśmīra itself is the abode of Nāga and also of Takṣaka known as Vitastā and removing all sins. A man having bathed there would indeed obtain the fruit of (having performed) a Vājapeya sacrifice. Being free from all sins, he would go to the highest position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>026 Kurukṣetra, Pāriplava, Śalvikinī, Koṭitīrtha etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. Thence, O lord of kings, he should go to Kurukṣetra praised (by all). All creatures who have gone there have been freed from their sins. He, who always says “I shall go to Kurukṣetra, I shall stay at Kurukṣetra”. is absolved of all sins. O king, a wise man should live there for a month, to which very meritorious (Brahmakṣetra) gods like Brahmā, brāhmaṇic sages, cāraṇas, gandharvas, celestial nymphs, yakṣas and pannagas go, O descendant of Bharata. O Yudhiṣṭhira, the sins of him who even mentally longs for Kurukṣetra, perish, and he goes to Brahmā’s heaven. O you, who are perpetuating the Kuru family, a man going to Kurukṣetra with faith, obtains the fruit of Vājapeya and Aśvamedha sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>027 Kanyātīrtha, Saptasārasvata, Pṛthūdaka, Sannihiti, etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/027/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/027/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-11. O you pious one, then a man should go to the excellent holy place (called) Kanyātīrtha. A man having bathed at Kanyā-tīrtha would obtain the fruit of Agniṣṭoma (sacrifice). Thence, O best among men, a man should go to the excellent place of Brahmā. Having bathed there a man of a low caste obtains brāhmaṇahood; and a brāhmaṇa, with his soul purified, would go to the highest position. Thence, O best among men, a man should go to the excellent Somatīrtha. Having bathed there, O king, a man would obtain (i.e., go to) Soma’s world. Thence, O king, he should go to the holy place (called) Saptasārasvata where (lived) Maṅkaṇaka, a siddha, a brāhmaṇic sage, famous in the world. O king, it is heard that formerly Maṅkaṇaka was injured on his hand by the tip of Kuśa (i.e., darbha). From it vegetable juice flowed. The brāhmaṇic sage of a great penance seeing that vegetable juice and being full of great joy and with his eyes dilated due to amazement, danced. Then, when he danced, all that was immovable and movable, both, being deluded by his lustre, danced. O king, gods like Brahmā, and also sages with penance as their wealth, requested Mahādeva (i.e., Śiva) for the sake of the sage, “O god, please act in such a way that this (sage) would not dance.” Then the god seeing the sage dancing with his mind full of joy said, with a desire for the good of the deities, to the sage: “O pious, great sage, why are you dancing? O best sage, what is the cause of your joy today?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>028 Dharmatīrtha, Śākambharī, Rathāvartta, etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/028/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/028/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. O pious one, thence he should go to the ancient (holy place called) Dharmatīrtha where formerly the illustrious Dharma practised excellent penance. He fashioned that holy place known by his name. O king, a religious and tranquil man having bathed there purifies his family up to the seventh (generation). There is no doubt about it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4. Thence, O pious one, he should go to the excellent (holy place called) Kalāpavana. Having gone there with a great difficulty and being calm and having bathed there he obtains (the fruit of) an Agniṣṭoma (sacrifice) and goes to Viṣṇu’s heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>029 Kālindītīrtha: Efficacy of Yamunā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/029/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/029/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-18. O lord of kings, then a man should go to the excellent (holy place called) Kālindītīrtha. O king, having bathed there one does not meet with misfortune. O best among men, one obtains that fruit (by bathing) in Yamunā which he gets (by bathing) at Puṣkara, Kurukṣetra, Brahmāvartta, Pṛthūdaka, Avimukta, Suvarṇākhya. Those in whose heart there is a great attachment for heavenly pleasures or who desire (long) life, good health, wealth, handsomeness, youth and virtues, should not give up the water of Yamunā. (These things can be had) especially by a bath in Yamunā, O best one. Those who are afraid of hell etc. and those who have a dread of poverty, should with all efforts take a bath in Yamunā. O Yudhiṣṭhira, except the water of Yamunā there is nothing else for (i.e., which is capable of) washing the mud of poverty, sins, misfortune. Deeds done without faith give half (i.e., a partial) fruit. But a bath in Yamunā gives the entire fruit. O king, he who with or without a desire bathes in the water of Yamunā, does not see (i.e., experience) miseries here (i.e., in this world) or in the next world. As the moon wanes and waxes in the two fortnights, in the same way by bathing in Yamunā sin perishes and religious merit increases. As in the ocean various gems are easily obtained, so (long) life, wealth, wife, riches are possible for (i.e. are obtained by) him. As the desire-yielding cow gives the desired object, or as the desire-yielding gem gives whatever is thought of, in the same way a bath in Yamunā gives all (the objects of) desire. In Kṛtayuga penance was great knowledge; in Tretāyuga sacrifice (was important); in Dvāparayuga and Kaliyuga giving (gifts) is (fruitful). (But) Yamunā is always auspicious. O king, for all the castes and for all the stages of life a bath in (the water) of Yamunā indeed showers piety in streams. In this country (called) Bharata, especially (named) as the land of religious rites, the life of men not bathing in Yamunā is said to be fruitless. As on the new moon day there is no affluence in the orb of the moon in the sky, in the same way no act shines (i.e., is effective) without a bath in Yamunā. Hari or Keśava (i.e., Viṣṇu) is not so much pleased by means of vows, gifts or penance as he is pleased by means of just a bath in Yamunā. There is no lustre like that of the sun. In the same way there is nothing like a bath in Yamunā. Equally potent are the sacrificial rites. For pleasing Vāsudeva, for removing all sins and for obtaining (i.e., going to) heaven men should bathe in Yamunā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>030 Hemakuṇḍala and His Two Sons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/030/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/030/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-13. O king, now I shall tell you an old history (i.e., an account). In Kṛtayuga, in the excellent city of Niṣadha, there lived a merchant resembling Kubera and named Hemakuṇḍala. He was of a high descent, of good deeds, a worshipper of deities, brāhmaṇas and fire. He practised agriculture and trade and purchased and sold various (things). He was eagerly engaged in rearing cows, horses and buffaloes etc. He always sold milk, curds, buttermilk, cowdung, grass, wood, fruits, roots, salt, ginger, long pepper, grains, vegetables, oils, garments of various kinds, metals, sugar and molasses. By these and various other means the merchant always earned eight crores of (coins of) gold. Thus he who had great wealth became grey up to his ears. Then thinking in his mind about the transitoriness of the worldly existence, he did acts of piety with (i.e., by spending) the sixth part of that wealth. He fashioned the temple of Viṣṇu and also the abode of Śiva. He got dug a tank, big and resembling an ocean. He also constructed many wells and lakes in many ways. According to his capacity he also put up the grove of (the trees like) vaṭa, aśvattha, mango, kaṅkola, jambu, nimba etc., and also a charming garden. He gave food and drink from sunrise to sunset. In all the four directions outside the city he set up stalls where travellers could drink water. That religious-minded one, always engaged in giving gifts, gave all (kinds of) presents that were well-known in the Purāṇas. He also underwent an expiation for the sins committed during his life (time). He was always engrossed in worshipping deities and guests.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>031 Vikuṇḍala’s Dialogue with the Devadūta</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/031/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/031/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then he (i.e., Vikuṇḍala) pleased in his mind, entertaining a doubt in his heart, and very much amazed and thinking in his mind (i.e., to himself), asked the messenger on the way (to heaven): “For what reason am I having (this) fruit?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vikuṇḍala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vikuṇḍala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O best messenger, I am asking you (to clarify) an important doubt. We two were born in the same family. Also we have done similar deeds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>032 Sugandha, Arundhatīvaṭa, Sindhuprabhava etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/032/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/032/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2, Thence, O best of kings, a man should go to Sugandha, well-known in the world. With his soul freed from all sins, he is honoured in Brahmā’s world. O king, from there a pilgrim should go to Rudravarta. O king, a man having bathed there, is honoured in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. O best of men, a man who has bathed at the confluence of Gaṅgā and Sarasvatī obtains (the fruit of) a horse sacrifice and goes to heaven. Having bathed at Karṇahrada there and having worshipped Śiva, he does not meet with misery and goes to heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>033 The Merits of Vārāṇasī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/033/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/033/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O sage, you have described in brief the importance of Vārāṇasī. (Please) tell it in detail. Then (only) my mind is (i.e. would be) pleased.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Now I shall tell you the account based on the merits of Vārāṇasī, merely by hearing which a man is absolved of (the sin of) killing a brāhmaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Formerly, goddess (Pārvatī) having gone to the seat of the lord asked Mahādeva, the enemy of Tripura, on the peak of Meru:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>034 The Greatness of Kṛttivāseśvara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/034/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/034/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-14a. There is a pure auspicious Phallus called Oṃkāra, merely by remembering which a man is freed from all sins. This is superior knowledge, the excellent Pañcāyatana, which is always resorted to by sages in Vārāṇasī, and which liberates (men). There actually Mahādeva, Rudra, who gives liberation to creatures rejoices in the form of the five abodes. This knowledge relating to Paśupati (i.e. Śiva) is called Pañcāyatana. This is that pure Phallus, Oṃkāra, that stands there. The Phallus of the lord is of five forms: Śāntyatītā, Śānti, Aparāvarā Vīdyā (i.e. higher and lower knowledge), Pratiṣṭhā and Nivṛtti. The Phallus that supports the five Liṅgas, Brahmā and others, and that is indicative of Oṃkāra, is called Pañcāyatana. A wise man should remember the immutable Liṅga, i.e. Pañcāyatana, of the lord. At the end of his body (i.e. when he dies) he enters the highest light, joy. There formerly gods, sages, siddhas, brāhmaṇic sages ultimately obtained the best position after having waited upon the lord. O lord of kings, on the auspicious bank of Matsyodarī there is the most secret place, of the size of gocarma (cow&amp;rsquo;s hide), the excellent Oṃkāreśvara; there is the Linga called Kṛttivāseśvara, the excellent Madhyameśvara, and also Viśveśvara, Oṃkāra and Kandarpeśvara. O Yudhiṣṭhira, these are the secret Liṅgas in Vārāṇasī. Nobody here knows (i.e. experiences) destruction due to Śambhu’s favour. O king, listen to the greatness of Kṛttivāseśvara. At that time formerly a demon having become an elephant came there near Śiva to kill the brāhmaṇas who were everyday worshipping Śiva. From the Liṅga of them Mahādeva, the three-eyed (god), affectionate towards his devotees, came there for the protection of his devotees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>035 Greatness of Kapardin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/035/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Now there is another excellent Liṅga, (called) Kapardīśvara. O king, having bathed there according to proper rites and offered oblations to manes, one is freed from all sins and obtains salvation and enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-11. Then there is another holy place called Piśācamocana. There is the wonderful (form of) god that gives salvation and that removes all blemishes. A demon taking up a terrible form of a tiger went to the excellent Kapardīśvara to eat up a female deer. There she with her heart frightened again and again circumambulated (the deity). Running and extremely perpflexed [perplexed?] she came under the sway of the tiger. That very strong tiger having torn her with sharp nails went to another place after having noticed the best sages. That young female deer almost dead looked in front of Kapardīśa, like a great flame, lustrous like the moon in the sky. (She appeared) to have three eyes, dark blue throat, and with her hair on the head marked with the moon, to have mounted upon a bull, and surrounded by men like her only. The (divine) beings roaming in the sky, showered upon her flowers on all sides. Being turned into one of the female chiefs of Śiva’s attendants she vanished just at that moment only. Seeing that great wonder the gods and others praised it. That is the Liṅga of Śiva called Kapardīśvara, the best one. By merely remembering, it a man gets quickly free from his sins. All blemishes like passion, anger, and difficulties of the residents of Vārāṇasī perish by worshipping Kapardīśvara.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>036 The Greatness of Madhyameśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/036/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/036/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. O great king, at Vārāṇasī, there is the best (place called) Madhyameśa. At that place that great lord Mahādeva always rejoices with the goddess (i.e. Pārvatī) and is surrounded by the Rudras. Formerly the universal god Hṛṣīkeśa, Kṛṣṇa, the son of Devakī, lived there for a year (and was) always surrounded by devotees of Śiva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-5a. With his entire body smeared with dust, and intent upon studying Rudra(-hymn), and observing the vow of the devotee of Śiva, Hari (i.e. Kṛṣṇa) worshipped Śiva. All those many disciples of him, intent upon celibacy, got knowledge from his mouth and saw Maheśvara.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>037 Other Holy Places of Vārāṇasī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/037/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/037/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Yudhiṣṭhira, O great king, there are also other holy places situated in Vārāṇasī. Listen to (the description of) them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9. The holy place superior to Prayāga (the place of the confluence of Gaṅgā and Yamunā) is the auspicious Prayāga (a holy place at Vārāṇasī). Similarly there is a holy place called Viśvatīrtha, and also the excellent holy place Tālatīrtha. There is the holy place called Ākāśa, so also the excellent one called Ārṣabha (i.e. sacred to Ṛṣabha). There is the great holy place called Sunīla, and the excellent holy place called Gaurītīrtha. So also there is the holy place called Prājāpatya and there is the (holy place called) Svargadvāra. There is also the (holy place called) Jambukeśvara and the excellent Dharma. The Gayātīrtha is a great holy place, so also Mahānadī is a holy place. Nārāyaṇa is a great holy place and Vāyutīrtha is excellent. Jñānatīrtha is a great secret place, and Vārāhatīrtha is excellent. Yamatīrtha is auspicious; so also Sammūrtika is holy. O great king, there is the Agnitīrtha, and there is also the excellent holy place Kalaśeśvara. So also there are (the holy places called) Nāgatīrtha, Somatīrtha and Sūryatīrtha. Then there is the very secret (holy place) called Parvata; so also there is the excellent Maṇikarṇya. Ghaṭotkaca is the best holy place, so also there is the Śrītīrtha (sacred to) the Grandsire. Gaṅgātīrtha is (sacred) to the lord of gods. So also Yayātitīrtha is excellent. There is the sacred place holy to Kapila; so also there is (the holy place called) Someśa; so also there is (the holy place called) Brahmatīrtha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>038 Gayā and Other Holy Places</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/038/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/038/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O lord, I have described to you in brief the greatness of Vārāṇasi, and the holy places (situated) in it. (Now) listen to (the description of) other holy places.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O descendant of Bharata, a man being restrained and calm, having gone to Gayā, obtains (the fruit of) a horse sacrifice merely by going there. There is (a place) named Akṣayavaṭa known in the three worlds. O lord, oblations offered to the manes at that place become inexhaustible. Having bathed in the Mahānadī he should offer oblations to manes and deities. (By doing so) he would obtain (i.e. go to) the imperishable worlds and would liberate his family.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>039 Savidyā Sandhyā, Lauhitya, Karatoyā, etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/039/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/039/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Then having reached Savidyā Sandhyā, the excellent holy place and having bathed there a man becomes learned. There is no doubt about this. Having reached the holy place Lauhitya, made the chief holy place by Rāma in olden days, he would obtain much gold.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Having reached Karatoyā a man who fasts (there) for three nights obtains (the fruit of) a horse sacrifice, and goes to Indra’s world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>040 Mārkaṇḍeya Recommends Pilgrimage to Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/040/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/040/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. O you of good vows, I have thus described the holy places, the bodies of Viṣṇu. A man becomes liberated by contact with any one of these. To hear about the holy places is blessed; to resort to the holy places is blessed. In Kaliyuga, there is no other means for destroying the heap of sins. He who everyday says, ‘I will stay at a holy place; I will bathe at a holy place’, goes to the highest principle. By his merely talking about the holy places his sins perish. O you of best vows, the holy places resorted to by the blessed ones are indeed blessed. By resorting to the holy place only, Nārāyaṇa, the author of the world is worshipped. There is no higher place than the holy places.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>041 The Greatness of Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/041/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/041/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O revered sir, I desire to hear how in the former kalpa men went there to Prayāga. What is the course of (i.e. for) the dead there? What is the fruit which those who bathe there get? Tell me also the fruit which those who stay in Prayāga get. Tell me all this. I have great curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇḍeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-22. O lord, O dear, I shall tell you what is desirable, and what is (its) fruit, which I heard while being told to brāhmaṇas and sages in olden days. From Prayāga, Pratiṣṭhāna, up to Dharmakī Vāsukī pool, there are the two nāgas. This is the region of (i.e. sacred to) Prajāpati, which is known in the three worlds. Having bathed here men go to heaven. Those that die here are not reborn. There gods like Brahmā, having come together protect (everything). There are many other holy places which destroy all sins. O king, it is not possible to describe them even by (spending) many hundred years. I shall give you the description of Prayāga in brief. Sixty thousand bows protect the Jāhnavī (i.e. Gaṅgā). The Sun with the seven horses always protects Yamunā. Indra himself particularly protects Prayāga. Viṣṇu, along with the gods, protects the highly esteemed region. Maheśvara (i.e. Śiva), with the trident in his hand, always protects that (famous) Vaṭa. The god protects the auspicious place which removes all sins. Men given to impiety do not go to that place. O king, all that sin—small or smaller—of a man who remembers Prayāga vanishes. A man, merely by seeing that holy place, or even by uttering its name, or even by taking clay from there, is free from sin. O lord of kings, there are five pools in (i.e. through) which Gaṅgā (flows). The sin of a man goes away the moment he enters Prayāga. A man who remembers Gaṅgā within a distance of thousands of yojanas, gets the highest position (i.e. salvation), even if he is a man of wicked deeds. By reciting (the name of Gaṅgā) a man is free from sins. By seeing (her) he sees (i.e. gets) happiness. By bathing in and drinking (the water of Gaṅgā) he purifies his family up to the seventh (descendant). A man who is truthful, who has conquered his anger, who has greatly resorted to harmlessness, who follows the proper course of conduct, who knows the truth, who is engaged in the well-being of cows and brāhmaṇas, is freed from sin after bathing in between (i.e. at the confluence of) Gaṅgā and Yamunā. He properly obtains many objects that he has thought of in his mind. Thence having gone to Prayāga, he should live there with restraint for a month and should offer oblations to gods. (Thereby) he gets his desired objects and is everywhere born in a high family. God Maheśvara is always actually present where the illustrious goddess Yamunā, the daughter of the Sun, well-known in the three worlds, goes. O Yudhiṣṭhira, the auspicious Prayāga is difficult to be reached by human beings. O lord of kings, having bathed there, gods, demons, gandharvas, sages, siddhas and cāraṇas, are honoured in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>042 Importance of Giving a Cow at Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/042/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/042/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇdeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇdeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-24. O king, hear again the greatness of Prayāga, going where, a man is freed from all sins. There is no doubt about it. Except Prayāga, there is absolutely no eternal place for the afflicted and the poor who are of a firm resolve. A man who having reached the confluence of Gaṅgā and Yamunā, would cast his life, goes in an aeroplane having the colour of heated gold and resembling the sun, (and) rejoices in heaven in the company of gandharvas and celestial nymphs. The best sages say that (such) a man obtains desired objects. He rejoices with all auspicious things, divine and full of gems, is accompanied by various flags and surrounded by excellent damsels. He when asleep is awakened by the sound of songs and musical instruments. As long as he does not call to mind (his earthly) existence (or life), he is honoured in heaven. Then deprived of heaven, having fallen from there due to the (fruit of) his deeds being exhausted, he is born in a rich family full of (i.e. accomplished with) gold and gems. He recollects that holy place, and merely by remembering it he goes there. The best sages say that a man, being in a region or in a forest or in a foreign country, or in his own house, who would cast his life (there) by just remembering Prayāga, obtains (i.e. goes to) Brahmā’s world, where the golden land is full of all desired objects, and to which world the seers and sages go. Due to the deeds done by him in this world a man rejoices along with the sages on the charming, auspicious bank of Mandākinī crowded with thousands of women. In heaven he is honoured by siddhas, cāraṇas, gandharvas and deities. Then fallen from heaven, he would be a lord in Jambudvīpa. Then repeatedly thinking about auspicious deeds, he undoubtedly becomes virtuous and endowed with wealth in this world. He who is well-settled in truthfulness by deeds, speech and mind, and gives gifts in between (the region of) Gaṅgā and Yamunā (gets liberation). He, who accepts gold, jewels, pearls or grains at his own rite or in honour of the manes, or in the worship of deities, has his visit to the holy places rendered fruitless as long as he gets the fruit of that (i.e. accepting gifts). Thus a man should not accept (gifts) at a holy place and a sanctuary. A twice-born should be careful about all omens. He who gives a tawny, red-coloured, golden-horned, silver-hoofed milch-cow with a piece of cloth round her neck (to a brāhmaṇa) at Prayāga (gets liberation). Having properly secured at Prayāga a learned, good, tranquil, pious brāhmaṇa, master of the Vedas, and wearing white garments, that cow should be given to him at the confluence of Gaṅgā and Yamunā. Costly garments, various jewels (should also be given). The man (who gives such a gift) is honoured in heaven for as many thousand years as there is hair on the limbs of the cow, O best one. The cow is born there where he is born. Due to that act he does not see (i.e. go to) horrible hell. Having reached Uttara Kuru, he rejoices for an inexhaustible period. (Instead of giving) hundreds and thousands of bulls he should give one milch-cow. One cow would liberate sons, wife and servants. Therefore, of all gifts, the gift of a cow is the best. In a terrible, insurmountable difficulty due to a horrible sin, a cow alone protects (a man). Therefore (a cow) should be given to a brāhmaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>043 The Fruit of Visiting Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/043/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/043/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O sage, as you have narrated the greatness of Prayāga, I am undoubtedly being freed from sins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O revered one, in what manner should people of religious resolve go (there)? O great sage, tell me about the rite which is declared (to be performed) at Prayāga.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇḍeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-27. O dear, I shall tell you the entire sequence of the religious rites to be performed during the pilgrimage. O best of Kurus, I will tell you the fruit accruing to him who mounted upon a bull goes to Prayāga united with gods. Due to the anger of bull he lives in a terrible hell. From such a man his dead ancestors do not accept water (offered by him); but he who would bathe his sons and all children and would make them drink (water at the holy place) like himself and would cause gifts to be given to brāhmaṇas (is liberated). A man who, due to his desire for (showing off) his affluence or to delusion, would go (to a holy place) in a vehicle, his (visit to the) holy place is fruitless. Therefore, a man should avoid (going in) a vehicle. He who (in the region) between Gaṅgā and Yamunā, gives his daughter (in marriage) according to the Ārṣa form of marriage and according to his wealth, does not see (i.e. go to) a terrible hell due to that deed. Having gone to Uttara Kuru he rejoices for an inexhaustible period. He obtains sons and wife that are pious and endowed with righteousness. There he should give gifts in accordance with his wealth. There is no doubt that due to the fruit of (the visit to) the holy place only, he prospers. O lord of kings, he stays in heaven till deluge. He who having resorted to the root of the Vaṭa (tree), would cast his life, goes to Rudra’s world after having crossed all (other) worlds. There the twelve suns resorting to Rudra shine. They completely burn the entire world. (Only) the root of the Vaṭa (tree), where, when the world is (but) one ocean, when the moon, the sun, and the wind have perished, Viṣṇu born again and again, sleeps, is not burnt. Gods, demons, gandharvas, sages, siddhas, cāraṇas always resort to that holy place on the confluence of Gaṅgā and Yamunā. O lord of kings, they go there. It is united with Prayāga. There gods like Brahma, quarters and lords of quarters, regents of quarters, sādhyas, the manes liked by people, and also great sages led by Sanatkumāra, and other brāhmaṇic sages like Aṅgiras, also nāgas, siddhas, suparṇas, those moving in the sky, rivers, oceans, mountains, nāgas and also vidyādharas (stay). The revered Viṣṇu led by Prajāpati (i.e. Brahmā) also stays there. O best of kings, Prayāga well-known in the three worlds and (lying) between Gaṅgā and Yamunā is said to be the hip and the loin of the earth. O descendant of Bharata, there is nothing more sacred than it in the three worlds. By hearing (the description) of that holy place, even by mentioning its name, or securing the clay from that place, a man is freed from sins. He who, of a severe vow, bathes there at the confluence, obtains the same fruit as Rājasūya and Aśvamedha (sacrifices) (give). O dear one, even you should not change your mind to go to Prayāga even by (i.e. depending upon) the words of the Vedas, or of the people. O descendant of Kuru, the presence of ten thousand holy places and sixty crore others is here only. He who casts his life at the confluence of Gaṅgā and Yamunā follows the same course, as a wise man endowed with abstract meditation and born of good parents follows. O Yudhiṣṭhira, those who have not visited Prayāga, well-known in the three worlds, do not (really) live in the world. Thus seeing that holy place—the highest place—Prayāga, a man is free from all sins as the Moon is from Rāhu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>044 The Fruit of Bathing in the Confluence at Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/044/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/044/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇdeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇdeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-20a. O king, hear again the greatness of Prayāga, having heard which a man is freed from all sins. There is no doubt about it. That (famous) Mānasa lake is on the left bank of Gaṅgā. Having fasted (there) for three nights a man would obtain all his desired objects. A man obtains that fruit when he remembers the holy place, which he would obtain by giving a cow, land, or gold. A man who, with or without a desire, dies in Gaṅgā, lives in heaven after death, and does not see (i.e. go to) hell. He is awakened by the music of that host of celestial nymphs from his sleep. He goes in an aeroplane to which swans and cranes are yoked. O lord of kings, he enjoys for many years—six thousand years. Then being deprived of heaven and having fallen from there due to (the fruit of) his acts being exhausted, he is born in a family rich with gold, jewels and pearls. There are sixty thousand sixty hundred holy places. They go to the confluence of Gaṅgā and Yamunā in the month of Māgha. That fruit which one gets by properly giving away a thousand cows is had by bathing for three days at Prayāga in the month of Māgha. He who would practise the vow of the five fires between (i.e. at the confluence of) Gaṅgā and Yamunā, is defectless in limbs, is free from diseases and has the five senses (intact). For as many thousand years as the number of pores of hair are there on his body, he is honoured in heaven. Then having fallen from heaven he would be the lord of Jambudvīpa. The man enjoying many pleasures resorts to that holy place. He who would enter water at the confluence well-known in the world, is freed from all sins as the Moon eclipsed by Rāhu (becomes free). He obtains (i.e. goes to) the world of Soma and rejoices with Soma. Being served by sages and gandharvas he obtains (i.e. lives in) heaven for sixty thousand sixty hundred years. Fallen (from there) he is born in an affluent family. The man who with his head down and feet up would drink (i.e. take in) the flame, is honoured for a hundred thousand years in heaven. Having fallen from there, O lord of kings, he becomes a performer of agnihotra. Having enjoyed many pleasures, the man resorts to that holy place. He who cuts off his body and offers (the pieces of) it to the birds (is honoured in heaven). Hear the fruit of him (i.e. which he gets), who (i.e. whose body) is enjoyed by birds. For a hundred thousand years he is honoured in the world of Soma. Then having fallen from heaven he becomes (i.e. is born as) a pious, virtuous, handsome, learned king, having a very lovable body. Having enjoyed many pleasures, he again resorts to that holy place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>045 Agnitīrtha, Virañjana, Svargatīrtha etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/045/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/045/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having heard this description of Prayāga which you have given, my heart has become very pure. O revered Sir, tell me what kind of fruit (a man gets) by fasting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇḍeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O king, O lord, listen to the fruit of fasting which a wise man who has faith, obtains. He becomes one who has no defect in any limb, is free from diseases, and endowed with (i.e. has his) five senses (intact). When he walks, at every step he gets the fruit of a horse sacrifice. O king, he liberates his ten predecessors and ten successors in the family. He is freed from all sins and would go to the highest position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>046 More about Merits Derived from Pilgrimage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/046/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/046/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. I have heard what Brahmā told and what gives religious merit, in the Purāṇa. There are thousands and hundreds and millions of holy places. All these are auspicious and pure and (are) said (to lead to) the highest position. Naimiṣa is meritorious on the earth and Puṣkara in the Intermediate Space; so also is Prayāga for the people, and Kurukṣetra also excels. How do you praise one (only) leaving all (others)? This is said to be unauthoritative, unbelievable and not good. How do you speak approvingly of divine and highest position, and pleasures as desired, and great merit through little yoga? Tell me about (i.e. remove) this doubt of mine according as you have seen and heard.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>047 Prayāga Again</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/047/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/047/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇḍeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. O king, hear again (about) the greatness of Prayāga. There are many holy places and other auspicious mountains like Naimiṣa, Puṣkara, Gotīrtha, Sindhusāgara, Kurukṣetra, Gayā, and Gaṅgāsāgara. The wise say that ten thousand holy places and thirty crore others are always situated at Prayāga. There are three fire-vessels, from which Gaṅgā, led by all (other) holy places has set out from Prayāga. The goddess (Yamunā), the daughter of the Sun is well-known in the three worlds. Gaṅgā causing people to enjoy, stays (here) with Yamunā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>048 Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Śiva Dwell in Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/048/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/048/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yudhiṣṭhira-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yudhiṣṭhira said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O great sage, you have told me all this account of Prayāga. Similarly tell me everything so that it would liberate me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mārkaṇḍeya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. O king, listen, I shall explain: This whole world is said to be Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Īśāna, the immutable lord of the deities. Brahmā creates the creatures and whatever is immobile and mobile. The highest Viṣṇu protects them, the created beings, in the world. At the end of a kalpa Rudra destroys the entire world. He neither gives, nor does he accept, and never perishes. He who sees him (to be) the lord of all beings, (indeed) perceives. Now Brahmā is at the north of Pratiṣṭhāna. The highest lord being Maheśvara, remains at Vaṭa. The gods with gandharvas, siddhas and great sages always take care of the highest one. Those who are bent on doing sinful deeds and others (like them) who are (there), do not obtain the highest position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>049 Kṛṣṇa Recommends Pilgrimage to Prayāga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/049/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/049/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. All the Pāṇḍavas bent upon meritorious acts, along with their brothers, saluted the brāhmaṇas and offered oblations to their (dead) elders and deities. Kṛṣṇa also at that time came there in a moment. All the Pāṇḍavas together honoured that Mādhava (i.e. Kṛṣṇa). All the noble ones, along with Kṛṣṇa, consecrated Yudhiṣṭhira, Dharma’s son, on the kingdom (i.e. the throne).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4. In the meanwhile (i.e. at this time) only, the great-souled Mārkaṇḍeya, then saying: ‘May it be well with you’, came in a moment to the hermitage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>050 Viṣṇu’s Name the Greatest Holy Place</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/050/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/050/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. You have told (i.e. explained) all that was asked. Now also we (want to) ask one (thing only). O you very intelligent one, (please) tell it. O you who know everything, tell us what fruit a man would obtain by resorting to these holy places. So also tell us by doing which one act (the fruit of visiting) all (these holy places) is had; tell us if there is such an act.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>051 Karmayoga or Rules of Conduct</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/051/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/051/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. How is that path of action (consisting of worldly and religious rites), propitiated by which Viṣṇu becomes pleased, O Sūta? O illustrious one, O best among speakers, tell that to us. (Tell us about that Karmayoga) by which those desirous of salvation can propitiate the revered lord. Tell us also about that path of action, that protects all the worlds and is the totality of dharma, and of an embodied form, O Sūta. With a desire to hear this the sages have settled in front of you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>052 Rules for Sipping Water</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/052/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/052/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-19. An excellent brāhmaṇa should again sip water having eaten, or drunk or slept, after walking in a street or having touched his lips after licking them, after putting on a garment, after having ejected semen, or urinated or cleared the bowels, after having told a lie, after spitting, at the beginning of study, after having (an attack of) asthma, so also after having crossed a place where many roads meet or a crematory, at the time of both the prayers, even though he has already sipped water. Similarly he should sip water after talking with a cāṇḍāla or a mleccha, or with a woman, or a śūdra, or a person who has not washed his hands etc. after eating food, so also on seeing a man who has not washed his hands etc. and on seeing leavings of food, or on seeing tears being shed or bleeding, at the time of taking food, at the time of both the prayers after bathing, having drunk (water etc.), and having come after urination or clearing his bowels or should sip water once after having slept (and then got up), so also for other (similar reasons). On touching fire or cows, or a holy person, so also on being touched by women, he should sip water, so also after having touched a diseased person, grass or ground; so also (he should sip water) on touching his own hair, or on touching a garment that has fallen down. Always desiring purity, he should, with his head or neck covered, or with his hair and the lock of hair on the crown of his head loose, and being seated with his face towards the east or north, sip properly, water that is not hot, does not have hair in it and which is pure. Without washing his feet he would not be pure from (the impurity of having walked over) a path. A wise man should not sip water with shoes on, or while in a carriage or with his turban on; so also with the streams of rain-showers, while standing, or with water drawn out (of a well etc.), or with water made over with one hand and without wearing the sacred thread. So also (he should not sip water) while sitting on a seat; or with his knees outstretched, so also while talking, laughing, seeing (something) or lying on a bed. (He should not sip water) impaired with foam etc. or (water) that is dropped from the hands of a śūdra or an impure person or saline water. (While sipping water) he should not produce sound with his fingers, should not be distracted; (he should not sip water) which is polluted with colours and liquids; so also (the water) from crevices; so also that which is agitated with the hands, or with his shoulders stretched out. A brāhmaṇa is purified when the water reaches his heart, a kṣatriya becomes pure when it reaches his throat; a vaiśya, a woman and a śūdra are purified when it touches (their bodies) from within after it is drunk. The part of the hand situated on the line at the root of the thumb is called Brāhma. The part between the thumb and the fore finger is said to be the holy place of the manes. The part below the little is called Prājāpatya. The tip of a finger is said to be divine. The same is called Ārṣa (‘of the sages’). The root is daiva or ārṣa, and the middle part is said to be Āgneya (of Agni). The same is sacred to Soma. Knowing this he is not confounded. A brāhmaṇa should always sip with the Brāhma holy place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>053 Rules of Conduct for a Celibate Student</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/053/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/053/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-22. Thus endowed with a staff etc. and with purity and (proper) conduct, when called he should study looking at the face of the preceptor. He should always have his hands raised (i.e. should be ready), and should be well-controlled having good conduct. When told by the teacher ‘sit down’, he should sit facing him. He should not lie, so also should be seated or be eating food, while listening to or talking (with his preceptor). So also he should not remain with his face turned away (from his preceptor). His bed or seat should always be near his teacher (but) downwards (i.e. at a low level). When within the range of the preceptor&amp;rsquo;s sight, he should not sit on a seat as he likes. Even in the absence of his preceptor he should not utter his name. He should not imitate his gait, speech or movement. He should cover his ears, or go to another place from the place where the preceptor is being censured or blamed. Remaining away (i.e. from a distance) he should not honour him, so also when angry he should not honour him, nor when he is near a woman. Being seated he should not give a reply to him; nor should he sit near him. He should always bring for him a jar with water (in it), kuśas, flowers and sacrificial sticks. He should cleanse his body and apply unguents to it. He should never cross over the remains of (flowers etc. used by) him, his bed, wooden sandals or shoes, so also his seat or shadow. He should secure pieces of wood used as a toothbrush etc. and report to him whatever is obtained by him. Without asking him (i.e. his permission) he should not go anywhere, and should be devoted to his well-being and what is liked by him. In the presence of the preceptor he should always avoid yawning, laughing, covering his neck or cracking (the limbs of) his body. He should study at the proper time, when the preceptor is not depressed. He should sit on a seat lower than that of the preceptor or by his side, and with concentration (offer him) service. He should never remain (i.e. sit) on his seat or bed. He should run after the preceptor when he is running; should go (i.e. walk) after when he is going. On kuśa seats or on a bull, a horse or a camel, so also on a slab or a plank or (while travelling) in boats, he should sit with (i.e. by) the preceptor. He should always control his senses, should control his mind, should be free from anger and pure. He should always use sweet and wholesome words. He should carefully avoid perfumes, flowers, drinks, (other) preparations, pearls, or harm to creatures, so also rubbing his body with unctuous substances, applying pigment to his body, or rubbing it, so also holding (i.e. using) an umbrella. (He should avoid) lust, greed, fear, sleep, singing or playing upon musical instruments, dancing, threatening, abuse, looking at or securing a woman, assaulting another person or wickedness. He should fetch a jar full of water, flowers, cowdung, clay, kuśas (for his preceptor). Everyday he should bring food and alms. Ghee, salt and all that is stale should be avoided. He should never witness dances, and should not long for (listening to) songs. He should not look at the sun, nor should he clean his teeth. Remaining in a lonely place with women is impure, so also talking with śūdras etc. He should not voluntarily take medicine or food left by his preceptor, so also should not excrete or bathe at his will.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>054 Rules for the Householder</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/054/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/054/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8a. O brāhmaṇas, having studied one Veda, two Vedas or (the four) Vedas, along with the Vedāṅgas, and having understood their meaning, the best twice-born should perform the ceremony of bathing at the time of leaving his spiritual teacher. Having given money to his teacher, he should perform the ceremony of bathing at the time of leaving his teacher with the teacher’s permission. Or if he has completed a vow, or has set his mind on the Supreme Soul or is capable, he deserves to perform the ceremony of bathing at the time of leaving his teacher (i.e. should stop his studies). He should hold a staff of bamboo, wear an inner garment, so also an upper one, a sacred thread of two strands, and carry a pot with water, an umbrella, a clean turban, wooden sandals and shoes. He should also put on golden earrings and should not wear a red chaplet except of gold. He should always wear a white garment, should always use perfumes, and should be of a pleasing appearance. When he is affluent, he should not wear old garments. He should not wear a red or a thick garment, so also a garment and ear-rings worn by others. So also he should not use shoes, chaplets or (wooden) sandals (used by others); so also the sacred thread, ornament, darbhas, the skin of a black antelope (worn by others). He should not wear the sacred thread allowing it to hang down from the right shoulder, nor he should wear a garment untidily.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>055 Dont’s for a Twice-born Householder</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/055/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/055/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. (A man) should not harm any creature. He should never tell a lie. He should not speak what is not beneficial or what is not agreeable. He should never be a thief (i.e. should never steal). A creature that takes away (even a blade of) grass, or vegetable, or clay or even water, goes to hell. (Even) if he is poor, he should not accept (anything) from a king or a śūdra or from one who is fallen or from anyone else. A wise man should (always) avoid censured persons. He should not always be a suppliant; he should not implore the same person again. Doing this the suppliant takes away the life of the wicked one. He, especially an excellent twice-born, should not take away the wealth of deities; even in difficulties he should never snatch away the wealth of a brāhmaṇa. Poison is not called poison. The wealth of a brāhmaṇa is called poison. He should also carefully avoid (taking away) the wealth of deities. Prajāpati Manu has said that (taking) flowers, vegetables, water, wood, roots, fruits, grass which are not offered, is not stealing. A twice-born should take flowers in the act of worshipping deities. He should not always take them from one person only, and without his permission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>056 Do’s and Don’t’s in Eating</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/056/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/056/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. A twice-born should not eat the food of a śūdra through infatuation or longing. He who eats it when it is not a time of distress, is reborn as a śūdra. That twice-born who eats the condemned food of a śūdra for six months, becomes a śūdra even when alive, and after death is born as a dog. O best sages, a man who dies with the food of a brāhmaṇa, or a kṣatriya or a vaiśya or a śūdra in his belly, would get his birth (i. e. would be born as a brāhmaṇa etc.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>057 Acts of Charity Prescribed for a Householder</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/057/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/057/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I shall now explain to you the excellent merit of giving gifts, which was formerly told by Brahmā to the sages—the teachers of the Vedas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-30. The giving of proper objects with faith to a worthy recipient is designated as ‘dāna’ and gives the fruit of enjoyment and liberation. I take that to be ‘datta’ which is given with great faith to deserving persons. The rest he preserves for someone else. Dāna (giving gifts) is said to be of three kinds: obligatory, occasional, and optional. The fourth called vimala (i.e. pure) is said to be the best of all gifts. That gift which is everyday given to a brāhmaṇa who does not oblige and without desiring its fruit is said to be obligatory. That gift which is given into the hands of the learned for the appeasement of sin is said to be the excellent gift called ‘occasional’. The sages who have thought about religious merit have called that gift which is given (for getting) a child, success, glory, happiness, as ‘optional’. That gift which is given to those who know Vedas, to please the lord, and with a mind full of piety is pure and auspicious. Having secured a worthy recipient, he should, according to his capacity, resort to the merit due to gift. That worthy recipient whom he waits upon, protects him all round. That which is surplus in the food or garments of the family, should be given. If given otherwise, it does not give the fruit of the gift. He should devoutly give (gifts) to a learned brāhmaṇa, one born in a noble family, one who is modest, one who is practising a vow, and one who is poor. He who devoutly gives land to a brāhmaṇa who has maintained the sacred fire, goes to the highest place, going where he does not grieve. He who gives land with sugarcanes (i.e. land where sugarcanes are growing), so also land with wheat (growing in it), to (a brāhmaṇa) learned in the Vedas, is not reborn. He who gives (a piece of) land, even of the measure of a cow’s hide, to a poor brāhmaṇa, is freed from all sins. Here (i.e. in this world) there is no greater gift than the gift of land. Giving food is equal to that, and gift of knowledge (i.e. teaching) is superior to that. He who duly gives knowledge to a calm, pure, religious brāhmaṇa is honoured in Brahmā’s heaven. A man should everyday give with devotion gold to a brahmacārī ‘religious student’. Being freed from all sins, he would obtain the position of Brahman. By giving food to a householder a man obtains (its) fruit. Food alone should be given to him. By giving it the giver obtains the highest position. Observing a fast with his mind controlled, and being calm and pure, he should honour seven or five brāhmaṇas with black sesamum and especially with honey on the full moon day of Vaiśākha (saying), ‘May Dharmarāja be pleased’; from the time he has this in mind, all the sin committed during his life time perishes in a moment. He who, having put sesamum seeds or gold, or honey or ghee on a hide of a black antelope, gives them to a brāhmaṇa, overcomes all sin. He who gives food with ghee, a jar with water to brāhmaṇas, especially on the full moon day of Vaiśākha, after having assigned it to Dharmarāja is freed from fear. He who pleases seven or five brāhmaṇas with water pots with gold and sesamum seeds, removes (the sin of) killing a brāhmaṇa. Being calm and fasting, wearing a white garment, a twice-born who gives on the twelfth day of the dark fortnight in the month of Māgha after offering sesamum seeds into fire, sesamum seeds only, to brāhmaṇas, overcomes all the sin that he has committed from his birth. When the new moon day arrives, he should give whatever little (he can) to a poor brāhmaṇa, dedicating it to Viṣṇu, the lord of gods, saying, ‘May the ancient god Hṛṣīkeśa Viṣṇu be pleased.’ That moment only his sin committed during the past seven births, perishes. He who would, on the fourteenth day of the dark half, propitiate the trident-holder god (i.e. Śiva) through a brāhmaṇa, would not be re-born. Especially on the eighth day of the dark half, he having bathed and honoured a religious brāhmaṇa should, after washing his feet etc. duly give him his own wealth saying, ‘May Śiva be pleased with me.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>058 Code of Conduct for an Anchorite</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/058/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/058/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Having thus remained in the householder’s stage during the second part of his life, he should, with his wife and (the sacred) fire, resort to the third stage of life. Or, having entrusted his wife to his sons, he should go to a forest after seeing the child of his child (i.e. the grandchild) and when his body has become infirm. He, observing a vow and being calm, should practise penance after having gone to a forest in the forenoon (of a day) in the bright half of a month in the auspicious uttarāyaṇa (i.e. the summer solstice). He should everyday fetch for his food pure roots and fruits. With that which is his food, he should please the manes and deities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>059 Rules of Conduct for a Sannyāsī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/059/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/059/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having thus lived in the stage of an anchorite for the third part of his life, he should gradually pass into the fourth stage of life in renunciation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. Having established the fires in the soul a twice-born would be a recluse. When he, engaged in the practice of abstract meditation, calm, intent on getting the knowledge of Brahman, has detachment in his mind for all objects, then (only) he should think of renouncing (the world). If reverse is the case, then he would fall. Having accomplished the Prājāpatya sacrifice (by giving away his own property) and the fire-sacrifice, he, being restrained, having put on a white or red garment should resort to the stage of the ascetic. Some are ascetics (following the path) of knowledge; some are ascetics (engaged in the study) of the Vedas; others are ascetics (following the path) of action. (Thus ascetics are said to be of three kinds.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>060 Restraints for a Sannyāsī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/060/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/060/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-15. Thus the livelihood of the sages who have controlled themselves and are in the (fourth) stage of life is said to be (had) by means of begging or fruits and roots. He should beg for one time only; he should not be attached to expansion (of begging). An ascetic attached to begging, becomes also attached to objects of senses. He should beg from seven houses. He should not move again (for alms) if he does not get it (during the first round). An ascetic should wait (for alms at a door) with his face hung down for the time required for milking a cow. Saying, ‘Alms (please)’, he, pure and controlled in speech, should remain silent. The man, having washed his hands and feet and sipped water according to proper rite, and having presented the food to the sun, facing the east, should eat it. Having offered oblations to the five vital airs, he, being calm, should eat eight morsels. Having sipped water, he should meditate upon the highest lord, Brahma. Manu Prajāpati has mentioned four (kinds of) pots for an ascetic: pumpkin gourd, wooden, made of clay and of bamboo. Before the fall of night, at midnight, during the last part of the night, he should everyday meditate upon the lord with special hymns at the twilights, after bringing to the lotus of his heart the lord called Viśva, the source of everything, the soul of all creatures dwelling beyond the darkness, the prop of all, the unmanifest, the joy, the immutable light, the one beyond Prakṛti and Puruṣa, the ether, fire and the auspicious one, that essence of all beings, the god of the form of Brahman. At the end of Oṃkāra, and having offered himself into the highest soul, he should meditate upon the lord, the ruler, living in the midst of the sky. He, meditating upon the ancient Puruṣa Viṣṇu, the cause of all objects and the only receptacle of joy, would be free from bondage. Or he should meditate in the heart, (on) the primal nature, the only cause of all beings, the abode of the illusion of the world, the life of all beings, where the world merges. The subtle joy of Brahman which those desiring salvation obtain, in that is placed Brahman—absolute and having knowledge as its characteristic. Having thought over the endless, true lord he should remain controlled in speech.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>061 Devotion to Viṣṇu the Best Way to Salvation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/061/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Thus Vyāsa of immeasurable lustre spoke to the brāhmaṇas. Having said this much, having cheered up all the sages, the revered Vyāsa, the son of Satyavatī, went as he had come.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-8a. I have told you the rules about the castes and the stages of life. Having done this only, a man becomes dear to Viṣṇu, not otherwise. O best brāhmaṇas, I shall tell you the secret about it. Listen. O brāhmaṇas, the duties regarding castes and stages that were told now, are not equal even to the sixteenth part of the devotion to Viṣṇu in this world. In Kaliyuga only devotion to Hari is to be achieved. A man has to practise the duties in the other yuga. That religious man who keeping god Nārāyaṇa, Viṣṇu, Hṛṣīkeśa, invoked by many, the ancient one, the great and the tranquil one, in his heart worships him, has conquered (all) the three worlds. A brāhmaṇa, having drunk the nectar of the devotion to Viṣṇu, has overcome the bite of the serpent of Kali-age, the blemish, the Kālakūṭa (poison).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>062 The Merit of Reciting the Padma Purāṇa, Svargakhaṇḍa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/062/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/062/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8a. Thus is the greatness of that highest lord Viṣṇu, taking up many forms, (Viṣṇu—) who is the cause of complete liberation in the world. One of the forms is the great &lt;em&gt;Padma&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;). The &lt;em&gt;Brahma&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is the head of Viṣṇu only. His heart is called &lt;em&gt;Padma&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is his right arm. The &lt;em&gt;Śaiva&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is the left arm of the great lord. The &lt;em&gt;Bhāgavata&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is said to be his thighs. The &lt;em&gt;Nāradīya&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is his navel. The &lt;em&gt;Mārkaṇḍeya&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is his right foot; the &lt;em&gt;Agni&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is said to be (his) left foot. The &lt;em&gt;Bhaviṣya&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is the right knee of the magnanimous Viṣṇu only. The (Purāṇa) called &lt;em&gt;Brahmavaivarta&lt;/em&gt; is said to be his left knee. The &lt;em&gt;Liṅga&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is said to be the right ankle and the &lt;em&gt;Varāha&lt;/em&gt; is the left ankle. The &lt;em&gt;Skanda Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt; is the hair, and the &lt;em&gt;Vāmana (Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is said to be his skin. The &lt;em&gt;Kūrma&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is said to be his back; the &lt;em&gt;Matsya&lt;/em&gt; is said to his fat. The &lt;em&gt;Garuḍa&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Purāṇa&lt;/em&gt;) is said to be his marrow; the &lt;em&gt;Brahmāṇḍa&lt;/em&gt; is said to be his bone(s). Thus Viṣṇu was having the Purāṇas as parts of his body. &lt;em&gt;Padma&lt;/em&gt; there (i.e. in the body) is the heart, having heard which a man obtains nectar (i.e. immortality).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>063 Section 4 - Brahma-khaṇḍa (Section on Brahman)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/063/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/3/063/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
