<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;नारायणास्त्र-वृन्दम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/meta/articles/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;नारायणास्त्र-वृन्दम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/meta/articles/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Shiva stuti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/meta/articles/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/shiva-stuti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/meta/articles/nArAyaNAstra-vRndam/shiva-stuti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Explanation: Shiva Stuti in Srimad Bhagavatam does not compromise Lord Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s supremacy&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Shiva stuti from the Srimad Bhagavatam (occurring in the Samudra Manthana episode)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There is a tendency among neo-Hindus and modern-day Adavaitins with a Shaivite bias to see Shiva-Vishnu equality or even Shiva’s supremacy in Mahabharata and Ramayana. Elsewhere in this blog, we have seen this tendency taking shape either in the form of treating texts to generous interpolations (such as in the Mahabharata, as we have shown in this article) or distorting the meaning of a few stray verses, showing scant regard to ancient commentators’ say, and exhibiting silence when it comes to certain important verses appearing everywhere in the text proclaiming the supremacy of Vishnu. An example of the latter form can be seen in the internet/social media interpretations of Ramayana, where verses such as “atra pūrvaṃ mahādevaḥ prasādamakarotprabhuḥ” are interpreted to show Shiva’s supremacy/Shiva-Vishnu equality while important verses such as the below are ignored:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
