<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;00 Meta on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;00 Meta on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Dedication</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Śrīla Prabhupāda&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bhaktisiddhānta Sarasvatī&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Gosvāmī Mahārāja&lt;br&gt;&#xA;MY SPIRITUAL MASTER&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the 26th Annual Ceremony of His&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Disappearance Day&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He lives forever by his divine instructions&lt;br&gt;&#xA;and the follower lives with him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We must know the present need of human society. And what is that need? Human society is no longer bounded by geographical limits to particular countries or communities. Human society is broader than in the Middle Ages, and the world tendency is toward one state or one human society. The ideals of spiritual communism, according to &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam,&lt;/em&gt; are based more or less on the oneness of the entire human society, nay, of the entire energy of living beings. The need is felt by great thinkers to make this a successful ideology. &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam&lt;/em&gt; will fill this need in human society. It begins, therefore, with an aphorism of Vedānta philosophy, &lt;em&gt;janmādy asya yataḥ,&lt;/em&gt; to establish the ideal of a common cause.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Introduction</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/00_meta/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The conception of God and the conception of Absolute Truth are not on the same level. The &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam&lt;/em&gt; hits on the target of the Absolute Truth. The conception of God indicates the controller, whereas the conception of the Absolute Truth indicates the &lt;em&gt;summum bonum&lt;/em&gt; or the ultimate source of all energies. There is no difference of opinion about the personal feature of God as the controller because a controller cannot be impersonal. Of course modern government, especially democratic government, is impersonal to some extent, but ultimately the chief executive head is a person, and the impersonal feature of government is subordinate to the personal feature. So without a doubt whenever we refer to control over others we must admit the existence of a personal feature. Because there are different controllers for different managerial positions, there may be many small gods. According to the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad-gītā&lt;/em&gt; any controller who has some specific extraordinary power is called a &lt;em&gt;vibhūtimat sattva,&lt;/em&gt; or controller empowered by the Lord. There are many &lt;em&gt;vibhūtimat sattvas,&lt;/em&gt; controllers or gods with various specific powers, but the Absolute Truth is one without a second. This &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam&lt;/em&gt; designates the Absolute Truth or the &lt;em&gt;summum bonum&lt;/em&gt; as the &lt;em&gt;paraṁ satyam.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
