<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिकृति on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/appayyaH_varadarAja-stavaH/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिकृति on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/appayyaH_varadarAja-stavaH/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>preface</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/appayyaH_varadarAja-stavaH/meta/preface/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/appayyaH_varadarAja-stavaH/meta/preface/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;VARADARADARAJASTAVA is one of the most precious gems from the erudite pen of that most renowned all-round scholar and poet, Sri Appaya Dikshita. Appaya Dikshita along with Sri Vidyaranya and Sri Sankara Bhagavatpadacharya form the most illustrious trio that adorn the firmament of the Sanskrit philosophical literature. All these three are mighty intellectual giants of whom any country and any literature might always be proud. It has been the privilege and good fortune of Mother India this Punyabhumi-to produce three such brilliant stars of the first magnitude. All these three are deservedly considered to be divine incarnations, Sri Sankara comes first and Dikshita last in point of time. By the blessings of His Holiness the Jagadguru of Sringeri the Sri Vani Vilas Press had the unique honour and rare distinction of publishing the memorial edition of the collected works of Sri Sankaracharya. And now it has embarked on the ambitious task of publishing the works of Dikshita one after another and if by God&amp;rsquo;s grace all the works are finished then they will be issued in a collected form, in uniform handy ii&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
