<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;१० on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;१० on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The summary of the First Chapter is as follows. This chapter describes how Kaṁsa, frightened by hearing an omen about his being killed by the eighth son of Devakī, killed Devakī’s sons one after another.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Śukadeva Gosvāmī finished describing the dynasty of Yadu, as well as the dynasties of the moon-god and sun-god, Mahārāja Parīkṣit requested him to describe Lord Kṛṣṇa, who appeared with Baladeva in the Yadu dynasty, and how Kṛṣṇa performed His activities within this world. Kṛṣṇa is transcendental, the King said, and therefore to understand His activities is the occupation of liberated persons. Hearing of &lt;em&gt;kṛṣṇa-līlā&lt;/em&gt; is the boat by which to achieve the ultimate goal of life. Except for an animal killer or one who is following a policy of suicide, every intelligent person must strive to understand Kṛṣṇa and His activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As described in this chapter, when the Supreme Personality of Godhead entered the womb of Devakī to kill Kaṁsa, all the demigods understood that the Lord was living within Devakī’s womb, and therefore in veneration they offered Him the &lt;em&gt;Garbha-stuti&lt;/em&gt; prayers.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kaṁsa, under the protection of his father-in-law, Jarāsandha, and with the help of his demoniac friends like Pralamba, Baka, Cāṇūra, Tṛṇāvarta, Aghāsura, Muṣṭika, Bāṇa and Bhaumāsura, began oppressing the members of the Yadu dynasty. Therefore, the members of the Yadu dynasty left their homes and sought shelter in such states as Kuru, Pañcāla, Kekaya, Śālva and Vidarbha. Only some of them stayed with Kaṁsa, as nominal friends.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As described in this chapter, the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Kṛṣṇa, Hari in His original form, appeared as Viṣṇu so that His father and mother could understand that their son was the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Because they were afraid of Kaṁsa, when the Lord appeared as an ordinary child they took Him to Gokula, the home of Nanda Mahārāja.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mother Devakī, being fully transcendental, &lt;em&gt;sac-cid-ānanda,&lt;/em&gt; does not belong to this material world. Thus the Supreme Personality of Godhead appeared with four hands, as if born from her womb. Upon seeing the Lord in that Viṣṇu form, Vasudeva was struck with wonder, and in transcendental happiness he and Devakī mentally gave ten thousand cows in charity to the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas.&lt;/em&gt; Vasudeva then offered prayers to the Lord, addressing Him as the Supreme Person, Parabrahman, the Supersoul, who is beyond duality and who is internally and externally all-pervading. The Lord, the cause of all causes, is beyond material existence, although He is the creator of this material world. When He enters this world as Paramātmā, He is all-pervading (&lt;em&gt;aṇḍāntara-stha-paramāṇu-cayāntara-stham&lt;/em&gt;), yet He is transcendentally situated. For the creation, maintenance and annihilation of this material world, the Lord appears as the &lt;em&gt;guṇa-avatāras&lt;/em&gt; — Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Maheśvara. Thus Vasudeva offered prayers full of meaning to the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Devakī followed her husband by offering prayers describing the transcendental nature of the Lord. Fearing Kaṁsa and desiring that the Lord not be understood by atheistic and materialistic nondevotees, she prayed that the Lord withdraw His transcendental four-armed form and appear like an ordinary child with two hands.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Kaṁsa, following the advice of his demoniac friends, considered the persecution of small children to be very diplomatic.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Vasudeva bound himself with iron shackles as before, all the doors of the prison house closed by the influence of Yoga-māyā, who then began crying as a newborn child. This crying awakened the doorkeepers, who immediately informed Kaṁsa that a child had been born to Devakī. Upon hearing this news, Kaṁsa appeared with great force in the maternity room, and in spite of Devakī’s pleas that the child be saved, the demon forcibly snatched the child from Devakī’s hands and dashed the child against a rock. Unfortunately for Kaṁsa, however, the newborn child slipped away from his hands, rose above his head and appeared as the eight-armed form of Durgā. Durgā then told Kaṁsa, “The enemy you contemplate has taken birth somewhere else. Therefore your plan to persecute all the children will prove futile.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As described in this chapter, Nanda Mahārāja very gorgeously performed the birth ceremony for his newborn child. Then he went to Kaṁsa to pay taxes due and met his intimate friend Vasudeva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There was great jubilation all over Vṛndāvana due to Kṛṣṇa’s birth. Everyone was overwhelmed with joy. Therefore the King of Vraja, Mahārāja Nanda, wanted to perform the birth ceremony for his child, and this he did. During this great festival, Nanda Mahārāja gave in charity to all present whatever they desired. After the festival, Nanda Mahārāja put the cowherd men in charge of protecting Gokula, and then he went to Mathurā to pay official taxes to Kaṁsa. In Mathurā, Nanda Mahārāja met Vasudeva. Nanda Mahārāja and Vasudeva were brothers, and Vasudeva praised Nanda Mahārāja’s good fortune because he knew that Kṛṣṇa had accepted Nanda Mahārāja as His father. When Vasudeva inquired from Nanda Mahārāja about the welfare of the child, Nanda Mahārāja informed him all about Vṛndāvana, and Vasudeva was very much satisfied by this, although he expressed his grief because Devakī’s many children had been killed by Kaṁsa. Nanda Mahārāja consoled Vasudeva by saying that everything happens according to destiny and that one who knows this is not aggrieved. Expecting many disturbances in Gokula, Vasudeva then advised Nanda Mahārāja not to wait in Mathurā, but to return to Vṛndāvana as soon as possible. Thus Nanda Mahārāja took leave of Vasudeva and returned to Vṛndāvana with the other cowherd men on their bullock carts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A summary of the Sixth Chapter is as follows: when Nanda Mahārāja, following the instructions of Vasudeva, was returning home, he saw a great demoniac woman lying on the road, and then he heard about her death.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While Nanda Mahārāja, the King of Vraja, was thinking about Vasudeva’s words concerning disturbances in Gokula, he was a little afraid and sought shelter at the lotus feet of Śrī Hari. Meanwhile, Kaṁsa sent to the village of Gokula a Rākṣasī named Pūtanā, who was wandering here and there killing small babies. Of course, wherever there is no Kṛṣṇa consciousness, there is the danger of such Rākṣasīs, but since the Supreme Personality of Godhead Himself was in Gokula, Pūtanā could expect nothing there but her own death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s pastimes of breaking the cart (&lt;em&gt;śakaṭa-bhañjana&lt;/em&gt;), killing the &lt;em&gt;asura&lt;/em&gt; known as Tṛṇāvarta, and demonstrating the entire universe within His mouth are especially described.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Śukadeva Gosvāmī saw that Mahārāja Parīkṣit was eagerly waiting to hear about Lord Kṛṣṇa’s pastimes as a child, he was very much pleased, and he continued to speak. When Śrī Kṛṣṇa was only three months old and was just trying to turn backside up, before He even attempted to crawl, mother Yaśodā wanted to observe a ritualistic ceremony with her friends for the good fortune of the child. Such a ritualistic ceremony is generally performed with ladies who also have small children. When mother Yaśodā saw that Kṛṣṇa was falling asleep, because of other engagements she put the child underneath a household cart, called &lt;em&gt;śakaṭa,&lt;/em&gt; and while the child was sleeping, she engaged herself in other business pertaining to the auspicious ritualistic ceremony. Underneath the cart was a cradle, and mother Yaśodā placed the child in that cradle. The child was sleeping, but suddenly He awakened and, as usual for a child, began to kick His small legs. This kicking shook the cart, which collapsed with a great sound, breaking completely and spilling all its contents. Children who were playing nearby immediately informed mother Yaśodā that the cart had broken, and therefore she hastily arrived there in great anxiety with the other &lt;em&gt;gopīs.&lt;/em&gt; Mother Yaśodā immediately took the child on her lap and allowed Him to suck her breast. Then various types of Vedic ritualistic ceremonies were performed with the help of the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas.&lt;/em&gt; Not knowing the real identity of the child, the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; showered the child with blessings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The summary of the Eighth Chapter is as follows. This chapter describes the ceremony of giving a name to Kṛṣṇa. It also describes His crawling, His playing with the cows, and His eating earth and again showing the universal form to His mother.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day, Vasudeva sent for Garga Muni, the family priest of the &lt;em&gt;yadu-vaṁśa,&lt;/em&gt; and thus Garga Muni went to the house of Nanda Mahārāja, who received him very well and requested him to give names to Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma. Garga Muni, of course, reminded Nanda Mahārāja that Kaṁsa was looking for the son of Devakī and said that if he performed the ceremony very gorgeously, the ceremony would come to the notice of Kaṁsa, who would then suspect that Kṛṣṇa was the son of Devakī. Nanda Mahārāja therefore requested Garga Muni to perform this ceremony without anyone’s knowledge, and Garga Muni did so. Because Balarāma, the son of Rohiṇī, increases the transcendental bliss of others, His name is Rāma, and because of His extraordinary strength, He is called Baladeva. He attracts the Yadus to follow His instructions, and therefore His name is Saṅkarṣaṇa. Kṛṣṇa, the son of Yaśodā, previously appeared in many other colors, such as white, red and yellow, and He had now assumed the color black. Because He was sometimes the son of Vasudeva, His name is Vāsudeva. According to His various activities and qualities, He has many other names. After thus informing Nanda Mahārāja and completing the name-giving ceremony, Garga Muni advised Nanda Mahārāja to protect his son very carefully and then departed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While mother Yaśodā was allowing Kṛṣṇa to drink her breast milk, she was forced to stop because she saw the milk pan boiling over on the oven. The maidservants being engaged in other business, she stopped allowing Kṛṣṇa to drink from her breast and immediately attended to the overflowing milk pan. Kṛṣṇa became very angry because of His mother’s behavior and devised a means of breaking the pots of yogurt. Because He created this disturbance, mother Yaśodā decided to bind Him. These incidents are described in this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Kṛṣṇa broke the twin &lt;em&gt;arjuna&lt;/em&gt; trees, from which Nalakūvara and Maṇigrīva, the sons of Kuvera, then came out.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Nalakūvara and Maṇigrīva were great devotees of Lord Śiva, but because of material opulence they became so extravagant and senseless that one day they were enjoying with naked girls in a lake and shamelessly walking here and there. Suddenly Nārada Muni passed by, but they were so maddened by their wealth and false prestige that even though they saw Nārada Muni present, they remained naked and were not even ashamed. In other words, because of opulence and false prestige, they lost their sense of common decency. Of course, it is the nature of the material qualities that when one becomes very much opulent in terms of wealth and a prestigious position, one loses one’s sense of etiquette and does not care about anyone, even a sage like Nārada Muni. For such bewildered persons (&lt;em&gt;ahaṅkāra-vimūḍhātmā&lt;/em&gt;), who especially deride devotees, the proper punishment is to be again stricken with poverty. The Vedic rules and regulations prescribe how to control the false sense of prestige by the practice of &lt;em&gt;yama, niyama&lt;/em&gt; and so on (&lt;em&gt;tapasā brahmacaryeṇa śamena ca damena ca&lt;/em&gt;). A poor man can be convinced very easily that the prestige of an opulent position in this material world is temporary, but a rich man cannot. Therefore Nārada Muni set an example by cursing these two persons, Nalakūvara and Maṇigrīva, to become dull and unconscious like trees. This was a fit punishment. But because Kṛṣṇa is always merciful, even though they were punished they were fortunate enough to see the Supreme Personality of Godhead face to face. Therefore the punishment given by Vaiṣṇavas is not at all punishment; rather, it is another kind of mercy. By the curse of the &lt;em&gt;devarṣi,&lt;/em&gt; Nalakūvara and Maṇigrīva became twin &lt;em&gt;arjuna&lt;/em&gt; trees and remained in the courtyard of mother Yaśodā and Nanda Mahārāja, waiting for the opportunity to see Kṛṣṇa directly. Lord Kṛṣṇa, by the desire of His devotee, uprooted these &lt;em&gt;yamala-arjuna&lt;/em&gt; trees, and when Nalakūvara and Maṇigrīva were thus delivered by Kṛṣṇa after one hundred years of the &lt;em&gt;devas,&lt;/em&gt; their old consciousness revived, and they offered Kṛṣṇa prayers suitable to be offered by demigods. Having thus gotten the opportunity to see Kṛṣṇa face to face, they understood how merciful Nārada Muni was, and therefore they expressed their indebtedness to him and thanked him. Then, after circumambulating the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Kṛṣṇa, they departed for their respective abodes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the inhabitants of Gokula left Gokula and went to Vṛndāvana and how Kṛṣṇa killed Vatsāsura and Bakāsura.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the &lt;em&gt;yamala-arjuna&lt;/em&gt; trees fell, they made a tremendous sound, like that of falling thunderbolts. Being surprised, Kṛṣṇa’s father, Nanda, and the other elderly inhabitants of Gokula went to the spot, where they saw the fallen trees and Kṛṣṇa standing between them, bound to the &lt;em&gt;ulūkhala,&lt;/em&gt; the wooden mortar. They could find no cause for the trees’ having fallen and Kṛṣṇa’s being there. They thought this might be the work of some other &lt;em&gt;asura&lt;/em&gt; who had met Kṛṣṇa on this spot, and they inquired from the playmates of Kṛṣṇa about how the whole incident had taken place. The children properly described how everything had happened, but the elderly persons could not believe the story. Some of them, however, thought that it might be true, since they had already seen many wonderful incidents in connection with Kṛṣṇa. Anyway, Nanda Mahārāja immediately released Kṛṣṇa from the ropes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes in detail Kṛṣṇa’s pastime of killing Aghāsura.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day Kṛṣṇa wanted to enjoy a picnic lunch within the forest, and therefore He went out early into the forest with the other cowherd boys, accompanied by their respective groups of calves. While they were enjoying their picnic, Aghāsura, the younger brother of Pūtanā and Bakāsura, appeared there, desiring to kill Kṛṣṇa and His companions. The demon, who had been sent by Kaṁsa, assumed the form of a python, expanding himself to a length of eight miles and the height of a mountain, his mouth seeming to extend from the surface of the earth to the heavenly planets. Having assumed this feature, Aghāsura lay on the road. Kṛṣṇa’s friends, the cowherd boys, thought that the demon’s form was one of the beautiful spots of Vṛndāvana. Thus they wanted to enter within the mouth of this gigantic python. The gigantic figure of the python became a subject for their sporting pleasure, and they began to laugh, confident that even if this figure were dangerous, Kṛṣṇa was there to protect them. In this way, they proceeded toward the mouth of the gigantic figure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes Lord Brahmā’s attempt to take away the calves and cowherd boys, and it also describes the bewilderment of Lord Brahmā and finally the clearance of his illusion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although the incident concerning Aghāsura had been performed one year before, when the cowherd boys were five years old, when they were six years old they said, “It happened today.” What happened was this. After killing Aghāsura, Kṛṣṇa, along with His associates the cowherd boys, went for a picnic within the forest. The calves, being allured by green grasses, gradually went far away, and therefore Kṛṣṇa’s associates became a little agitated and wanted to bring back the calves. Kṛṣṇa, however, encouraged the boys by saying, “You take your tiffin without being agitated. I shall go find the calves.” And thus the Lord departed. Then, just to examine the potency of Kṛṣṇa, Lord Brahmā took away all the calves and cowherd boys and kept them in a secluded place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the prayers Brahmā offered to Lord Kṛṣṇa, who is also known as Nanda-nandana.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For His satisfaction, Brahmā first praised the beauty of the Lord’s transcendental limbs and then declared that His original identity of sweetness is even more difficult to comprehend than His opulence. Only by the devotional process of hearing and chanting transcendental sounds received from Vedic authorities can one realize the Personality of Godhead. It is fruitless to try to realize God through processes outside the scope of Vedic authority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Balarāma and Lord Kṛṣṇa, while tending Their cows in the pastures of Vṛndāvana, killed Dhenukāsura, enabled the residents of Vṛndāvana to eat the fruits of the &lt;em&gt;tāla&lt;/em&gt; trees and saved the young cowherds from Kāliya’s poison.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Revealing Their boyhood (&lt;em&gt;paugaṇḍa&lt;/em&gt;) phase of pastimes, Rāma and Kṛṣṇa were one day bringing the cows to pasture when They entered an attractive forest decorated with a clear lake. There They began playing forest sports along with Their friends. Pretending to tire, Lord Baladeva laid His head upon the lap of a cowherd boy and rested as Lord Kṛṣṇa helped relieve His elder brother’s fatigue by massaging His feet. Then Kṛṣṇa also placed His head on the lap of a cowherd boy to rest, and another cowherd boy massaged His feet. In this way Kṛṣṇa, Balarāma and Their cowherd friends enjoyed various pastimes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s pastime of subduing the serpent Kāliya within the lake adjoining the river Yamunā and His showing mercy to Kāliya in response to the prayers offered by Kāliya’s wives, the Nāgapatnīs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To restore the purity of the Yamunā’s waters, which had been contaminated by Kāliya’s poison, Lord Kṛṣṇa climbed into a &lt;em&gt;kadamba&lt;/em&gt; tree on the riverbank and jumped into the water. Then He began fearlessly playing within the water like a maddened elephant. Kāliya could not tolerate Kṛṣṇa’s trespassing upon his personal residence, and the serpent quickly went up to the Lord and bit Him on the chest. When Kṛṣṇa’s friends saw this, they fell down on the ground unconscious. At that time all sorts of evil omens appeared in Vraja, such as earth tremors, falling stars and the trembling of various creatures’ left limbs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Kāliya left the island of the snakes and how the sleeping residents of Vṛndāvana were saved from a forest fire.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When King Parīkṣit inquired about Kāliya’s leaving Ramaṇaka Island, the abode of the serpents, and about why Garuḍa acted inimically toward him, Śrī Śukadeva Gosvāmī replied as follows: All the serpents on the island were afraid of being devoured by Garuḍa. To placate him, every month they would leave various offerings for him at the foot of a banyan tree. But Kāliya, puffed-up as he was with false pride, would eat these offerings himself. Hearing of this, Garuḍa became furious and went to kill Kāliya, whereupon the snake began biting the great bird. Garuḍa fiercely beat him with his wing, sending Kāliya fleeing for his life to a lake adjoining the Yamunā River.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The killing of Pralambāsura is described in this chapter. While playing happily in Vṛndāvana, Lord Baladeva climbed up on the shoulders of the demon Pralamba and struck his head with His fist, destroying him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Śrī Vṛndāvana, where Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma enacted Their pastimes, was even during the summer decorated with all the qualities of spring. At that time Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa would become absorbed in various sports, surrounded by Balarāma and all the cowherd boys. One day they were intently dancing, singing and playing when a demon named Pralamba entered their midst, disguised as a cowherd boy. The omniscient Lord Kṛṣṇa saw through the disguise, but even as He thought of how to kill the demon, He treated him as a friend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa saved the cows and the cowherd boys from a great fire in the Muñjāraṇya forest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day the cowherd boys became absorbed in sporting and allowed the cows to wander into a dense forest. Suddenly a forest fire blazed up, and to escape its flames the cows took refuge in a grove of sharp canes. When the cowherd boys missed their animals, they went searching for them, following their hoofprints and the trail of blades of grass and other plants they had trampled or had broken with their teeth. Finally the boys found the cows and removed them from the cane forest, but by that time the forest fire had grown strong and was threatening both the boys and the cows. Thus the cowherd boys took shelter of Śrī Kṛṣṇa, the master of all mystic power, who told them to close their eyes. They did so, and in a moment He had swallowed up the fierce forest fire and brought them all back to the Bhāṇḍīra tree mentioned in the last chapter. Seeing this wonderful display of mystic potency, the cowherd boys thought Kṛṣṇa must be a demigod, and they began to praise Him. Then they all returned home.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To enhance the description of Lord Kṛṣṇa’s pastimes, Śrī Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes in this chapter the beauty of Vṛndāvana during autumn and the rainy season. In the course of his presentation he gives various charming instructions in metaphorical terms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;text-1&#34;&gt;Text 1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;devanagari&#34;&gt;Devanagari&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;श्रीशुक उवाच&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तयोस्तदद्भ‍ुतं कर्म दावाग्नेर्मोक्षमात्मन- ।&lt;br&gt;&#xA;गोपा- स्त्रीभ्य- समाचख्यु- प्रलम्बवधमेव च ॥ १ ॥&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;verse-text&#34;&gt;Verse text&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;śrī-śuka uvāca&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;tayos tad adbhutaṁ karma&lt;br&gt;&#xA;dāvāgner mokṣam ātmanaḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;gopāḥ strībhyaḥ samācakhyuḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;pralamba-vadham eva ca&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa entered the enchanting forest of Vṛndāvana upon the arrival of autumn, and the praises the young cowherd girls sang when they heard the vibration of His flute.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As Lord Kṛṣṇa, Lord Balarāma and Their cowherd friends entered the forest to graze the cows, Kṛṣṇa began playing His flute. The &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; heard the enchanting flute-song and understood that Kṛṣṇa was entering the forest. Then they narrated to each other the Lord’s various activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the marriageable daughters of the cowherd men worshiped Kātyāyanī to get Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa as their husband, and how Kṛṣṇa stole the garments of the young girls and gave the girls benedictions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the month of Mārgaśīrṣa, every day early in the morning the young daughters of the cowherds would take one another’s hands and, singing of Kṛṣṇa’s transcendental qualities, go to the Yamunā to bathe. Desiring to obtain Kṛṣṇa as their husband, they would then worship the goddess Kātyāyanī with incense, flowers and other items.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, after inducing the cowherd boys to beg for food, showed mercy to the wives of some &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; performing a sacrifice and made the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; themselves feel remorse.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the cowherd boys became very hungry, they asked Śrī Kṛṣṇa about obtaining food, and He sent them to beg some from a group of &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; who were performing a sacrifice nearby. But these &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; ignored the boys, thinking Śrī Kṛṣṇa an ordinary human being. The boys returned disappointed, but the Lord sent them off again, advising them to ask the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas’&lt;/em&gt; wives for the food. These ladies had heard of Kṛṣṇa’s transcendental qualities and were very much attached to Him. Thus as soon as they learned He was nearby, they went to Him in great haste, bringing all four varieties of food. In this way they offered themselves to Śrī Kṛṣṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa crushes the pride of Indra by prohibiting a sacrifice intended for him and initiating a substitute sacrifice in worship of Govardhana Hill.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Śrī Kṛṣṇa saw the cowherd men busily preparing for a sacrifice to Indra, He inquired about it from their king, Nanda. Nanda explained that the rain given by Indra enables all living entities to maintain their lives, and therefore this sacrifice would be executed to satisfy him. Kṛṣṇa responded, “It is because of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; alone that living entities take their birth in a certain body, experience varieties of happiness and suffering in that body, and then give it up as the &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; pertaining to it runs out. Thus it is &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; alone that is our enemy, our friend, our &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt; and our lord, and Indra can do nothing to alter the happiness and distress of anyone, for everyone is tightly bound by his karmic reactions. The material modes of goodness, passion and ignorance bring about the creation, maintenance and destruction of this world. The clouds give forth rain when they are impelled by the mode of passion, and cowherds prosper by protecting the cows. Furthermore, the cowherds’ proper residence is in the forest and on the hills. Therefore you should offer worship to the cows, the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; and Govardhana Hill.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Indra was overcome by anger when the residents of Vraja canceled his sacrifice, how he tried to punish them by sending forth a devastating rainfall to Vṛndāvana, and how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa protected Gokula by lifting Govardhana Hill and for seven days using it as an umbrella to ward off the rain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indra, angered at the disruption of the sacrifice meant for him and falsely presuming himself the supreme controller, said, “People often give up the pursuit of transcendental knowledge — the means for self-realization — and imagine that they can cross over the ocean of material existence by mundane fruitive sacrifices. Similarly, these cowherd men have become intoxicated by pride and have offended me by taking shelter of an ignorant, ordinary child — Kṛṣṇa.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Nanda Mahārāja describes Kṛṣṇa’s opulences to the cowherd men, as Nanda had heard of them from Garga Muni.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The cowherd men, unaware of Lord Kṛṣṇa’s power, were amazed to see His various extraordinary activities. The men approached Nanda Mahārāja and told him that after seeing how Kṛṣṇa, a boy only seven years old, had lifted a mountain, and how He had previously killed the demoness Pūtanā and generated extreme attraction in the hearts of everyone in Vṛndāvana, the men had become doubtful and bewildered about how Śrī Kṛṣṇa could possibly have taken birth in the unsuitable environment of a cowherd community. Nanda replied by relating to them what Garga Muni had told him about Śrī Kṛṣṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the Surabhi cow and Indra, having seen the amazing power of Lord Kṛṣṇa, performed a bathing ceremony for Him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ashamed of having attacked Vṛndāvana with a violent storm, Indra secretly came before Lord Kṛṣṇa, offered obeisances and praised Him. Indra stated that although Śrī Kṛṣṇa is never caught in the current of material illusion, which is born of ignorance, He nevertheless accepts a humanlike body and performs various activities to establish religious principles and chastise the wicked. By this means He crushes the false prestige of those who presume themselves great controllers. Indra went on to declare that Kṛṣṇa is the father, &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt; and Lord of all living entities, and that in the form of time He is the agent of their punishment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa brought Nanda Mahārāja back from the abode of Varuṇa and how the cowherd men saw Vaikuṇṭha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The king of the cowherds, Nanda Mahārāja, observed the prescribed fast on the eleventh day of the lunar month and then considered how to break his fast properly on the twelfth day. By circumstance only a few more minutes remained, and so he decided to take his bath at the very end of the night, although astrologically that was an inauspicious time. Thus he entered the water of the Yamunā. A servant of Varuṇa, the demigod of the ocean, noticed Nanda Mahārāja entering the water at a time forbidden by scripture and took him away to the demigod’s abode. In the early morning the cowherd men unsuccessfully searched for Nanda, but Lord Kṛṣṇa immediately understood the situation and went to see Varuṇa. Varuṇa worshiped Kṛṣṇa with great and variegated festivity. Afterwards he begged the Lord to forgive his servant for having foolishly arrested the king of the cowherds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, intending to enjoy the &lt;em&gt;rāsa&lt;/em&gt; dance, engaged in arguments and counterarguments with the &lt;em&gt;gopīs.&lt;/em&gt; Then there is a description of the beginning of the &lt;em&gt;rāsa&lt;/em&gt; dance and the Lord’s pastime of disappearing from the midst of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Remembering the promise He had made to the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; when He had stolen their clothes, Lord Kṛṣṇa employed His Yoga-māyā potency and manifested within Himself the desire to enjoy pastimes during an autumn night. Thus He began to play His flute. When the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; heard the flute’s sound, the impulses of Cupid were violently aroused within them, and they immediately abandoned all their household duties and hastily went to Kṛṣṇa. All the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; had purely spiritual bodies, but when some of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs’&lt;/em&gt; husbands and other family members stopped the young girls from going, Lord Kṛṣṇa arranged for them to temporarily exhibit material bodies, which they then left at the sides of their husbands. In this way they deceived their relatives and went off to meet Kṛṣṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; tormented through the long night by separation from Kṛṣṇa, wandered like madwomen from forest to forest in search of Him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Śrī Kṛṣṇa suddenly disappeared from the arena of the &lt;em&gt;rāsa&lt;/em&gt; dance, the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; their minds fully absorbed in thoughts of Him, began looking for Him in the various forests. From all the moving and nonmoving creatures they asked for news of Kṛṣṇa’s whereabouts. Finally they became so distraught that they began imitating His pastimes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; overwhelmed by feelings of separation from Kṛṣṇa, sat down on the bank of the Yamunā and began praying for His audience and singing His glories.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; had dedicated their minds and very lives to Kṛṣṇa, they were beside themselves with the transcendental pain of separation. But their crying, which appears like evidence of misery, actually shows their exalted state of transcendental bliss. As it is said, &lt;em&gt;yata dekha vaiṣṇaver vyavahāra duḥkha/ niścaya jāniha sei paramānanda sukha&lt;/em&gt;: “Whenever one sees a Vaiṣṇava acting unhappy, one should know it for sure that he is actually experiencing the highest spiritual bliss.” Thus each of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; began addressing Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa according to her individual mode of ecstasy, and they all prayed for Him for His mercy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Śrī Kṛṣṇa manifested Himself in the midst of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; who had become extremely disturbed by their separation from Him. After He consoled them, they expressed to Him their deep feelings of ecstasy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; having shown in various ways their great eagerness to see Kṛṣṇa, the attractor of Cupid, He appeared before them wearing silken yellow garments and a beautiful flower garland. Some of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; overwhelmed with ecstasy at seeing Him, grasped His hands, others placed His arm on their shoulders, and others accepted the remnants of betel nut He had chewed. Thus they served Him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s &lt;em&gt;rāsa&lt;/em&gt; dance, which He enjoyed with His beloved girlfriends in the forests along the Yamunā River.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Personality of Godhead, Śrī Kṛṣṇa, is most expert in the knowledge of transcendental moods. In the company of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; who were tightly bound to Him by the ropes of affection and totally dedicated to His service, the Lord expanded Himself into numerous forms. The &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; became intoxicated with their enthusiasm to enjoy the &lt;em&gt;rāsa&lt;/em&gt; dance, and thus they began satisfying Kṛṣṇa’s senses by singing, dancing and gesturing amorously. The sweet voices of the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; filled all the directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa saved His father Nanda from the clutches of a serpent and delivered a Vidyādhara named Sudarśana from the curse of the Āṅgirasa sages.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day Nanda Mahārāja and the other cowherd men placed their family members on their bullock carts and went to the Ambikāvana forest to worship Lord Śiva. After bathing in the Sarasvatī River and worshiping Lord Sadāśiva, a form of Lord Viṣṇu, they decided to spend the night in the forest. As they slept, a hungry serpent came and began to swallow Nanda Mahārāja. Terrified, Nanda cried out in distress, “O Kṛṣṇa! O my son, please save this surrendered soul!” The cowherd men immediately awoke and began beating the serpent with wooden torches, but the serpent would not release Nanda. Then Lord Kṛṣṇa came and touched the serpent with His lotus foot. The serpent was immediately freed from his reptilian body and appeared in his original form as a demigod. He told them about his previous identity and described how he had been cursed by a group of sages. Then he offered his homage at the lotus feet of Śrī Kṛṣṇa and, on the Lord’s order, returned to his own abode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter contains the songs the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; sing to express their feelings of separation from Kṛṣṇa when He goes to the forest during the day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the &lt;em&gt;gopīs’&lt;/em&gt; mood of separation from Śrī Kṛṣṇa becomes ever more intense, His names, forms, qualities and pastimes begin spontaneously manifesting in their hearts. Thus they join together and sing as follows: “The beauty of Kṛṣṇa attracts the minds of all. When He stands in His threefold-bending way and plays upon His flute, the Siddhas’ wives, flying in the sky with their husbands, become attracted to Him and forget external reality. The bulls, cows and other animals in the pasture become stunned in ecstasy, and they stand so still, with the grass unchewed between their teeth, that they appear like figures in a drawing. Indeed, even the unconscious rivers stop flowing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Kṛṣṇa killed Ariṣṭāsura and how Kaṁsa reacted when he learned from Nārada that Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma were the sons of Vasudeva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The demon Ariṣṭa wanted to kill Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma, and thus he assumed the form of a huge bull with sharp horns. Everyone in Kṛṣṇa’s cowherd village became terrified when Ariṣṭāsura approached it, but the Lord pacified them, and when the bull demon charged Him He seized him by the horns and threw him about six yards. Though weakened, Ariṣṭa still wanted to attack Kṛṣṇa. Thus, dripping with sweat, he charged the Lord once again. This time Kṛṣṇa grabbed his horns, threw him to the ground and thrashed him like a pile of wet clothing. The demon vomited blood and gave up his life. Then Kṛṣṇa and Rāma, while being honored by the demigods and cowherd boys, returned to the village.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the killing of the horse demon, Keśī; Nārada’s glorification of Lord Kṛṣṇa’s future pastimes; and Kṛṣṇa’s killing of Vyomāsura.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On Kaṁsa’s order the Keśī demon assumed the form of a huge horse and went to Vraja. As he approached, his loud neighing terrified all the inhabitants, and they began looking for Śrī Kṛṣṇa. When He saw the demon, Kṛṣṇa came forward and challenged him to come near. Keśī charged Kṛṣṇa and tried to strike Him with his front legs, but the Lord seized them, whirled the demon around several times, and then threw him a distance of one hundred bow-lengths. Keśī remained unconscious for some time. When the demon regained consciousness, he furiously charged Kṛṣṇa again, his mouth agape. The Lord then thrust His left arm into the horse demon’s mouth, and as Keśī tried to bite the arm, it felt like a red-hot iron rod. Kṛṣṇa’s arm expanded more and more, finally choking the demon, and in extreme agony Keśī gave up his life. Lord Kṛṣṇa then removed His arm. He stood calmly, showing no pride at having killed the demon, as the demigods showered down flowers from the sky and glorified the Lord with prayers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes Akrūra’s trip from Mathurā to Vṛndāvana, his meditation on Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma along the way and the honor the two Lords showed Akrūra upon his arrival.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Early in the morning on the day after Kaṁsa had ordered him to bring Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma to Mathurā, Akrūra prepared his chariot and set off for Gokula. As he traveled, he thought as follows: “I am about to attain the great good fortune of seeing Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s lotus feet, which are worshiped by Brahmā, Rudra and the other demigods. Although Kaṁsa is an enemy of the Supreme Lord and His devotees, still, it is by Kaṁsa’s grace that I will get this great boon of seeing the Lord. When I first catch sight of His lotus feet, all my sinful reactions will be destroyed at once. I will descend from my chariot and fall at the feet of Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma, and even though I have been sent by Kaṁsa, the omniscient Śrī Kṛṣṇa will certainly harbor no animosity toward me.” As Akrūra thus thought to himself, he arrived in Gokula at sunset. Alighting from his chariot in the cowherd pasture, he began rolling about in the dust in great ecstasy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>३९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Akrūra informed Lord Kṛṣṇa and Lord Balarāma of Kaṁsa’s plans and his activities in Mathurā; what the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; cried out in distress when Kṛṣṇa left for Mathurā; and also the vision of Lord Viṣṇu’s abode that Akrūra saw within the water of the Yamunā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma offered Akrūra great respect and comfortably seated him on a couch, he felt that all the desires he had reflected on while traveling to Vṛndāvana were now fulfilled. After the evening meal, Kṛṣṇa asked Akrūra whether his trip had been peaceful and whether he was well. The Lord also inquired about how Kaṁsa was behaving toward their family members, and finally He asked why Akrūra had come.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates Akrūra’s prayers to the Supreme Personality of Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Akrūra prayed, “Brahmā, who created this visible world, emanated from the lotus navel of the Supreme Lord. The five elements of physical nature, the five corresponding objects of perception, the ten senses, the ego, the total nature, the primeval creator and the demigods all originate from His bodily limbs. He cannot be known by sensory knowledge, and thus even Brahmā and the other demigods are ignorant of His real identity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa entered the city of Mathurā, killed a washerman and bestowed benedictions upon a weaver and a garland-maker named Sudāmā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After showing His Viṣṇu form to Akrūra in the waters of the Yamunā and receiving Akrūra’s prayers, Lord Kṛṣṇa withdrew that vision just as an actor winds up his performance. Akrūra emerged from the water and in great amazement approached the Lord, who asked him whether he had seen something wonderful while bathing. Akrūra replied, “Whatever wonderful things there are in the realms of water, earth or sky, all have their existence within You. Thus when one has seen You, nothing remains unseen.” Akrūra then began driving the chariot again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the benediction Trivakrā received, the breaking of the sacrificial bow, the destruction of Kaṁsa’s soldiers, the inauspicious omens Kaṁsa saw and the festivities at the wrestling arena.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After leaving Sudāmā’s house, Lord Kṛṣṇa came upon Trivakrā, a young hunchbacked maidservant of Kaṁsa’s who was carrying a tray of fine ointments. The Lord asked her who she was and requested some ointment from her. Entranced by His beauty and joking words, Trivakrā gave both Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma a good deal of ointment. In return, Kṛṣṇa stepped on her toes with His lotus feet, took hold of her chin and lifted, thus straightening her spine. The now beautiful and charming Trivakrā then grabbed the edge of Kṛṣṇa’s upper cloth and asked Him to come to her house. Kṛṣṇa replied that after He had taken care of some business He would certainly come and relieve her mental torment. Then the two Lords continued Their sightseeing tour of Mathurā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter tells how Lord Kṛṣṇa killed the lordly elephant Kuvalayāpīḍa, how Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma entered the wrestling arena and what Kṛṣṇa said to the wrestler Cāṇūra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After finishing Their early-morning rituals, Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma heard kettledrums heralding the start of the wrestling match, and They went to see the festivities. At the gate of the wrestling arena They encountered an elephant named Kuvalayāpīḍa, who attacked Kṛṣṇa at the urging of his keeper. The mighty elephant grabbed at Kṛṣṇa with his trunk, but the Lord struck back and then disappeared from the beast’s sight among his legs. Enraged at not being able to see Kṛṣṇa, Kuvalayāpīḍa sought Him out with his sense of smell and seized Him. But the Lord pulled loose. In this way Kṛṣṇa teased and tormented Kuvalayāpīḍa, finally yanking out one of his tusks and beating him and his keepers to death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter tells how Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma killed the wrestlers, how Kṛṣṇa killed Kaṁsa and consoled Kaṁsa’s wives, and how the two Lords were reunited with Their mother and father.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Deciding to wrestle, Lord Kṛṣṇa faced off against Cāṇūra, and Lord Baladeva took on Muṣṭika. Battling arm to arm, head to head, knee to knee and chest to chest, the opponents attacked each other so fiercely that they appeared to be harming even their own bodies. The ladies in the arena, seeing the violent battle, began to condemn the King and all the members of the assembly: “A respectable audience should never have allowed a wrestling match between such huge wrestlers, whose limbs are as tough as lightning bolts, and such tender young boys, who are just entering youth. An intelligent person should never enter an assembly if he sees injustice being done there.” Because Vasudeva and Devakī did not fully understand the power of Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma, they became extremely unhappy when they heard the women of the audience speak these words.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa consoled Devakī, Vasudeva and Nanda Mahārāja and installed Ugrasena as king. It also relates how Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma completed Their education, retrieved the dead son of Their &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt; and then returned home.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Noting that His parents — Vasudeva and Devakī — had realized His true position as God, Śrī Kṛṣṇa expanded His Yogamāyā to again make them think of Him as their dear child. Then, with Lord Balarāma, Kṛṣṇa approached them and said how unhappy He was that He and they had been unable to enjoy the mutual satisfaction of parents and children who live together. Then He stated, “Even in a lifetime of one hundred years, no son can ever repay the debt he owes his parents, from whom he receives his very body. Any capable son who fails to support his parents will be forced, in the hereafter, to eat his own flesh. Indeed, any person who does not maintain and nourish those under his care — children, wife, spiritual masters, &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas,&lt;/em&gt; elderly parents, and so on — is simply a living corpse. It was out of fear of Kaṁsa that We could not serve you, so now please forgive Us.” Vasudeva and Devakī, overcome with emotion upon hearing these words of Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s, embraced their two sons and in ecstasy shed a torrent of tears.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Śrī Kṛṣṇa sent Uddhava to Vraja to relieve the distress of Nanda, Yaśodā and the young &lt;em&gt;gopīs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day Lord Kṛṣṇa asked His intimate friend Uddhava to take news of Him to Vraja and thus relieve His parents and the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; of their misery caused by their separation from Him. Riding on a chariot, Uddhava reached Vraja at sunset. He saw the cows returning home to the cowherd village and the calves jumping here and there as their mothers followed slowly behind, weighed down by their heavy milk bags. The cowherd men and women were chanting the glories of Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma, and the village was attractively decorated with burning incense and rows of lamps. All this presented a scene of exceptional transcendental beauty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Uddhava, on the order of Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, delivered the Lord’s message to the &lt;em&gt;gopīs,&lt;/em&gt; consoled them and then returned to Mathurā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the young maidens of Vraja saw lotus-eyed Uddhava, who wore a yellow garment and attractive earrings, they were astonished at how much he resembled Kṛṣṇa. Thinking “Who is this?” they approached and encircled him. When they realized that Kṛṣṇa must have sent him, they brought him to a secluded place where he could speak to them confidentially.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa first visits Trivakrā (also known as Kubjā) and enjoys with her, and then He visits Akrūra. The Lord sends Akrūra to Hastināpura to satisfy the Pāṇḍavas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Uddhava had related to Śrī Kṛṣṇa the news of Vraja, the Lord went to the home of Trivakrā, which was decorated with diverse ornamentation conducive to sexual enjoyment. Trivakrā welcomed Kṛṣṇa with great respect, giving Him a raised seat and, together with her female companions, worshiping Him. She also offered Uddhava a seat, as befitted his position, but Uddhava simply touched the seat and sat on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>४९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Akrūra went to Hastināpura, saw Dhṛtarāṣṭra’s unfair behavior toward his nephews, the Pāṇḍavas, and then returned to Mathurā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the order of Lord Kṛṣṇa, Akrūra went to Hastināpura, where he met the Kauravas and Pāṇḍavas and then set about to find out how Dhṛtarāṣṭra was treating the latter. This task would keep Akrūra in Hastināpura for several months.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vidura and Kuntīdevī described to Akrūra in detail how Dhṛtarāṣṭra’s sons, envious of the exalted qualities of the Pāṇḍavas, had tried to destroy them by various evil means and were contemplating further atrocities. With tearful eyes, Kuntīdevī asked Akrūra, “Do my parents and other relatives, headed by Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma, ever think of me and my sons, and will Kṛṣṇa ever come to console us in our distress?” Then Kuntīdevī began to chant Lord Kṛṣṇa’s names for her protection, and she also chanted &lt;em&gt;mantras&lt;/em&gt; expressing surrender to Him. Akrūra assured Kuntīdevī, “Since your sons were born from demigods like Dharma and Vāyu, there is no reason to expect that any misfortune will befall them; rather, you should be confident that very soon they will receive the greatest possible good fortune.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Kṛṣṇa defeated Jarāsandha seventeen times in battle and then constructed the city of Dvārakā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Kaṁsa was killed, his two queens, Asti and Prāpti, went to the home of their father, Jarāsandha, and sorrowfully described to him how Kṛṣṇa had made them widows. Upon hearing this account, King Jarāsandha became angry. He vowed to rid the earth of all the Yādavas, and he gathered an immense army to lay siege to Mathurā. When Śrī Kṛṣṇa saw Jarāsandha attacking, the Lord considered the reasons for His descent to this world and then decided to destroy Jarāsandha’s army, which was a burden to the earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa caused Mucukunda to kill Kālayavana with his harsh glance, and it also relates the conversation between Mucukunda and Lord Kṛṣṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After placing His family members safely within the Dvārakā fortress, Śrī Kṛṣṇa went out of Mathurā. He appeared like the rising moon. Kālayavana saw that Kṛṣṇa’s brilliantly effulgent body matched Nārada’s description of the Lord, and thus the Yavana knew He was the Personality of Godhead. Seeing that the Lord carried no weapons, Kālayavana put his own weapons aside and ran toward Him from behind, wanting to fight with Him. Śrī Kṛṣṇa ran from the Yavana, staying just barely beyond Kālayavana’s grasp at every step and eventually leading him a long distance toward a mountain cave. As Kālayavana ran, he hurled insults at the Lord, but he could not grasp Him, since his stock of impious &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; was not yet depleted. Śrī Kṛṣṇa entered the cave, whereupon Kālayavana followed after Him and saw a man lying on the ground. Taking him for Śrī Kṛṣṇa, Kālayavana kicked him. The man had been sleeping for a very long time, and now, having been violently awakened, he looked around angrily in all directions and saw Kālayavana. The man stared harshly at him, igniting a fire in Kālayavana’s body and in a moment burning him to ashes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Balarāma and Lord Kṛṣṇa, running as if in fear, went to Dvārakā. Then Lord Kṛṣṇa heard the message of Rukmiṇī from the mouth of a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; and chose her as His wife.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;King Mucukunda, shown mercy by Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, offered obeisances and circumambulated Him. The King then left the cave and saw that humans, animals, trees and plants were all smaller than when he had fallen asleep. From this he could understand that the Age of Kali was at hand. Thus, in a mood of detachment from all material association, the King began worshiping the Supreme Lord, Śrī Hari.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/53/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/53/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa arrived in Kuṇḍina, the capital of Vidarbha, and kidnapped Rukmiṇī in the presence of powerful enemies.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Lord Kṛṣṇa had heard the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; messenger recite Rukmiṇī’s letter, the Lord said to him, “I am indeed attracted to Rukmiṇī, and I know of her brother Rukmī’s opposition to My marrying her. Therefore I must kidnap her after crushing all the low-class kings, just as one might generate fire from wood by friction.” Since the solemnizing of vows between Rukmiṇī and Śiśupāla was scheduled to occur in only three days, Lord Kṛṣṇa had Dāruka ready His chariot at once. Then He immediately set out for Vidarbha, which He reached after one night’s travel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa defeated the opposing kings after kidnapping Rukmiṇī, disfigured Rukmiṇī’s brother Rukmī, brought Rukmiṇī to His capital and married her.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As Śrī Kṛṣṇa was taking Princess Rukmiṇī away, the inimical kings gathered their armies and pursued Him. Lord Baladeva and the generals of the Yādava army turned to face these opponents, blocking their advance. The enemy armies then began pouring incessant showers of arrows upon Lord Kṛṣṇa’s army. Seeing her husband-to-be’s forces under such violent attack, Śrīmatī Rukmiṇī looked at Śrī Kṛṣṇa fearfully. But Kṛṣṇa simply smiled and told her there was nothing to fear because His army would surely destroy the enemy in short order.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/55/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/55/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter tells how Pradyumna was born as the son of Lord Kṛṣṇa and then kidnapped by the demon Śambara. It also describes how Pradyumna killed Śambara and returned home with a wife.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Kāmadeva (Cupid), an expansion of Lord Vāsudeva, had been burned to ashes by Lord Śiva’s anger and was reborn as part and parcel of Pradyumna from the womb of Rukmiṇī. A demon named Śambara, thinking Pradyumna his enemy, kidnapped Him from the maternity room even before He was ten days old. Śambara threw Pradyumna into the ocean and returned to his kingdom. A powerful fish swallowed Pradyumna and was caught by fishermen in a net. They presented the huge fish to Śambara, and when his cooks cut it open they found a child within its belly. The cooks gave the infant to the maidservant Māyāvatī, who was astonished to see Him. Just then Nārada Muni appeared and told her who the infant was. Māyāvatī was actually Kāmadeva’s wife, Ratidevī. While waiting for her husband to be reborn in a new body, she had taken employment as a cook in the household of Śambara. Now that she understood who the infant was, she began to feel intense affection for Him. After a very short time, Pradyumna grew to youthful maturity, entrancing all the women with His beauty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/56/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/56/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa recovered the Syamantaka jewel to allay false accusations against Him and married the daughters of Jāmbavān and Satrājit. By enacting the pastime involving the Syamantaka jewel, the Lord demonstrated the futility of material wealth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Śukadeva Gosvāmī mentioned that King Satrājit offended Lord Kṛṣṇa on account of the Syamantaka jewel, King Parīkṣit became curious to hear the details of this incident. Thus Śukadeva Gosvāmī narrated the story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/57/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/57/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa, after the murder of Satrājit, killed Śatadhanvā and had Akrūra bring the Syamantaka jewel back to Dvārakā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa heard that the Pāṇḍavas had supposedly been burned to death in the palace of lac, He went to Hastināpura with Lord Baladeva to maintain the principles of worldly protocol, even though, being omniscient, He knew the report was false. With Kṛṣṇa out of Dvārakā, Akrūra and Kṛtavarmā incited Śatadhanvā to steal the Syamantaka jewel from Satrājit. Bewildered by their words, the sinful Śatadhanvā murdered King Satrājit in his sleep and stole the gem. Queen Satyabhāmā was overcome with grief at the death of her father, and she rushed to Hastināpura to report the sorrowful news to Śrī Kṛṣṇa. Together with Lord Baladeva, Kṛṣṇa then returned to Dvārakā to kill Śatadhanvā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/58/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/58/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa married five brides, beginning with Kālindī, and went to Indraprastha to visit the Pāṇḍavas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After the Pāṇḍavas had completed their incognito exile, Lord Kṛṣṇa went with Sātyaki and other Yadus to see them in Indraprastha. The Pāṇḍavas greeted the Lord and embraced Him in great ecstasy. Their new bride, Draupadī, shyly approached Kṛṣṇa and bowed down to Him. Then the Pāṇḍavas properly worshiped and welcomed Sātyaki and the Lord’s other companions, offering them sitting places.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>५९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/59/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/59/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter tells how Lord Kṛṣṇa killed Narakāsura, the son of the earth-goddess, and married the thousands of maidens the demon had kidnapped. It also describes how the Lord stole the &lt;em&gt;pārijāta&lt;/em&gt; tree from heaven and how He behaved like an ordinary householder in each of His palaces.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Narakāsura stole Lord Varuṇa’s umbrella, mother Aditi’s earrings, and the playground of the demigods known as Maṇi-parvata, Indra went to Dvārakā and described the demon’s transgressions to Lord Kṛṣṇa. Together with Queen Satyabhāmā, the Lord mounted His carrier Garuḍa and traveled to the capital of Narakāsura’s kingdom. On a field outside the city He decapitated the demon Mura with His disc. Then He fought Mura’s seven sons and sent them all to the abode of death, after which Narakāsura himself entered the battlefield on the back of an elephant. Naraka threw his &lt;em&gt;śakti&lt;/em&gt; lance at Śrī Kṛṣṇa, but the weapon proved ineffective, and the Lord cut the demon’s entire army to pieces. Finally, with His sharp-edged disc Kṛṣṇa cut off Narakāsura’s head.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/60/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/60/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa provoked anger in Queen Rukmiṇī with joking words and then consoled her, thus demonstrating the opulence of a lovers’ quarrel.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day Lord Kṛṣṇa sat at ease in Queen Rukmiṇī’s bedroom while she and her maidservants attended to Him in various ways. Rukmiṇī always responded to Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s moods, whatever they might be. On this occasion the Lord looked at Rukmiṇī, whose beauty was faultless, and began to tease her: “Previously many wealthy kings, worthy of you in their appearance and character, wanted to marry you. In fact, your father and brother intended to give you in marriage to Śiśupāla. Why, then, did you accept such an unsuitable husband as Me, who once renounced My kingdom and fled to the sea in fear of Jarāsandha? Besides, I transgress worldly morality, and because I own nothing I am dear to other paupers. Certainly the well-to-do would not worship one such as Me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/61/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/61/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter lists Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s sons, grandsons and other progeny. It also describes how Lord Balarāma killed Rukmī at Aniruddha’s marriage ceremony and how Lord Kṛṣṇa arranged for His sons and daughters to be married.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Not understanding the full truth about Śrī Kṛṣṇa, each of His wives thought that since He remained constantly in her palace she must be His favorite wife. They were all entranced by the Lord’s beauty and His loving conversations with them, but they could not agitate His mind with the charming gestures of their eyebrows or by any other means. Having attained as their husband Lord Kṛṣṇa, whom even demigods like Brahmā find it difficult to know in truth, the Lord’s queens were always eager to associate with Him. Thus, although each of them had hundreds of maidservants, they would personally render Him menial service.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/62/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/62/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter recounts the meeting of Aniruddha and Ūṣā, and also Aniruddha’s battle with Bāṇāsura.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Of the one hundred sons of King Bali, the oldest was Bāṇāsura. He was a great devotee of Lord Śiva, who favored Bāṇa so much that even demigods like Indra would serve him. Bāṇāsura once satisfied Śiva by playing musical instruments with his one thousand hands while Śiva danced his &lt;em&gt;tāṇḍava-nṛtya.&lt;/em&gt; In response, Śiva offered Bāṇa whatever benediction he chose, and Bāṇa asked Śiva to become the guardian of his city.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/63/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/63/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the battle between Lord Kṛṣṇa and Lord Śiva, as well as Śiva’s glorification of Kṛṣṇa after the Lord had cut off Bāṇāsura’s arms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Aniruddha did not return from Śoṇitapura, His family and friends passed the four months of the rainy season in extreme distress. When they finally heard from Nārada Muni how Aniruddha had been captured, a large army of the best Yādava warriors, under Kṛṣṇa’s protection, set off for Bāṇāsura’s capital and laid siege to it. Bāṇāsura fiercely opposed them with his own army of equal size. To help Bāṇāsura, Lord Śiva, accompanied by Kārtikeya and a horde of mystic sages, took up arms against Balarāma and Kṛṣṇa. Bāṇa began fighting against Sātyaki, and Bāṇa’s son fought against Sāmba. All the demigods assembled in the sky to witness the battle. With His arrows Lord Kṛṣṇa harassed the followers of Lord Śiva, and by putting Lord Śiva into a state of confusion He was able to destroy Bāṇāsura’s army. Kārtikeya was so strongly beaten by Pradyumna that he fled the battlefield, while the remnants of Bāṇāsura’s army, harried by the blows of Lord Balarāma’s club, scattered in all directions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/64/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/64/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Śrī Kṛṣṇa released King Nṛga from a curse and instructed the royal order on the great danger of taking a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa’s&lt;/em&gt; property.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day Sāmba and other young boys of the Yādava dynasty went to the forest to play, and after playing for a long time they became very thirsty and began looking for water. Inside a dry well they found an amazing creature: a huge lizard resembling a hill. The boys felt sorry for it and tried to pull it out. But after several attempts with leather thongs and ropes, they saw that they would not be able to rescue the creature, and thus they went to Lord Kṛṣṇa and told Him what had happened. The Lord accompanied them to the well and, extending His left hand, easily lifted the lizard out. By the touch of Lord Kṛṣṇa’s hand the creature transformed at once into a demigod. Then Lord Kṛṣṇa asked, “Who are you, and how did you assume such a lowly form?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/65/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/65/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Balarāma went to Gokula, enjoyed the company of the cowherd girls and dragged the Yamunā River.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day Lord Balarāma went to Gokula to see His relatives and friends. When He arrived there, the elder &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; and Lord Kṛṣṇa’s parents, Nanda and Yaśodā, who had all been in great anxiety for a long time, embraced Him and blessed Him. Lord Balarāma offered appropriate respects and greetings to each of His worshipable elders according to age, friendship and family relation. After Gokula’s residents and Lord Balarāma had inquired about each other’s welfare, the Lord rested from His journey.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/66/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/66/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Kṛṣṇa went to Kāśī (present-day Benares) and killed Pauṇḍraka and Kāśirāja, and how the Lord’s Sudarśana disc defeated a demon, incinerated the city of Kāśī and killed Sudakṣiṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While Lord Baladeva was visiting Vraja, King Pauṇḍraka of Karūṣa, encouraged by fools, announced that he was the real Vāsudeva. Thus he challenged Lord Kṛṣṇa with the following message: “Since I alone am the true Personality of Godhead, You should give up Your false claim to this position, as well as my divine symbols, and take shelter of me. If You do not, then prepare for battle.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/67/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/67/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Baladeva enjoyed the company of the young girls of Vraja on Raivataka Mountain and killed the ape Dvivida there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Narakāsura, a demon whom Lord Kṛṣṇa killed, had a friend named Dvivida, an ape. Dvivida wanted to avenge the death of his friend, so he set fire to the homes of the cowherds, devastated Lord Kṛṣṇa’s province of Ānarta and flooded coastal lands by churning the ocean’s water with his mighty arms. The rascal then tore down the trees in the &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt; of great sages and even passed stool and urine on their sacrificial fires. He kidnapped men and women and imprisoned them in mountain caves, which he sealed off with boulders. After thus disrupting the entire land and polluting many young women of respectable families, Dvivida came upon Raivataka Mountain, where he found Lord Baladeva enjoying in the company of a bevy of attractive women. Ignoring Lord Baladeva, who was apparently intoxicated from drinking &lt;em&gt;vāruṇī&lt;/em&gt; liquor, Dvivida displayed his anus to the women right in front of the Lord and further insulted them by making crude gestures with his eyebrows and passing stool and urine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/68/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/68/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the Kauravas captured Sāmba and how Lord Baladeva dragged the city of Hastināpura to secure his release.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sāmba, the darling son of Jāmbavatī, kidnapped Duryodhana’s daughter Lakṣmaṇā from her &lt;em&gt;svayaṁvara&lt;/em&gt; assembly. In response, the Kauravas joined forces to arrest him. After Sāmba held them off single-handedly for some time, six warriors of the Kaurava party deprived him of his chariot, broke his bow to pieces, seized him, tied him up and brought both him and Lakṣmaṇā back to Hastināpura.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>६९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/69/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/69/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Nārada Muni was amazed to see the household pastimes of Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, and how he offered prayers to the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After killing the demon Naraka, Lord Kṛṣṇa had simultaneously married sixteen thousand maidens, and sage Nārada wanted to observe the Lord’s diverse activities in this unique family situation. Thus he went to Dvārakā. Nārada entered one of the sixteen thousand palaces and saw Goddess Rukmiṇī personally rendering menial service to Śrī Kṛṣṇa, despite her being in the company of thousands of maidservants. As soon as Lord Kṛṣṇa noticed Nārada, He got up from His bed, offered obeisances to the sage and seated him on His own seat. Then the Lord bathed Nārada’s feet and sprinkled the water on His own head. Such was the exemplary behavior of the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/70/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/70/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa’s daily activities and two proposals placed before Him — one by a messenger from Dvārakā and another by the sage Nārada.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the early hours of the morning, Lord Kṛṣṇa would rise from bed and bathe Himself in clear water. After executing the dawn rituals and other religious duties, He would offer oblations into the sacred fire, chant the Gāyatrī &lt;em&gt;mantra,&lt;/em&gt; worship and pay tribute to the demigods, sages and forefathers, and offer respects to learned &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas.&lt;/em&gt; Then He would touch auspicious substances, decorate Himself with celestial ornaments and gratify His subjects by giving them whatever they desired.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/71/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/71/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Kṛṣṇa followed Uddhava’s advice and went to Indraprastha, where the Pāṇḍavas celebrated His arrival with great festivity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Wise Uddhava, knowing Lord Kṛṣṇa’s inner desire, advised the Lord as follows: “By conquering all directions and then performing the Rājasūya sacrifice, King Yudhiṣṭhira will fulfill all his purposes — defeating Jarāsandha, protecting those who have taken shelter of You, and executing the Rājasūya-yajña. Thus the Yādavas’ powerful enemy will be destroyed and the imprisoned kings freed, and both deeds will glorify You.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/72/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/72/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa heard King Yudhiṣṭhira’s request and then arranged for Bhīmasena to defeat Jarāsandha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One day King Yudhiṣṭhira addressed Lord Kṛṣṇa as He sat in the royal assembly: “My Lord, I wish to perform the Rājasūya sacrifice. In this sacrifice people uninterested in Your devotional service will be able to see firsthand the superiority of Your devotees and the inferiority of nondevotees. They will also be able to see Your lotus feet.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/73/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/73/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, after freeing the kings imprisoned by Jarāsandha, mercifully gave them His audience and bestowed royal gifts upon them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Lord Kṛṣṇa freed the 20,800 kings Jarāsandha had imprisoned, they immediately fell to the ground to pay Him obeisances. Then they stood with joined palms and began to pray to Him. Seeing their imprisonment as an act of mercy by the Lord to smash their false pride, the kings prayed only to be granted whatever would facilitate their perpetual remembrance of His lotus feet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/74/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/74/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa received the honor of first worship during the Rājasūya sacrifice, and how He killed Śiśupāla.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After glorifying Lord Kṛṣṇa, King Yudhiṣṭhira selected qualified &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; such as Bharadvāja, Gautama and Vasiṣṭha to serve as the priests of the Rājasūya sacrifice. Then many exalted guests of all the four social orders arrived to see the sacrificial performance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As the sacrifice proceeded, the ritual of “first worship” had to be performed, and the members of the assembly were called upon to decide who would receive this honor. Sahadeva spoke up: “Śrī Kṛṣṇa, the Supreme Lord, is indeed the most exalted person, for He Himself comprises all the deities worshiped by Vedic sacrifice. In His role as the Supersoul in the heart, He arranges for everyone in the universe to engage in his particular kind of work, and by His mercy alone human beings can perform various kinds of pious activities and receive the resultant benefits. One who worships Him worships all living entities. Surely Lord Kṛṣṇa should be worshiped first.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/75/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/75/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the glorious conclusion of the Rājasūya sacrifice, and how Prince Duryodhana was humiliated in King Yudhiṣṭhira’s palace.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the time of Mahārāja Yudhiṣṭhira’s Rājasūya sacrifice, many of his relatives and well-wishers endeavored to please him by performing necessary services. When the sacrifice was complete, the King adorned the priests, the exalted members of the assembly and his own relatives with fragrant sandalwood paste, flower garlands and fine clothing. Then they all went to the banks of the Ganges to perform the ritual bathing that marks the end of the sponsor’s period of initiation for the sacrifice. Before the final bathing, there was much sporting in the river among the male and female participants. Sprinkled with aromatic water and other liquids, Draupadī and the other ladies appeared most beautiful, their faces shining with bashful laughter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/76/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/76/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how the demon Śālva acquired a huge and terrifying airship, how he used it to attack the Vṛṣṇis in Dvārakā, and how Lord Pradyumna was taken from the battlefield during the fighting that ensued.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Śālva was one of the kings who had been defeated at the time of Rukmiṇī-devī’s marriage. Having vowed then that he would rid the earth of all the Yādavas, he began worshiping Lord Śiva each day by eating only a palmful of dust. After a year had passed, Śiva appeared before Śālva and asked him to choose a benediction. Śālva begged for a flying machine that could go anywhere and that would strike terror into the hearts of demigods, demons and humans alike. Lord Śiva granted this request and had Maya Dānava construct for Śālva a flying iron city named Saubha. Śālva took this vehicle to Dvārakā, where he and his huge army laid siege to the city. From his airplane Śālva bombarded Dvārakā with tree trunks, boulders and other missiles, and he produced a mighty whirlwind that obscured everything with dust.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/77/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/77/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa disposed of Śālva, the master of deception, and destroyed his airship Saubha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having been removed from the battlefield, Pradyumna was extremely ashamed, and He ordered His driver to take His chariot once again into the presence of Dyumān. As Pradyumna fought with Dyumān, other Yadu heroes like Gada, Sātyaki, and Sāmba began to create havoc among Śālva’s army. The battle continued in this way for twenty-seven days and nights.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/78/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/78/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Kṛṣṇa killed Dantavakra and Vidūratha, visited Vṛndāvana, and then returned to Dvārakā. It also describes how Lord Baladeva killed the offensive Romaharṣaṇa Sūta.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Intent upon avenging the death of his friend Śālva, Dantavakra appeared on the battlefield with club in hand. Lord Kṛṣṇa took up His own club and came before him. Dantavakra then insulted the Lord with harsh words and struck Him a terrific blow on the head. Without budging in the slightest, Lord Kṛṣṇa bludgeoned Dantavakra’s chest, shattering his heart. Dantavakra had a brother named Vidūratha, and he became distraught at Dantavakra’s death. Taking up his sword, Vidūratha confronted Śrī Kṛṣṇa, but the Lord cut off Vidūratha’s head with His Sudarśana disc. Lord Kṛṣṇa then visited Vṛndāvana for two months, and finally He returned to Dvārakā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>७९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/79/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/79/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Baladeva satisfied the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; by killing Balvala, bathed at various holy pilgrimage sites and attempted to dissuade Bhīmasena and Duryodhana from fighting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;At the sacrificial arena of the sages at Naimiṣāraṇya forest, a harsh wind began to blow on the new-moon day, spreading the obnoxious smell of pus and obscuring everything with dust. The demon Balvala then appeared there with a trident in his hand, his massive body pitch black and his face very frightening. Lord Baladeva caught the demon with His plow and then struck him a ferocious blow on the head with His club, killing him. The sages chanted Lord Baladeva’s glories and presented Him with lavish gifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/80/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/80/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Kṛṣṇa worshiped His &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; friend Sudāmā, who came to His palace seeking charity, and how the two of them discussed the pastimes they had shared while living at the home of their spiritual master, Sāndīpani Muni.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; Sudāmā, a personal friend of Lord Kṛṣṇa’s, was completely free of material desires. He maintained himself and his wife with whatever came of its own accord, and thus they were poverty-stricken. One day Sudāmā’s wife, unable to find any food to prepare for her husband, went to him and asked that he visit his friend Kṛṣṇa in Dvārakā and beg some charity. Sudāmā was reluctant, but when she persisted he agreed to go, reflecting that an opportunity to see the Lord was extremely auspicious. His wife begged a few handfuls of flattened rice as a gift for Śrī Kṛṣṇa, and Sudāmā set off for Dvārakā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/81/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/81/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa ate a morsel of the flat rice brought by His friend Sudāmā and bestowed upon him wealth greater than that of the King of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the course of His loving talks with His friend Sudāmā, Lord Kṛṣṇa said, “My dear &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa,&lt;/em&gt; have you brought any gift for Me from home? I regard as very significant even the smallest offering from My loving devotee.” But the poor &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; was ashamed to present Kṛṣṇa with his meager gift of flat rice. However, since Lord Kṛṣṇa is the Supersoul dwelling in all hearts, He knew why Sudāmā had come to visit Him. So He grabbed the bundle of flat rice Sudāmā was hiding and ate a handful of it with great pleasure. He was about to eat a second morsel when Rukmiṇī devī stopped Him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/82/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/82/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the Yādavas and many other kings met at Kurukṣetra during a solar eclipse and discussed topics concerning Lord Kṛṣṇa. It also relates how Kṛṣṇa met Nanda Mahārāja and the other residents of Vṛndāvana at Kurukṣetra and gave them great joy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hearing that a total eclipse of the sun was soon to occur, people from all over Bhārata-varṣa, including the Yādavas, converged at Kurukṣetra to earn special pious credit. After the Yadus had bathed and performed other obligatory rituals, they noticed that kings of Matsya, Uśīnara and other places had also come, as well as Nanda Mahārāja and the cowherd community of Vraja, who were always feeling the intense anxiety of separation from Kṛṣṇa. The Yādavas, overjoyed to see all these old friends, embraced them one by one as they shed tears of happiness. Their wives also embraced one another with great pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/83/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/83/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates a conversation between Draupadī and Lord Kṛṣṇa’s foremost queens, in which each of them describes how the Lord married her.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa returned from His meeting with the &lt;em&gt;gopīs&lt;/em&gt; and asked King Yudhiṣṭhira and His other relatives whether they were well. They replied, “My Lord, anyone who has just once imbibed through his ears the honey of Your pastimes can never know misfortune.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Then Draupadī inquired from Lord Kṛṣṇa’s wives how the Lord had come to marry them. Queen Rukmiṇī spoke first: “Many kings, headed by Jarāsandha, were intent on giving me in marriage to Śiśupāla. Thus at my wedding they all stood with bows in hand, ready to support Śiśupāla against any opponents. But Śrī Kṛṣṇa came and forcibly took me away, as a lion takes his prey from amidst goats and sheep.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/84/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/84/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the arrival of great sages at Kurukṣetra to observe the auspicious occasion of a solar eclipse, the sages’ glorification of Lord Kṛṣṇa, and Vasudeva’s enthusiastic performance of sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the occasion of a solar eclipse at Kurukṣetra, exalted ladies like Kuntī, Draupadī and Subhadrā got the chance to associate with Lord Kṛṣṇa’s queens. Seeing how much the Lord’s consorts loved their husband, the ladies were struck with wonder. As the women talked among themselves, and the men did likewise, great sages headed by Nārada and Vyāsadeva arrived there, desiring to see Lord Kṛṣṇa. The various kings and other leading personalities who were sitting at their leisure, including the Pāṇḍavas, Kṛṣṇa and Balarāma, stood up as soon as they saw the sages. The leaders all bowed down to the great souls, inquired about their well-being and worshiped them by offering them sitting places, water and so on. Lord Kṛṣṇa then said, “Now our lives are successful, for we have obtained the goal of life: the audience of great sages and &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt; masters, which even demigods only rarely obtain. The water at a holy place of pilgrimage and the deity forms of the gods can purify one only after a long time, but saintly sages purify just by being seen. Those who identify themselves with their bodies and neglect to honor transcendental sages like you are no better than asses.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/85/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/85/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter relates how Lord Kṛṣṇa imparted divine knowledge to His father and, along with Lord Balarāma, retrieved His mother’s dead sons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Having heard the visiting sages glorify Kṛṣṇa, Vasudeva ceased to regard Him and Balarāma as his sons and began praising Their omnipotence, omnipresence and omniscience as the Supreme Personality of Godhead. After glorifying his sons, Vasudeva fell at Lord Kṛṣṇa’s lotus feet and begged Him to drive away the conception that the Lord was his son. Instead, Lord Kṛṣṇa restored that conception by instructing Vasudeva in the science of Godhead, and upon hearing these instructions, Vasudeva became peaceful and free of doubt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/86/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/86/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Arjuna kidnapped Subhadrā and how Lord Kṛṣṇa went to Mithilā to bless His devotees Bahulāśva and Śrutadeva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When King Parīkṣit desired to learn about the marriage of his grandmother, Subhadrā-devī, Śrī Śukadeva Gosvāmī said, “While touring on pilgrimage, Arjuna heard that Lord Baladeva intended to give the hand of His sister Subhadrā to Duryodhana in marriage. Wanting to kidnap Subhadrā and marry her himself, Arjuna disguised himself as a renunciant and went to Dvārakā. So effective was the disguise that neither Balarāma nor any other resident of Dvārakā recognized him; rather, they all showed him the respect due a Vaiṣṇava mendicant. In this way the four months of the rainy season passed. One day Arjuna received an invitation to dine at Lord Balarāma’s home. There he caught sight of Subhadrā and was immediately overwhelmed with desire for her. Subhadrā also desired to have Arjuna as her husband, and thus she glanced back at him shyly. A few days later, Subhadrā left the palace to participate in a chariot festival. Taking this opportunity, Arjuna abducted Subhadrā and defeated the Yādavas who tried to stop him. Lord Balarāma was at first greatly angered to hear of this, but when Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa and other family members pacified Him, He became joyful and sent the bride and groom off with elaborate wedding gifts.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/87/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/87/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter presents the prayers by the personified &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; glorifying the personal and impersonal aspects of Lord Nārāyaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;King Parīkṣit asked Śrīla Śukadeva Gosvāmī how the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; can directly refer to the Supreme Absolute Truth, Brahman, since the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; deal with the material realm governed by the three modes of nature and Brahman is completely transcendental to these modes. In reply, Śukadeva Gosvāmī described an ancient encounter between Śrī Nārāyaṇa Ṛṣi and Nārada Muni at Badarikāśrama. Traveling to that sacred hermitage, Nārada found the Lord surrounded by exalted residents of the nearby village of Kalāpa. After bowing down to Nārāyaṇa Ṛṣi and His associates, Nārada submitted this same question to Him. In reply, Nārāyaṇa Ṛṣi related an account of how this very question had been discussed long ago among the great sages living on Janaloka. Once these sages, feeling inquisitive about the nature of the Absolute Truth, chose Sanandana Kumāra to speak on the subject. Sanandana told them how the numerous personified &lt;em&gt;Vedas,&lt;/em&gt; appearing as the first emanations from the breathing of Lord Nārāyaṇa, recited prayers for His glorification just before the creation. Sanandana then proceeded to recite these elaborate prayers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/88/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/88/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how it is that the devotees of Viṣṇu obtain liberation, while the devotees of other deities obtain material opulences.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Viṣṇu possesses all opulences, while Lord Śiva lives in poverty. Yet the devotees of Viṣṇu are generally poverty-stricken, while Śiva’s attain abundant wealth. When Mahārāja Parīkṣit asked Śukadeva Gosvāmī to explain this puzzling fact, the sage replied as follows: “Lord Śiva manifests as false ego in three varieties, according to the three modes of nature. From this false ego arise the five physical elements and the other transformations of material nature, totaling sixteen. When a devotee of Lord Śiva worships his manifestation in any of these elements, the devotee obtains all sorts of corresponding enjoyable opulences. But because Lord Śrī Hari is transcendental to the modes of material nature, His devotees also become transcendental.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>८९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/89/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/89/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Bhṛgu Muni proved the supremacy of Lord Viṣṇu, and how Lord Kṛṣṇa and Arjuna recovered the dead sons of an aggrieved &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; in Dvārakā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Once, long ago, on the shore of the river Sarasvatī, a discussion arose among a group of sages as to which of the three chief lords — Brahmā, Viṣṇu or Śiva — is the greatest. They deputed Bhṛgu Muni to investigate the matter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>९०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/90/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/90/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINETY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Kṛṣṇa enjoyed with His queens in the lakes of Dvārakā. It also relates the queens’ ecstatic prayers in the mood of intense separation from Him, and summarizes the Lord’s pastimes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa continued to reside in His opulent capital of Dvārakā, together with the Yadus and His queens. He would enjoy sporting with His wives in the ponds on the palace grounds, squirting water on them with a syringe and being squirted in turn. With His graceful gestures, loving words and sidelong glances, He would enchant their hearts. In this way the queens would become totally absorbed in thoughts of Him. Sometimes, after playing with the Lord in the water, they would address various creatures — &lt;em&gt;kurarī&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cakravāka&lt;/em&gt; birds, the ocean, the moon, a cloud, a cuckoo, a mountain, a river and so on — declaring their great attachment to Śrī Kṛṣṇa on the pretext of commiserating with these creatures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>९१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/91/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/10/91/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-ten&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eleven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twelve&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fourteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventeen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nineteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
