<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 LOCATION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/01_LOCATION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/01_LOCATION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-I&#xA;LOCATION AND PHYSICAL FEATURES&#xA;According to the author, Dr. K. V. Raman, Attiyur was the name of the locality where the Temple of Varadaraja is situated and this place did not originally form part of Kanchi. This requires a careful scrutiny.&#xA;Kanchi is the name of the town which covers a wide area including the region where our Lord Varadaraja&amp;rsquo;s Temple is situated. The Sanskrit works refer to the town by this name as noticed in the Puranas like Brahmanda. The name Kanchi occurs in all works written in Tamil. The name Kacchippedu also occurs which according to some scholars, should have meant only suburbs of the ancient town, Kacchi&amp;rsquo;. The Temples of Tiruvehka, Uragam and of Ekamreswara are stated to have been situated in Kacchippedu2. The palace of the Chola Kings is (and not within the town)3 said to have been here.&#xA;The compositions of the Alwars specifically mention the name Kacchi, with reference to many of these Temples and also refer to some of the Temples as lying within the town surrounded by ramparts5. None of these temples are said to lie in Kacchippedu. The Inscriptions&amp;quot; which are dated in the tenth century, A.D are cited to show that some of these temples lie in Kacchippedu, but the Alwars who, according to the author, lived between 650 and 850 A.D 6a, do not use this name with reference to any temple whatsoever. The inscriptions serve only as links in history and cannot by themselves serve to play the role of history itself.&#xA;Besides, the Tamil classic Perumpanarruppadai states that the ramparts of Kacchi lie beyond the Tiruvehka Temple Veltu kkai which must have been to the south of Tiruvehka, is stated- in the Periya Tirumadal to lie within the ramparts of Kacchi 8. The town of Kacchi is however held on the strength of evidence available from Tamil literature, to have ben located to the north of Tiruvehka.&amp;quot;&#xA;43&#xA;The word &amp;lsquo;Pedu&amp;rsquo; shall mean a suburb but when it occurs with the word Kacchi, must mean related to Kacchi. Otherwise &amp;lsquo;Pedu&amp;rsquo; could have been used with the name of any other town. what was &amp;lsquo;Pedu&amp;rsquo;, according to inscriptions, must mean the area of the same region, lying outside the city proper wherefrom administrtion was carried on.&#xA;In all probability, the distinction could have been made for administrative purposes. Hence, Kacchi and Kacchippedu must be taken to refer to the same town Kacchi, Pedu&amp;rsquo; referring to the divisions of the town. Otherwise, the references in the composi- tions of the Alwars could not have adequate explanation.&#xA;From the inscriptions, it is clear that Kacchippedu was a town in the taluk or district of Eyilkottam, lying in the kingdom of Jayankondan These inscriptions date from 1118 to 1268 A.D.10 Inscriptions of the subsequent periods refer to the town as lying in the taluk of Uttukkadu, sometimes mentioning the kingdom as Chandragiri. Such inscriptions are more than thirtyfive. Beginning with the inscription dated 1128, the Temple of Varadaraja is stated as that of Arulalar in Tiruvatti- yur&amp;quot;. The Temple is called Perumal Kovil12. That the name of the Deity is also Varadaraja is made clear in one inscription where the words Varamtharum Perumal13 are used. The locality Tiruvattiyur must have become reputed as having been part of the town Kanchi before 1118 A.D. This must be conce- ded, since support is avilable for this from Yapparungalavritti of the 11th century A.D., which describes the town Kanchi as a peacok with Attiyur as its head and the splendid groves its plumage. The literary evidences which are thus available, show, beyond doubt, that even before 1100 A.D. Tiruvattiyur formed part of Kanchi. The name, Kacchippedu must not, therefore, be given too much importance particularly because this word occurs mainly in the inscriptions.&#xA;Vedanta Desika (1268-1399) refers to our Lord uniformly as Attigiri Tirumal&amp;rsquo;s and as Tiruvattiyurar. Much heat has been generated by the author on the use of the Tamil name Tiruvattiyur. One has to bear in mind that the name Kacchi is the Tamilised form of the Sanskrit word Kanchi, which&#xA;44&#xA;occurs as the name of this town not only in the Puranas but also in the ancient Sanskrit works17.&#xA;The suggestion made by the author that the locality of Tiruvehka could have been the eastern limit of Kanchi does not stand to reason. There are firstly the lingas lying to the east of the present Little Kanchipuram&amp;rsquo; which indicate that the town of Kanchi extended beyond the present limits in the east 18. Secondly, the Deity at Tiruvehka is stated in all sources&amp;rsquo; as having become a&#xA;having become a dam to the River Vegavati Why did the Deity serve as a dam? The answer cannot be given without reference to the Hastigirimahatmya detailing the Avatara of Lord Varadaraja on the Hastigiri, despite the author&amp;rsquo;s assertion that it &amp;ldquo;is an appeal to faith and not to reason&amp;rdquo;. So Tiruvattiyur should be as ancient as Tiruvehka. It will be improper to hold that Tiruvattiyur, a Temple not for off from Tiruvehka and intimately related to the latter, did not form part of Kanchi while the latter did.&#xA;The Alwars who were steeped in the concept of the Deity as available from the Vedic sources, framed their compositions following the literary traditions of Tamil literature and so used the name Kanchi. The name Kanchi is specifically applied in the Vaishnava tradition to the locality where our Lord&amp;rsquo;s Temple is situated. Yamuna paid a visit to this Temple and worshipped the Lord20. Tirukkacchi Nambi is also known as Kanchipura mainly because of his devoted service to the Lord of Kanchi2! During Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s time, this Temple became very much more reputed. In the &amp;ldquo;Kanchi Divyadesa Sangraha Slokamalika Manavalamamuni uses the word Kanchi to mean this Temple&#xA;alone.&#xA;Regarding the author&amp;rsquo;s observations on the absence of any specific references to this Temple in the compositions of the Alwars, it must be stated that Budattalwar has mentioned this Temple and its Lord22. Tirumangai Alwar calls this Deity as dark complexioned giver of boons and mentions Him in the same verse where he places the Lord of Tiruvehka before this Deity23. It is perhaps this mention of the two Deities together that inspired Vedantadesika to offer an identical depiction in45&#xA;his Vegasetustotra24. Although&#xA;Although there is no other direct reference to this Deity in the hymns of tha Alwars, it is not impossible to take the first century (Pratamasataka) of the Tiruvaaimozhi of Nammalwar as composed in praise of Varadaraja. The opening verse itself states that the Alwar worships and visualises our Lord (Amararkal Atipati) i.e. Devaraja, in his mind. Significantly the idol of Nammalwar in this Temple has its fingers in the right hand, closely in touch with his heart. Vedantadesika while summarizing in sanskrit the verses of Nammalwar, observes that the Alwar found Varada in the first century (first hundred verses) of the Tiruvaaimozhi, evidently meaning that Varadaraja (Amarakal Atipati) is being extolled in this century25.&#xA;It is perhaps the reference to Varadaraja in the Periya Tirumozhi26 that could be taken to support the incident which occured in the life of Tirumangai Alwar. The incident refers to this Alwar&amp;rsquo;s getting a vast sum of money from the spot in the river Vegavati where it was imbedded. He was able to locate it at the direction of Varadaraja Who appeared in his dream and gave him the location of this wealth.27&#xA;What is stated above regarding the greatness of our Lord Varadaraja as made out from or suggested by the compositions of the Alwars should convince anybody that the Alwars had sung the glory of this Lord. The objection to this position is made by some scholars on the ground, that apart from Butatalwar, others have not made a direct reference to this God and also that this Deity could not be taken to have received the glorification from Tirumangai Alwar who included Him in a decad solely devoted to Parmeswaravinnagaram28. It is needless to argue upon these lines. Either we have to admit that such indirect references should be recognised in liteary pieces of religious kind or totally deny to this Deity the reception of the homages from the Alwars. The latter position is taken up by some scholars who cite the sloka from the Varadarajapanchasat.29 The word &amp;ldquo;munisarvabaumah &amp;quot; occurring in this sloka is taken to refer to the Alwars. Some scholars do not agree to this interpretation also. Their stand is that the word &amp;ldquo;munisarvabaumah&amp;rdquo; could refer only to the&#xA;46&#xA;eminent sages and Devatas who were present at the time of our Lord&amp;rsquo;s Avatara out of the sacrificial fire, taking into consideration the context of the previous sloka. The second objection too is baseless, since the Alwars are found to have sung in one and the same verse, the glory of more than one Deity30. Besides, it is to be noted that more often the Alwars refer to the temples by the names of the locality specifically applicable to each, such as Attiyur, Tiruvenka, Patakam, Uragam, Tirutanka and not directly associating them with Kanchi.&#xA;While seeking to derive the word Attiyur, the author has made much of the word Atti, name of a tree out of which the Mulabera is admitted to have been made. Yet the name Attiyur is based on &amp;ldquo;Hastigiri&amp;rdquo; which word means a place where the Ashtadig-gajas (the elephants of the eight sides) worshipped the God, in the hoary past3 No ancient writer, particulary Vaishnava, chose to take the word &amp;ldquo;Atti&amp;rdquo; to have given rise to the name Attiyur. Andrapurna, also known as Vatukanambi, who was a direct disciple of Ramanuja, refers to our Lord as &amp;ldquo;Karisa32. This word means the Lord of the elephants and shall be taken to be similar to the word &amp;ldquo;Tiruvattiyurar&amp;rdquo;. It must be noted here that the names &amp;ldquo;Varanasailanata&amp;quot;33 Karigiripati &amp;ldquo;34&#xA;and others are also used besides Karisa36,&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Hastisaileswara &amp;ldquo;35 Hastisa37 and others.&#xA;In the sloka Kanchi Divyadesa sangraha slokamalika, Manavalamamuni refers to the shrine by&#xA;by the name &amp;ldquo;Karibudara” (“Karibhutara&amp;rdquo; is wrong). It is thus clear, that to connect the words atti and hasti and as the name of a wood to have been&#xA;wrong.&#xA;take the word atti changed to hasti is&#xA;As regards the author&amp;rsquo;s theory that the &amp;ldquo;Hastigiri&amp;rdquo; is an artificial mound and and not a hill, we have answered it in Chapter III showing that it is really a small natural hillock.&#xA;FOOT NOTES&#xA;CHAPTER I-PART II&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 POLITICAL BACKGROUND</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/02_POLITICAL_BACKGROUND/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/02_POLITICAL_BACKGROUND/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-II&#xA;POLITICAL BACKGROUND&#xA;In this Chapter Dr. K. V. Raman gives an elaborate description of the various dynasties which ruled over the south, after the Pallavas, especially with reference to Kanchi. In fairness to him it should be said that he has arranged to bring forth the history of South India in a chronological order, on the basis of the inscriptions found in the Temple of Sri Varadaraja as well as his own historical knowledge. Had it not been diluted with sectarian bias, this piece of research work could have brought him kudos. But, alas! in this treatise he has wasted his whole energy with attempts to establish a theory that this Temple is Tenkalai in character, through various flimsy and unreliable data. He has also referred to some records in the Tenkalai-Vadakalai litigation of the Temple and some books written by staunch leaders of the Tenkalai sect, whose litigant spirit and hostility to Vadakalais, are very well known. This is highly undesirable in a dissertation seeking a University Degree of the Doctor of Philosophy.&#xA;.&#xA;As far as the historical and inscriptional facts given here are concerned we can have no dispute with them as long as they do not contradict with each other and prove to be basically wrong. Thus we can skip over the details of the Cholas, Pandyas, Cheras, Hoysalas, Sambuvarayas, and even Vijayanagar Kings upto the portion where the author comes to deal with &amp;lsquo;Sadasiva&amp;rsquo; (AD 1542-1576), on page 30. But on page 32 the author says that Sadasiva was killed three years after 1567 by Tirumala&amp;rsquo;s son that is, in or about 1570. He also gives out that Tirumala and Sriranga ruled between 1570 and 1585. This confused chronicling needs clarity&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;1&#xA;In the appendix on the page 187, author himself gives the date of Venkata I as AD 1586-1614. Again on page 50, he says that Lakshmikumara Tatacharya was the manager of this Temple during the times of Vijayanagar King Venkata Į.&#xA;4&#xA;50&#xA;found in the Kanchi and &amp;ldquo;South Indian Shrines&amp;rdquo; by Dr. S. K. Aiyangar&amp;rsquo;s South Still the author mentions&#xA;This accords with the dates T.T.D. inscriptions and also P. V. Jagadisa Aiyer as well as Indian History and Gopinatha Rao.&amp;rsquo; him as Venkata II.&#xA;Page 334 Here, under &amp;ldquo;Venkata II (AD 1586-1614)&amp;rdquo; Dr. K. V. Raman concedes that inscriptions of &amp;ldquo;Venkata II &amp;quot; are found in Varadarajasway Temple, ranging from 1587-1605 AD. But he says &amp;ldquo;they are not of any particular importance&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Inscriptions Nos. 421, 381, 382, 419, 462, 475, 499, 531, 587, 649, 354, 650, 651 etc., of 1919 are some of them, thus brushed aside by the author as of no particular importance. These inscriptions give an account of the great service rendered by Sri Lakshmikumara Tatacharya who was styled as the &amp;lsquo;Srikaryadurandara&amp;rsquo; (Manager-General of Temple affairs), at Kanchi and other places. His services especially to our Temple during the reign of Venkatapati-deva-maharaya are glorified and praised, in a most telling manner, which if recognised cannot suit the purpose of the author. Hence his ignoring them as of &amp;ldquo;no particular importance.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Since the object of the author is to make out a case for the Tenkalai predominance in the Temple he has salvaged some flimsy information through 2 or 3 inscriptions2, out of the numerous inscriptions found in our Temple in which one Alagiya-Manavala Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s name finds a place. He is said to have gifted some properties to the Temple and is also styled as Koil-Kelvi (Superintendent) in one of the two inscriptions. Only this much and out of this, the author tries to build a theory that this Jiyar was responsible for almost all the Vijayanagar structures that are in existence in our Temple. There is no evidence whatsoevor to accept this theory. That he was rendering Srikaryam during the period of these two inscriptions does not indicate that he had the authority from the rulers of Vijayanagar for these constructions. Not even remotely can such a conjecture be made. On the other hand there is specific mention of these structures, which bear the emblem of Vijayanagara style, as having been executed by the Tatacharyas3 who were admittedly the royal preceptorsof&#xA;51&#xA;the Vijayanagar rulers and whose influence over them made it possible to achieve them,&#xA;That the members of the Srisailapurna family had the honour of having been the spiritual heads of Kings from the period of Devaraya and Virupaksha down to the last ruler in this line cannot be disputed. It is equally impossible to disprove to the growth and spread of Vaishnavism among the rulers of this line and in the region over which they had their sway. That the Tatacharyas were mainly responsible for this cannot be denied. The rulers of Vijayanagar had their interest aroused in the maintenance of Varadarajaswami Temple at Kanchi only by the Tatacharyas and not by any other religious teacher. The spiritual leader&#xA;spiritual leader of great distinction of the Tatacharya family should have been living then with the rulers.&#xA;Other members of the family must have been living at Kanchi and are not mentioned in the inscriptions. This is not a proof that they ceased to enjoy their rights to render service in the Temple. It is not unlikely that Alagiyamanavala Jiyar (C1550 A.D.) was then a person found fit for getting entrusted with the work of Srikaryam in the Temple. He must have been only an agent of Panchamatabanjanam Tatadesika whose absence from Kanchi was necessitated by his presence with the rulers for instruction and guidance in both religious and secular affairs. (Some inscriptions have called him as &amp;lsquo;Ettur Tirumala Kumara Tatacharya&amp;rsquo;). That the Jiyar was well versed in Ubayavedanta does speak highly of his attainments for being the head of a religious Math known after his name but this does not even suggest that he was the sole wielder of power in the administra- tion of the Temple. He was only an agent then.&#xA;The last portion of Chapter II deals with the concealing of the Utsavar idol of Sri Varadaraja at Udayarpalayam during the last decades of the 17th century and its restoration in or about 1711 A.D after the iconoclastic zeal of Aurangazeb was over. There can be no dispute over the secreting or restoration of the Idol or the dates given here. The complete omission of the presence or existence of the Tatacharya custodians of the Temple during this period and the assertion that one Attan Jiyar and his&#xA;52&#xA;disciple Todarmalla were alone in the picture and they them- selves caused the restoration without anybody&amp;rsquo;s prompting, is a point which we cannot accept as correct. We shall have occa- sion to deal with this aspect later in Chapter IV wherein also, the author has reiterated this version. Just to avoid repetition, we do not elaborate it here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 LAYOUT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/03_LAYOUT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/03_LAYOUT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-name-tondaradippodi-is-there-ever-since-this-second-enclosure-was-constructed-which-was-very-much-earlier-than-that-of-todarmal-simply-because-the-statue-of-todarmal-is-placed-near-the-tondaradippodi-its-name-cannot-be-twisted-as-todar--malpadi-as-the-author-would-like-to-have-it-the-statues-three-in-number-in-a-niche-next-to-tondaradippodi-vasal-are-not-also-that-of-todarmal-they-must-be-of-one-of-the-vijaya--nagar-kings-his-son-and-wife-most-probably-venkata-i&#34;&gt;CHAPTER-III&#xA;THE LAYOUT OF THE TEMPLE AND SEQUENCE OF CONSTRUCTION&#xA;In this chapter, the author, gives out at the outset that the purpose of this chapter is to decribe the general layout of the Vardarajaswami Temple and the disposition of the various shrines, mantapas and other structures therein. It is true he has described these items very minutely. But we can at the same time discern here an under-current of sectarian bias. Adnau- seam, he brings out the name of one Alagia Manavala Jiyar as the architect of the important constructions and structures of the Temple like the big rampart wall- Periyatirumadil, Gopura, Kalyana mantapa, the front porch of the Abhisheka Mantapa and the Ornamental Mantapa where both Lord Varada and Sri Perundevi are seated together on the same dias on the Maha- Navami Day. He concedes also that these were done in the 16th century by the patronage of the Vijayanagar Kings. These Vijayanagar Kings were the acknowledged disciples of the Tata- charyas. There is nothing on record to show that Alagiya Manavala Jiyar was the Guru of the Vijayanagar Kings nor the author himself claims such a position to this Jiyar. Whileso, we are unable to see the logic in asserting that this Jiyar did all these Kainkaryams in the sixteenth century. There is no inscriptional or historical basis for such an assertion.&#xA;In this context it is also relevant to note that while the words &amp;ldquo;Srimad Vedamarga&amp;rdquo; etc. occur before the name Ettur Tirumala Kumara Tatacharya in the inscriptions, these prefixes or &amp;ldquo;Birudus&amp;rdquo; and also &amp;ldquo;Paramahamsa Parivrajakacharya&amp;rdquo; are not used for Alagia Manavala Jiyar. He is simply mentioned as &amp;ldquo;Srikaryam Seyvar Alagia Manavala Jiyar&amp;rdquo;. If he has to be placed on a par with the Tatacharya, these prefixes would have certainly found a place in the inscriptions before his name. The pontiffs of the Ahobila Math are all mentioned with such prefixes, in the inscriptions, that are due to the ascetic order. This sig- nificant absence of the &amp;ldquo;birudus&amp;rdquo; to the Alagia Manavala Jiyar in the inscriptions do certainly indicate the difference in their&#xA;54&#xA;status and that he was only doing the Srikaryam service under the overall control of the Tatacharya who was the Manager- General (Srikarya-durandara) of Temple Affairs. (see also Chapter VI)&#xA;Another interesting point that is noteworthy here is that one Jana Mudaliar is also described as &amp;lsquo;Srikainkarya Durandara&amp;rsquo; in the inscriptions (Saka 1493-1571 A.D). By this, it can be seen that this title &amp;ldquo;Srikaryam Seyvar&amp;rdquo; alone cannot be made much of, unless augmented with other stronger factors of proof for establishing the position of a superior authority in the Temple&amp;rsquo;&#xA;On the other hand, it has been recognised by history and inscriptions found not only in the temples of Kanchi but also other places like Tirupati, that Sri Tatacharya and his venerable father, Panchamata-banjanam Tatacharya, his ancestors and their descendants were the Raja-gurus and responsible for the several constructions mentioned above, as well as so many other items like Bali-pitam, Vahanas, Jewels, Kavachas and Vimanas, through the bounteousness of their royal disciples the Vijayana- gar Kings Krishnadevaraya, Achyutaraya, Ramaraya, Sri Ranga, Venkatapatideva I, etc. The slokas which deal with some of the said Kainkaryas are inscribed in the Temple in stone, in several places2.&#xA;Another inscription deals with his services at Tirupati (Panipatigiri)3. Yet another one describes his kainkaryas not only at Kanchi but also in several other places like Srirangam, Kumbakonam, and Tirupati in his capacity as the most respected royal preceptor of the Karnataka Monarch3.&#xA;We shall have occasion to deal with this aspect in detail in the succeeding chapter. For the present, it is sufficient to point out that the author&amp;rsquo;s assertion in this chapter in-season and out of season that Alagia Manavala Jiyar, a Tenkalai Sanyasin, did, all these services has absolutely no basis. As pointed out earlier he might have acted on certain occasions as the &amp;ldquo;Koil Kelvi&amp;rdquo; or Superintendent under the control of Sri Tatacharya. One other thing also may be remembered. It was a time when no such animosity between Tenkalais and Vadakalais existed as we wit- ness nowadays. Even though the Jiyar was a Tenkalai who&#xA;155&#xA;hailed from Mysore and whose headquarters is still at Melkote in Mysore he could have come and camped at Kanchi to wor- ship the Lord during the 16th century. As an ardent Vaishnavite devotee he would have been only too glad to supervise these sacred works under the guidance of the Tatacharya, So there is nothing contradictory or surprising about the mention of this Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s name casually in some of the inscriptions. But the author maker a mountain out of a mole-hill. Let us now see the other aspects dealt with here which are also wrong in many respects.&#xA;Page 44: As Dr. K. V. Raman is not prepared to accept that the present Abode of the Lord is a Hill, he has purposely put inverted commas to the word, Hill. We may also equally stress that this is a small, natural hillock, now completely covered by construction. If it is an artifical mound as the author asserts, it could not have withstood the colossal structures upon it and Sri Narasimha&amp;rsquo;s shrine below it, would have crumbled by its weight. Despite his persistence about his theory in chapters III, IV, VII and VIII we can even now see the original features of the &amp;lsquo;rock&amp;rsquo; over the Garbagraha of Sri Narasimha&amp;rsquo;s shrine and on the wall of the twenty-four steps leading to Hastigiri.&#xA;The author has ignored to mention the Kacchivaaitan Mantapa in the north-east corner of the prakara in the Hill and also the figure of the lizard. The paintings in the ceiling depicting the Kalakshepagoshti of Nadadur Ammal with the figures of Sudarsanasuri, Atreya Ramanuja, Vedantadesika and others are completely ignored.&#xA;There is a small mantapa with a flight of ten steps leading to the twentyfour steps. This mantapa has on its top the figures of lion and not &amp;lsquo;garuda&amp;rsquo; as in every corner of the top of the walls of all prakaras. Likewise we can notice the figures of two lions on both sides of &amp;lsquo;garudas&amp;rsquo; on the corners of the outer-prakara (Periya Tirumadil)&#xA;Page 45: The author&amp;rsquo;s inference regarding the conse cration of Malayala Nacchiyar that &amp;lsquo;perhaps it was a result of the brief conquest of Kanchi by the Chera King Ravivarman&#xA;56&#xA;Kulasekara in A.D. 1316, etc.&amp;rsquo; is not in accordance with the tradition attached to it. The tradition is that a Malayala (Kerala) princess was enchanted by the Lord&amp;rsquo;s divine beauty and just like Goda (Andal) she vowed that if she would marry at all, she would marry only the Lord. Her royal father finding it difficult to change her heart, brought her with all riches, pomp and splendour to the Temple to offer her to Him: Just as the princess entered the doorway leading to the Dwarapalakas on the Hill, she disappeared and joined her Divine Husband. To illustrate this anecdote there is still a painting of the Malayala Nachiyar on the south wall next to the Dwarapalaka where her &amp;lsquo;andardyanam&amp;rsquo; (disappearance) is said to have taken place. Another version is that our Lord Varadaraja&amp;rsquo;s name is &amp;ldquo;GIRISAN&amp;rdquo; i.e. the Lord of the Giri or mountain (Hastigiri). Girisan in Tamil is &amp;lsquo;Malayalan&amp;rsquo; His Nachiyar or Consort is therefore called Malayala Nachiyar. For the purposes of celebrating the marriage or Kalyana festivals this Nachiyar was installed and consecrated by our forebears in a standing posture to suit the occasion. (Sri Perundevi Tayar is consecrated in a sitting posture). The important Panguni Uttra Kalyana Festival takes place to this Nachiyar and the Lord, in all grandeur even now, which may justify this version.&#xA;Page 46: The mention of Sri Alavandar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Historic Meeting&amp;rdquo; with Sri Ramanuja in the third prakara is not quite in consonance with our Guruparampara. It is true Sri Alavandar observed from a distance his future disciple (Sri Ramanuja) from this courtyard or &amp;lsquo;murram&amp;rsquo; when the latter was proceeding to worship Lord Varadaraja along with his teacher Yadava Prakasa. But Sri Yamunai Turaivar (Alavandar) stopped short without attempting to meet him This change in his idea was said to be that he (Sri Alavandar) wanted him (Sri Ramanuja) to complete his learning (of Purva paksha) under his advaita Guru Yadavaprakasa, without being disturbed in the middle, so that he might be able to tackle all the aspects later under his guidance. Therefore, he is said to have offered his benedictions to him from the distance with a prayer to the Lord of Hastigiri.*&#xA;57&#xA;With that he returned to Srirangam with the idea of sending for him later. The story proceeds that Sri Alavandar could not meet him before he reached the Lotus feet of the Lord and Sri Ramanuja who was hastening to offer his obeisance to him to Srirangam heard the news of his expiry even before he could reach Srirangam. It is said also that in his utter disappointment he returned to Kanchi after the cremation of Sri Alavandar and after taking a vow that he would fulfil the three aspirations of Sri Alavandar (Sri Bashya, Sahasranama Bashya and Bagavat Vishaya) which he learnt through his&#xA;disciples, even without worshipping Lord Ranganata5.&#xA;•&#xA;Page 47: Here starts again the author&amp;rsquo;s story of the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s performances. The item mentioned here is &amp;rsquo;the front porch with the balustraded stepped entrance&amp;rsquo; of the Abisheka Mantapa. He surmises that this &amp;lsquo;was probably constructed in the 16th century by one Alagiya Manavala Jiyar, etc.&amp;rsquo; As pointed out in the outset, of this chapter and accepted also by the author at the end of this chapter, the Vijayanagar rulers, were the ones, who had all these items constructed, during the 16th century, under the guidance of their Acharyas the Tatacharyas. The Jiyar was not their guru or inspirer. The royal dynasty of the Vijayanagar, had their inspiration only through their spiritual gurus, the TATACHARYAS. The author&amp;rsquo;s surmise is therefore, neither supported by history nor inscriptions. Since the author himself is not sure of his ground, he carefully puts it as,&#xA;was probably constructed&amp;hellip;..by the Jiyar&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;Page 49: The Mahanavami Mantapa has some inscriptions in its ceiling. We are not sure whether Dr. K. V. Raman has seen them or knows about them. Dr. K. V. Raman says this Mahanavami Mantapa was built by Alagia Manavala Jiyar. This is contrary to the tradition and inscriptions on the ceiling. This and the mantapa leading to Sri Tayar Shrine south of the Abisheka Mantapa are said to have been constructed by Sri Sankaracharya. His portraits are carved in the pillars of the leading Mantapa. The Madwas also lay claim to these portraits as that of their guru, Madwacharya. They are carved not only&#xA;58&#xA;in the pillars of the mantapa in front of Sri Tayar&amp;rsquo;s Shrine but also in the four pillared Mantapa, in the steps of the southern side of the Ananta Saras (Pushkarani or tank) which is called the Tirtavari Mantapa. Vasantotsava Tirtavari or Avabrata- Snana takes place here. At any rate the author&amp;rsquo;s version that this mantapa was built by Alagia Manavala Jiyar in the middle of the 16th century cannot therefore be correct.&#xA;The 350 inscriptions found all over the fabric of the Temple gives the names of hundreds of donors to the various construc- tions and to the religious, social and other purposes and those who were entrusted to manage these trusts. But all those persons mentioned cannot be said to have held the management of the Temple itself. The hundred pillared mantapa which the author styles as the Kalyanamantapa, is also mentioned as the Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s work which is also not true. This will also be dealt with later in detail.&#xA;The author gives a very new name to the Andal Unjal court- yard,as &amp;ldquo;Alagiya Manavala Tirumurram&amp;rdquo; adjacent to Sri Tayar Shrine. This may be or can be &amp;ldquo;Sri Manavalan Tirumurram” and not &amp;ldquo;Alagiya Manavala Tirumurram&amp;rdquo;. Long ago, it is said that one of the &amp;ldquo;Panchaberas&amp;rdquo; enshrined in the main Sanctum Sanctorum of Lord Varadaraja behind Sri Selvar or Bali-Bera, used to be taken to Sri Tayar Shrine in the night. He is called &amp;ldquo;Sayna Bera&amp;rdquo; meaning One who sleeps along with the Devi. The night&amp;rsquo;s last offering to Sri Tayar is used to be accompanied by a separate quantity of nivedana to be offered to this Sayana Bera or Manavala as he is called. This is called &amp;ldquo;Tirusadam meladai.&amp;rdquo; This &amp;lsquo;meladai,&amp;rsquo; a separate quantity of &amp;ldquo;Tirusadam&amp;rdquo; is even now sent along with the last nivedana to Sri Tayar, though the practice of taking Sri Manavalan the &amp;ldquo;Sayana Bera&amp;rdquo; to Sri Tayar Shrine had been stopped, when and why we are unable to guess. On the morning Sri Manavalan will be brought out of Sri Tayar Shrine and placed in the Unjal Mantapa. Then, when the Alankara Tirumanjanam comes with the paraphernalia, pipers etc., He will be taken along with it to the Hill in procession. Hence this &amp;ldquo;murram&amp;rdquo; in front of the Unjal Mantapa may be &amp;ldquo;Manavala Tirumurram&amp;rdquo;. The author evidently in his obsession of the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar sought&#xA;Andal Unjal Mantapa&#xA;(P.58)&#xA;Tondaradippodi Vasal (II Entrance)&#xA;(P. 59)&#xA;The Abisheka Mantapa&#xA;(P. 57)&#xA;59&#xA;to call it as Alagiya Manavala Tirumurram for which there is no authority.&#xA;The name &amp;ldquo;Tondaradippodi&amp;rdquo; is there ever since this second enclosure was constructed which was very much earlier than that of Todarmal. Simply because the statue of Todarmal&amp;rsquo; is placed near the Tondaradippodi, its name cannot be twisted as &amp;ldquo;Todar- malpadi&amp;rdquo; as the author would like to have it. The statues, three in number in a niche next to Tondaradippodi-vasal are not also that of Todarmal. They must be of one of the Vijaya- nagar Kings, his son and wife, most probably Venkata I.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Page 51 Under &amp;ldquo;Ananta Saras (Pushkarani), the sacred tank&amp;rdquo; the author, in describing the Krishna and Varaha shrines, says that their &amp;ldquo;rear portion go very near but do not abut the outer compound wall of the temple&amp;rdquo;. This is clearly a proof of the author&amp;rsquo;s lack of personal knowledge, The &amp;lsquo;, Varaha&amp;rdquo; Shrine abuts the outer compound wall whereas there is a gap only in the rear of the &amp;ldquo;Krishna&amp;rdquo; shrine. The descriptions regarding the &amp;ldquo;Krishna Shrine&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Varaha and other ruined Shrines&amp;rdquo; in this page are also lacking in exactitude. Regarding the former, it is called as &amp;ldquo;Sri Venugopalan&amp;rsquo;s Shrine and not &amp;ldquo;Krishna Shrine&amp;rdquo; according to the Temple records. Secondly the Mulavar idol is always there. The author&amp;rsquo;s version that it is now without the Deity&amp;rsquo; is wrong. It may be stated at this juncture that this Shrine was recently renovated and pujas restored by the trustee Sri R. T. Tatacharya at a cost of Rs. 10,000/-.As regards the latter, &amp;ldquo;Varaha&amp;rdquo; Shrine, this was also renovated recently by the Mudal Tirumaligai Tatacharya brothers of Srirangam (familiarly known as Thatham Brothers) and pujas restored after sampro- kshana, at a cost of more than twenty thousand rupees. The author says that further north also to the Varaha Shrine &amp;rsquo;there is a ruined unused mantapa&amp;rsquo; There is no such mantapa to the north of the Varaha Shrine. Probably he means the one on the south.&#xA;The author betrays here one more instance of his lack of personal knowledge when he says under &amp;ldquo;Dorai Thottam (Garden)&amp;rdquo; that the annual Davana Utsava (Garden Festival) for Lord Varadaraja is celebrated here, in the month of Chaitra&#xA;60&#xA;(April). This is patently wrong since the Davanotsava to the Lord takes place in this Dorai Tottam during the month of Masi (February). He cites &amp;ldquo;an epigraph of Sadasiva dated Saka 1473&amp;rdquo; for this, as mentioning the festival in the Vasanta Thoppu in the month of Chitirai. Probably this refers to the &amp;lsquo;Thoppu&amp;rsquo; festival which used to be celebrated in the month of Chitrai at the garden some four furlongs south of the Temple, on the southern outskirts of Kanchi on the bank of the river Vegavati. At any rate neither the festival can be called as Davanotsava nor the Thoppu&amp;rsquo; as Dorai Thottam as stated by the author. There is a reference to a gift of land for certain festivals in the sixteen pillared mantapam situated in the &amp;lsquo;Viswapanditar Thoppu to Viswapanditar son of Timma Pandita and grand son of Viswapandita, agent of Ettur, Tirumala Kumara Tatacharya, for the merit of the latter&amp;rsquo; in the reign of Venkatapati Deva Maharaya&amp;rdquo;. A correct version of the festival is given on page 108 somehow.&#xA;C&#xA;This may be either due to the author&amp;rsquo;s confused state of understanding, as we have been saying, due to his lack of definiteness, concerning our Temple&amp;rsquo;s history or his unwilling- ness to recognise the importance of this festival which is celebrated in this garden for several centuries under the auspices of the Tatacharyas to whom it belongs. This garden or &amp;ldquo;Thoppu &amp;quot; is also popularly called as &amp;ldquo;Dharmakartha Garden&amp;rdquo;. One Viswapanditar agent of Tirumalai Kumara Tatacharya was given a gift of land towards performing the festival, by Venkatapati Deva Maharaya, in this garden in the month of Chitirai, for &amp;ldquo;the merit of&amp;rdquo; Sri Tatacharya, his Acharya. Hence, the name &amp;ldquo;Viswapanditar Thoppu &amp;quot; derived at that time. The festival is subsequently being continued till today without break by the descendants, the Tatacharya trustees. This is one of the most beautiful festivals of the year and celebrated on the next day of the return of the Lord from Aiyangarkulam festival on the Chitra Purnami day. Venkata- pati Deva Maharaya evidently wanted to celebrate this peaceful and restful festival to the Lord after the strenuous one previously at Aiyangarkulam, Nadabavi and river Palar. The Aiyangarkulam festival on the banks of the river Palar and the Tottam festival on the banks of the river Vegavati are the two&#xA;61&#xA;most important and grand festivals of the year commemorating Sri Tatacharya&amp;rsquo;s signal services to the Temple.&#xA;66&#xA;Page 53 Under &amp;ldquo;Kalyana Mantapa&amp;rdquo; the author repeats his pet theory that it appears to have been built by Alagiya Manavala Jiyar in the latter half of the sixteenth century A. D. evidently under the royal patronage&amp;rsquo;. The Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s portrait figures are sculptured on two pillars of the Mantapa&amp;rdquo;. We strongly refute these two averments as baseless and false. The author has given a list of photographic illustrations of the Kalyana Mantapa. If as he asserts here, it is true that the &amp;ldquo;Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s portrait figures are sculptured on two pillars of this Mantapa&amp;rdquo;, he would not have failed to take the photos of these two and display them to establish his case. This only shows the barrenness of his assertion. The author himself is not sure of his statement and hence it is, he carefully uses the words &amp;ldquo;appears&#xA;and &amp;ldquo;evidently&amp;rdquo; with regard to its construc- tion by the Jiyar.&#xA;99&#xA;The Vijayanagar style of building as evidenced here, is also noticed in mantapas in the temple of Virupaksha at Hampi, at Srirangam, Rameswaram and in the Jalakanteswara temple at Vellore Fort.&#xA;One point is worthy of note in this connection. The patrons who financed the construction of temples and building the structures, were, as far as our Temple is concerned, the Cholas in the early stages and Vijayanagara rulers later. Under their patronage these constructions were carried out. If in this hundred-pillard mantapa (which is not commonly known as Kalyana-mantapa), there is a figure of a Sanyasin it cannot be identified with that of Alagia Manavala Jiyar, who flourished during the reign of Sadasivaraya and who was not at any rate the spiritual preceptor of any ruler of the Vijayanagara. Panchamatabanjanam Tatadesika (1509-1591) the royal precptor of the Vijayanagar rulers started constructing this mantapa. This receives support from the old sloka: Namaskrtya gajadrisam preritastena tadbalaat mantape satapadhakye Tata- desika nirmite. Tatadesika means evidently Panchamata- banjanam Tatadesika. Lakshmikumara Tatadesika completed this mantapa and others which his father began, adding some&#xA;62&#xA;more artistic items and figures in it and many other structures in the Temple&amp;rsquo;. There is a sloka in the stotras, in praise of Sri Lakhmikumara Tatadesika, composed by his eldest son Sri Tirumala Tatadesika. It starts with &amp;ldquo;Sow Varnam Sikaram&amp;rdquo; and ends with &amp;ldquo;Chitra Stamba Satavrutham - Tribuvanascharyavahan Mantapam meaning the hundred- pillard Mantapa.&#xA;99&#xA;In the latter half of the sixteenth century Sri Lakshmi- kumara Tatadesika who was the Srikaryadurandara (Manager- General of Temple Affairs) had at his command the resources of the Vijayanagar Kings. According to Prapannamrtam. Venkata entrusted the whole kingdom to Tatacharya and himself led a life of retirement&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;The Dipastamba in a single stone is a marvel that should have attracted the attention of historians and archaeologists. Its non-mention is inexplicable. While the author has taken care to note the figure of Tirukkacchinambi in all pillars of the four-pillard mantapas in the Tirumurraveli (courtyard), he has ignored to note the carving at the lower end of the pillar in the north-east, of Ramanuja and Mahapurna beneath the Vakula tree and Yadavaprakasa in the form of Udumbu eating the remnants of food taken by Sri Vaishnavas.&#xA;On pp 54-55, Dr. K.V. Raman chooses to refer to Manavala- mamuni&amp;rsquo;s Kanchi Divya Desa Sangraha Slokamalika and com- ment upon it. The sloka as given on page 57 under footnote 34, has some mistakes and does not make clear the sense for certain words. Dr. K. V. Raman has not followed the order of the sloka while enumerating them on pp 54-55. For instance, Battanata is to be mentioned after Varahavapusha. Purnam refers to Mahapurna and this has been left out. The practice according to tradition, is to climb the steps to reach Sri Rama&amp;rsquo;s shrine.and come to Tayar&amp;rsquo;s shrine after going through the third prakara. Garuda&amp;rsquo;s shrine is opposite to Narasima&amp;rsquo;s and the order is wrongly stated by the author. Chakrattalwar is Hetisa and Anantalwar is Bogisvara. There is no strength in saying that the Chakrattalwar&amp;rsquo;s shrine was built in the second prakara in Vijayanagar times. If this were the case, there must be some vestige for this shrine in the third prakara. According to tradition, there are two or200 SAW.&#xA;Dipastambam and the Renovation Slab of 1930-31&#xA;(P. 62)&#xA;ஸிதர்சனம்.&#xA;M&#xA;ஐயங்கார் கைங்கர்யம்&#xA;Sri Bashyakar Mulavar &amp;amp; Utsavar with Kurattalwar (Utsavar) (P. 62)&#xA;Chakkaratalwar (West Face) Mulavar&#xA;Chakkaratalwar (East Face) Mulavar &amp;amp; Utsavar&#xA;(P. 62)&#xA;(P. 62)&#xA;63&#xA;more sacred pools in the Anantasaras tank in the second prakara, The pool in front of Chakrattalwar shrine is said to be &amp;ldquo;Chakra Tirta&amp;rdquo; and the one in front of Varaha&amp;rsquo;s shrine on the northwest corner, &amp;ldquo;Varaha Tirta&amp;rdquo;. So, the author&amp;rsquo;s inference at page 55 that the Chakrattalwar shrine was &amp;ldquo;probably&amp;rdquo; originally in the third prakara and was subsequently &amp;ldquo;built in its present position i.e., in the fourth prakara&amp;rdquo; has neither historical basis nor related to physical facts. The author describes this prakara wherein the Chakrattalwar&amp;rsquo;s shrine is situated, as the fourth prakara, whereas it is actually in the second prakara, if counted from the outermost prakara of the Temple consisting of the four Mada Streets around the Periyatirumadil.&#xA;Page 56 The author repeats here what he has said on page 49 that &amp;rsquo;the compound wall of the third prakara &amp;lsquo;was reconstruc- ted by Alagiya Manavala Jiyar in the 16th century&amp;rsquo;. What is the basis of this assertion and why he had to reconstruct it when the author himself cites here the inscription which says that this &amp;rsquo;lofty stone-built prakarawall that cannot be destroyed by time&amp;rsquo; is beyond one&amp;rsquo;s comprehension. This sort of reiteration alone cannot in any way help to establish his theory about the Jiyar constructing all these items, without advancing valid proofs.&#xA;Lastly the author&amp;rsquo;s concluding portion of this chapter is worthy of note. He says &amp;ldquo;moreover the Vijayanagar monarchs who zealously fostered the best Hindu traditions evinced sympathetic interest in fulfilling the religious aspirations of the people. Thus under their patronage were built the towering Gopura on the east; the Kalyana Mantapa, the Tulabara Mantapa, the Unjal Mantapa and the Vasantha Mantapa and probably separate shrines for Alwars and Acharyas. This was indeed the brightest period in the history of the temple when there was a great spurt in the celebration of festivals in the elaborate arrangements for offerings in the various benefactions of lands, jewels etc., as will be shown in the sequel&amp;rdquo;. This is almost true from history, inscriptions, etc. These Vijayananagar Kings were inspired only by Sri Kumara Tatacharya their spiritual guru and his venerable ancestors and descendants in coming forward with their offer of munificence towards these important services described above.&#xA;64&#xA;The author should have noted that the Mahanasa (Kitchen) and the Shrine of Tayar are located at the places assigned according to the Pancharatra Agamas.&#xA;PART II-CHAPTER III&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 ROLE IN GROWTH OF VAISHNAVISM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/04_ROLE_IN_GROWTH_OF_VAISHNAVI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/04_ROLE_IN_GROWTH_OF_VAISHNAVI/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;has-sung-in-praise-of-him-as-attiyuran-this-is-strange-logic-indeed&#34;&gt;CHAPTER-IV&#xA;THE ROLE OF THE TEMPLE IN THE GROWTH OF VAISHNAVISM&#xA;In the &amp;lsquo;Introduction&amp;rsquo; as well as on page 88 of the concluding portion of this chapter the author maintains that our Temple was &amp;rsquo;not prominent in the beginning&amp;rsquo;. He bases this stand on the absence of any reference to Sri Varada, by the early Alwars, Poigai and Peyalwars, though admitting at the same breath that Budatalwar - one of the early Alwars&#xA;has sung in praise of Him as &amp;lsquo;Attiyuran&amp;rsquo;. This is strange logic indeed!&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;that-nadadur-azhwan-took-sri-ramanujas-permission-for-this-just-before-the-latters-demise&#34;&gt;His stand is that &amp;lsquo;Vehka&amp;rsquo; (The Yatoktakarin Temple) &amp;lsquo;was the most prominent&amp;rsquo; Vishnu Temple at Kanchi in the beginning by virtue of its having been sung by Poigai and Peyalwars. But we would like to point out that the origin of the Lord at &amp;lsquo;Vehka&amp;rsquo; was necessitated in order to prevent- the &amp;lsquo;Vegavati&amp;rsquo; which was rushing to destroy the &amp;lsquo;Yaga&amp;rsquo; performed by Brahma, before whom, it is said in the Puranas, Sri Mahavishnu emerged in all His effulgence as Lord Varada1&#xA;It is highly difficult to determine the priority or otherwise of one temple to another. The songs made by an Alwar about a temple or their absence cannot by themselves determine the ancient character of a temple. With our limited know- ledge and insight into the past occurrences, we fail thoroughly to settle this issue. It is prudent to admit that almost all the temples were there since very earliest times but they had their structures built at various times by the different rulers. The temples at Madurantakam, Srimushnam Pandarpur, Puri (Jagannath) and other places were not taken note of by the Alwars. Which of these temples was more ancient than the other ?&#xA;The author need not have entered into such unnecessary theories and discussions of questions of prominence, ancient or modern, about these two allied Temples.&#xA;66&#xA;On page 62 he says that Tirukkacchinambi &amp;quot; asked him to bring daily a jarful of water from a well, known as &amp;lsquo;sala-well for the worship at the Varadaraja temple which Ramanuja faithfully carried out&amp;quot;. This is not in consonance with the tradition found in the Guruparampara and the version of Vatukanambi a close and trusted disciple of Ramanuja. They say that Ramanuja started doing this service (Kainkaryam) on and from the time of his safe return to Kanchi after escaping from the plot hatched by his Advaitic Teacher Yadavaprakasa to kill him. It is said that our Lord and his Consort Perundevi Tayar guided him through the thick jungles to reach Kanchi in the guise of a hunter and huntress. At the place where the &amp;lsquo;sala-well&amp;rsquo; is situated the hunter-couple feigned thirst and asked Ramanuja to fetch them water from the well. The Divine Couple disappeared after drinking two handfuls of water given by him. On coming out of the well with the third handful of water Ramanuja could not find his benefactors. Just then it was dawning and from the place be could see the Punyakoti Vimana of our Lord. He realised at once that his benefactors were no other than our Lord and his Consort and that he had reached the outskirts of Kanchi. This made him start this&#xA;Tirta-kainkaryam.&#xA;On page 65, the author writes, &amp;ldquo;Many of the reforms in the Temple set up and form of worship he introduced at Srirangam had their influence in this Temple as will be seen in latter chapters. In recognition of his great services, Ramanuja was deified in the Varadarajaswami Temple within fifty five years after his demise&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;There is no evidence to support this contention. It is true that Ramanuja had special attraction for the Lord of our Temple. He does not appear to have introduced any reform in this Temple and hence there is no meaning in referring to them. On the other hand the fact that his disciples particularly Sri Nadadur Azhwan desired to have his image installed here and had it sanctified after his (Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s) demise is given in the Guruparampara. It is said&#xA;67&#xA;that Nadadur Azhwan took Sri Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s permission for this, just before the latter&amp;rsquo;s demise.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;arayirappadi-the-first-gloss-or-interpretation-of-tiruvaai--mozhi-of-sri-nammalwar-otherwise-called-bagavat-vishaya&#34;&gt;In the concluding portion of the &amp;lsquo;Introduction&amp;rsquo; to this chapter, and under section 2 &amp;ldquo;Post Ramanuja period&amp;rdquo;, he deals with Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s school of Vaishnavism. Here also he has started a most controversial theory of Sri Bashya or the northern school and Prabandic or southern school, implying a Vadakalai - Tenkalai cult2. The very terms are fallacious and contradictory, since both the Vadakalais and Tenkalais even now take pride in styling themselves as &amp;lsquo;Ubaya- Vedantins&amp;rsquo;, meaning that they swear by both Sri Bashyam and Bagavad-vishaya (Prabandas). It is only to misguide and confuse the uninformed and also the courts in the Tenkalai Vadakalai disputes, such theories were recently started by the ingenuity of the Tenkalai litigants. The Tenkalais claim themselves to belong to the southern cult or the Prabandic school (Tamil) and the Vadakalais, they say belong to the northern cult or Sri Bashya school (Sanskrit). By representing that they are pro-Tamils, they attempt to earn the sympathy and backing of the public of these parts who are all almost Tamilians. In the same way they try to mislead the courts also. A deeper study into the real significance of these two terms, will show the falsity of their claim. As said above both the sects revere Sri Satakopa (Nammalwar) and Sri Ramanuja (Bashyakar) and their works Divyaprabandas and Sri Bashya respectively. The author will be contradicting himself if he is going to say that the Vadakalais are more, if not &amp;lsquo;solely interested in Sri Bashya and Tenkalais in Bagavad- Vishaya, since the Tenkalais are equally vociferous in claiming to be the true followers of Sri Ramanuja (Emberumanar) the apostle of Visishtadvaita Siddanta. Specialising in a particular line of our Vaishnavite religion through certain scriptures by a person does not mean that the other scriptures are discarded by him or treated by him as against his cult.&#xA;Sri Pillan, it was, upon whom the title of &amp;ldquo;Ubaya-Vedanta Simhasanadipati&amp;rdquo; was conferred by his Acharya Sri Ramanuja and adopted by him as his spiritual son. It is under the behests of the latter that Sri Pillan brought out the commentary,&#xA;68&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Arayirappadi&amp;rdquo;, the first gloss or interpretation of Tiruvaai- mozhi of Sri Nammalwar, otherwise called Bagavat-Vishaya.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While directing Pillan to write a gloss on Tiruvaaimozhi, Ramanuja was influenced by the interest which Pillan evinced for this composition. Ramanuja also took into his consideration the fact that Pillan belonged to the family of Srimann Natamuni- kal. Yamuna too refers to Nammalwar as the Lord of his familys. It is but natural that Pillan should have been made the Chief for Ubaya-Vedanta. The Tatacharyas are the descen- dants of Pillan directly. So the bogey of two schools - Sri Bashya and Prabandic - northern and southern raised by the author has no basis, since they are not opposed to each other. The author himself concedes that there was no sectarian rancour even until and after Vedanta Desika&amp;rsquo;s time between the two schools and they are of recent origin,and &amp;ldquo;it is untenable to say that Vedanta Desika did not know the Tamil Prabandams&amp;rdquo;. The two schools, if schools they can be called, are not contra- dictory but complimentary to each other. They do not pres- cribe or teach the distinctions of Tenkalai - Vadakalai sampra- dayas or practices as we observe in these days. like the &amp;ldquo;tons- uring of widows&amp;rdquo;, sect marks etc.&#xA;These two interpretations, not two schools, of Vedas and Prabandas are the two eyes of a true Vaishnavite. But the author for reasons best known to himself brings out here, his own theory that they are two different schools. He blows both hot and cold when he says that &amp;ldquo;even regarding the texts, the difference was one of preference. In fact, most of the followers of Rama- nuja like Embar, Battar, Kurukesa, Nanjiyar, Nampillai, Periya- vacchan Pillai, Pillailokacharya, Vedanta Desika and others were well versed in both Sanskrit and Tamil lore. In their works they struck a balance by adopting the manipravala style a free mixture of Sanskrit and Tamil words etc.&amp;rdquo; Striking a balance may mean, as though there is a difference between these two scriptures which are in Sanskrit and Tamil. The &amp;lsquo;manipravala&amp;rsquo; is only a script apopted by our elders containing both Sanskrit and Tamil words. Loosely used, they create confusion. After saying that the above mentioned Acharyas were well versed in both, the author attributes that the differences and cleavages between the&#xA;69&#xA;two studies, started later. Here also we cannnt agree with the author. It is not the difference between the two studies but the difference between the the two sects viz the Tenkali and Vadakalai with regad to their &amp;lsquo;sampradayas&amp;rsquo; or pratices. These differences are not taught by the &amp;rsquo;two studies&amp;rsquo;. This concept of distinction, based on the study of Sri Bashya and Bagavat- Vishaya which the author tries to introduce, is fundamentally wrong. Such sophisticated theories to delude the ignorant and uninformed are of recent origin and there is no place for such distinctions in our Vaishnavism. Sri Bashya interprets the Vedas, in Sanskrit and Bagavad-Vishya in Tamil. The philoso- phy contained in both of them is the same. Are not the Ten- kalai temples have Vedas and Mantras (Sanskrit) in their rituals and vice-versa the Vadakalai temples the Prabandas (Tamil) ?&#xA;Vedanta Desika asserts that there is no contradiction in the traditions followed by the pupils of the author of the Sri Bashya with reference to what these traditions mean. If at all there is any contradiction, it is only in the way of offering the purport by bringing together the words occurring in the passages in question. The &amp;lsquo;Sastras&amp;rsquo; permit any difference that arises in the traditions due to place, time aud stages or conditions in life. If those ignorant of tradition choose to interpret according to their free will, then the defects belong only to those who speak of them 50.&#xA;But in the litigations of the Tenkalai-Vadakalai disputes in our Temple and elsewhere, we may find instances of each beli- ttling the other in order to establish his own right as superior. To be more clear, the Tenkalais who are the office-holders of Adyapakam (Tamil Prabandas) in our Temple will assert that their service alone is very essential and that no other service even exists. On the other hand, the Vadakalais who are the Vedaparayana mirasdars will try to claim that their service alone is essential and the Prabandas are not necessary for the pujas or services in the Temple. Stranger still is the position with regard to the Temple at Tiruvahindrapuram in South Arcot District, which is purely a Vadakalai one. Here the dispute between the reciters of the Vedas and Prabandas are between Vedakalais&#xA;.&#xA;.&#xA;70&#xA;themselves, each trying to decry the other and rushing to courts, criminal and civil to establish their rights. By such ugly squa- bbles caused on account of purely selfish motives to gain certain preferences in the temples, we cannot take it that the Vedas and Prabandas are themselves contradictory and conflicting to each other. These are super-imposed by interested litigants and have nothing to do with our religion or philosophy.&#xA;The remakrs at the end of Page 66 and the beginning of Page 67 that &amp;ldquo;Similarly, Kurukesa and Vedanta Desika of the so-called Vadakalai group wrote works in Tamil&amp;rdquo;, etc. are not happily worded. By such remarks the author betrays only his sectarian bigotry. He could have avoided such biased expressions like &amp;rsquo;the so-called Vadakalai group&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;In fine, a Tenkalai may be a great Sri Bashya Adikari and a Vadakalai, a Bagavat-Vishya Adikari (specialist) as and accor- ding to his personal propensity. Therefore, it is not necessary or desirable to advance arguments for or against the one or the other, in treatises like this, especially when our Acharyas have handed down them both to us as the most equally sacred.&#xA;The author further harps and develops this theory on page 68 again. He says &amp;ldquo;the main doctrinal difference between these &amp;rsquo;two schools, may be summed up here&amp;rdquo;. Thus stating, he points out certain differences.&#xA;They are based on the differential approaches by the two sects while interpreting certain concepts and theories regarding God and His qualities. They are enumerated as eighteen in number&amp;quot;. They have been there in the Vaishnava Sampradaya since the time of Periyavacchan Pillai. Pillai Lokacharya and Vedanta Desika noted some of them and offered their remarks, admitting the interpretations which they found admissible and rejecting others. It is certainly wrong to find a basis for the split of the Vaishnavasampradaya into Vadakalai and Tenkalai. Inspite of these differences in the doctrines, the sampradaya did never choose to exhibit mutual dislike or hatred. These differ- ences did not cause the split.71&#xA;The very names Vadakalai and Tenkalai came into the picture long after the period of Manavala Mamuni. Certain practices dopted by a section of people were held by them as the most sacred, deriving their authority from the conduct of pious people taken to be the strict followers of tradition. Others who took objection to these are taken to belong to the other section taking to such acts which are opposed to theirs. This much is the difference that marks out the two sects as belonging to rival groups particularly evincing interest in Temples, rituals there and exercise of their rights. The two sects swear, on the sampradaya level by the eighteen differences which are needless to get elaborated here. The present-day dispute between the two sects has no sanction on the side of religion and philosophy, but neither of them has stopped the spread of mutual ill will.&#xA;To say that Tenkalais are more liberal in their outlook with regard to caste-system and the Vadakalais are rigid is also a travesty of truth. As already observed above, it is only a device to play to the gallery and earn the sympathy of law officers. Both the Tenkalais and Vadakalais have regard to Alwars, who were from diffierent castes. Sri Vedanta Desika, the great Vadakalai Acharya, had chosen to claim Tiruppanalwar, a Harijan by birth, as Nampananathan (our Pananathan) 5b. He has even written a commentary on his (the Alwar&amp;rsquo;s) &amp;quot; Amalanadipiran &amp;ldquo;, by name &amp;ldquo;Munivahana-Bogam&amp;rdquo;. Sri Desika also swears by the Prabandas of Alwars. The Tenkalais who claim to be the followers of Ramanuja could not find a single work of Sri Ramanuja in Tamil. Will they give him up because of this? All that was in Sanskrit originally viz the Vedas, Sutras, Upanishads, Gita etc., were reproduced as it were, in Tamil, by the Alwars. Later, our Acharyas reproduced them again in Sanskrit, according to the times and needs of the society towards its emancipation. Sidditrayam Geetartha Sangraham, Stotra- Ratnam and Chatussloki of Sri Alavandar, Sri Bashya, Geeta Bashya, Gatya Trayam etc., of Sri Ramanuja, Panchastavams by Sri Kurattalwar and the Stotras of Parasara Batta and other Acharyas like Sri Vedanta Desika in Sanskrit are all almost the interpretations of the Divyasuktis of Alwars, which in turn were the interpretations of the Vedas&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;72&#xA;We are really fed up with such distortions and misinter- pretations with regard to our great religion advanced both in the law courts and outside by this sect, adnauseam, to gain certain narrow ends, through their journals and other media. So let us proceed to Section 3 of this Chapter IV.&#xA;The author concedes in the beginning of this section that the Vijayanagar Kings during the 16th century A. D. have extended their patronage on a lavish scale to the Vaishnava Acharyas and constructed the several mantapas, gopuras, vimanas etc., in the Sri Varadarajaswamy Temple. So far, so good. But in, so say- ing he wants to make it appear that one Alagiya Manavala Jiyar was the chief architect of these constructions. There are some inscriptions about this Jiyar. But nowwhere in these or any- where else it is said that he constructed the Kalyana Mantapa, the Rampart walls and the front Mantapa of the Tayar Shrine. There is also no mention of his connection with the Vijayanagar rulers either as a guru or adviser in these inscriptions. They simply mention some gifts by him to the Temple and in one of them as the Koil-Kelvi or Superintendent or Manager even. Excepting the author&amp;rsquo;s assertion, there is no other proof or basis that this Jiyar was the architect of all these construc- tions. On the other hand we have positive evidence of inscri- ptions, history and records to establish that the Tatacharyas who were the recognised royal preceptors of the Vijayanagar rulers, were alone responsible in securing the royal patronge for all these monumental works. This, the author himself accepts without naming the &amp;ldquo;Vaishnava-Acharyas&amp;rdquo; to whom they &amp;ldquo;extended their patronage &amp;ldquo;9. There are evidences in support of this10 Sri Lakshmikumara Tatadesika and his father Panchamatabanjanam Tatadesika are admittedly, the spiritual preceptors or royal gurus of Kings Krishnaraya, Sadasiva Raya, Ramaraya, Sriranga and Venkata I &amp;ldquo;. These constructions took place during the times of these Kings only. viz 16th century A. D. The readers may draw their own conclusions from this. We are certainly one with the author in calling this period (16th century when these Kings were reigning) as &amp;ldquo;a golden age for Vaishnavism and Vijayanagar Kings &amp;ldquo;who&#xA;oleration as evidenced by&#xA;also for the Temple.&amp;rdquo; The despite their despite their general religious their charities to both Siva and&#xA;73&#xA;Vishnu Temples seem however in later times to have developed a special predilection to Vaishnavism and to have made the the Varadaraja temple an object of their special adoration&amp;rdquo; 12.&#xA;The author next deels with the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar who lived between 1420 to 1468 A. D., calling him as &amp;ldquo;the most prominent Jiyar at Kanchi in the post-Manavala Mamuni period&amp;rdquo;. But this Jiyar does not find a place in any of the inscriptions of our Temple. The T. T. D. inscriptions mention the activities of certain Jiyars at Srirangam and Tirupati. From this, the author without any connection or relevance starts saying abruptly that this Jiyar of the 15th century &amp;ldquo;seems to have held a similar position at Kanchi from the last decade of the 15th century&amp;rdquo;. But this Jiyar did not even see the last decade of the 15th century A.D. since even according to the author, this Jiyar did not live after 1468 A.D. The first two paragraphs of this section regarding the &amp;ldquo;Alagiya Manavala Jiyar&amp;rdquo; are most confusing and contradictory as can be seen from the way in which the author while describing one Alagiya Manavala Jiyar at Kanchi, suddenly turns to some other Jiyars at Srirangam and Tirupati and comes to describe again a different Jiyar of the same Math as having lived at Kanchi as the preceptor to one Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyangar.&#xA;Further while speaking about the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar who lived between 1420-1468 A.D. the author says that he (the Jiyar) is mentioned in &amp;quot; several inscriptions datable to the latter balf of the 15th century and the earlier half of the 16th century&amp;rdquo;. Though the author freely speaks &amp;ldquo;of his services to the Temple and his eminent position in the Temple affairs of Kanchi&amp;rdquo;, he has not given any idea about the particulars of the inscriptions in which he is mentioned. We will have to be very guarded therefore, in giving them credence or taking them for granted without any reliable data or basis. As stated by us at the outset, to section 3 of this chapter, the Jiyar of the 16th century finds a place in some of the inscriptions. In those times when there was no such ill-feelings as we witness in these days between the Tenkalais and Vadakalais the management or supervision of the Temple works, worship and conduct of festivals were entrusted with and allotted to those who were&#xA;74&#xA;sincere and devoted without any distinction of sect or even caste. The Tatacharyas who were &amp;ldquo;the Manager-General of Temple Affairs&amp;rdquo; could not themselves attend to each and every item of the stupendous works they had started not only in our Temple but also in the other Temples at Kanchi and elsewhere. Naturally, this Jiyar who was a pious and sincere devotee might have been entrusted with &amp;lsquo;some of the works and services by them as an agent.&#xA;In some of the inscriptions occur the names of such agents like Tirumalai Nambi Chakrarayarı3, Ramanujayyan of Tiruppullani&amp;rsquo;, Alagiyasingar17, Tiruppani Singarayyangar1, Emberumanar Aiyyan&amp;rdquo;, Tiruvengada Aiyangar17a, Viswa- pandita&amp;rsquo;s, Vaidyanatha Iyer18a, Jana Mudaliar, etc.186.&#xA;It is learnt from these that in those times, &amp;ldquo;the several affairs of the Temple were assigned to different persons or bodies each in his or its time attended to the work for which he or it was nominated &amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo;. Thus it is quite possible that Alagiya&amp;rsquo; Manavala Jiyar was also entrusted with some of the works that were progressing under the aegis of the Tatacharyas as an agent which caused the mention of his name in some inscriptions.&#xA;There are also similar inscriptions in our Temple about Ahobila swamis, Sankaracharyas, Madwacharyas and other pro- minent persons, mentioning about their gifts of villages and services to our Temple, during the same period (16th century A. D). Several other inscriptions describe the various offerings of devotees at different times!9a. These dignitaries who are equally, if not more prominent are not known to lay any such extravagant claims to the authorship of the major constructions in the Temple on the basis of their gifts or services in the 16th century A.D.&#xA;The author gives an exaggerated account similarly with regard to the Kandadai Ramanuja Ayyan20, Paravastu25, and Prativadi Bayankaram22 families on the basis of one or two inscriptions, he was able to delve from the ocean of inscriptions mentioning some gifts and services by them. Kandadai Ramanuja Ayyan or Ayyangar was a disciple of Alagiya&#xA;75&#xA;Manavala Jiyar23. He was in charge of Ramanuja Kutams at Tirumalai, Kanchi and other places24. He was instrumental for the conduct of some festivals in several places including Kanchi25. But the author is not justified in exaggerating his contributions to our Temple. A report of the Archaeological Department26 describes these Vaishnavites in the following manner, who existed during the time of Achyutaraya. &amp;ldquo;Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyangar, Paravastunayanar and Vada Tiruvenkada Jiyar are some of the names occurring in the inscriptions of this King&amp;rsquo;s reign and the distinguishing prefixes of Kandadai and Paravastu are found among the family names of important Vaishnavite families, like the Tatacharyas of Conjeevaram&amp;rdquo;. The italics is by us to show, even then, they are compared with the prominent Tatacharya family.&#xA;On page 82, the author gives an account of the Tatacharya family in his own way. He acknowledges that the Vijayanagar monarchs of the earlier period gave their high respects to the forefathers of the Tatacharyas. He next deals with Panchamatabanjanam Tatacharya casually saying that &amp;ldquo;he lived in the court of Ramaraya &amp;ldquo;. He proceeds further to say that one branch of the Tatacharya family settled down at Kanchi during the time of Sriranga I (1572-1585 A. D.).. This statement is not correct. The Tatacharyas might have been visiting the courts of Vijayanagar Kings or even stayed there at times for longer periods. They might have been called with the prefixes of the names of places they had been staying, for the sake of distinguishing them from other local persons. But from a long time past their orginial homes were only Kanchi, Kumbakonam and Tirumalai“.&#xA;Next the author&amp;rsquo;s comment (on page 83) that “the specific mention of Tatacharya&amp;rsquo;s agreement to perform the Janma- nakshatram of Manavala Mamuni on his annual birth day is indeed very significant as it shows his devotion to this acharya is very amusing. Without making any distinction, the great Tatacharya might have magnanimously and out of respect to a Vaishnavite devotee consented to do this. The author has been a bit careless in using the word devotion. Devotion is displayed generally to God, parents and Acharyas. It is not&#xA;76&#xA;shown indiscriminately to any Acharya but to one&amp;rsquo;s own and to the line of Acharyas who belong to him. Respect could have been a better word. It is needless to remark that a true Vaishnava should show his respect to everyone who is a Vaish- nava, whether he be a friend or a foe. Being an ardent Vaish- nava, how could he have refrained from showing his consider- ation to Manavalamamuni, a Vaishnavite Acharya? This occurr- ence should open the eyes of the warring members of both the sects as to the need to cultivate a healthy attitude on the lines taken up long ago by Sri Tatadesika. He had also contributed to the Vedapuriswarar Temple, when approached, liberally towards the construction of a mantapa, at Tirukkalikunram. This religious tolerance, benevolence and magnanimity should not be taken as devotion to that particular sect or religion, by the donor. We are led to believe the author has used the word &amp;lsquo;devotion&amp;rsquo; here intentionally in order to derive a pleasure lacking in taste.&#xA;On Page 84 of this Chapter IV, he says that because of the fall of Vijayanagar Kings, the family of &amp;ldquo;Ettur Kumara Tata- charya moved to Srirangapatna, the capital of the Mysore Kings, in the latter half of the 17th century in search of better for- tunes&amp;rdquo;. This is not only derogatory to the great family and its greater ancestor who were solely responsible for the construction of temples, endowing of properties towards the maintenance of Temples in general and our Temple in particular making of the several vehicles, ornaments and various other important necess- aries to our Temple, the philanthropic deeds like the construction of big lakes at Aiyangarkulam and Tenneri called &amp;ldquo;Tata- samudram &amp;ldquo;, the establishment of Agraharas (Villages) etc., but uncharitable and wrong to say that they migrated to Mysore &amp;ldquo;in search of better fortunes&amp;rdquo;. The fortune and wealth which the Tatacharyas acquired from out of their position, as the royal gurus (preceptors) to the Vijayanagar rulers for nearly three centuries would have sufficed to maintain several generations in royal splendour if they had but appropriated them for their own personal use. History, inscriptions and othor ancient works like Prapannamratam, Sadvamsa Guna Kirtanam, Maha Vamsa Mahimai etc., mention about the selfless services of the Tata-&#xA;77&#xA;charya family and their undying enthusiasm towards the uplift of the temples. That was the only goal and aim of life of that great Lakshmikumara Tatadesika his ancestors and his descen- dants. In order to make out an imaginary case for Tenkalai influence in the Temple at this period he has to avoid the pre- sence of the Tatacharyas and their influence at that period. To avoid this embarassing situation he has started on a theory on page 85 that the Stanatar who were managing the Temple affairs entrusted the management to Todarmal and that he in his turn gave it to his Acharya Attan Jiyar in the beginning of the 18th century. This is completely wrong. The Attan Jiyar agree- ment also will falsify this story. What was the necessity to enter into an agreement with a non-existent family! To get over this, the author starts with yet another story of &amp;quot; The Return of the Tatacharya Family to Kanchi in 1711&amp;rdquo; on page 86.&#xA;To say that one Ettur Tirumalai Kumara Tatacharya returned to Kanchi from Mysore in 1711 A.D is yet another piece of the author&amp;rsquo;s inventive genius. As already observed there were several members of the family who had remained at Kanchi and the family of Sri Venkatavarada Tatacharya alone left for Mysore. The family of &amp;ldquo;Venkata Varada&amp;rdquo; had not also left Mysore once and for all in 1711. They remained there till the middle of the 19th century as the royal preceptors of the Kings of Mysore28 visiting Kanchi off and on. They wielded great influence by which they not only spread Sri Vaishnavism but also secured several large amounts of wealth to our Temple. So, both the stories of the family leaving entirely for Mysore in the later half of the 17th century and returning in the beginning of the 18th century, are, on the face of it, distortions 29. When the Jiyar was all in all, as the trustee, why should he enter into an agreement with persons who had lost all touch with the Temple? These are patent misrepresentations that can be easily observed by a discerning eye. Could anybody by any stretch of imagination, conceive of the family abandoning and leaving in lurch everything they had so devoutly built, fondly reared and cherished and maintained for the sake of &amp;ldquo;seeking better&#xA;99&#xA;78&#xA;ortunes as if they were in need of it. As the unquestioned and great &amp;ldquo;Acharyapurushas&amp;rdquo; of the day they were sought after by the kings of Mysore, the Nayak Chieftains of Tanjore and others. Simply because some of them had to go to different places for some time as spitirual preceptors, it cannot be said that the entire family had once for all left Kanchi bag and baggage. Most of the descendants were certainly staying behind, to look after the Temple and other interests, while only one family, viz., that of Venkata Varadacharya, the second son of Kotikannikadanam Lakshmikumara Tatadesika, left for the court of Devaraja Wodeyar at Srirangapatnam (Mysore). The remaining sons were certainly staying behind at Kanchi. This is testified even according to the author, by an inscription on page 84 of his Treatise. But in the same breath, the author builds a story that the Tatacharya families left in its entirety for Mysore&amp;rdquo; in search of better fortunes&amp;rdquo;, to suit his theory of the Stalattars managing the Temple and subsequenty transferring it to Todarmal during the last and the beginning of the 17th and 18th centuries respectively.&#xA;We have given a detailed historical version of the continuous interest. influence and management of the descendants of Sri Lakshmikumara Tatadesika before and after the fall of the Vijayanagar dynasty, in part I of this book, regarding our Temple.&#xA;99&#xA;The next item is &amp;ldquo;Attan Jiyar on page 85. The Tatacharyas, who secreted the Utsavar idols of Sri Varada and Nachiyars to Udayarpalayam on account of the fear of Muslim depradation, were said to have been reeling in agony and despair due to the separation. It was further, heightened when they were unable to restore them back, after the scare subsided, by the refusal of the Zamindar of Udayarpalayam to part with the Idols. Accidentally and fortunately just then, there was present at Kanchi, one Attan Jiyar, who was the guru of Todarmalla the Chieftain of a regiment. This Jiyar who was a Telugu Brahmin Sanyasin had come to Kanchi fleeing Golkonda after the killing of his relatives Akkanna and Madanna by the forces of Aurangazeb 29a. The Tatacharyas approached this Jiyar for help in restoring the idols through his disciple Todarmalla. The&#xA;79&#xA;Jiyar readily agreed and made his disciple act. Todarmalla accordingly went to the Zamin with his regiment and forced the zamindar to part with the idols. Having thus secured back the images, the Tatacharyas were prepared to give anything to Attan Jiyar for this great help. But as a true Sanyasin he only desired that the Tanian or Sloka in praise of his Acharya Manavala Mamuni, &amp;ldquo;Sri Sailesa Dayapatram&amp;rdquo; should be allowed to be recited before the commencement of the recital of Prabandas in the Temple. To this, the Tatacharyas readily agreed. This consent has been given by an agreement called &amp;ldquo;Attan Jiyar Agreement&amp;rdquo; not an undertaking as Dr. K. V. Raman would name it. What more? They have even allowed him to run the affairs of the Temple itself, in their ecstatic moment. Thus leaving almost everything in his hands in good faith, they started going on tours of &amp;quot;&#xA;tours of &amp;ldquo;Sishyarjana&amp;rdquo;&#xA;periodically.&#xA;The judicial decisions in the second half of the 19th century will establish that Attan Jiyar and the scions of his family were running the administration of the Temple on behalf of the Tata- charyas until 1792, when one Rama Rao, the last of the Attan Jiyar family was dismissed by the then Collector for misbe- haviour. One Srinivasaragavachari a grand son by daughter of Tatacharya was appointed by the Government in 1794 to manage the affairs, as a deputy to Tatacharyas. Even this person&amp;rsquo;s term was terminated in 1796 and the Government took over the management under their direct control which lasted till 1842 when it was restored back to the Tatacharyas as the &amp;ldquo;original mirasdars&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Church-Wardens&amp;rsquo;) of the Temple30.&#xA;Still more fantastic, is the story that they were given this priority of honours by their undertaking to honour the Tenkalai traditions (mamul) of the Temple, as if there was such a tradi- tion. When a person is honoured on account of his worthiness nobody will take an undertaking from him. The author states here (Page 86 and 89) that this agreement or &amp;ldquo;undertaking&amp;rdquo; is the famous agreement known as Attan Jiyar Agreement and this &amp;ldquo;was signed by Ettur Immadi Lakshmikumara Tatacharya and delivered to Attan Jiyar&amp;rdquo;. This is not correct since &amp;ldquo;Sri Lakshmikumara Tatacharya&amp;rdquo; was not in the picture in 1711 A.D.&#xA;80&#xA;He lived between 1572 to 1632 A. D. One Lakshmikumara Tirumalai Tatacharya and some others were the signatories to it. This &amp;ldquo;Ettur Tirumalai Lakshmikumara&amp;rdquo; is an appella- tion and not a name by itself, and is prefixed to all the names of the descendants of Sri Lakshmikumara Tatadesika. Secondly, the presumption itself is wrong. As said above the Attan Jiyar had no such right or position&amp;rsquo; to confer the right of Agratambulam on Tatacharyas. It was the Tatacharyas, on the other hand who conceded to Attan Jiyar his request to recite, the Tanian of his Acharya as a return for his help in restoring back the idols. The history of the Tatacharyas in connection with the Temple and the influence they wielded as the spiritual preceptors of the Vijayanagar monarchs are all narrated in glowing terms by the chroniclers of history and the inscriptions found in several temples of South India. From at least the 15th Century A. D., these Acharya Purushas of an exalted line of the Vaishnavite hierarchs, prescribed the mode of worship and ri uals to be observed in the Temple, as the Srikaryams of the Temple affairs. While so, the author&amp;rsquo;s story on Page 86 of his book that Attan Jiyar, a newcomer in 1710 A. D. to Kanchi conferred the Agratambulam honours on the Tatacharyas after taking an undertaking from them that they would honour the Tenkalai tradition and mode of worship in the Temple, to say the least, is ridiculous. &amp;ldquo;The Tatacharyas connected with this Temple were very orthodox in the observance of religious rites and rituals to their meticulous prefection as precribed in the scriptures. The same system of observance has been handed down to their posterity and is still observed&amp;quot;3&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;Still more strange is author&amp;rsquo;s conclusion that because of some Arulappadu honours conferred on one Nallanchakravarthy of Srirangam who was a Tenkalai in 1713 A. D, &amp;ldquo;the Tenkalai preponderance in the temple is confirmed&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;What has this to do with the Tenkalai preponderance in the Temple ? Sri Sankara- charya, Sri Madvacharya and many other devotees were given privileges and honours in the Temple in lieu of their services to the Temple in the past. The Ahobilamath &amp;ldquo;Jivars &amp;quot; who are ardent Vadakalais are also honoured on certain occasions and honours and emoluments are even now sent with the TempleIC&#xA;U&#xA;U&#xA;AVA&#xA;U&#xA;244&#xA;U&#xA;Some of the Temple Paraphernalia (P. 81)&#xA;Sri Vishwaksenar&#xA;(P. 113)&#xA;Dwarapalakas at the Azhakiyasingar Vasal (III Entrance)&#xA;(P. 81)&#xA;Dwarapalakas on the Hastigiri (IV Entrance to the Garbagraham)&#xA;பெருமாள்கோவில்ஸ்லம்&#xA;(வீடகலை)-5&#xA;U&#xA;(P. 81)&#xA;Inscription &amp;ldquo;Perumal Koil Stalam-Vadamalai&amp;rdquo; on the Prakara of&#xA;Hastigiri&#xA;(P. 122)&#xA;Sita, Rama &amp;amp; Lakshmana (Mulavars &amp;amp; Utsavars) with Hanuman&#xA;(P. 81)&#xA;D&#xA;ல், சி&#xA;Entrance View of the Mirror Room&#xA;(P. 81)&#xA;81&#xA;paraphernalia on three occasions in the year even today, in memory of their past services. These cannot therefore indicate the predominance of any particular sect. The only criterion is the sect-mark worn by the Cheif Deity (Mulavar) and other, important deities of Gods enshrined in the Temple, like Sri Rama, Krishna, Narasimha, Varaha, Ranganatha, Karu- manicka Varada, Danvantrin, the Parijanas like Ananta, Garuda Vishwaksena, Dwarapalakas, Hanumans, Sudarsanalwar etc., the Paraphernalia, Vahanas, Utensils Curtains, Fans, Pillows etc. In this Temple all these have only Vadakalai marks. The first Tirtakars are admittedly the Vadakalai Tatacharyas. The Archaka Paricharakas who officiate in the pujas are all Vadakalais. The Vadakalai marks are carved, embossed, painted and displayed all over the fabric of the Temple boldly in places like Gopuras, Prakaras, Vimanas, Walls and Entrances. Many of them are stone cut namams (See Illustra- tions.) These are definitely indicative of the Vadakalai predominance in the Temple. But the author vainly puts up attempts to make out a case otherwise. The author wants us to understand that the Tenkalai mode of ceremonies and worship prevailed in the Temple by citing some documents32 connected with the litigation of the Temple. What are the modes of Tenkalai worship and what are&#xA;what are the Tenkalai ceremonies we fail to understand, despite the author&amp;rsquo;s parrot- like assertions without clarity or truth. Strictly speaking there can be no Tenkalai or Vadakalai mode of worship in a Temple. The worship is performed according to the Agamas which are neither Tenkalai nor Vadakalai. But we generally call a temple Vadakalai or Tenkalai on the basis of sectarian marks and those who officiate in the pujas. Even on this basis our Temple is definitely Vadakalai, as aforesaid. If the temple&amp;rsquo;s character is to be determined on the basis of service holders, the majority of the services like Vedaparayanam, Puranam reading, Stotra- patam, Mantrapushpam etc., are in the hands of the Vadakalais. The Tenkalais have only the Adyapakam service in which the Vadakalais also participate. The author&amp;rsquo;s case fails here also.&#xA;82&#xA;The author&amp;rsquo;s next item of the subject matter in this Chapter IV is &amp;quot; Vaishnava-Sect-Marks&amp;rdquo;. The author makes out a very big case for the preponderant Tenkalai sect marks in the Temple. These marks which the author delves from the ocean of Vadakalai marks in the Temple are comparable to a mouse and a mountain. As detailed above the innumerable Vadakalai marks all over the fabric of the Temple in the most prominent and important places, starting from the Chief Deity bear eloquent testimony to the Vadakalai character&#xA;and pre- dominance in the Temple. The so-called Tenkalai marks do not belong to the Vijayanagar period as alleged by the author. The Vijayanagar Kings were all Vadakalai Vaishnavaites and disciples of the Tatacharyas33. They would not have allowed or caused the Tenkalai marks to be displayed. The insignificant marks were surreptitiously introduced during the latter half of the 18th century by the scions of Attan Jiyar family when they had a free hand in running the affairs of the Temple in the absence of the leading Tatacharyas who tours of Sishyartanas. When these tamperings were noticed on their return, the Tatacharyas tried to wrest the management from Rama Rao the last scion of the family of the Jiyar. This man resisted and refused to hand over back the charge of the Temple to the Tatacharyas. Thereupon the Tatacharyas who were then popularly called the &amp;lsquo;Brahmins&amp;rsquo; by the authorities approached the Collector for removing him. The Collector finding Mr. Rama Rao, guilty of gross insubordination dismissed him in 1792 and appointed one Srinivasaragavachari to manage the Temple as a deputy of the Tatacharyas.&#xA;It will be interesting to note the observation of Mr. Balfour, the Collector, in this regard on 7th May, 1792. He says, &amp;ldquo;as far as I am enabled to judge from the different conversation I have had with Brahmins&amp;rsquo; and others regarding the disputants&amp;rsquo; claims to the Church-wardenship, I am led to believe the ancestors of those men whose names, I now enclose, were the original Church-Wardens and that the ancestors of Mr. Rama Rao were put in by the former as their Gumastha or Manager.&amp;rdquo; The names forwarded by the Collector were those&#xA;83&#xA;of the ancestors of the respondents, Sri Sudarsana Tatacharya Sri Viraragava Tatacharya and Sri Gopala Tatacharya, in a suit filed by one Appoo Row claiming Darmakartaship as the descendant of Attan Jiyar, in O. S. 5 of 1844 in the Jillah Court of Chingleput. The suit was dismissed and an appeal was preferred in the Court of Suddar Udalut in A. S. No. 29 of 1849. The appeal was also dismissed. The Jillah Judge while dismissing the suit of Appoo Row observes as follows: the whole it appears to the Civil Judge firstly that the Plaintiff has no right or title to the office of Darmakartha, some of his ancestors having officiated only as Gumasthas, secondly that the Defendants&amp;rsquo; ancestors, Tatachari having been in 1794 declared to be the rightful mirasdar by competent authority while also the Plaintiff or his father failed to institute proceedings within 12 years after the establishment of the Jillah Court, the Plaintiff&amp;rsquo;s claim even if he had shown a better one, than he has done would be barred by both sections 10 and 18, Regulation II of 1802.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;The Court of the Suddar Udalut in dismissing the appeal observes as follows: &amp;ldquo;From 1792 upto the present time the right and title of the appellant to the privilege he now lays claim to, has never been recognised. Whereas during the same period the members of the family of the respondents have been considered the lawful warden of the pagoda in question. In 1792 a violent dispute arose between two sects of Brahmins the Tenkalai and Vadakalai fomented entirely by the misconduct of one Rama Rao the Gumastha of the original mirasdar which ended in the disgrace of Rama Rao who was declared by the Government forever disqualified for the office of Church-warden and prevented from any future interference with the Church or any of its ceremony. It is through the connection this person then had with the pagoda, that the appellant now chiefly rests his claim to the office of Dharmakartha.&#xA;&amp;ldquo;All the authorities therefore for the last 57 years have had one opinion of the claims of the respondent&amp;rsquo;s family to the office he now holds, and on what grounds the appellants rests his hopes to dislodge them and obtain the appointment for himself, the Court fails to discover. The appellant&amp;rsquo;s exhibits&#xA;84&#xA;prove nothing in his favour whereas those of the respondents and the public records show most distinctly that their ancestors have always been considered and acknowledged to be the original mirasdars of the institution&amp;rdquo; A further appeal to the highest Court was also of no avail.&#xA;66&#xA;From the foregoing extracts it will be clearly seen that the few Tenkalai namams seen lurking in some insignificant places in the Temple represent the work of those who had opportunities to introduce them stealthily during the latter half of the 18th century. On the basis of such insignificant features of Tenkalai marks the author tries to make out that the Temple is a Tenkalai one. Another important factor that will belie the author&amp;rsquo;s assertion, in this regard, on Pages 85 and 89, can be noted while going through the report to the Government of Madras Archaeological Department.34 While describing the slab Bearing an inscription on both sides (639 of 1919) and embellished at its top with the Tenkalai Vaishnavite mark flanked on either side by a conch and a discus&amp;rdquo;, the report says in para 64 that &amp;ldquo;it is also one of the 12 items within the temple which bear this mark as distinguished from Vada- kalai which is the recognised mark of the TEMPLE and the God therein&amp;rdquo;. The italics is by us to show the indisputable nature or character of the Temple as Vadakalai. What else is required to show the utter uselessness and falsity of the claim of the author in this regard? We shall have occasion still further to prove the hollowness of this assertion in a later context. To recapitulate, the Tenkalai namams which the author mentioned both in writing and through photos carefully avoiding the Vadakalai namams, are the creations of the period when the Attan Jiyar&amp;rsquo;s heirs were looking after the affairs of the Temple in the absence of the prominent Tatacharya proprietors of the Temple during the second half of the 18th century. But even in these photos many Vadakalai marks appear.&#xA;In the concluding portion of this chapter the author once again repeats about the &amp;rsquo;two schools&amp;rsquo; and says that the Tenkalais who belong to the Prabandic school are more liberal in their outlook towards the caste system and the Vadakalais are&#xA;85&#xA;conservative. In what manner they were more liberal is the question. The Tenkalai Brahmins who claim to be liberal do not even allow the non-brahmin devotees who are well-versed in the Prabandas to join them in the recitation in their goshtis in the temples which are places of public worship not to speak of their disinclination to receive the prasadams in their company but yet they proclaim their catholicity vociferously, just to delude the uninformed, as already stated. And on this claim of their liberal outlook, the author says that &amp;ldquo;the vast majority of the temples of South India came under the spell of the eclectic Tenkalai school including the Varadarajaswamy Temple.&amp;rdquo; Absurdity can go no further. The author goes on repeating the same version of the Tenkalai predominance to the end by bringing forward the names of certain Jiyars and Tenkalai Tirtakars and the insignificant Tenkalai namams found in the Temple. We can only say that a lie cannot become a truth by repeating it several times. We have already pinpointed the fact that our Temple from the very ancient times has been only Vadakalai and continues to be so. We will have occasion to prove the Vadakalai character of the Temple during the course of this treatise in the succeeding chapters also with still more materials and force. Before concluding this chapter it may be relevant to relate some more instances which will clinch the issue and establish the Vadakalai predominance in the Temple. Sri Vedanta Desika, the great Acharya of the Vadakalai sect, has certain unique and special honours and privileges in the Temple which no other Alwar or Acharya has. On his birthday, the annual Tirunakshatram day of Purattasi-Sravanam-his deities enshrined both at Tuppul (a place about two miles from the Temple where his Avatara or birth took place) and in the Temple are the recipients of exclusive and extraordinary honours. The celebration of the daylong Mangalasasanam festival to Sri Tuppul Desika and the usual Sattumurai festival to the Temple Desika after that, are the two tell-tale evidence of the Vadakalai character of the Temple. Sri Andal&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Feast&amp;rdquo; at Sri Desika&amp;rsquo;s shrine on the Bogi Tiru-Kalyanam day with Alankara Tirumanjanam (Holy bath) Astanam, etc. from morning to evening may also be added to the list. (See also Appendix-D for full details).&#xA;86&#xA;In four instances, the author reveals that he did rely upon what others had told him. Among these, one is Appillar&amp;rsquo;s writing a commentary on the Sri Bashya (Page 70) which is, a news not heard of before by any Vaishnava scholars. The second (Page 71) is Krishna Misra&amp;rsquo;s defeat at the hands of Vedanta Desika. It is true that Mahacharya&amp;rsquo;s Vedanta Desika Vaibava Prakasika35 mentions this incident. This is not borne out by the periods when the two scholars flourished. Krishna Misra lived in the first half of the eleventh century while Vedanta Desika, two and a half centuries later. The third instance is his mentioning the admirer who wrote the Acharya. Champu without reference to his name (Page 72). The author of this work was Kousika Vedantacharya son of Venkatacharya36. So, the Acharyachampu and the Vaibava Prakasika do not contain anything like an acceptable and valid treatment for some of the incidents in Sri Desika&amp;rsquo;s life. It is not proper to dis- miss the statement found in the Vadakalai Guruparampara, for this may be taken to be directed against those who are jealous of Vedanta Desika&amp;rsquo;s eminence. Where is the evidence to take&#xA;the Tenkalais as meant here ?&#xA;It is also not correct to state that &amp;ldquo;the Tenkalai school in- stalled his image in almost all the Temples under their control and celebrated festivals for him&amp;rdquo;. First of all, as we had occa- sion to controvert the notion of Tenkalai (Prabandic) and Vadakalai (Sri Bashya) schools elsewhere in this book, there is no such division of schools during his time. It is very doubtful whether the Temples which the author claims to belong to his school were originally Tenkalai at all. On the other hand, it can very well be inferred that the Temples in which Sri Desika&amp;rsquo;s Deity is found installed should have been originally Vadakalai. It is also noteworthy that even the Temples of the so-called &amp;ldquo;Tenkalai School&amp;rdquo; of the present day are having the Desika&amp;rsquo;s idols with Vadakali mark only with one or two unfortunate exceptions. But even these one or two are of very recent conversion.&#xA;PART II-CHAPTER IV&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 PUJAS AND FESTIVALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/05_PUJAS_AND_FESTIVALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/05_PUJAS_AND_FESTIVALS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-V&#xA;PUJAS AND FESTIVALS&#xA;&amp;quot;&#xA;In this Chapter under Section 1-&amp;quot; Puja or worship Dr. K.V. Raman describes the procedure with regard to the ceremonial worship, again in his own way and as a true Tenkalai. The description in the first para of the &amp;lsquo;puja&amp;rsquo; is exactly a verbatim reproduction of the Adyapaka&amp;rsquo; case, reported in the 15 Madras weekly Notes, of our Temple. His fixation of time for Mantra pushpa service and the details about Stotrapata and Sevakalam all smack of the Tenkalai claims and allegations in the concerned litigations. Even then he errs in saying that Mantrapushpa is performed in the fifth asana whereas admittedly it is in the third asana or Alankarasana &amp;lsquo;.&#xA;•&#xA;Whatever it is, the fact that Dr. K. V. Raman has been openly canvassing for the cause of his sect in each and every part of this treatise&amp;rsquo;, in season and out of season, with or without context, has become plain by&#xA;now.&#xA;The author is not correct while making the statement that the Pancharatra literature was considered superior to the Vedas. A careful study of Pancharatra works reveals that the system is not held to be superior to the Vedas, nor anti-vedic as held by some scholars. In fact, many vedic mantras are bodily reproduced and recommended in the manuals, for use in the rituals! Again, the rituals in this Temple have been primarily governed by the Jayakhya Samhita adopting the Padma Samhita now and then for clarification. Some of the Archakas in the Temple have been following Padmasamhita.&#xA;It is also not correct to say that portions of the Prabandas are recited during the entire duration of Puja, for it is only on specified inner periods of the Puja, the Prábandas are recited.&#xA;44&#xA;Another factual error is his recital on page 97 about the &amp;lsquo;Holy Bath&amp;quot;. He says that it is done to Utsava-bera on the&#xA;7&#xA;•&#xA;90&#xA;day following New Moon and Full Moon days. This is not correct. It is done on Ekadasi days apart from the other days mentioned by him. These are called Panchaparva Utsavas in the Temple parlance. He next deals with the Divyaprabanda recital on pages 98 and 99. His admiration and praise for the recitation of the Prabandas need not be disputed.. Only thing is, he could have mentioned about the recitation of Vedas also, which is very special and important in this Temple. The vast concourse of Vedic reciters who are Vadakalais gather here voluntarily. The Vedic-goshti follows the Deity, during the grand Brahmotsava throughout the entire length and breadth of the procession the longest of its kind in the whole of India, both in the morning and evening, without any remuneration, out of devotion. In all the ordinary and other important festivals as well as festivals celebrated in places like Seevaram and Aiyangarkulam outside the town, they accompany the Deity throughout, day and night and end only when the Deity returns to the Temple without break.&#xA;Pavitrotsava and Adyayana Utsava are two other very important festivals where this Vedic congregation attracts the devotees both by its numbers and the melody of the recitation. Despite his unwillingness to mention this sacred and important Vedic recital along with the Divyaprabanda recital on pages 98 and 99, the author has to concede this on page 105 while describing the &amp;ldquo;Pavitrotsava &amp;quot; festival. In doing so, he commits certain flagrant mistakes. He refers to an epigraph which is said to attest to the celebration of this festival&amp;rdquo; even as early as 1521 A. D.&amp;quot; For this he cites inscription No. 346 of S.I.T.I.I under foot Note No. 39 on page 109. But this inscription does not mention anything about this festival. It is with regard to certain details of offering by the &amp;lsquo;Jiyar&amp;rsquo; of Ahobila Math, Secondly, he has wrongly stated that &amp;ldquo;the performance of this festival is referred to in a record of Achyutaraya dated 1533.&amp;rdquo; He cites the inscription No. 406 of S. I. T. 1. I under Foot Note No. 40. But it is 405 and the king mentioned therein is Sadasivaraya. The date of the record is also 1552 and not 1533, It is really amazing to see how such gross misleading errors have been allowed to occur in a Treatise&amp;rsquo; submitted and approved of for the award of Ph.D.&#xA;91&#xA;There is a graphic description in Tamil of this grand Vedaparayana goshti by a modern editor Sri A. K. Chettiar. He refers to the heat of the sun, strain of accompanying the Deity for the full length of the procession and their large number. He puts the number between 100 and 300 for the entire festival days. He admires their unlimited devotion and sincerity for rendering this service for which there is neither remuneration or any income nor any &amp;lsquo;prasadam&amp;rsquo; from the Temple. This is certainly Kainkarya par excellence, as it is done without expecting any reward in return and is carried out only to please God.2&#xA;Many of us still remember the number of such persons at about thousand in the thirties. Those who had the pleasure of simply accompanying the goshti still remember how even after the passing of the Deity in the procession people from streets adjoining the main street of the procession stay on and wait till the goshti passes through, bow to it and return home. This practice is observed even today,3&#xA;If Dr. K. V. Raman had been impartial he could not have afforded to omit to mention this most important service and feature of our Temple, alongside of the recital of Prabandas which is not continuous but partial in processions of the Deity. But the sectarian instinct in him got the better of him. It cannot be helped. It is true, that in our Temple both the goshtis are sincere and very enthusiastic in coming foward in their numbers for rendering the services. This is a special feature of our Temple which has got to be appreciated certainly and which cannot be found anywhere else.&#xA;Sri A. K. Chettiar has poetically represented the goshtis of the two kinds as the ministrels going in the front singing the titles and achievements of the King in procession and the Vedic Scholars invoking the blessings of God (Swasthivachana) for the welfare of the king by following Him.*&#xA;FESTIVALS&#xA;The festivals in the year starting from the Tamil month of Chittirai are described with the utmost care and precision one&#xA;92&#xA;by one.. The Tenkalai Acharya Manavalamamuni&amp;rsquo;s festival in Aipasi is glorified extensively. But what is noteworthy here is the glaring omission of. the Kartikai Anusham festival of Sri Tatadesika. This festival is celebrated for ten days and on the tenth day, the Tirunakshatram day of Sri Tatadesika, Sriperundevi Tayar and Lord Varadaraja are taken, to the shrine of Sri Tatadesika in the morning, adorned with all the precious jewels after a grand procession around the Alwar prakara with the big umbrellas and all other paraphernalia of the Temple. There are Satari honours during the starting of the procession to Sri Vedantadesika (Mulavar and Utsavar), Sri Tatadesika and Sri Ammangar. Then after the procession round the Alwar prakara, the Deities are alighted in the shrine after the &amp;ldquo;Darsana Tambulam&amp;rdquo; (reception ceremony) and a second time honours of garland and Satari to Sri Tatadesika. This time Sri Satari honours are shown first to Sri Desika&amp;rsquo;s Mulavar and Utsavȧr and garland and Satari honours are then shown to Sri Tatadesika and his consort Sri Ammangar. These honours will be taken with the gold and silver umbrellas, samarams, torches and &amp;ldquo;kattiyam&#xA;kattiyam&amp;rdquo; recitals.&#xA;In the mid-day there is an elaborate ceremonial Holy bath or Alankara Tirumanjana to Sri Perundevi Tayar and Lord Varadaraja when again the Tulasi and rose garlands of the Deities and Satari honours are shown to Sri Tatadesika and his consort with Sri Satari first to Sri Desika. In the afternoon. there is the grand Astanam to the Deities when the puja, with Mantrapushpa and Tiruppavai Sattumurai takes place. The Lord and Sri Perundevi will be adorned with many other precious jewels and lace cloths (vastras). Offerings of several kinds of delicacies will be made at this time. This worship will last for two to three hours. After the Nivedana, once again the garland and Satari honours will be repeated as described above. Then the Deities will be adorned with fresh flowers and big garlands. At about seven in the evening there will be a still more grand procession to the Lord upto the Tiruvadi Koil (Hanuman Temple) at the end of the Sannidi Street with great pomp and splendour. On return the Lord will wait at the Gopuravasal till Sri Tayar who had remained at the&#xA;The Divyadampatis on the Sattumurai Day of Sri Tatadesika at the Latter&amp;rsquo;s Shrine&#xA;(P. 92)&#xA;Mangalasasanam of Sri Tuppul Desika in the Mirror Room&#xA;(P. 85)&#xA;Sri Tatadesika Blessed by the Divine Couple with Parivattam, Garlands and Thagadi, on His Birthday&#xA;(P. 93)&#xA;:93&#xA;•&#xA;shrine; joins Him and then Both are taken in procession once  ́again round the Alwar prakara. Before alighting at the shrine there will be the usual Veda Sattumurai and Satari honours to Sri Desika, Sri Tatadesika and Sri Ammangar. Then the final Tiruvaradana, with Mantrapushpa and Tiruvaymozhi Sattumurai and Nivedana, will take place and this time apart from the garlands and Sri Satari, Lace Duppatta (Thagadi) and parivattam honours will be shown to Sri Tatadesika and Sri Ammangar preceded by. Satari to Sri Desikar, After the distribution of Tirta and Prasadas, the Lord and Sri Perundevi will leave the shrine, in the early hours of the next morning after bestowing the final honours. The Malai-matral (the exchange of garlands between Sri Tayar and Sri Perumal) is another unique feature during the course of this festival. There will be the ceremony of &amp;ldquo;Padiyetram&amp;rdquo; when they get down the steps of the shrine, with the burning of camphor and &amp;ldquo;Kattiyam&amp;rdquo; (stotras in praise of the Lord) for four or five times. The unique and spectacular Darsana (Sight) of the Divine Couple without garland and &amp;lsquo;prabai&amp;rsquo; at this juncture will be thrilling and soul stirring. It will be a futile exercise to attempt to describe this exquisite spectacle by words or writing. One has to enjoy and worship this occasion only personally in order to realise the uniqueness in its fullness. We have been compelled to narrate this Sattumurai festival of Sri Tatadesika in such a great detail to show how this very important and big festival has been completely omitted and ignored wantonly by Dr. K. V. Raman in this chapter, whereas he describes in minute detail all other festivals of the year and especially that of his Acharya Manavala Mamuni.&#xA;One more point that has got to be mentioned about the Sattumurai festival of Sri Tatadesika is that both Sri Perundevi and Lord Varadaraja are taken to the shrine of Sri Tatadesika on his Sattumurai day whether the day is Friday or any other day of the week, whereas for the Sattumurai festivals of all the other Alwars and Acharyas both will be taken only if the Sattumurai festival falls on a Friday. This is because of the fact that Sri Tatadesika is the Lakshmikumara&amp;rsquo; and Sri Tayar has to be necessarily taken to Her son&amp;rsquo;s shrine along with the Lord on his birth day.&#xA;6&#xA;*94&#xA;Further, the Lord or Both, (if it is a Friday) will be taken to the shrine of the Alwars or Acharyas only in the evening of their Sattumurai day, unlike Sri Tatadesika&amp;rsquo;s Sattumurai, when They are taken in the morning itself followed by an elaborate ceremony of two processions Alankara Tirumanjanam, two Astanams etc., for a full day. The Thagadi Bahumanam (honour) mentioned above is done exclusively to Sri Tatadesika and Sri Tuppul Desika alone, on their Annual Tirunakshatram days.&#xA;Apart from the non-mention of this grand festival, the author did not choose to mention the Ganda ppodi Vasanta Utsava on the day following the Panguni Uttiram festival, which is used to be attended by a vast gathering. Likewise, the author should not have missed referring to the festival as described in Hamsasandesas. The beautiful fast moving procession of the Lord to the car festival and the Irattaippurappadu festivals with the Goddess Perundevi on Panchaparva days when they happen to be Fridays could have also been mentioned.&#xA;At least three erroneous statements are found made on Page 103. The Deity is not given a bath in a tub on the eighth day of Brahmotsava, but only the Holy Feet of the Lord and His Consorts are dipped in the sacred saffron water kept in a big silver tub. On the tenth day night, the procession is through the streets around the Temple. Vedanta Desika did not specially&amp;quot; mention Garudotsava, for other vehicles also get mentioned along with Garuda.&amp;quot;.&#xA;In a work exclusively devoted to the treatment of this Temple and a Chapter which is devoted to the treatment of festivals it is quite essential to describe why the festivals are grand in the Temple. In all processions, from the elephant and horse in the front and Vedaparayanam in the rear, everything in this Temple is grand and unique. Mention must be made of a peculiar instrument of music accompaniment called &amp;lsquo;Surya Vadya&amp;rsquo; played upon in the vicinity of God. The sound of Tirucchinnam, which is only one in this Temple, has a sweetness, the like of which is not available anywhere else. It is observed that this sound is not to be had for any Deity in any Temple&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;While every part in the procession contributes to the overall attractiveness, it is the Deity that is the centre of·&#xA;95&#xA;enchantment. The person of the Lord is by Itself captivating in Its unadorned state. Embellishments do enhance this artless charm. A carefully made selection of the ornaments with the aim of maintaining a happy blending of their role with the natural beauty of the Lord is attempted on every occasion and Brahmotsava, in particular. The skill of the Archakas in the decoration of the Lord has also got to be appreciated here. The Lord appears new and new and more and more attractive on every occasion. The garlands are sparingly used to the extent the Conch and Discus could contain. The only other Temple where this is practised is the one at Srirangam. Such is the enthralling impression created in the devotees which makes them remain with the Lord as long as they can.&#xA;Evidently Dr. K. V. Raman had no occasion to observe these specific features of the festivals in this Temple. This chapter has thus lost its importance without the depiction of these festivals and features.&#xA;PART II-CHAPTER V&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 HISTORY OF MANAGEMENT</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/06_HISTORY_OF_MANAGEMENT/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/06_HISTORY_OF_MANAGEMENT/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-VI&#xA;FUNCTIONARIES AND HISTORY OF MANAGEMENT&#xA;The theory of Tenkalai predominance in the Temple is again canvassed in this chapter by projecting the image of Alagiya Manavala Jiyar and other Tenkalai functionaries who had some connection or other with the Temple in the past. Functionaries like Stanattar, Bandarattar, Karanattan etc. are all described in great detail while safely leaving aside the sustained and continued connection, management and influence wielded by the Tatacharyas in the Temple at least from the 15th century A. D. This is as it should be, since the main aim of the &amp;ldquo;author in this Treatise&amp;rsquo; is to make out a case for the Tenkalai character of the institution. We have already dealt with this wrong assumption earlier. Such a theory of predominance in our Temple is but a figment of the author&amp;rsquo;s imagination without any historical inscriptional or even a traditional basis.&#xA;6&#xA;Dr. K. V. Raman could not at the same time avoid mentioning and. recognising the important role of the Tatacharyas in the Temple. The facts and figures stare so glaringly, that he had perforce mention them, while at the same time trying to belittle and under-estimate their services and influence as far as possible. This can be observed by his remarks at page 123. of this chapter wherein he says &amp;ldquo;The Tatacharya almost lived in royal splendour and could even in one of his inscriptions boast of performing eleven Tulabaras along with his eleven wives! Whether this could have been possible at a time when the Vijayanagar Kingdom lost its glory as Kings Sriranga I and Venkata II were ruling from Chandragiri over a crippled territory threatened by hostile forces is indeed doubtful. But it would be however taken to show the general affluent position of the Tatacharya which enabled him to do many beneficial acts to the Temple like the recoating of the Punyakoti Vimana with gold, the construction of the Vimana over the Tayar Shrine, the presentation of many Vahanas or vehicles&amp;rdquo;. We are really very much amused at this remark&#xA;91&#xA;and reminded of an old story of the pond-frog doubting the story of its friend the sea frog about the vastness of the sea. Though the Vijayanagar Empire had a rude shock by the battle of Talikota in 1565 A. D., it never declined or was crippled irretrievably till the middle of the 17th century. The heirs of Tirumala of Aravidu dynasty were able to hold out in tact the Empire from another capital farther south. Dr. Krishnaswamy Aiyangar says: &amp;ldquo;It is a well-known fact that the Empire of Vijayanagar did suffer vital injury at the so-called battle of Talikota much more fittingly Rakshasathangadi&amp;rsquo; in 1565. The Empire held out in tact, though from another capital further to the south and much better placed for defence against the enemies, in Penugonda. Hiri Timmaraya (Tirumala) shifted his capital to Penugonda. He died here leaving three sons, Srirangaraya, Ramaraya and Venkatapatiraya. Sriranga ruled from Penugonda, nominally the whole of Telugu country. Ramaraya had for his share the Kannada country with capital at Srirangapatnam. Venkatapatideva ruled from Chandragiri over the largest portion as would appear viz., over the Tonda, Chola and Pandya Mandalams. After the death of his brothers, the whole Empire devolved upon Venkatapatiraya&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;The last great ruler who can ever be credited with having succeeded to a great extent in bringing the Empire back to its original greatness was the great Venkatapatiraya, Venkata I of Vijayanagar&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; Dr. A. Krishnaswamy also testifies to the fact of the Empire continuing to exist with great splendour and glory for more than half a century under the Vijayanagara rulers, Tirumala, Sriranga and Venkata I after Talikota2. This will go to show how the Emipre was held in tact even beyond its original greatness by Venkata I, the royal disciple of Sri Tatadesika, after the battle of Talikota, and the Empire was not a &amp;ldquo;crippled territory&amp;rdquo; as described by Dr. K. V. Raman.&#xA;The author&amp;rsquo;s own version on page 33 will contradict his comment that it was &amp;ldquo;a crippled territory&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;a crippled territory&amp;rdquo;. He says here &amp;ldquo;the reign of Venkata which lasted for nearly three decades was marked by a revival of strength and prosperity of the Empire &amp;ldquo;. Venkata I&amp;rsquo;s Empire extended up to even Ceylon. Another telling piece of evidence to the fact that the Vijayanagara&#xA;8&#xA;કુંવ&#xA;98&#xA;•&#xA;Empire was restored back to more than its original glory after the battle of Talikota can be had from the following description. Venkata II.was the greatest sovereign of the Aravidu dynasty, a man of ability and character. By his military genius and statesmanship, he succeeded in retaking the lands that had been lost in the days of his predecessor. He raised the status of the Empire in the eyes of the foreigners, so that several embassies visited Chandragiri in 1604 and presented themselves at his He was also in direct correspondence with Philip III of Spain. According to one Portuguese reporter he was a lord of great authority, prudence and understanding as much as any European. Almost all the Portuguese and Hindu authorities pay a tribute to his wisdom and valour his generosity and love of learning. He was not behind any ruler of Vijayanagara in his liberal donations to Brahmins and temples etc., etc.&amp;ldquo;4 Another remark of the author for which we take exception is, that &amp;ldquo;Tatacharya could even in one of his inscriptions boast of performing eleven Tulabaras&amp;rdquo; etc. Sri Tatacharya never boasted nor inscribed the inscriptions himself. It is the work of his royal and other disciples, subsequent to the events mentioned in them. King Venkatapati gave his whole Kingdom to his guru Tatacharya who managed to have eleven tulabaras out of such bounteousness.&amp;rdquo; It is most unjust, and uncharitable to make such a remark, about that great soul who merited the exalted. position of deification in our Temple.&#xA;&amp;quot;&#xA;The persistent assertion that the &amp;ldquo;Stalattars of the Temple are all Tenkalais, is yet one more piece of the perverted story of the author in this portion of the Treatise&amp;rsquo;. In our Temple, the Stalattars&amp;rdquo; are all Vadakalais. They are five in number. The first are the Tatacharyas. The second and third are the Archakas and Paricharakas. The fourth and the fifth are the Mudaliars and Karnams who are respectively the Sripadam- tangis and accountants. The first three are Brahmins and the last two are non-Brahmins: Among the Karñams, there are a few who wear the Tenkalai sect-mark also. But the majority of them are Vadakalais. The honours and privileges shown to these Stalattars on occasions, can be seen from the Temple records (Registers).&#xA;99&#xA;One such record is the Stala-Varahan&amp;rsquo; account. When Mata- tipatis like Ahobila Swami, Sankaracharya, Madvacharya visit the Temple, they deposit a certain amount called Stala-Varahan into the Temple treasury. The same will be distributed to the Stalattars in a certain proportion. Similarly, in the case of a new Mandapapadi, where Sri Perumal is made to stay for a small time the Ubayakars of these Mandapapadis will have to deposit a certain amount (Stala Varahan) before Sri Swami is taken to the place. Be it as it may. The author&amp;rsquo;s assertion that the Stalattars are Tenkalais is therefore patently wrong.&#xA;Dr. Raman has taken pains to report in detail &amp;ldquo;the Functionaries in the Temple&amp;rdquo; here. He writes, that &amp;ldquo;the most highly respected spiritual or religious dignitaries who were in charge of the proper conduct of the religious ceremonies, worship and other procedures were the-Jiyars&amp;rdquo;. This is not borne out by the evidence of history or the inscriptions. Alagia Manavala Jiyar was only attending to the work of Srikaryam.&amp;rdquo; He is of course stated to be well-versed in Vedanta&amp;rsquo; but the undated inscription does not tell us whether this was the Jiyar of an earlier period. It is quite possible that he alone is meant8: Yet he or his successors are simply referred to as Jiyar, while the Tatacharyas9 and the Ahobila Math Swamisio are referred to as &amp;lsquo;Srimad- vedamarga pratishtapanacharya ubhaya vendantacharya&amp;rsquo;, the latter having&amp;rsquo; paramahamsaparivrajakacharya&amp;rsquo; in addition, that is due to an ascetic order. While these epithets are not used with reference to Alagia Manavala Jiyar, it is not proper to describe the Jiyars as the most highly respected, spiritual or religious dignitaries, as far, at least, as our Temple is concerned. The Tatacharyas and other families like those of Nallan Chakravarti, Kandadai, Kidambi, Nadadur have been at Kanchi centuries before Alagia Manavala Jiyar Math came into existence. Is it not improper to imagine that the members of these familes of Acharyapurushas are not respected with Temple honours?&#xA;Lastly, it is not correct to say that the first person to hold the post of Manager in this Temple was Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyangar in 1538 A. D. The post of the Temple agent or Manager was held by Ramanuja Thiruppanippillai in 1535 A. D.&amp;rdquo; It is not proper even to assert that Thiruppanippillai&#xA;100&#xA;was the first person to hold this post. On the strength of inscriptional evidence, we can only note what was obtained then. There is no, evidence to show that the post of Srikaryam was created then in the Temple for the first time.&#xA;In the last portions of this chapter, he has been narrating the history of management of the Temple twisting it in his usual manner, about the period from 1645 A. D. to the present day. We are also presenting an account of this period based on history, inscriptions and records below, for a correct assessment by the readers.&#xA;Though the Vijayanagar Empire declined during the middle of the 17th century the Temple did not feel the impact of it. It was already well provided for and improved in all respects by the tireless efforts of Sri Lakshmikumara Tatadesika. But in the last quarter of the 17th century, there appeared a danger in the form of the iconoclastic zeal of Aurangazeb.&#xA;The Tatacharya custodians secreted the Utsavar Idols of Lord Varadaraja and Nachiars in Udayarpalayam for safety in or about 1688 A. D. They had to put up with this unavoidable grief of parting with the object of their devotion and adoration for more than two decades. This agony was further heightened when in or about 1710 A.D. they tried to bring back the Idols, the Zamindar of Udayarpalayam, refused to part with them, captivated by the divine beauty of the Idols.&#xA;One Attan Jiyar a Telugu Vaishnavite Sanyasin had come to Kanchi at that time, fleeing Golkonda, his original home, on account of the sacking of the place by the forces of Aurangazeb, which killed the brothers Akkanna and Madanna, his rela- tives12. He had a disciple called Todarmalla who was a general under Sadat- Ullah- Khan, the Nawab of the Karnatic. On hearing about this Jiyar, the Tatacharyas approached him for help. The Jiyar readily agreed and eventually restored back the Idols, through his disciple Todarmalla who went to Udayarpalayam with a contingent of force and forced the Zamindar to part with the Idols.&#xA;101&#xA;The Tatacharya proprietors of the Temple in their exhuber- ance, granted the wish of the Jiyar to recite his Acharya&amp;rsquo;s Tani- yan in the beginning of the Prabandam recital. The agreement (Udanpadika) in Telugu which is said to have been entered into with the Jiyar by the Tatacharyas, allowing the Taniyan of Mana- vala Mamuni in the beginning of the Prabandas, is popularly called the &amp;ldquo;Attan Jiyar Agreement&amp;rdquo;.12 The Tatacharyas, had even allowed him to look after the affairs of the Temple and run the administration during their absence on tours of Sishyar-&#xA;tanas.&#xA;After Attan Jiyar, his daughter Papammal also was running the affairs of the Temple. The Tatacharyas in those days, when there was absolutely no animosity or rancour between these two sects, allowed her and the heirs of the Jiyar full freedom in the matter of running the affairs of the Temple. on their behalf. They were absent on most of the time during the year, busy with their tours and fully complacent with the position of the Temple thinking that they had safely entrusted it into competent and faithful hands. In this, they were completely mistaken, as proved by subse- quent events in the years that followed. This state of affairs continued upto the last decade of the eighteenth century. The complete faith placed by them in the family of Attan Jiyar in attending to the Temple affairs turned out to be a misplaced one. Subsequent to Attan Jiyar the scions of his family made many inroads into the original Vadakalai features of the Temple and also introduced many Tenkalai features. The Tatacharyas, did not notice the changes in the beginning. But gradually when they were able to find them out and wanted to wrest back the power of administration from the hands of the man in charge at that time, they faced opposition. Mr. Rama Rao who was then at the helm and who was a distant relative of the Attan Jiyar family refused to part with the powers claiming that he was there as of right and was not to be disturbed. Thereafter the Tatacharyas had to approach the Collector to dislodge him. It was in 1792 that when the grand Brahmotsava was fast appro- aching, they preferred a petition to Mr. Balfour, the Collector, requesting his intervention and praying that he may prevent Mr. Rama Rao from proceeding with the arrangements for the festival&#xA;102&#xA;which they urged would cause breach of the peace, if allowed. The Collector issued instructions to Rama Rao not to proceed with the arrangements, pending disposal of the complaints before him. But Rama Rao without paying any heed to the Collector&amp;rsquo;s order was proceeding with his own arrangements for the festival. This was duly reported to the Collector who at once ordered his removal in a disgraceful manner by beat of tom tom. One Srini- vasaragavachari, a grandson of Tatacharya by daughter, was appointed in his place as the Manager of the Temple by the Collector, on his undertaking to manage the affairs of the Temple on behalf of Tatacharyas. Till 1796 every thing went off well. But there were complaints again against this person also. So in 1796 the Government terminated the services of this person also and took over the administration of the Temple directly through their Collectors. In describing the particulars between 1792 to 1796 the author gives a twisted version even here, by defending Rama Rao and finding Srinivasaragavachari guilty of gross mismanage- ment. Whatever it be, the Government of the East India&amp;rsquo; Company was administering the Temple directly through its Collectors from 1796 to 1842. The first such Collector was Mr. Place who is credited with the presentation of some valuable head-ornaments to our Lord. There was one Collector by name Hodgson in the first quarter of the 19th century whose name was perpetuated, till very recently, in Kanchipuram, by the big bazaar, where the Temple&amp;rsquo;s car stand. is situated, being named after him, as Hodgsonpet. After the attainment of Independence by India in 1947, the name of the bazar has been changed as Gandhi Road. There were two other Collectors by name Henry Vivash and Hyde whose names also appear in our Temple records in the beginning (first quarter) of the last century. In 1842, the East India Company, in pursuance of its policy to give up all sorts of interference with the religious institutions handed over back the Temple to its &amp;ldquo;original mirasdar&amp;rdquo; Sri Kumara Tatacharya as the hereditary trustee. Before handing over the administration of the Temple to Sri Kumara Tatacharya, the Government had called for applications from the original trustees of all the temples. After considering all the applications carefully the Government came to the conclusion that the Tata- charyas were the &amp;ldquo;original church-wardens&amp;rdquo; of the Temple and&#xA;103&#xA;rejected the applications of the Tenkalais and the heirs of Attan Jiyar. The facts relating to the several applications and the ultimate decision of the Board of Revenue, are dealt with in detail in Part I of this book regarding the history of the Tatacharyas in connection with the Temple.&#xA;FOOT NOTES&#xA;PART II-CHAPTER VI&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 TEMPLE AND SOCIETY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/07_TEMPLE_AND_SOCIETY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/07_TEMPLE_AND_SOCIETY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-VII&#xA;THE TEMPLE AND SOCIETY&#xA;4&#xA;The pet-concept of Dr. K. V. Raman about Attiyur&amp;rsquo; as a village originally unconnected with Kanchi, his unfailing mention of the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar as an important personage of the Temple in almost all the Chapters of this book except perhaps one or two, his theory regarding the Tenkalai- Vadakalai cult and tenets especially his claim that the Tenkalais are more liberal and catholic in their outlook towards the caste-system than the Vadakalais and their championing &amp;ldquo;the cause of the Tamil language and the Tamil Hymns&amp;rdquo; are the main features of this chapter. They are almost controversial unacceptable and baseless. These points were already answered by us earlier. He has once again brought forward the names of some Tenkalai personages to show their predominance in the Temple. Additional materials and new factors alone may improve a certain theory and not repetitions. The author brings Chakra- vartiar, Vinjimur and Gomadattar families and others under Tenkalai group. There is no justification for this hasty conclusion. While it is hardly possible to prove that this distinction was obtained in the earlier period, i. o., before 1500 A. D., it is still more difficult to bring some of the Acharyapurusha families exclusively under one sect. What is noticed at Kanchi at present regarding the identity of some of these sects should not be advanced as a sound evidence to declare all those who belonged to these families were originally members of only that sect. Unbiased deliberation is very much required to take up these issues and caution should guide while drawing conclusions.&#xA;Another interesting portion of this chapter is his description of the &amp;lsquo;Maths in our temple&amp;rsquo; in ancient times and one such Math is &amp;ldquo;Vedamath&amp;rdquo; of the Madwacharyas Vyasatirta, and Satyavijayatirta who have evinced interest in this Temple and honoured with certain privileges. He has also mentioned about105&#xA;the former who was held in high respect by King Krishna- devaraya. These leaders of the Dwaita School, who are treated casually by the author, are in no way less important or less influential in those days than the Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyan or Alagiya Manavala Jiyar in respect of their services in securing certain gifts to the Temple and acquiring honours and privileges to themselves. One of the important ornaments a pendant made of precious stones, called Satya-Purna Swamy Padakkam, is even now adorned to the Deity on important occasions. The Serpent-vehicle and a village called Pulambakkam towards the celebration of a festival in the month of Avani, was got by Vyasatirta through Krishnaraya&amp;rsquo; in Saka 1433 (1511 A. D.) and certain privileges were bestowed upon Satya Vijayatirta2.&#xA;Another important Math which contributed towards the improvement of the Temple during the 16th century is, that of the Ahobila Math which is purely a Vadakalai one. Three villages were gifted by Parankusa Jiyar and Van Satagopa Jiyar and the latter&amp;rsquo;s Kaisikapurana reading and receiving the emoluments during the time of Achyutarya.&amp;rsquo; is mentioned in an inscription. &amp;ldquo;The Jiyars of Ahobila Math appear to have played an important part in extending the influence of Vaishnavism. Van Satakopa Jiyar, the founder of the Math seems to have been closely in touch with the religious life in the court. He was the guru of the great poet, Alasani Peddanna, the poet laureate of Krishnadevaraya.” This important Math has been omitted in the particular context where the other Maths of the Tenkalai sect have been included. The Alagia Manavala Math situated in the East Mada Street behind the Temple, is mentioned as having been attached to the Temple, without stating in what manner it is so. Its existence and continuance as a centre of religious and philosophical studies&amp;rsquo; even today, as mentioned here, on page 137 is quite contrary to facts. It is almost locked most of the time and if and when a. Jiyar comes to camp here from Mysore which is its headquarters, he is forced to become a party, to some litigation or other in the Tenkalai-Vadakalai disputes. This is the only contribution and activity of the Head of the Math in the religious and philosophical fields as far as Kanchipuram and our Temple is concerned. It will be interesting to note&#xA;C&#xA;106&#xA;that these Jiyars who are eulogised by Dr. K. V. Raman as having supreme position in the past in the Temple do not have any privileges in the Temple, whereas the Ahobila Math, Vyasaraya Math and Sankara Math have certain exclusive honours and privileges even now. The Ahobila Math receives on three occasions in the year honours and emoluments from the Temple including the Annual Tirunakshatram day of Sri Adi-Van-Satakopa Swamy, the founder of the Math. The only Tenkalai Jiyar that has certain honours in the Temple is that of the Vanamamalai Math. But this Math has not the fortune to find a place in the author&amp;rsquo;s account whereas a non- existent Math (Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyan Math) and the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar Math which are in no way connected with our Temple are given undue prominence in the Treatise&amp;rsquo; The hollowness of the claim on the basis of such flimsy and unrealistic fiction, that our Temple is Tenkalai, can be easily understood.&#xA;·&#xA;As pointed out under chapter IV that even when mentioning the existence of the Kandadai, Paravastu and Tiruvengada Jiyar, they are only likened to the names of &amp;ldquo;important Vaishnavite families like the Tatacharyas of Conjivarams&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyangar was a preceptor of the Sattada Vaishnavas and this is not a proof to declare him to have been himself a Sattada Vaishnava. If Kandadai Ramanuja Aiyangar was a Sattada Vaishnava as stated by the author on page 132, how did he have the family name Kandadai which is exclusively had by the descendants of Mudaliyandan ? Careless writings give rise to these problems.&#xA;PART II-CHAPTER VII&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 ARCHITECTURE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/08_ARCHITECTURE/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/08_ARCHITECTURE/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-VIII&#xA;ARCHITECTURE&#xA;The theory that &amp;ldquo;Hastigiri&amp;rsquo; is an artificial mound and an elevated platform is once again harped upon in para 2 of this chapter. The dates of the second stage of the construction of the Temple, which includes the Sanctum Sanctorum on the Hill and Sri Narasimha&amp;rsquo;s shrine below, are fixed to the regime of the Chola Kings Rajathiraja-I and Kulothunga I, in the 11th and 12th centuries A. D. The greater constructional activity during the succeeding Vijayanagara period like the Kalyana, Tulabara, Unjal and Vasanta Mantapas are also detailed, as also the Gopura in the east. Then he goes on describing the architecture one by one starting from the first prakara.&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;rdquo;&#xA;On page 149 under &amp;ldquo;first prakara&amp;rdquo;, the Punyakoti Vimana (Fig. 4)&amp;quot; is described as having &amp;ldquo;completely been renovated and replastered in the thirties of the present century, thus obliterating all the old features&amp;rdquo;. This statement is entirely wrong. The renovation took place, when the Temple was under the management of a Smarta Receiver, a common person appointed by the District Judge in 1929 pending the Scheme suit in OS-I of 1928. He was in sole charge of the administration. Considering the sectarian disputes and controversies in the Temple the Receiver. Sri C. Somasundara Aiyar, under the orders of the District Judge, took photos and details of the structures, had them signed by all the parties concerned in the presence of common persons and sent it to the Judge for his approval. The District Judge directed the Receiver to see to it that the original features of the structures as submitted by him are in no way changed or obliterated by the renovation. The renovation was effected, strictly in accordance with the above direction and the above list prepared by the Receiver with regard to its original features without any change. Dr. K. V. Raman evidently has his own reasons to state that all the old features of the Vimana were obliterated by the renovation. The main irritant to his eyes is the existence of a bold Vadakalai mark flanked by Sankum and&#xA;108&#xA;Chakaram on both sides, built in brick and mortar on the &amp;ldquo;Punyakoti Vimana&amp;rdquo; Evidently because of this he has taken his figure No. 4 from the back portion of the Vimana instead of the front one, since the latter will display the Vadakalai mark prominently. We are now giving the illustration of the front portion of the Vimana in this book. The four garudas on the four sides of the Vimana also have Vadakalai marks on their faces. Another point that has to be noted here, is his mention, about the &amp;ldquo;epigraph that Krishnadevaraya covered this Punyakoti Vimana with gold some time in A. D. 1514&amp;rdquo;. Here he has left out purposely the repairing and regilding of the Vimana by Sri Tatadesika, though he himself has to admit it on page 83 under &amp;ldquo;Tatacharya family&amp;rdquo; that Sri Tatacharya &amp;ldquo;repaired and regilt the Vimanam set up by Krishnadevaraya as it got defaced and weather beaten in the course of a century&amp;rdquo;. If the latter renovation, by Sri Tatadesika in mentioned in this context it will clearly establish the existence of the Vadakalai features of the Vimana which the author wants to avoid. As the author himself has stated earlier on page 87, the Vijayanagar Kings started the practice of putting the sectarian marks on the structures. Vadakalai marks were carved in the Temples renovated and on the slabs, put on, mentioning gifts or offerings, during the reign of Sadasivadeva Maharaya, the Vijayanagar ruler. As a great Vadakalai Acharya Sri Tata- desika with the patronage of the Vijayanagar Kings who were particular in putting the sectarian marks could not have omitted to put the Vadakalai mark on the Vimana which is a most suitable and essential place for displaying the mark. But the author by his remarks here, wants to make it appear that something new has been introduced during the renovation of the Vimana in the thirties of this century. Hence his careful omission of the renovation of the Vimana by Sri Tatadesika in early 17th century A. D. in this context.&#xA;Even Krishnadevaraya, who was a staunch Vaishnava and a disciple of &amp;ldquo;Tatacharya&amp;rdquo; could not have omitted. to put this sectarian mark when he effected the repairs in 1514 A. D.&#xA;In describing Perundevi Tayar shrine on page 153, he fixes the date of its coming into existence in the beginning of the 13th century and its subsequent replacement during the end of the&#xA;Inside View of the Mirror Mansion&#xA;A View of the Punyakoti Vimanam&#xA;(P. 108)&#xA;(P. 108)&#xA;Danvantrin&#xA;(P. 115)&#xA;Tiruvanantalwar&#xA;(P. 111)&#xA;109&#xA;15th century. We are not sure about this also. Improvements might have been effected at various periods. But to fix a particular time for its (the shrine&amp;rsquo;s) coming into existence viz., the 13th century, may not correspond to reality and also not proper. Sri Perundevi Tayar is enshrined along with Sri Varada- raja from time immemorial in this Temple. The Kalyana-Koti Vimana&amp;rsquo;s architectural features&amp;quot; are said to be &amp;ldquo;masked by copper sheets&amp;rdquo;. The copper plates are designed totally to fit in with the original features of the Vimana and therefore there is no question of their being masked&amp;rsquo; or hidden. The author cannot be expected to know about this, since he is not conversant with all these minute particulars of the Temple.&#xA;C&#xA;The usual repetition of Alagiya Manavala Jiyar as the archi- tect of the front Mahamantapa of the Tayar Shrine is made under the heading &amp;ldquo;Vijayanagar Mandapas&amp;rdquo;. It may be once for all stated here with all the emphasis at our command, that wherever the Vijayanagar Architecture is to be found in the Temple, it is the work of the Tatacharyas alone who were the acknowledged royal gurus of the Vijayanagar rulers and to whom alone the royal patronage was extended for undertaking these works.&#xA;Next comes the heading &amp;ldquo;Gopura Entrance and the Compound Wall&amp;rdquo; on page 154. The &amp;ldquo;Todarmal Vasal&amp;rdquo; which is mentioned by him is called &amp;ldquo;Thondaradippodi Vasal&amp;rdquo;. The reconstruction of the compound wall (prakara) enclosing the third prakara, according to the author, is said to have been done by the Alagiya Manavala Jiyar. Earlier we had occasion to show in dealing with chapter III, that it was not so. There was no necessity to reconstruct it since it was originally built so strongly and solidly. This is also attested by an epigraph3.&#xA;In order to connect the name of Alagiya Manavala Jiyar, in each and every item of the structure of the Temple in his narrative, the author took this also as one more opportunity. The portrait figures which are said to be kept in small niches at the top of this compound wall is described by him, as belonging to this Jiyar. There is no warrant or basis for this assumption also. If at all, it may be the work of the Attan Jiyar family who introduced several innovations during the period between&#xA;110&#xA;1711 to 1792 A. D. At any rate Alagiya Manavala Jiyar has no place or any sustained connection with the Temple, as sought to be made out by the author. One more interesting factor, that can be deduced from this, is the most insignificant and shady places where the author claims the existence of the Tenkalai features in this Temple. If they are true they would have been displayed in the front and prominent portions of the Temple. Not a single place is important, prominent or sacred, where these Tenkalai features are alleged to exist in our Temple. This is a clear proof of their stealthy introduction. Some of these which lurked during the course of the litigations in later times had been permitted to remain, due to their existence previously for sometime. This however cannot give the impress of Tenkalai predominance in the Temple.&#xA;&amp;ldquo;The Krishna Shrine&amp;rdquo; mentioned on page 155 is called &amp;ldquo;Venugopalan Sannidhi &amp;quot; and not as &amp;ldquo;Krishna Shrine&amp;rdquo; though both can mean the same. The author at the end of this chapter repeats the bogey of the artificial mound for &amp;ldquo;Hastigiri&amp;rdquo; while at the same time recognising its being sung by Kuratalwar, Tiru- kkachinambi etc., as a Hill. We need not go into this question once again, as we have already answered it earlier in chapter III to show that &amp;ldquo;Hastigiri&amp;rdquo; is really a Hill. When improvements were effected in later times, it was fully covered by walls and structures. This makes it more compact and look more artistic. The &amp;ldquo;camouflaging&amp;rdquo; attributed by the author for this improve- ment, that took place in later times, is therefore meaningless.&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 ICONOGRAPHY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/09_ICONOGRAPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/09_ICONOGRAPHY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-IX&#xA;ICONOGRAPHY&#xA;At the outset under the&amp;quot;General Features&amp;quot; on page 1, &amp;lsquo;Anantalwar&amp;rsquo; is categorised under the list of metal icons in the Temple. As far as we know there is no metal (Utsavar) icon for this Murthy. Only a stone image is installed in the &amp;lsquo;Anantal- war&amp;rsquo; shrine. Be that as it may, let us now proceed to examine the other aspects of this chapter. Here and on page 76, the author&amp;rsquo;s assertion that Manavala Mamuni was the last of the ACHARYAS deified in the Temple during the Vijayanagar period is a misstatement. Sri. Lakshmikumara Tatadesika along with his consort Sri Ammangar, is the last of the Acharyas who is deified in the shrine in front of the Dwajastambam where Sri Vedanta- desikar&amp;rsquo;s Mulavar and Utsavar idols are also installed. In all the perambulations of Lord Varadaraja and Sri Perundevi, showing Satari and other honours to these great Acharyas and Sri Ammangar, by turning south towards their shrine and then proceeding westwards for the processions, is an unfailing feature of our Temple. (See alo Appendix-Extracts from Sri K. N. Srinivasan&amp;rsquo;s book-&amp;ldquo;An examination of Dr. Raman&amp;rsquo;s theory on the Character of the Temple&amp;rdquo;) Then in section I the &amp;ldquo;Icons (enshrined) &amp;ldquo;the author fixes the date of the Utsavar idol of Sri Varadaraja and his Consorts Sri Devi and Budevi to the earlier half of the 11th century A. D. This sort of research to fix a date to the origin of Sri Varadaraja&amp;rsquo;s Utsavar Idol is not quite in consonance with our orthodox beliefs and sentiments. Even the historical deduction of the author about the age of the Idols do not tally with the actual facts. The date, the earlier half of the 11th century A. D. is that of Sri Ramanuja. Before him Budatalwar who belonged to the pre-christian era had sung about the Lord which is conceded by the author. According to him the age of the Alwar is the 7th century A. D&amp;rsquo;. Tirumangai- alwar is said to have flourished in the 8th century A. D. He is the last of the Alwars whereas Budatalwar is the earliest of the&#xA;the Alwars&#xA;Alwars who flourished before the advent of Kaliyuga according to our elders. So here also there is a&#xA;.&#xA;112&#xA;difference of opinion. Anyhow the date 11th century fixed by the author do not correspond to facts. If the date the author fixes for the Utsavar idols is proved to be wrong by this reasoning, viz the Mangalasasanams of Budatalwar and Tirumangaialwar the author may still try to explain it away by saying that the songs of Alwars are in praise of the Lord of Attigiri and does not necessarily mean the present Utsavar Idol.&#xA;The author has not also advanced adequate evidence to his fixation of the period to which the Utsavar belongs. It may be urged by some scholars that since according to the agamas Mula-Bera is the most important among the Beras the Alwars sang in praise of them alone. But this cannot be admitted unless strong proofs are adduced in support. Instances are not wanting to prove that references are available in their composi tions to the processions in which the Utsava Bera alone is carried through the streets 2.&#xA;46&#xA;&amp;lt;&#xA;Ranganatha&amp;rdquo; (page 164): Some of the remarks or comments of the author are peculiar in this book. One such is his statement that the popularity of the Temple of Ranganatha at Srirangam has probably influenced the erection of this Deity here.&amp;rsquo; Popularity is not the criterion for erection or installa- tion of a particular diety in a temple. Vaishnavites generally instal Deities of the three important Stalams&amp;rsquo; (places) of Srirangam, Tirupati and Kanchi in their temples. For instance Sri Varadaraja is installed at Srirangam, Tirupati, Tiruvallikkeni and so many other temples. Similarly Lord Srinivasa is also installed in many of our temples. The absence of Lord Srinivasa in our Temple or at Srirangam does not mean Tirupati is not popular. All these three.&amp;rdquo; Koil, Tirumalai, and Perumal Koil&amp;quot; are, as already stated, popular and are particularly important to Sri Vaishnavites. The Ranganath shrine has been renovated at a cost of about Rs. 10,000/- recently by Sri R. Tatadesika Tatacharya, one of the trustees of our Temple. Every structure or construction gets dilapidated due to efflux of time. Even the main Temple had to be renovated frequently and one such renovation took place recently. This cannot be therefore remarked adversely as the author has chosen to do by saying though the shrine is unfortunately in a state of neglect, the deity is graceful and&#xA;6bold in its features&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;.&#xA;113&#xA;C&#xA;6&#xA;·&#xA;But such insinuations and remarks are not uncommon in this Treatise.&amp;rsquo; We may add, this shrine is said to have been closed on account of the unsuitability of the deity for the puja. The granite which goes to make the deity is said to contain stone frog&amp;rsquo; Such a stone image they say is unsuited for pujas according to sastras (agamas). But anyhow the shrine is now completely repaired as said above and presents a very neat and elegant appearance. The Varaha&amp;rsquo; shrine is also renovated very recently by the Thatham Brothers&amp;rsquo; of Mudal Tirumaligai, the Tatacharyas of Srirangam, at a cost of more than Rs. 20,000/-. In coming to the description of &amp;ldquo;Perundevi Thayar&amp;rdquo; he fixes a date for this icon also as the first half of the 13th century A. D. Then he goes on describing the icons of Sri Andal, Sri Malayala Nachiar, Senai Mudaliar, Anantalwar, Garuda, Sudarsana etc., in their order. Before, passing on to the next item Icons of Alwars and Acharyas&amp;rsquo; in this chapter, we may mention an important fact which the author has not made or will not mention. Except in the case of the icons of Tayar, Andal and Malayala Nachiyar, all other idols viz. Sri Varadaraja, Narasimha, Ranganata, Varaha, Krishna, Rama, Anantalwar, Garuda, Sudarsana, Viswaksena, Danvantrin, Karumanicka Perumal (though not described in this chapter) and also Hanumans, are all wearing Vadakalai marks only. All the shrines in which the above idols are installed and described in this portion of the chapter do prominently display the countless Vadakalai marks in all the important portions of the shrines viz entrances cornices, walls&#xA;etc.&#xA;Now we come to the portion where &amp;ldquo;Icons of Alwars and Acharyas&amp;rsquo; are described. What has to be noticed here is the glaring omission of the icons of Sri Vedantadesika&amp;rsquo;s, &amp;lsquo;Mulavar and Utsavar&amp;rsquo; and Sri Tatadesika with Sri Ammangar enshrined in front of the Dwajastamba in the Temple. On the other hand the author is all praise and admiration for the Poise and handsomeness&amp;rsquo;, of the icon of his Acharya Manavala Mamuni. This is as it should be. But it is not fair or justifiable on the part of a true writer to omit to mention in this context, the existence of these great. Acharyas of the. Vadakalai.sect, when&#xA;8&#xA;6&#xA;114&#xA;he is discussing in detail the various other icons enshrined in the Temple. These icons representing these Acharyas are held in high esteem and importance, and they are the recipients of greater and exclusive honours from the Main Deities and senior Bakta Vigrahas of the Temple.&#xA;Next under Icons (not enshrined)&amp;rsquo; the familiar statement that Alagiya Manavala Jiyar built the Kalyana Mantapa (the hundred pillared mantapa) and his portrait figure is found here, is made. This is, most baseless, fallacious and un- warranted. The author&amp;rsquo;s persistence in repeating such unauthorised versions to make out a case that the Temple was managed originally by this Jiyar and he was responsible for the construction cannot stand the test of history, scrutiny, authenti- city or inscriptions. (See Chapter III page 61 also.) As said earlier, this mantapa is the monumental work of Sri Tata- charyas, the royal gurus of the Vijayanagar rulers.&#xA;The mantapa was started during the time of Sriranga I and completed during the period of Venkatapati Deva Maharaya (Venkata I) when the Jiyar was not in the picture at all. Mantape Sathapathakye-Tatadesika nirmithe, and Chitra Sthambasatha-vritham-Tribuvanascharyavaham mantapam&amp;rsquo; are the slokas in praise of Sri Panchamata-banjanam-Tatadesika and Lakshmikumara Tatadesika respectively that are found in the ancient texts, parts of which are inscribed in many places of the Temple.&#xA;Before concluding the examination of this chapter, certain factual mistakes contained here may be pointed out. The Utsavar Idols of the Mudal Alwars and Tirumalisai Alwar are in a standing pose whereas their Mulavars are in a seated pose. The author has stated simply these Alwars are seated, without mentioning whether they relate to Mulavars or Utsavars. Evidently, he thinks both the Mulavar and Utsavar deities are seated. Similarly, he says, on the same page 167 under Icons of Alwars and Acharyas that Alavandar and Kurattalwar are also seated. This is true with regard to the Mulavar and Utsavar deities of Alavandar. But the Utsavar idol of Kurattalwar is&#xA;standing and the Mulavar is sitting. In the case of&#xA;Garudalwar&#xA;(P. 113)&#xA;Tondaradippodi Tower from the Abishekamantapa Pradakshnana&#xA;(P. 59)&#xA;Mulavars of Budam, Pey, Tiruppani, Tondaradippodi &amp;amp; Tirumalisai Alwars&#xA;(P. 114)&#xA;Mulavars of Perialwar, Kumudavalli, Kalian, Kulasekara Alwar &amp;amp;&#xA;Sri Alavandar&#xA;(P. 114)&#xA;115&#xA;&amp;lsquo;Danvantrin&amp;rsquo; there is no Utsavar deity at all. But the author on page 167 says that both the Mula and Utsava images are small&amp;rsquo;. These statements clearly indicate the authors superficial knowledge of the Temple.&#xA;In the last para on page 173 under &amp;ldquo;Raja Todarmal&amp;rdquo;; the author describes the three statues as Todarmal and his family, that is, the central one as Todarmal and that the other two are &amp;ldquo;probably his mother Mata-Mohan De and his wife Pita Bibi&amp;rdquo;, This is, on the face of it, wrong. Only one of the two is a female statue. Even the &amp;ldquo;guides&amp;rdquo; published by the Devastanam have erred in that they describe the statues as that of Todarmal and his &amp;ldquo;wives&amp;rdquo; or his daughters&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;CHAPTER IX-PART II&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 PAINTING AND OTHER ARTS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/10_PAINTING_AND_OTHER_ARTS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/2/10_PAINTING_AND_OTHER_ARTS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-X&#xA;PAINTING AND OTHER ARTS&#xA;Under &amp;ldquo;General Features&amp;rdquo; In Section I, &amp;ldquo;Places where paintings are found&amp;rdquo; the author calls the sect-marks on the paint- ings on the walls surrounding the central shrine as &amp;rsquo;traces of vandalism&amp;rsquo;. The paintings which are very much decayed and cannot boast of the Ajanta or Ellora type, are not very clear and in most cases completely disfigured due to long age. The author himself concedes this on page 177 where he says most of the colour has vanished or become dull and what remains can only be seen in patches. Vadakalai sect-marks appear on the top of the walls, where the aforesaid paintings exist in a withered state, but they do not in anyway cause damage or disfigurement to the already decayed paintings. This causes a great eyesore to our author naturally because these sect-marks are all Vada- kalai. Such &amp;lsquo;vandalism&amp;rsquo;, if vandalism they could be called is in&amp;rsquo; abundance in Temples like Srirangam, Tiruvallikkeni and so many other Temples of the south where the Tenkalai features are displayed prominently. But they will not create any such impression in the author&amp;rsquo;s mind since these sect-marks belong to his own sect. This is one more instance of the staunch sectarianism exhibited by the author in this book. The interesting point of this remark is that he carefully avoids mentioning them as Vadakalai marks. He simply says &amp;lsquo;caste marks&amp;rsquo; so that he may not commit himself to testify to the existence of Vadakalai sect marks. This is a general policy usually adopted by the members of his sect, not to commit themselves to accept or recognise the existence of Vadakalai marks in the Temple. The use of the&#xA;the word caste before the word marks is erroneous. Whether the mark is of the Vadakalai or Tenkalai kind, the mark has nothing to do with caste as it is not worn by the members of a particular caste alone. The urdvapunram as it is worn by the Sri Vaishna- vas belonging to Ramanuja school must be called only creed mark and those of the Vadakalai or Tenkalai shall be called as&#xA;sectarian marks.&#xA;117&#xA;Section: 2-Wood Carvings&amp;rsquo; (Page 178): It is a welcome silver lining in the clouds to see here the author&amp;rsquo;s saying that &amp;ldquo;in the beginning of the 17th century Ettur Kumara Tatacharya is said to have presented a number of vahanas though the names are not specified&amp;rdquo;. But it is strange how the author says that the names of the vahanas are not specified when he refers to the particular inscription which, mentions this. This inscription &amp;rsquo; specifically details the list of vahanas made by Sri Tatacharya and various other items. They are the Elephant, Horse, Serpent, Garuda, Anjaneya, Sun, Moon, Palanquin, made of pearls and gems, Hamsa &amp;amp; Simha (Lion) all,made of gold and silver. &amp;ldquo;Vahan-rupyai-Swarnai etc&amp;rdquo;. is the sloka.&#xA;In the same inscription we get the information of the offering of the gem-set Kiritams, Kavachas and other costly jewels by Sri Tatacharya2. This evidently refers to the &amp;ldquo;Tho- ppaharam&amp;rsquo; a head-wear of the Lord used on only one occasion in the year, viz. the grand Garuda Sevai day, the third day of the Brahmotsavam, and the Tiruvabishekams of the Lord and his Consorts Sri and Budevis, which are called Kireetams made of precious stones.&#xA;The author while mentioning the presentation of certain jewels to our Lord by various persons under &amp;lsquo;Jewellery&amp;rsquo; does not deem it fit to include some of the most important items. Among the valuable collections of jewels in our Temple, the next most important and precious item after Thoppaharam and Tiruvabis- hekam is the head-wear called &amp;lsquo;Venkatadri Kondai&amp;rsquo; offered by the Vaishnavite poet and devotee by name Venkatadriswamy. This is adorned to the Lord on many important occasions and displayed along with the special items of jewellery like Thoppaharam and Tiruvabishekam, to the V. I. P. visitors both foreign and Indian. These omissions of such a marvellous and important items of jewellery, have prompted us to mention and describe them in detail. We have to add some more information regarding the jewels which are of outstanding importance in our Temple.&#xA;Tiruvabishekams: This crown like head-wear of precious stones is adorned to the Lord and his Consorts (Sri and Budevis)&#xA;118&#xA;on very many important occasions and especially on the Hastam Star&amp;rsquo; days which is also the birth star of our Lord Varadaraja.&#xA;Thoppa-haram: The name &amp;lsquo;Thoppi&amp;rsquo; means cap. The Thoppi- haram has changed into Thoppaharam and then into Thopparam evidently. And this jewel (Thoppaharam) is, as already men- tioned above, adorned to the Lord on only one special occasion viz. the grand Garudotsavam day.&#xA;Venkatadri Kondai: There flourished in the 19th century an ardent Vaishnavite devotee and a poet by name Venkatadri. His mother-tongue was Telugu as evidenced by his devotional songs in praise of our Lord and the Archamurthis of Srirangam and other sacred places. He seems to have presented first some precious ornaments to Lord Ranganata of Srirangam. Then he came to Kanchi. He wanted to offer a similar head-wear ornament to our Lord also. For this he had to raise donations from the public, since he was not affluent. He took a vow that unless he collects a certain amount each day he would not take his meals. Even if the collections of a day exceeded his target for the day, he would not account it for the next day. That is, he had to collect again the amount he had fixed for every day. Just like this he persevered and was able to complete the task finally. He faced very many difficulties for completing this sacred task. One such difficulty was about his securing back the precious emerald, set in the middle of the front portion of the ornament from a Dasi (dancing girl) at Thanjavur, which was stolen by the goldsmith and given to his sweetheart. It seems that having come to know about the possession of this by the &amp;lsquo;Dasi&amp;rsquo; he appealed to her to part with it. She refused at first. But Sri Venkatadri was not to be thwarted in his efforts. He started a fast before her house. Ultimately the lady yielded and returned the precious stone. Subsequently, the two Nachiars Sri Devi and Budevi appeared in the dream of Sri Venkatadri and bade him make similar headwears to them also. Such, is the story attached to this prized possession of the Lord of our Temple. Somehow this has not appealed to Dr. K. V. Raman to make mention of this along with his description of the jewels of our Temple. But he may also be not aware of all this.&#xA;U&#xA;Front View of Sri Azhakiyasingar Shrine&#xA;Sri Azhakiyasingar (Mulavar &amp;amp; Utsavar)&#xA;(P. 113)&#xA;(P. 113)&#xA;L&#xA;Lord Varada Adorned with the Diamond Vadakalai Tiruman, the Conch &amp;amp; Discus on the Eighth Day Festival of Brahmotsavam.&#xA;(P. 119)6&#xA;119&#xA;He has mentioned Urdvapundra&amp;rsquo; among the possessions on page 179 as having been presented by Achyutaraya along with Conch and Discus. We cannot expect him to be more explicit in this regard. There are two Vadakalai Urdvapundrams studded with gems and diamonds, one for the Mulavar and the other for the Utsavar. Whereas the Mulavar wears it throughout the year, the smaller Vadakalai Tiruman-Jewel is adorned to the Utsavar Idol only on special occasions along with the Conch and Discus. The Urdhvapundra mentioned is evidently the smaller one of the Utsavar since the Mulavar&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Diamond Tiruman&amp;rdquo; was of the early present century, presented by Sri V. V. Srinivasa Aiyangar a former judge of the High court. Clive&amp;rsquo;s Makara- Kanti was said to have been presented to the Lord, when he chanced to visit Kanchi at the time of a festival probably the Brahmotsavam. He was said to have been very much moved by the enchanting divine beauty of the Lord, and in his admiration gave away this jewel as a presentation, on the spot. This is a pendant jewel, aiso used on important festivals. Mr. Place, the Collector of Chingleput District, in the beginning of the 19th century had presented some important head ornaments, as the author himself has described. These ornaments have to be fixed on the head when the Deity is adorned with a Chikku-Thadu&amp;rsquo; (Sai Kondai) or Sevari&amp;rsquo; (plaited hair) or &amp;lsquo;Savari pakai&amp;rsquo;. Anantachar Makara Kanti&amp;rsquo; is also a pendant of rare variety adorned on several important occasions. There is a saphire (precious blue stone) carved like a peacock at the lower end of this padakkam which is a rare piece of skilful workmanship.&#xA;&amp;quot;&#xA;C&#xA;A recent addition is another Makara-Kanti&amp;rsquo; presented by the 43rd Jiyar of Ahobila Math. One Sri Ramanujachariar who was a Receiver in the Temple in the beginning of this century had presented the gem-set Conch and Discus,3 and also the &amp;lsquo;Tilak &amp;rsquo; to the Utsavar Deity. Echamma Padakkam, and Satyapurnaswamy (Madwa Acharya) Padakkam are among the stock of jewellery in the Temple which also deserve mention.&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
