<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;५ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;५ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>001 Rāma Sees Nandigrāma from Puṣpaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Salutation to Śrī Gaṇeśa. Salutation to the family-deity. Salutation to the lotus-like feet of the preceptor.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. After having saluted Nārāyaṇa and Nara, the best man, (so also) goddess Sarasvatī and Vyāsa, a man should recite Jaya.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O you glorious one, we have heard from you the entire charming Svargakhaṇḍa. O you long-lived one, tell us now the account of Rāma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Once the excel lent sage Vātsyāyana asked the lord of serpents, the prop of the earth (i.e. Śeṣa to tell him) this very virtuous tale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>002 Rāma Meets Bharata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Then Rāma, with his heart being distressed by the eagerness to see him, repeatedly remembered his brother Bharata who was the foremost among the righteous persons; and removing the darkness with the moon-like lustre of his teeth that became visible, he said to the powerful Hanūmat, the son of Wind:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-9. “O hero Hanūmat, hear my words which are impelled by my long-standing separation from my brother, and which are faltering and confused. O hero born from the body of Wind, go to that (my) brother whose body is emaciated due to separation from me and which he sustains forcibly (i.e. against his will). He puts on a bark-garment, he wears matted hair; being affected by separation from me, he would not even eat fruits. For him the wife of another person is like his mother, and gold is like a clod. My brother who knows the right way, would look upon his subjects as his own sons. Quickly sprinkle him whose body is burning with the flames of the fire of grief due to separation from me, with the shower of the water of the message of my arrival. Tell him that Rāma has come with Sītā, is accompanied by Lakṣmaṇa, and the lords of monkeys like Sugrīva and demons with Bibhīṣaṇa and that he is com foríably seated on a seat in the Puṣpaka (aeroplane), so that my younger brother quickly becomes happy due to my arrival.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>003 Rāma Enters Ayodhyā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Rāma, the intelligent hero, who, for a long time, desired to see the capital was delighted on seeing it where his own people lived.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Bharata too sent to the city his friend, minister Sumukha, to prepare the city for the festivity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bharata-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bharata said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-12. The people should quickly celebrate the festival of Rāma’s arrival. They should have gay pictures drawn in every house. The royal roads should be free from dust. They should be sprinkled over with liquid sandal. They should be furnished with abundant flowers. They should be crowded with delighted and rich people. All the big courtyards should be adorned with flags of various colours and painted. The fronts of the ridges of the thatched roofs should appear like the bow at the time of the arrival of the clouds (i.e. like the rainbow). The people should send forth agaru (sandal), seeing the smoke of which peacocks would dance sportively. They should paint with the minerals from mountains my elephants resembling mountains and well-controlled by the drivers. The horses having the speed of mind and painted should also look beautiful, seeing whose speed the heavenly horse gives up his pride. Beautiful virgins in thousands adorned with all ornaments and mounted on elephants, should scatter pearls. The married brāhmaṇa-women with vessels in their hands containing dūrvā (grass) and turmeric (powder) should wave lights before Rāma, the great king. May Kauśalyā who is afflicted by the information about the union with her son, and who very much longs for seeing him, be delighted. The delighted people should make such arrangements giving beauty to the city on the arrival of Rama.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>004 Rāma’s Consecration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vātsyāyana-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vātsyāyana said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. O great lord of the serpents, O lord capable of sustaining the burden of the earth, listen to one doubt of mine; and please explain (i.e. remove) it. Since the departure of Rāma to the forest she (Kauśalyā) lives with body but with a vacant mind. She is afflicted by separation from him; her body is emaciated; she is extremely unhappy. How indeed was she happy when she heard from Sumukha, the minister, that Rāma had come (back)? What happened (to her)? What were the marks (of her feelings)? What did she say to him who had brought the message of Rāmacandra? Remove this doubt of mine. Do me a favour and tell me who am listening, about the rich virtues of Raghunātha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>005 The Coming of Sage Agasti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then the gods, with their minds delighted due to (Rāma’s) killing the lord of demons called Rāvaṇa, humbly praised Rāma, consecrated (as the king).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;gods-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gods said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-10. Victory to you, O son of Daśaratha, O you who remove the sufferings of gods; victory to you who burnt the race of the demons; victory to you, O god, destroying the enemy whose hands were engaged in seizing the bevies of excellent women. The eager poets describe your destroying the lord of demons. O lord of the worlds, at the time of the deluge you again easily swallow the group of the worlds. Victory to you who are free from the causes of birth, old age etc. O mighty one, emancipate (us). Victory to you who have taken birth in the ocean of the family of the righteous, O you ageless, immortal and the fixed one. By means of (reciting) the names of you, the greatest god, even those who have committed great sins are purified. What then if good, foremost brāhmaṇas have obtained the human existence with a good body? The pair of your feet, praised by Śiva and Brahmā gives abundant things that are desired. We mentally desire it which is well arranged in the heart with the marks like those of pure barley (grains) etc. O you having the loveliness that excels Madana’s frame, if you do not grant fearlessness to the world, then how can, O you compassionate and purifying one, the hosts of gods be happy? You take birth on the earth whenever the demons trouble us, O lord, though you are unborn and immutable, though you are the greatest lord. You who are the self-adorned one and you who are praised by those who approve of virtues, quickly enter (i.e. go back to) your own place, after having filled the earth with your superhuman good deeds like nectar to the dead and destroying sins. May the beginningless one, the foremost one, who takes the form of a god, who has put on a necklace and a crown, who looks like Cupid, who has forcibly killed his enemies, whose lotus-like feet are served by Cupid’s enemy (i.e. Śiva), be victorious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>006 Agastya Begins Rāvaṇa’s Story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The intelligent Rāma, the lord of all worlds, thus said to the sage, the treasure of celibacy and penance and pleased with the welcome:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. “O you illustrious one, O you born of a pitcher, O you treasure of penance, welcome to you. All of us, with the members of our family are purified (by your arrival). I hope, your respect for the Vedas and sacred texts continues. On the globe there is none that would obstruct your penance. O glorious one, Lopāmudrā is your virtuous wife due to whose conduct as a devoted wife everything becomes auspicious. O you best sage, O you glorious one, O you piety embodied, O you treasure of compassion, tell me what thing should I do for you who are greedless. Everything takes place due to your penance, and you can have many things through your own penance, and you can have many things through your own desire. Yet, O best sage, just favour me, and tell me (what I can do for you)”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>007 Elimination of Rāvaṇa by Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;agastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Agastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. Then the demon practised a severe penance for ten thousand years. Looking at the sun with his eyes, he remained with his feet upwards. Kumbhakarṇa also practised a very difficult penance. The righteous Bibhiṣaṇa also practised penance. Then the lord, the god of gods, the lord of beings, served by the crowns of the gods, demons, yakṣas and others, was pleased, and gave him a great kingdom, shining in the three worlds; he also made his body charming and waited upon by gods and demons. Then he always tormented Kubera having a religious mind. He took away his aeroplane, and forcibly (captured) the city of Laṅkā. He tormented the entire world; the gods also went to heaven. He killed brāhmaṇa families, and cut off the roots of the sages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>008 Agastya Advises Rāma to Perform a Horse-Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O best sage Vātsyāyana, well-versed in the Vedas, the story of the god of gods, the only protector of all righteous ways, destroys sins. Seeing Rāma (fallen) unconscious, Agastya, the treasure of penance, immediately wiped his tears slowly with his hand, and said: “O Rāma, revive quickly, why do you sink? You are the ancient Viṣṇu, the destroyer of the demons’ family. Without you the world—the past, present, future, the immovable and the movable—does not go on. (Then) why have you fallen unconscious here?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>009 Instructions in Religious Practices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. What kind of horse should be (used) there (i.e. in that sacrifice)? What is the manner in which he is to be honoured? How can it be performed? Which enemies are to be conquered in (i.e. while performing) that sacrifice?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;agastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Agastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-11. A horse that is having the colour of the water of Gaṇgā, that is auspicious in body, that is dark in ears (i.e. that has dark ears), that is red in face (i.e. that has a red face), that is yellow in the tail (i.e. that has a yellow tail), that has good characteristics, that has the speed of the mind, that can move everywhere, that resembles Uccaiḥśravas, that has auspicious marks is said (to be used) in a horse-sacrifice. Having worshipped the horse on the full-moonday of Vaiśākha, having written (and having put) a note marked with one’s name and power on his forehead, one should let him loose, carefully guarded by guards. The powerful guards should go wherever the horse to be sacrificed goes. The guards should forcibly bring him back from him who, with force, binds him due to his own heroism and power. The sacrificer should remain (practising) and should observe celibacy. Till two years pass while the man is observing the vow, the poor, the blind, and the helpless should be satisfied by (giving) them wealth etc. O venerable (Rāma), abundant food should be given, and much wealth (also) should be given. The intelligent one gives whatever (a suppliant) asks for. O you destroyer of your enemies, the sacrifice of him who does acts like this, when completed, destroys all sins. Therefore, you are able to perform it, to protect it and to honour it. O king, having had auspicious fame, purify other people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>010 Rāma Appoints Śatrughna as the Protector of the Horse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. While Rāma was thus listening to religious duties (from sages) the spring season in which beginning of very great rites is made, set in. Seeing that season (had set in), the intelligent Vasiṣṭha, born from the pitcher, said to the great king Rāma, what was proper.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vasiṣṭha-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vasiṣṭha said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. O Rāmacandra of mighty arms, for you the time when the horse fully honoured is let loose for the sacrifice, has come. Make preparations for it. Invite the best brāhmaṇas. May the lord worship the brāhmaṇas properly. May he give gifts that have come up to his mind (i.e. desired by him) to the helpless, blind and the miserable according to the proper rite after having worshipped and honoured them. Initiated along with the golden (image of your) wife, sleeping on the ground, being restrained, and avoiding excellent enjoyments, keeping the deer’s horn on the waist, wearing a girdle, deer-hide, and a staff, you should make preparations for the (horse-sacrifice) with (all) the (required) things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>011 The Aśvamedha Horse Is Let Loose</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Having thus ordered (Śatrughna), the glorious Rāma, the tormentor of his enemies, looked at the heroes and spoke to them with (i.e. using) good words: “Protecting from the rear my brother Śatrughna, protecting the horse, and obeying his orders, who would vanquish, with his multitudes of missiles, all the heroes that would come (to fight) the chief one (i.e. Śatrughna), let him spreading his very great fame on the earth take up the sword of (i.e. offered by) me.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>012 Ahicchatrā City, King Sumada and Kāma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-14. She, smiling a little and looking at him with great love, spoke in a faltering voice to her husband who had spoken thus: “O lord, may you be victorious everywhere in battles (i.e. in every battle). You should obey Śatrughna’s order in such a way that the horse would be protected. Always remember (this) your servant, always following your foot (steps). O lord, my mind never goes away from you to any other (person). O dear one, you should never think of me in a great battle. When I am (lurking) in your heart, victory in the battle is doubtful. O you lotus-eyed one, you should act in such a way that Urmilā and others will not laugh at me and clap their hands on seeing me (and say:) ‘This is the wife of the great coward, running away in (i.e. from) the battle. When the cowards fight, where can there be an opportunity for the brave? O you of mighty arms, act, while protecting Rāma’s horse, in such a way that the wives of my brothers-in-law will not loudly laugh (at me). You are everywhere a warrior first. The ones who are behind you, and the mighty enemies should be made deaf with the twang of your bow (-string). The enemy’s army should be speedily confused with fear due to the dread of the sword in your raised hand. By conquering your enemies you should adorn this great family. O lord, O you of mighty arms, go; may you have good fortune here (i.e. in your undertaking). Quickly take this bow which is adorned with a great string (and with a great virtue), and hearing the roar of which the host of the enemies becomes greatly frightened. O hero, tie up these two quivers which are full with tips of arrows (i.e. pointed arrows) capable of killing crores of enemies, so that happiness will take place. Put this armour on your body which is handsome like thunder-bolt and so is strong enough to remove darkness. O dear one, put on your crest (i.e. head) this beautiful helmet. Put on these two bright ear-rings decorated with jewels and gems.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>013 Śatrughna Enters Ahicchatrā City</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. Hearing these words of Sumada, the treasure of penance, the army of Cupid, i.e. the celestial nymphs like Rambhā, joyfully said to him: “O dear one, all of us, beautiful damsels, have come to you due to your austerities. Enjoy the wealth of our youth, and give up the fruit of your penance. This is the pleasing Ghṛtācī, having a body like campaka, and charming due to the fragrance of camphor. You may enjoy the nectar from her mouth. O illustrious one, O dear one, quickly enjoy her who has charming gestures, whose body is attractive, whose breasts are compact and large, who has come (to you) as a result of your severe penance; and give up all your unhappiness. Firmly embrace me who am adorned with priceless ornaments, whose breasts are graced with the garland of mandara flowers, and who am expert in thinking about many tales about sexual union. Drink the nectar coming out from my mouth; enjoy, having reached the peak of Sumeru resorted to by means of great religious merit, pleasures—the fruit of your good penance. Let Tilottamā adorned with youth and beauty, hold on your head two good chowries—removing heat—like two streams of Gaṅgā with a constant flow, O most handsome one. O you, listen to the charming account of Cupid; drink the nectar longed for by the hosts of gods etc.; O lord, having, along with excellent damsels, reached the garden called Nandana, amuse yourself (there).”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>014 The Cyavana Episode</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then, the king, the best among men, longing to listen to the excellent account of Rāma, spoke to Śatrughna who was pleased with the reception.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. I hope Rāma who is the crest-jewel of the entire world, who has descended (On the earth) to protect his devotees, and who has favoured me, is happy. The people who with the cups of their eyes constantly drink the lotus in the form of Rāma’s face and are delighted, are blessed in the city (of Ayodhyā). O you best among men, O you very intelligent one, my entire wealth and all my family, land etc. and my possessions are blessed. Formerly, Kāmākṣā, tender with kindness, showed favour to me. (She told me:) “With your family you will see the lotus-like face of Rāma.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>015 Cyavana’s Penance and Enjoyments</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Then the sage went to his hermitage with Manu’s daughter, his wife, endowed with yoga (abstraction), and with all sins destroyed was happy. That daughter of Manu, served, like her family-deity giving desired objects, her excellent husband who was blind, whose prowess was lost due to old age, and was excellent due to having intelligence like Viṣṇu. She who knew (his) internal thoughts, served her dear husband who was a treasure of penance, and the charming one became very much delighted like Śacī (i.e. Indrāṇī) diligent in serving Indra. The beautiful, slim princess, endowed with all (good) characteristics, and subsisting on fruits, roots and water, served his feet. She was always eagerly engaged in obeying his words (i.e. orders) and in serving him, and engaged in the welfare of all beings she spent her time. Having given up (i.e. free from) desires, religious hypocrisy, hatred, greed, sin and pride, and always careful and diligent, she pleased Cyavana. O great king, having, in this way, served him for a thousand years with words and physical acts, she entertained a desire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>016 The Horse Goes to Cyavana’s Hermitage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Thus sporting with her everywhere on the earth, he did not notice the years counted in hundreds that rolled by. Then the brāhmaṇa, being a ware of the lapse of his time, and realising that his excellent dear wife was full of (i.e. fully satisfied with) her desires (being satisfied), returned to his best hermitage which was situated on the bank of Payoṣṇī and which was crowded with foeless beings and people and resorted to by beasts. He, of an excellent penance, lived there with his disciples, endowed with (the knowledge of) the Vedas; and with his pair of feet being served (by his disciples etc.) everyday, he practised a great (i.e. severe) penance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>017 Arrival of a Brāhmaṇa Ascetic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Having seen the power of the penance of Cyavana, which was inconceivable, Śatrughna praised the brāhmaṇic penance which alone was adored in the world. (He said to himself:) ‘Oh! see the perfection of abstract meditation in the best brāhmaṇa who just in a moment fashioned the aeroplane difficult to have. What a great disparity is there between the complete attainment of pleasure on the part of the sages of pure hearts and the desire for enjoyment on the part of human beings without the power of penance!’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>018 A Miraculous Happening</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-10. O king, listen to the account (of the events) that took place on the mountain Nīla, believing which men go to the eternal Brahman. I who was wandering, went to that mountain called Nīla, the courtyard of which is repeatedly washed by the water of the ocean. There, on the top of the mountain, I saw bhillas, holding bows, having four arms and with their fatigue removed by eating roots and fruits. Then immediately a great doubt arose in my mind: ‘How (is it that) these men are having four arms and they are holding bows and arrows? Their forms appear to be (like those) who have conquered their souls and live in Vaikuṇṭha. How have they obtained what is difficult to be obtained even by Brahmā and others?’ They, with their hands shining with conches, discs, maces, śārṅga (bows) and lotuses, and with their bodies covered with sylvan garlands, and resembling the devotees of Viṣṇu were near (me). With my mind full of doubt I asked them at that time, O king, (I said:) “Who are you? How have you obtained this condition of having four hands?” Then they laughed much and said to me: “This brāhmaṇa does not know the wonderful importance of piṇḍa.” Hearing this, I said (to them): “What is piṇḍa? To whom is it given? Tell it to me. O you most religious ones, having bodies with four hands.” Then having heard my words, the magnanimous ones told me the entire account of the acquisition of four hands etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>019 Ratnagrīva Goes on a Pilgrimage to Puruṣottama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Having heard the highly amazing words of the bhillas and thinking that it was a great wonder, I was delighted. Having bathed at the confluence of Gaṅgā and the ocean, with my body rendered auspicious, I climbed up the peak, variegated with gems and rubies. O great king, there I saw the god saluted by gods and others. I had become blessed by saluting him and by having eaten the food (from the offering). Due to having seen the lord Viṣṇu, I obtained the four-armed condition, marked with a conch, a disc etc. (and) did not enter a womb again (i.e. did not have rebirth). O king, you too quickly go to the mountain called Nīla, and make yourself blessed and free from the agony of remaining in the womb (i.e. being born).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>020 The Importance of Gaṇḍakī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-11. Then, when the king, accompanied by all people proceeded (to Nīlagiri), he, the great king, heard on the way the narration of Kṛṣṇa, of Govinda, sung by distinguished singers, the devotees of Viṣṇu: “Victory to you, O Mādhava, O you Puruṣottama, who are fit to protect.” On his way he visited many holy places and saw their greatness. From the ascetic brāhmaṇa he heard about their greatness. The king, with his mind amused with diverse accounts of Viṣṇu, made the singers sing about Viṣṇu on every path (that he took). The great, intelligent king whose senses were restrained, gave gifts to the helpless, blind, poor, lame persons, as desired by them. Very much devoted to the meditation on Viṣṇu, he, making himself auspicious and free from passion by means of visiting many holy places, went (on the pilgrimage) with his own people. The king while going saw ahead the river which destroys sins, which contained stones marked with discs, which was pure like the sages’ minds, which was adorned with many rows of the hosts of many sages, which looked beautiful with the cooings of birds like the cranes. Having seen it, he asked the ascetic, the best brāhmaṇa who knew piety and who was full of the special knowledge of the significance of many holy places: “O lord, what is this auspicious river, resorted to by hosts of sages and making my heart full of joy?&amp;quot; Hearing these words of the intelligent king of kings, the learned (brāhmaṇa) commenced narrating the excellent significance of the holy places.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>021 Puruṣottama Appears to the King in the Guise of an Ascetic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. The best king having heard this matchless importance of Gaṇḍakī looked upon himself as blessed. Having bathed and having gratified all his (dead) ancestors, the great one was delighted. Having, according to the words of the brāhmaṇa, worshipped the śālagrāma, the best king took there twenty-four śālagrāma (stones) and with affection worshipped them with such means of worship as sandal etc.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. Then the king, having given gifts there, especially to the poor and the blind, started to go to the temple of Viṣṇu. Thus, in due order, he reached the confluence of Gaṅgā an d the ocean. Having brought it within the range of his sight (i.e. having seen it), he joyfully asked the brāhmaṇa:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>022 The Greatness of Nila Mountain</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Then having passed the entire day with (i.e. in) the recollection and narration (of the glory of) Viṣṇu, at night he slept on the bank of Gaṅgā, giving a large fruit. In a dream he saw himself having four arms and holding a conch, a disc, a mace, and a bow, dancing in front of Viṣṇu with gods like Śiva with their pleasing bodies, with missiles like a disc, a mace, a conch and a lotus etc., (so also) with the excellent attendants of Viṣṇu having good bodies. Having seen (Viṣṇu) the lord of Śrī, the talk of the world, giving whatever is desired by the (devotees’) mind, and called Puruṣottama, he was amazed and obtained very wonderful joy. The very intelligent one looked upon himself as worthy of his grace. In this way the best king saw the dream. When he got up in the morning he narrated the dream that he had seen to the brāhmaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>023 Damana Fights with Pratāpāgrya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. The horse, having a chowrie (on his head), having the speed of mind, surrounded by a line of the heroes, bearing a note on his forehead, protected by the great hero Śatrughna, by king Lakṣmīnidhi, by Puṣkala, Ugravāha and Pratāpāgrya went to the city Cakrāṅkā protected by Subāhu. O lord, he was protected and followed by many crores of warriors. At that time his great (i.e. Subāhu’s) son, Damana, who had gone ahunting, saw the horse with a note on his forehead and besmeared with sandal etc.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>024 Puṣkala Defeats Damana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Śatrughna who was overpowered with anger, was grinding his teeth, shaking his hands, repeatedly licking his lip with his tongue, again and again asked them: “Who has taken (away) my horse? Who has vanquished Pratāpāgrya, the crest-jewel of all the heroes?” Then the servants said: “Damana, Subāhu’s son, and the killer of his enemies, conquered Pratāpāgrya and has taken aways the horse.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-10. Hearing this, viz. that his enemy Damana had taken (away) the horse, he speedily came to (the spot) where the battle had taken place. There Śatrughna saw (his) elephants that were (once) haughty due to rut, with their cheeks torn and merging in the water (i.e. pool) of blood. That very angry, brave Śatrughna saw his horses wounded and dead along with their riders. That killer of the enemies seeing his men, chariots and elephants completely vanquished was extremely angry as the ocean at the time of final deluge (is agitated). Seeing before him that preeminent Damana who had, after belittling his army, taken away the horse and had vanquished Pratāpāgrya, the king, with his eyes full of anger, said to his warriors: “Who is here (among the warriors) that would conquer Damana, wielding all (kinds of) weapons and missiles, and who, being fearless, will vanquish with a missile the brave prince skilled in fighting?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>025 Subāhu Gets Ready with His Army in the Krauñca Array</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1 -3. Then, seeing his warriors with their bodies covered with streams of blood, the king was not happy. He grieved; and asked them about the movements of his son (Damana): “Tell me his entire act. How did he take away the excellent horse? Tell me also how much army (the enemy has)? How many heroes came there to fight? How did my hero Damana, intent on fighting with the enemy’s army, fight and someone, having conquered this invincible hero, destroyed him.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>026 A Fierce Fight Between Lakṣmīnidhi and Suketu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Seeing that army like a cloud of a fearful size, and surrounded by many elephants, horses, chariots and foot-soldiers, Śatrughna spoke thus to Sumati in serious words. Waited upon by learned men knowing many words and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śatrughna-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śatrughna said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6. O Sumati, whose city has reached my best horse? I see this army resembling the ripples of an ocean. Whose army is this which is endowed with four divisions, is very joyful, and appears before (me) standing with eagerness to fight? Properly tell all this to me who am asking you, knowing which I shall order my soldiers to take position for the fight.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>027 Killing of Citrāṅga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/027/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/027/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Citrāṅga who was seated in his chariot and was at the neck of the Krauñca(-array), and was adorned with heroes, plunged into that army as a boar plunges into the ocean. Having stretched his very strong bow, resounding like thundering, he discharged sharp arrows burning crores of enemies. Great heroes with their entire bodies very much pierced with the arrows, lay (there) with the diadems and armours on their bodies and with their lips bitten.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>028 Subāhu’s Defeat</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/028/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/028/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Then the king, having seen his pre-eminent son fallen dead (on the ground), was pained by the grief due to (the death of) his son, and wept very much. Being extremely afflicted, he struck on his head with his hands. Trembling very much, he shed tears from his lotus-like eyes. Taking the son who was fallen (dead), who was charming like the curved orb of the moon (i.e. like the crescent moon), who was wet with the blood (oozing) from the wounds caused by the arrows of Puṣkala, who looked charming by means of the ear-rings, whose pair of eye-brows was curved, who was the best, who had bitten his budlike lower lip, he kissed him with his lotus-like mouth and lamenting said these words:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>029 King Subāhu Surrenders to Śatrughna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/029/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/029/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. They, the strikers (of their enemies), (too) hearing the words of their father, said joyfully, “Let it be so”, to the great king longing to see Rāma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sons-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sons said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9. O king, we do not know anything except the lotuses of your feet. Let that which you have in your mind, take place quickly. Let this horse, adorned with a white chowrie, very much beautified with a jewelled necklace, and smeared with sandal (-paste) etc. be taken there. Your kingdom has the fruit of your orders (i e. your orders are obeyed), O lord. Your treasures are very rich. Your garments are very costly, fine and excellent. There is (plenty of) sandal; so also there is camphor. Your horses are very charming. The elephants are haughty due to rut. The chariots have golden poles. There are a hundred thousand female servants who are adorned with many ornaments of various colours. There are very agreeable servants. There are gems resembling the sun. There are various jewels. There are white pearls produced from the temples of elephants. There are a hundred thousand corals. O you very intelligent king, give all those things which are very splendid, to Rāmacandra. O king, offer us, your sons and your servants (to Rāmacandra). O king, how is it that you do not make your throne over to him?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>030 Janaka Releases Sinners from Hell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/030/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/030/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Then the horse, adorned with the note, reached Tejaḥpura (city) in which king Satyavān truthfully protected his subjects. Then Raghunātha’s younger brother (Śatrughna) with a retinue of a crore going after the horse went in front of (the king) the conqueror of cities. Having seen the beautiful city, adorned with variegated ramparts, shining with golden pitchers all round, adorned at every place with thousands of temples of deities (Śatrughna said to Sumati). “In it monasteries of ascetics, full of ascetics, look beautiful. Here flows the great goddess (Gaṅgā), remaining on the head of him having three eyes (i.e. Śiva), and crowded with swans and ducks, and resorted to by hosts of sages. O Sir, in every house of brāhmaṇas smoke produced from the sacred fire purifies those whose minds were overflowing with sins.” With his mind amazed due to the joy produced on seeing that city Śatrughna, the subduer of his enemies, said to Sumati.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>031 King Ṛtambhara is Blessed with a Son</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/031/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/031/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jābāli-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jābāli said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. When those men living in hell went (to heaven), king (Janaka) asked Yama, the best among those who know dharma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-king-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;king said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O Dharmarāja, you have said that men who commit sins and are not interested in religious discourses, come to your place. O you righteous one, tell me for what sin I have come here, and the cause of my sin, from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>032 Satyavān Meets Śatrughna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/032/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/032/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-9. O dear one, this king too who was well known by the name Satyavān pleased by means of his duty Raghunātha, the lord of the worlds. Being pleased (with him) the lord of Ramā (i.e. Viṣṇu) gave him unswerving devotion to his feet, difficult to obtain through crores of religious deeds by his worshippers. He, full of pity and not being fatigued, everyday told the purifying tale of Śrī Raghunātha to people. He beat with sticks, causing fear even to Yama, the man who did not worship Ragunātha (i.e. Rāma), the lord of Ramā (i.e. Viṣṇu). He made every man who would be above the age of eight till he would be eighty years old, observe the fast of Ekādaśī. To him Tulasī was dear; his neck never abandoned the excellent garland from the lotuslike feet of Raghunātha. He was venerable even to the sages. How then was he not (so) to others? He loved remembering Ragbunātha. His sins were washed. His misfortune was destroyed. He, knowing that the very wonderful horse of Rāmacandra has come, will come and give you the kingdom free from troublesome fellows. O king, I have told you the best (thing) that you have asked for. O lord, what more do you ask? Order it (and) I (shall) do it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>033 Śatrughnā’s Army Gets Ready to Fight Vidyunmālin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/033/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/033/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7a. When many excellent warriors like Śatrughna and all great kings having crores of chariots were going, there was all of a sudden, on the way, very fearful darkness in which kinsmen could not recognise their own man or a stranger. The sky was covered with dust and was full of lightning and thunder. In such a very fearful confusion clouds showered profuse blood with puss and (other) foul things. The heroes who were great enemies, became very much confounded. When the people were perplexed, the condition was: ‘What is this? What is this?’ The eyes of people of renowned vigour were pervaded with darkness. (A demon) who was well known as Vidyunmālin who was Rāvaṇa’s friend, lived in the nether world and was surrounded by a line of demons took away the horse. He was seated in an aeroplane made of iron and going according to (occupants’) desire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>034 Vidyunmālin Killed in Battle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/034/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/034/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. With chariots having good horses (yoked to them), rich in charm and full of all weapons and missiles and endowed with various jewels, they went to (i.e. marched against) the mean demons. Seeing them the demon seated in a vehicle going according to (occupants’) desire, as it were, repeatedly threatening them, said with a deep-sounding voice: “Let the brave warriors not go to fight. Let them go home. Let them not cast their life. I shall not release the excellent horse. I am well-known as Vidyunmālin, and am the friend of Rāvaṇa. I have come to atone for my friend who is dead. Where has that Rāma who has killed (my) friend Rāvaṇa, gone? Where also is his brother (Śatrughna) who is the crest-jewel of all the brave men? Having killed him-the younger brother of Rāma, and drinking his blood along with bubbles coming up from his neck, I shall atone for (the death of) him (i.e. Rāvaṇa).” Hearing these words Puṣkala, the best among the excellent warriors, said to him endowed with valour and bravery:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>035 Dialogue between Lomaśa and Āraṇyaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/035/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. King Śatrughna, along with Puṣkala, obtained great joy on obtaining the horse taken away by the demons. Those warriors, with their bodies sprinkled with blood, so also Lakṣmīnidhi praised the great king full of energy to fight. When that great demon Vidyunmālin, difficult to conquer, was killed, all gods, O sage, gave up their fear and obtained happiness. The rivers became clean; and the sun became clear. Breezes sprinkled with scented water blew. The great heroes, with spotless lustre and of clean bodies seated in the chariots, became ready. All of them endowed with the good luck of victory said to the king:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>036 Lomaśa Narrates the Deeds of Rāma to Āraṇyaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/036/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/036/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The best brāhmaṇa, having heard this very important (advice) from Lomaśa, again asked that sage, who knew everything and who was best among the meditating saints.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;āraṇyaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Āraṇyaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O best of sages, O you very intelligent one, tell me (what) I am asking you. Preceptors are full of compassion, and explain everything to their servant(s). O magnanimous one, who is that Rāma who is reflected upon by you everyday? What are his deeds? O best brāhmaṇa, tell me. Why has he taken the incarnation? Why is he born as a human being? (Please) quickly tell me all that to remove my doubt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>037 Sage Āraṇyaka Goes to Viṣṇu’s Heaven</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/037/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/037/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. By the best sage they were asked (about) the wonderful deeds of Rāma. Regarding themselves as blessed and fortunate they spoke with respect.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-people-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The people said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. On seeing you we are now purified, since by (telling us) the account of Rāma you are purifying people (like) us. Listen to the true statement. You are the best among the brāhmaṇic sages. We shall tell all that you have asked us. By the words (i.e. at the suggestion) of Agastya Rāma is performing a very great sacrifice furnished with all ingredients for removing (the sin due to) the killing of a brāhmaṇa. We who all look after him have come along with the horse to your hermitage. O very intelligent one, know it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>038 Getting Back the Horse from the Possession of an Under-Water Female</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/038/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/038/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having heard this account, the noble-minded Vātsyāyana obtained great joy and said to the lord of the serpents.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vātsyāyana-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vātsyāyana said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. O lord of the serpents, I who listen to the story of Raghunātha who is famous for destroying the affliction of his devotees, am not (at all) satified. The great sage Āraṇyaka possessing (the knowledge of) the Vedas, who cast his perishable body after seeing Raghunātha, is blessed. From there where did the king’s horse go? By whom was he restrained? How was the glory of the lord of Rāma produced there? O lord of serpents, tell me all the truth, since you are omniscient. You hold the body of Viṣṇu; you actually possess his form.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>039 The Seizure of the Horse by Vīramaṇi’s Son</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/039/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/039/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. When everywhere the tabors were sounded and when everywhere there were the sounds of lutes, the horse was released. From there he (went) to Devapura fashioned by gods, in which men’s houses laughed, as it were, (i.e. were bright) by means of the constructions of crystal walls at the spotless Vindhya mountain resorted to by elephants. Even the houses of the subjects (i.e. ordinary people) were made of silver here (i.e. in this city). Here the ornamental ruby gateways were girdled by variegated gems; in every house there were attractive, most beautiful women that with side-glances attracted the hearts of men. Here, O brāhmaṇa, in every house rubies were seen to have been fixed in the good (i.e. beautiful) floors, as it were, to vie with the lips of the women. In every house the pleasure-mountains fashioned with sapphires produced the hope of (the arrival of) clouds in (the minds of) the peacocks having plumages. In this city swans, restrained on the crystal-floors in the houses were not afraid of a cloud and did not remember the Mānasa lake. (In it) at the abode of Śiva darkness was always dispelled by the moonlight; (so) the men there did not distinguish between the bright half and the dark half (of the month).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>040 Śatrughna Resolves to Fight Against Vīramaṇi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/040/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/040/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śesa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śesa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Looking for king Rāma’s horse the great king’s soldiers endowed with great power (or army) came (there). (They said:) “Where is the horse? Who has taken him? How is it that he is not seen? Who, a very dull one, will go to Yama’s city after having (i.e. because of his having) taken the horse?” While the soldiers of Raghu were searching the course of the horse, the great king surrounded by a large army came (there). He asked all his servants: “Now where is my horse? How is it that the horse, adorned with the golden note is not seen?” Hearing these words of (i.e. uttered by) him, the servants who were following the horse, said: “The horse having the mind’s speed has been snatched away by someone into the forest. Therefore, even though we know the path well, the horse is not noticed. Therefore, O lord, an effort should be made now to get (back) the horse.” Hearing their words, Śatrughna, the killer of his enemies, and having a fascinating form, asked Sumati:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>041 Rukmāṅgada Is Defeated by Puṣkala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/041/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/041/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Those very powerful heroes of Śatrughna, endowed with valour and quite ready to fight, went into the army of Vīramaṇi. The men discharging arrows, piercing many soldiers, holding, bows were seen standing in the battlefield. Many elephants were killed there. On the battlefield were seen jewelled chariots shattered with their horses. Having heard about their destruction the mighty Rukmāṅgada, standing in a jewelled chariot, came there to fight with the soldiers. He fixed arrows on his bow and had two inexhaustible quivers. That mighty Rukmāṅgada, full of great anger and with blood in his eyes, making thousands of brave men terrified with his arrows causing wailing (in the enemy’s camp), went (to fight). The mighty prince challenged. Śatrughna and Bharata’s son Puṣkala like himself in fame and glory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>042 Vīramaṇi Is Defeated</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/042/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/042/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Seeing him challenging king Puṣkala in the ocean of the great army, even Hanūmat, the lord of monkeys, having with a sound raised the tail of his big body and having made a sound like that of a cloud, ran to him. When the best heroes stood in the battlefield, the lord of monkeys went to the best king. Seeing Hanūmat coming the mighty hero Puṣkala looked at him with his eyes full of much blood (i.e. very red) due to anger towards his enemy with a deep-sounding voice like (the sound of) a cloud and filling the battlefield with his sound Puṣkala who knew (the use of) great missiles, spoke to that Hanūmat:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>043 Defeat of Puṣkala and Śatrughna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/043/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/043/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Hanūmat having come to Vīrasiṃha, said these words: “O brave one, stop; where are you going? In a moment I shall conquer you.” Hearing these powerful words of the monkey, he burning with a flood of (i.e. great) anger sounded his bow having the sound of clouds and discharging sharp arrows shone on the battlefield. Hanūmat, Añjanī’s son, seeing those sharp arrows firmly stuck to his body, (and therefore looking) charming as in a heavy downpour of rain from a cloud in Āṣāḍha, became extremely angry in his heart. With his fist having adamantine strength he struck (Vīrasiṃha) on his chest. The hero struck with the fist fell on the ground. Seeing his uncle fainting, Śubhāṅgada (came to the battlefield). Rukmāṅgada also abandoning his swoon, went to the battlefield. Both of them showering arrows, loudly thundering like two clouds and causing great destruction, marched against the monkey (i.e. Hanūmat).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>044 Hanūmat on the Droṇa Mountain</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/044/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/044/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa&lt;/em&gt; said:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The hero Hanūmat, desirous of killing the lord of gods, came near Rudra on the battlefield and said (to him):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;hanūmat-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hanūmat said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. O Rudra, what you are doing is against religious merit. Therefore, I desire to punish you eager to kill Rama’s devotee. Formerly I heard it said variously by gods and sages that Rudra, the trident-holder, always remembers Rāma’s feet. All that has become (i.e. proved) false in your case, who are fighting with Śatrughna. My b rave (hero) Puṣkala is killed and Śatrughna also has become unconscious. Therefore, I shall today knock you, ready to destroy the three worlds, down. O Śarva (i.e. Śiva), you who are averse to Rāma’s devotion, stand carefully.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>045 Śrī Rāma Appears on the Battlefield</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/045/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/045/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Having heard the words of Bṛhaspati, the Supreme Being, the enemy of Vṛṣaparvan, having come to know that Wind’s son (Hanūmat) had come there on Rāma’s mission gave up the fear in his mind that was due to the monkey and was delighted and said to Bṛhaspati.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;indra-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indra said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. How shall we manage, O master of gods, if this Droṇa (mountain) is taken (by Hanūmat)? Tell me further, how can the gods survive? Now properly propitiate the son of Wind. Rāma will be very much delighted, and the gods would have happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>046 Vīramaṇi Surrenders the Horse to Śrī Rāma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/046/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/046/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Seeing his brother Śrī Rāma destroying the affliction of him who had saluted him to have come (there) Śatrughna became free from all unhappiness, O best brāhmaṇa. The confused Hanūmat seeing with joy Rāma’s feet saluted him who had come (there) for the protection of his devotees and said: “O lord, it is (but) proper for you to protect your devotees, since you freed everyone vanquished and tied with a noose in the battle. O you descendant of Raghu, we are now blessed that we shall see your feet. In a moment only we shall conquer the enemies by your grace.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>047 The Sacrificial Horse Develops Stiffness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/047/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/047/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. Then, O brāhmaṇa, the horse went to Hemakūṭa close to Bhārata. The horse with chowries tied (on to his body) was protected by thousands of warriors. That Hemakūṭa was (many) yojanas in expanse and length on all sides and had myriads of silver and golden peaks. There was an excellent garden adorned with trees (like) śāla, tala, tamāla, karṇikāra, hiṃtāla, nāga-punnāga, kovidāra and bilva, also campaka, bakula, megha (a kind of fragrant grass), madana, kuṭaja and others. It was also adorned with creapers like jātikā, yūthikā and navamālikā (varieties of jasmine), so also with mango-trees, vines with sweet grapes, and pomegranates. It was noisy with many birds; it was resounding with (the humming of) bees. It had the sounds of peacocks’ notes. It gave joy in all seasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>048 The Horse Is Relieved of Stiffness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/048/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/048/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. He who killed the enemy’s heroes, having heard what the sage told, was amazed at heart, and said to Śaunaka:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śatrughna-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śatrughna said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. The way of fate is mysterious, due to which that (brāhmaṇa) named Sāttvika, though he had reached heaven (i.e. had become divine), was made a demon by his deeds. O lord, O great sage, tell me about the path (i.e. the consequence) of deeds, and which hell is (obtained by beings) due to the result of which deeds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>049 King Suratha Seizes the Horse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/049/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/049/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Seven months passed as the horse easily roamed over Bhāratavarṣa full of kings. He going round all the excellent Bhārata (country) was honoured by excellent kings. Surrounded by excellent warriors and mighty soldiers like Śatrughna he roamed over many countries near the Himālayas. Taking into consideration Rāma’s might nobody seized him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-11. Praised by the kings of Aṅga, Vaṅga and Kaliṅga the horse went to the beautiful city of Suratha. The city was named Kuṇḍala, where the ear-rings fell from Aditi’s ears trembling with joy and fear. There no man ever violated religious laws. The people there remembered Rāma everyday. There everyday men, Rāma’s servants, free from sins, worshipped Aśvattha and Tulasī. There everyday men of pure hearts, free from fraud, worship charming temples having Rāma’s idols. There is the name of Rāma (told) in words and never the account of a quarrel. In the heart he alone is meditated on, and no memory of sex finds a place. There men whose bodies are purified by the story of Rāma and who have assiduous devotion to truth, never indulge in gambling. In it lives the mighty and righteous (king) Suratha whose mind is delighted by recollecting Rāma’s feet, and is very mad (after Rāma).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>050 Aṅgada Delivers Śatrughna’s Message to Suratha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/050/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/050/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. Then the younger brother of Rāma came (there) and asked his servants: Where is the very charming sacrificial horse?” At that time those very mighty heroes said (these) words to Śatrughna: “We do not know. Some warriors took the horse and went into a city; and all of us were despised by the mighty servants of the king. You are now the authority as to what should be done now.” Hearing those words of them, Śatrughna became very angry and the hero gnawing his teeth and repeatedly licking (his lips) with his tongue said: “Snatching my horse where will you go? Now (only) I shall ruin with (my) arrows (your) city with the people (i.e. the inhabitants).” Saying so, he said to Sumati: “Whose city is this? Who is its lord that took away my horse?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>051 Hanūmat Frees Puṣkala from Campaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/051/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/051/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. On hearing the words of Suratha from the mouth of (i.e. through) Aṅgada all (the soldiers) proficient in fighting and seated in their chariots became ready (to fight). There was the sound of the war-drums, so also of kettle-drums. On the battlefield the sounds of the roars of the soldiers arose. All the world was full of the sounds of the chariots and the trumpets of the elephants. The great sound (even) reached the sky. The soldiers skilled in fighting and full of enthusiasm for fighting made various sounds which scared the timid ones. When such a din took place, the king named Suratha surrounded by his sons and soldiers went to the battlefield. Pervading fully the earth with elephants, chariots, horses and hosts of foot-soldiers, and inundating it as the ocean (inundates it), he was seen with (or by) soldiers. Seeing that army resounding with the sounds of conches and also with cries of victory, and ready to fight, the king said to Sumati.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>052 King Suratha Wins the Battle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/052/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/052/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Seeing Campaka fallen Suratha, the mighty kṣatriya, with his body filled with grief, went, seated in a chariot (to the battlefield). Suratha who was very powerful, was angry and heaving heavy sighs, called (i.e. challenged) the monkey. Seeing the king challenging him the very brave hero, the lord of monkeys, having great speed, went to (i.e. marched against) him. King Suratha with his beautiful voice deep-sounding like (that of) the clouds, seeing Hanūmat who despised great heroes coming, said:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>053 Rāma Frees the Bound Heroes</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/053/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/053/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-11. Seeing the army defeated and also seeing his master (lying) unconscious, Sugrīva went to fight with the king. “Come, O king, where are you going after rendering all the warriors unconscious? O you proficient in fighting, quickly fight with me.” He possessing power saying so uprooted some huge tree with branches and struck it on his head. Due to that stroke the very mighty, very brave king looked at Sugrīva and angrily fixing sharp arrows (on his bow) struck them on his chest. Sugrīva laughed and at once foiled all those arrows. He, the very powerful one, struck Suratha on his chest. Tearing Suratha with his nails he violently struck him with mountains, peaks (of mountains), trees and bodies of elephants. With the very terrible missile called Rāma (i.e. presided over by Rāma) he quickly bound him also. The best monkey (i.e. Sugrīva) took Suratha to be a servant of Rāma. He became like an elephant which, having an iron chain hanging from his feet, cannot do anything. Putting all the warriors into his chariot he went to his own city. Going to his assembly, the very great one said to Hanūmat who was bound: “Remember the kind Raghunātha, the protector of his devotees, so that he of the best mind will instantly release you. Otherwise, even after a myriad years I shall not free you from bondage.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>054 Lava Binds the Sacrificial Horse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/054/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/054/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Jānaki’s son Lava surrounded by sages’ sons went to bring sacred fuel fit for the rites in order to perform the rites. There he saw the sacrificial horse marked with a golden note and made fragrant with the divine perfume of saffron, agaru (sandal) and musk. Seeing (the horse) and with curiosity aroused he said to the sons of the sages: “Whose horse having mind’s speed has fortunately come to my hermitage? Come with me; observe (him); do not be afraid.” Saying so that Lava quickly went near the horse. He born in the family of Raghu and standing near the horse, holding a bow and an arrow, stood invincible like Jayanta near the horse.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>055 The Observation of the Spies</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/055/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/055/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having heard this charming account of the powerful Lava the sage entertaining a doubt again asked the serpent (i.e. Śeṣa) having a thousand faces.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-vātsyāyana-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Vātsyāyana said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. Formerly you had said that Rāma due to the censure by a washerman and ardently longing for fame abandoned Sītā all alone in the forest. Where were the two sons born to Jānakī (i,e. Sītā)? Where did they learn archery? How did they learn the science which enabled them to take away the horse of Rāma?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>056 Rāma Seeks Bharata’s Advice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/056/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/056/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-9. Having performed the daily morning duties, having duly gratified the brāhmaṇas, the most learned in the Vedas, with presents of gold, he went to the assembly. All men went to the assembly to salute Raghunātha, the king looking after all the subjects like his own sons. Lakṣmaṇa had held an umbrella over the king&amp;rsquo;s head. Bharata and Śatrughna had at that time held the chowries. Sages led by Vasiṣṭha attended there (upon Rāma). Ministers led by Sumantra who did justice, (were present) there. When the time moved on like this, the six well-adorned spies came to salute the king seated in the assembly. Seeing them desirous of speaking, the best king, being eager, entered the interior, private chamber in the assembly. The good-minded king asked all the spies in private: “O spies, O you who restrain your enemies, tell me correctly how people talk about me; how (they talk) about my wife; in what way do they talk about the acts of my ministers?” Hearing these words the spies spoke in a grave tone like that of the (thundering) clouds to the lord of the Raghus who was asking them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>057 The Washerman’s Former Birth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/057/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/057/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vātsyāyana-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vātsyāyana said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O you of a good vow, tell me how the lord received the utterance of the censure of Jānakī having pure, excellent fame in the world. O Śeṣa, do that by which my mind shall have very splendid happiness, so that I who drink the nectar coming out from your mouth, shall be satisfied, and by which my worldly existence will be cut off.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-11. In Mithilā, a great city, there lived a king by name Janaka. Pleasing his subjects, he ruled righteously. When that Sīradhvaja (i.e. Janaka) was ploughing the field, an extremely beautiful girl came out from the long, first furrow. Then king Sīraketu (i.e. Janaka) became extremely glad. He named her, the fascinating one, the glory of the world, Sītā. When she, extremely charming, was playing in the grove of the garden, she saw a pair of a male and a female parrot that delighted her mind. The parrots were extremely delighted and lustful, and affectionately talking to each other in pleasant words. That pair, enjoying (each other’s company), quickly flew in the sky, settled on the lap of a mountain, and spoke (to each other): “On the earth, charming Rāma will be the king. His wife will be (a woman) by name Sitā. The intelligent, powerful king, vanquishing (his enemies), will rule (over the earth) along with her for eleven thousand years. Blessed is that queen Jānakī, and blessed is he, named Rāma, who having approached each other, will gladly enjoy.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>058 Lakṣmaṇa Leaves Sītā in the Forest</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/058/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/058/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. Seeing Bharata unconscious, Raghunātha who was very much afflicted, said to the door-keepers; “Bring Śatrughna quickly to me.” Hearing these words, (the door-keeper), in a moment brought Śatrughna where his brother Rāma remained with Bharata. Seeing Bharata unconscious and Rāma afflicted, he who was grieved, saluted (Rāma) and said: “What has this frightful (incident) come about?” Then Rāma, with his face hung down with a piteous voice and with his words faltering and with tremor, told Śatrughna, the servant of his feet, the words of the śūdra—the popular censure: “O brother, listen, and quickly and carefully do what I tell you, so that my fame will go (i.e. flow) like Gaṅgā on the earth. Having heard the words unequalled in the world, uttered about Sītā by the śūdra, I indeed decided to abandon my body or Jānakī.” Hearing these words of Rāma, Śatrughna, the killer of his enemies, being afflicted fell down with a termor on the earth. Having regained consciousness after some time, he said to Raghunātha:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>059 The Birth of Kuśa and Lava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/059/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/059/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. Then Lakṣmaṇa, having made Sītā cross Gaṅgā in a boat to the other bank, took her by hand and went to the forest. On the way she who was marked with her face parched up, walked. Her good (i.e. delicate) feet were hurt with thorns. She tumbled at every step. At that time Lakṣmaṇa carrying out the order of Rāghava took her into the very fearful forest causing misery, in which there were fierce dense trees like barbula, khadira. śleṣmātaka, ciñciṇīka, which were dry due to wild fire. Serpents living in the hollows of trees and getting very angry, hissed. Owls causing fear to the minds of people, cried. (In the forest) artless, very wrathful, tigers, lions, foxes, and elephants, eaters of human beings were noticed. Buffaloes, hogs which were wicked, which were marked with two fangs, afflicted the minds of beings. Sītā seeing such a forest suffered from grief through fear. With her feet pricked by thorns she said (these) words to Lakṣmaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>060 Lava Defeats the Army and Kills the General</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/060/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/060/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Seeing his soldiers with their arms cut off, Śatrughna getting very angry and biting his lower lip with anger, said to them: “O you, which hero has cut off your arms? I shall cut off both the arms of him, (even though he is) protected by gods, O soldiers. The great fool does not know (anything about) the great might of Rāmacandra. Now through my valour I shall show (him) my might. Where is that hero? Where is the charming hero? Which fool, not knowing the valour, would seize sleeping serpents?” When the heroes were told (like this) they were amazed and much afflicted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>061 Hanūmat Falls Unconscious</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/061/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śatrughna-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śatrughna said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O great minister, do you know who is the boy that took away the horse and who destroyed all my army like an ocean?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumati said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. O lord, this is the great hermitage of the best sage Vālmīki. O you who torment your enemies, kṣatriyas do not at all live here. It might be that Indra became (i.e. took the form of) the great sage and snatched the horse, or it might be Śiva. Otherwise, who else would take away your horse? O great king, who else but Puṣkala can go to (i.e. march against) him who killed the very fearful Kālajit? O you destroyer of your enemies, go there surrounded by all your brave warriors, kings, and your great army.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>062 Lava Becomes Unconscious</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/062/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/062/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-14. Hearing that Hanūmat was unconscious, Śatrughna was distressed: ‘What should I do in the battle? This boy is very powerful.’ Himself seated in a golden chariot along with excellent heroes he went where Lava, skilled in fighting in a wonderful way, stood. He saw Lava, as if Rāma reduced to childhood had come on the earth, having a bow and arrows in his hand and discharging (arrows) in the battle. At that time he thought: ‘Who is this having Rāma’s form and having a charming body dark like the petals of a blue lotus? This must be the son of (Sītā) the daughter of (the king of) Videha; not otherwise (i.e. none else), (who) having vanquished us in the battle, will go like the lord of beasts. There is no possibility of the victory of us who are void of power. What shall we, (though) proficient in fighting, (yet) being weak, do?’ He, having thought like this, said (these) words to the boy who fought with vehemence, knocking down crores of heroes: “O boy, who are you that are knocking down our heroes on the ground? You do not know the power of Rāma who killed the demons. Who is your mother? Who is your father? Being very lucky, you got victory. O you very mighty one, what is your name well-known in the world? Release (the horse); how (i.e. why) have you caught the horse? (Since it is) due to your being a child, I forgive you. Come, see Rāma, he will give you large (wealth).” The boy who was addressed like this, said (these) words to Śatrughna: “What have you to do with my name, or my father, or my family, or my age? O hero, if you are endowed with power, then fight (with me) in the battle; otherwise, salute the hero Kuśa (by falling) at his feet; otherwise you cannot go. You are the brave brother of Rāma; (but) for us you are not the best among the mighty. If you have power, then forcibly release the horse.” Saying so, the mighty warrior, taking aim with his arrow, struck him on his chest, head and arms on the battlefield.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>063 Kuśa’s Victory</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/063/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/063/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Seeing Lava, the destroyer of his enemies, unconscious, Śatrughna, the very mighty one, obtained victory in the battle. Putting Lava, the boy adorned with a helmet etc. and the likeness of Rāma in form, in the chariot he desired to go from there. Seeing that their friend was arrested by the enemy, the boys who were full of grief, quickly reported it to his mother, Sītā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-boys-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The boys said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-9. O mother Jānakī, your son forcibly snatched the horse of some proud king endowed with power. Then, O Jānakī, the great brave boy vanquished all the army. Later also he got victory. Having made that king unconscious, he obtained victory in the battle. Then the very fearful king, having given up the swoon (i.e. having regained consciousness), got angry and knocked down your son on the battlefield. We had in the beginning warded him off (saying): “Do not seize this excellent horse.” Despising all of us, the brāhmaṇas who have mastered the Vedas, (he seized him).”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>064 Rāma’s Army Revives</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/064/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/064/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Seeing Śatrughna fallen, the excellent king Suratha getting into his very wonderful chariot fashioned with jewels went (to fight). Realising that Puṣkala was formerly defeated in battle, he went to fight with Lava, the crest-jewel (i.e. the best) of the great heroes. Suratha, the crest-jewel (i.e. the best) of the great heroes, having reached Kuśa and discharging arrows in various ways, troubled him. With ten arrows with rising flames he deprived Suratha of his chariot. He speedily cut off his bow, strong and strung. The battle between the two heroes (fought with) destruction of missiles and counter-missiles and throwing and counter-throwing of missiles was fierce and thrilling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>065 Sumati Describes the Adventurous Events to Rāma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/065/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/065/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. In a moment Śatrughna, the hero, gave up his swoon onthe battlefield. Other mighty warriors also, who had fainted, revived. Śatrughna saw the best among the horses, standing before him, and saw (i.e. found) himself to be without the helmet and the army revived. Seeing this he wondered in his mind and spoke to Sumati, the best among ministers, who had then revived: “Having shown pity, the boy has returned the horse for the completion of the sacrifice. We (shall) quickly go to Rāma desiring (i.e. waiting for) the horse’s arrival.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>066 Singing of Rāmāyaṇa by Kuśa and Lava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/066/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/066/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having come to know that the two boys in Vālmīki’s hermitage were his sons, he (i.e. Rāma) went to Vālmīki.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. Who are the two boys having my resemblance and the best among the mighty? Why do the two, skilled in archery, live there? Having heard what the minister told about them who easily bound Śatrughna and Hanūmat, I am amazed. Therefore, O sage, tell me all the deeds of the two boys, since a great, desirable delight thus comes to me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>067 The Commencement of the Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/067/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/067/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Then Lakṣmaṇa, having come (there) repeatedly saluted her, and with (his voice) faltering through love, he told her the words uttered by Rāma. Having seen Lakṣmaṇa full of modesty to have come (there) and having heard Rāma’s message through his mouth, Sītā being abashed, said: “O Lakṣmaṇa, how (i.e. why) have you come? I forsaken by Rāma in the great forest and remembering Rāma, am staying in Vālmīki’s hermitage.” Having heard the words that came out from her mouth Lakṣmaṇa said: “O mother, O you chaste lady, Rāma is inviting you again and again. A chaste wife does not bring to her mind the fault committed by her husband; therefore, seated in an excellent charriot, come with me.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>068 The Horse Sacrifice Ends</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/068/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/068/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śeṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śeṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. Indra together with the gods tasting at the sacrifice the oblations cooked and seen by Rāmacandra, did not obtain satisfaction. Viṣṇu, Śiva, so also Brahmā having four faces, Varuṇa, Kubera and other gods tasted the oblations refined by Vasiṣṭha. The best brāhmaṇas also were as it were oppressed with hunger after taking the food. The treasure of pity (i.e. Rāma), having gratified all gods with the oblations, and being urged on by Vasiṣṭha, did what was necessary to be done according to the rules. The brāhmaṇas were pleased with the gifts; the great gods were pleased with the oblations. All being gratified on receiving their portions, went home. To the priests headed by the hotṛ (i.e. the priest reciting the prayers of the Ṛgveda at the sacrifice) he gave kingdoms in the four directions. Those brahmaṇas who were pleased, gave blessings to Rāma in an auspicious manner.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>069 The Story of Kṛṣṇa Begins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/069/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/069/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O glorious one, we have duly heard from you the (description of) Rāma’s horse-sacrifice. Now tell us the greatness (i.e. glory) of noble Śrīkṛṣṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. O best sages, (please) listen to the nectar-like story of Śrīkṛṣṇa. I shall tell you what Pārvatī asked the lord of beings. Once goddess Pārvatī with her mind affectionate towards Śiva, having saluted him with reverence, said these words to him:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>070 A Description of Śrīkṛṣṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/070/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/070/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pārvatī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pārvatī said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O lord, I desire to hear (the account worth) hearing of him and about those who are the members of his assembly. O you treasure of kindness, (please) narrate it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. (One can see) Govinda along with Rādhā seated on a golden throne. He has the loveliness of form as described before. His ornaments, garments and garland are divine. He, in his crooked posture (assumed with his body bent at three points while playing on his flute) is sweet and very glossy and is the pupil of the eyes of the cowherdesses. Outside sitting on the seat for abstract meditation (Yogapīṭha) covered with a golden sheet resembling a lion’s skin(?) are the chief ladies dear to Kṛṣṇa and having a strong devotion for him in every limb (of their bodies). They are Lalitā and others, and are the portions of the primordial matter. Rādhikā is the primordial matter. In front of him is goddess Lalitā; in the north-west is Śrīharipriyā; in the east is Viśākhā; and after her, in the south-east is Śaibyā; Padmā is in the south; and then in the south-west, on the Yogapīṭha, in front of a bakula tree, is Candrāvatī, dear to him. Thus they remain in order. These eight are auspicious and chief natural forms, dear to Kṛṣṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>071 The Greatness of Rādhākṛṣṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/071/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/071/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-goddess-pārvatī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The goddess&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Pārvatī&lt;/em&gt;) &lt;em&gt;said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3 O holy one, O lord of all beings, O soul of all, O you the origin of everything, O lord of gods, O great god, O omniscient one, O you who show pity (to everyone), since I was pitied by you, I again say tenderly. O lord, you told me the hymns enticing the three worlds. (Now) tell me, by means of which particular things that god (Kṛṣṇa) having a very fascinating form, played with the cowherdesses.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>072 Devotees of Kṛṣṇa Born in Gokula as Cowherdesses</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/072/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/072/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6a. O you beautiful goddess, listen with a concentrated mind: There was a sage, named Ugratapas who was firm in his vow. He, performing rites in honour of Agni, ate (i.e. subsisted on) fire, and practised a very wonderful penance. He muttered the great hymn, fit to be muttered and having fifteen letters, bound together by a desire-yielding hymn, securing desired objects from one giving the desired boon, with the word &lt;em&gt;Kṛṣṇāya&lt;/em&gt; (to Kṛṣṇa), along with the word &lt;em&gt;Svāhā&lt;/em&gt; (offered to), and giving great prosperity. He meditated upon the dark Kṛṣṇa, mad with dance, eager to grant a boon, having put on a yellow garment, with a flute put at his lower lip, endowed with fresh youth, and dragging his beloved with his hand. Thus, the great sage, engaged in meditation, cast his body after the end of hundred kalpas and was born as the daughter of the cowherd by name Sunandā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>073 The Greatness of Mathurā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/073/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/073/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. I have told you in (due) order, the wonder about which you asked me. Who is not stupefied there, where Brahmā and others are stupefied? Yet I shall tell you what the great sage (Vyāsa) said to Ambarīṣa, a devotee of Viṣṇu, connected with Śiva. The king, having come to the Badaryāśrama, saluted and praised, with a desire to know the Vaiṣṇava way of life, Veda-vyāsa who was seated there, who had restrained his senses, who was noble, omniscient, and best among men: “Please protect me from this mundane existence. I am detached from the sensual pleasures; I salute them, I salute everything. How would I always obtain mental recourse to that highest Brahman, a position free from dejection, having a form of auspiciousness, intelligence and joy, the highest sky, the absence of ether, which is healthy, and seeing which the sages cross the ocean of worldly existence?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>074 Arjuna’s Wish and Its Fulfilment</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/074/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/074/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Once, in private, glorious Uddhava, dear to the lord and an attendant of his, asked Sanatkumāra: “Where is that great place which is always the abode of gods, where Govinda sports everyday with the cowherdesses? If you have affection for me, tell me the account of (Govinda’s) sport and whatever else that is wonderful, if you know it.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sanatkumāra-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sanatkumāra said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-6. As occasion arose, I have told what that noble Arjuna, of a good vow, and the attendant of the lord, at some time seated on the bank of Yumunā, at the root of a certain tree, saw and did—his experience in loneliness. I shall tell you that. Listen with great attention. But you are not to divulge it here and there (i.e. anywhere).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>075 Nārada’s Experience</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/075/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/075/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pārvatī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pārvatī said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I. O lord, you have told me in various ways the secret of Vṛndāvana. Due to which particular religious merit did Nārada obtain the natural form?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. Once, formerly I desired to know a wonderful account. From the lotus-like mouth of Kṛṣṇa I heard the secret told by Brahmā. Nārada asked me. Then I got this. “I am not at all able to tell its greatness. What shall I do? Remembering his oath I am distressed in my mind.” Hearing these words of mine, when he became sad, then, O dear one, I called Brahmā and ordered him: “Tell Nārada what you told me.” Then Brahmā, hearing my words, went with Nārada near Kṛṣṇa and asked him that only.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>076 The Greatness of Kṛṣṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/076/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/076/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Here, hearing that Śiśupāla was killed, Dantavakra came to Mathurā to fight with Kṛṣṇa. Hearing that Kṛṣṇa got into a chariot and came with him to Mathurā. Then he killed him, and having crossed Yamunā, and having gone to Nanda’s abode, he saluted his parents and consoled them. He was embraced by them. He embraced all the old cowherds, consoled them, and pleased all living there by (giving them) many garments and ornaments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>077 A Description of Kṛṣṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/077/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/077/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pārvatī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pārvatī said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Tell me in detail the importance of the meaning and the words of the hymn; so also (tell me) the nature of the god, and (about) the splendour of his places. O lord of gods, (tell me) all (about) the great abode of Viṣṇu and Hari’s (i.e. Viṣṇu’s) different modes called eternal bliss.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6a. In the excellent Vṛndāvana (one sees) Kṛṣṇa surrounded by crores of cowherdesses. Gaṅgā is a great power there. The Ānandakānana is (also) there. It is made fragrant by fragrant breezes (blowing) over many good flowers. It is cool and has the colour of the divine ripples of the daughter of Kalinda (i.e. Yamunā). It has come in contact with the best sages—the devotees of the lord like Sanaka etc. It is adorned with flocks of cows, bellowing joyfully and sweetly. It is covered with boys having charming garlands and ornaments and dancing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>078 Worship Prescribed for a Devotee of Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/078/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/078/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pārvatī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pārvatī said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Tell me the correct way of life of the followers of Viṣṇu, practising which all men will cross the ocean of worldly existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9. Here the purification of the devotees of Viṣṇu is said to be in twelve ways: Smearing the house, similarly approaching Hari (i.e. Viṣṇu), going round (his idol) with devotion, (lead to) purification of the feet. Taking leaves and flowers with devotion only for the worship of Hari (leads to the purification) of the hands. This purification is the most important of all purifications. Narration of the names, so also of the virtues of god Śrīkṛṣṇa with devotion, is said to cause the purification of speech. Listening to his account, and witnessing his festival—this is said (to lead to) the proper purification of the ears and eyes. Putting on one’s head the water (used for washing the idol’s) feet, the flowers that had been offered (to the idol), and the garlands (offered to the deity) is said to cause the purification of the head of him who has bowed down before Hari. O dear one, smelling the flowers etc. offered to him (leads to) the purification of the heart, and it is laid down as causing the purification of the nose also. That (place) alone, where there are flowers (and other objects) offered at the couple of feet of Kṛṣṇa, is purifying in the world, and that (alone) would purify everything.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>079 Do’s and Don’t’s for a Devotee of Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/079/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/079/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Not only in the house (but everywhere) the worship of Hari should be done everyday on the Śālagrāma, a gem, a mystical diagram or images. In one region of Gaṇḍakī there is a great place of Śālagrāma (i.e. where Śālagrāma stones are found). May the stone found there protect. This is the case.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5a. By the touch of the Śālagrāma stone, the destruction of sins committed during crores of existences takes place. Then (what can be said) about Viṣṇu’s worship there? It is the cause of (being in) the vicinity of Hari. One would obtain the fruit of worshipping a hundred liṅgas. If one would obtain a black stone (i.e. Śālagrāma) having a mark of a cow’s foot, as a result of religious merit of many existences, then (the mission of) one’s life is accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>080 Month-wise Rites Prescribed for a Viṣṇu Devotee</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/080/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/080/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pārvatī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pārvatī said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Then, how does (a man) survive, when the terrible Kali age, full of the alligators in the form of objects of senses, and having the distress in the form of a son, a wife and wealth, has arrived, O lord? O great god, O treasure of kindness, tell the remedy for it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-8. Kali does not harass them who always utter the name of Hari and Hari only, or the auspicious (utterance) ‘Hare Rāma, Hare Kṛṣṇa’ or ‘Kṛṣṇa, Kṛṣṇa’. Doing (his) deeds one after another, a man should remember (Viṣṇu’s) epithets. He repeatedly says, ‘Kṛṣṇa, Kṛṣṇa, Kṛṣṇa, Kṛṣṇa’. He should also use your name and my name with inversion. He too would be free from sin as fire (goes away) from a heap of cotton. He who mutters my auspicious name with your name as ‘Victory to the First One’, or preceded by the word ‘Śrī’, is freed from the worldly existence. He should remember it by day, at night, in the evening-at all times. He, remembering Rāma day and night, sees Kṛṣṇa with his eyes. He being pure or impure, just by remembering always and at all times, (Viṣṇu’s) name, is, just at that moment, freed from the worldly existence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>081 Mantracintāmaṇi for Devotees of Kṛṣṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/081/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/081/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O Sūta, O good one, live long. You have disclosed the nectar of the deeds of Śrīkṛṣṇa, which emancipates all devotees from the mundane existence. O lord, tell (us) all the daily sports of Śrīkṛṣṇa, on hearing which devotion to Kṛṣṇa increases, O good man. O glorious one, tell us separately the application and characteristic of the prayer of the teacher and the disciple; for, you are our great friend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>082 The Greatness of Vṛndāvana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/082/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/082/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śiva-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śiva said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O Nārada, I shall now accurately tell the rite of initiation. Listen to it. Even without doing it a man would be freed just by listening to it. The wise one, realising that all this world from Brahmā is evanescent, having experienced the threefold misery like that of the mind, and due to all pleasures being transitory, putting them on the side of (i.e. looking upon them as) misery, and being free from them, and being detached should think about the means of the cessation of the worldly existence. He should be very much satisfied to obtain highest happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>083 Kṛṣṇa’s Love Sports in Vṛndāvana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/083/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/083/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O lord, O great one, you have told me whatever I had asked (for). Now I desire to know the excellent path of devotion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śiva-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śiva said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-11. O brāhmaṇa, you, desiring the well-being of all the worlds, have asked well. I shall tell you the secret also. Listen as I (shall) tell it to you. O greatest sage, the maid-servants, friends, parents and beloveds of Hari live here. All of them are eternal and virtuous. As they are described in the Purāṇas (indulging) in open sports, in the same way they remain in sports on the Vṛndāvana ground. They always go from the grove to the cow-pen and come back. They, along with their friends, also graze the cows without any harm from the demons. Similarly people dear to him are proud of those having water-pitchers (the ascetics). With secret devotion they delight their beloved persons. A man should there look upon himself among them as one who is charming, who is endowed with beauty and youth, who is a young woman, who has the form of a young beautiful woman, who knows many crafts and arts, who is fit for Kṛṣṇa’s enjoyment, who is averse to enjoyment though solicited by Kṛṣṇa, who is the follower of Rādhikā and who is devoted to serving her, who loves Rādhikā and who is devoted to serving her, who loves Rādhikā even more than Kṛṣṇa, who, through love, day by day brings about the union of the two (i.e. Kṛṣṇa and Rādhā), who is extremely happy due to the pleasure and joy of serving them. Thus looking upon oneself, one should, beginning with the early part of the day till late night, offer service there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>084 Meditation of the Lord</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/084/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/084/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. O Sūta, O Sūta, O glorious, pleasing Romaharṣaṇa, you have told (us) a story giving delight to the world. O highly virtuous one, we have heard the entire, very wonderful life of Śrīkṛṣṇa, as you narrated it. We are pleased with it. Oh, since (the recital of) the glory of Śrikṛṣṇa gives (the highest) position (i.e. salvation) to the devotees, who would not then obtain joy by (listening to) it? Therefore, we again desire to hear the great account of Śrīkṛṣṇa, so also other vows, presents, worship or bath which were formerly done by whom and how. Tell all that in detail so that we would be satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>085 Greatness of Vaiśākha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/085/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/085/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambarīṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ambarīṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Well (done), well (done), O greatest sage who favour the world, since you told (me about) the meditation of Viṣṇu, with and without qualities. O you who favour the good, now explain (to me) devotion of what kinds (it is), by whom (it is done), how (it is done), where (it is done), and when (it is done).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. Hearing these words uttered by the best king, the delighted sage again spoke to the king: “O king, listen; I shall (now) properly tell you (about) devotion to Hari, which removes all sins. (Now) I shall tell you (about) devotion of various kinds, which destroys sins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>086 Acts to be Performed in Vaiśākha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/086/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/086/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Hearing these words of the high-souled Nārada, the royal sage Ambarīṣa who was amazed, said (these) words:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambarīṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ambarīṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-11. O great sage, leaving auspicious months like Mārgaśīrṣa etc. why do you praise Vaiśākha as the month superior to all (other) months? Why is Vaiśākha most dear to Viṣṇu? What are the rites (to be done) in it? What are the gifts (to be given)? What is the penance (to be practised) and the deities (to be invoked in it)? O sage, please be graceful by favour of your advice, to me who am purified by the dust of your lotus-like feet. O great sage, you alone know the way of life;you emancipate (men) on the ways of religious life. You know the entire truth, you teach the way of life. You are an author, you are an instructor; you are a thinker; you respect (others); you are an employer. O best sage, those who distribute equally, are remembered by those who know sacred texts. All that fruit which is obtained by vows, sacrificial sessions, penance, gifts, is obtained by (giving) instruction in the way of life. O sage, he who prompts another, is also the sharer of the fruit of a bath at a sacred place, penance, and sacrifices which he (who is prompted) gets. Other people do what the pre-eminent people do. The people follow the authority accepted by them. Therefore, you deserve to teach (i.e. please teach) me that wonderful way of life. The advice of a teacher proper for the place and occasion is difficult to get. There are no other objects such as gaining a kingdom, which cool us (i.e. me) down as a meeting with you.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>087 Subtle Are the Ways of Dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/087/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/087/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having heard these words of Nārada the king who was amazed, saluted him, and thinking of Viṣṇu said (to him):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambarīṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ambarīṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O sage, we are confused. How can a very difficult fruit be obtained by a little exertion—merely by means of a bath?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5a. O king, you have spoken the truth that with little exertion great fruit is obtained. Have faith in it. It is the statement of the Creator. The ways of religious merit are subtle; for they are difficult to understand even for the masters. (Even) the learned are bewildered about the act of Viṣṇu whose power is inconceivable. O king, kṣatriyas like Viśvāmitra attained brāhmaṇa-hood due to the excellence of religious merit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>088 Sumanā on Kinds of Sons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/088/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/088/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-11. (Now) I shall describe to you the son connected through debt. Someone having taken debt from someone dies. The giver of wealth (lender) being a son, or a brother, or a father, or a beloved, would, always wicked internally, remain in the form of a friend. He, of a rough figure, would not at all notice virtue(s). He always speaks cruel words to his relatives. He eats sweet (articles of food), and always enjoys pleasures. He is always engaged in gambling, and longs for stealing. He steals money from the house, and, when prevented, gets angry. Every day he abuses his father and mother. He is a thief; he frightens (others); he speaks very harsh words. Thus having seized his wealth, he remains happily. In childhood he takes formidable wealth through the ceremony performed at his birth etc. Again on the occasions of marriage etc. (he takes money) many times and in various ways. In this way the wealth is reduced, and he says this much also: ‘All this—the house, the field—is mine. There is no doubt about it.’ Every day he torments his father and mother with strong sticks, pestles and by ruthlessly plucking their hair. On the death of his father and mother the very cruel one becomes affectionless and harsh. There is no doubt about it. He never performs the śrāddha-rites and never gives gifts. O king, dear sons become like this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>089 Devaśarman’s Life in the Previous Birth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/089/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/089/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Thus addressed (by his wife) the best brāhmaṇa, Devaśarman, again spoke to his wife, having (his) welfare in mind, and talking wisely: “O good one, you have told the truth which destroys (i.e. removes) all doubts, for it has been said that good men, the truly wise ones, desire (the continuity of) their family. O dear one, I am not so much anxious about (getting) wealth as about (having) a son. With whatever means I shall produce (i.e. have) a son.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>090 An Account of Devaśarman’s Good Deeds of Previous Birth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/090/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/090/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;devaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Devaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. You have described to me these deeds done (by me) in my former existence; for, O brāhmaṇa, I earned wealth as a śūdra only. (But) O best brāhmaṇa, how is it that I attained brāhmaṇa-hood? Tell me the reason for all this, O you who are proficient in sacred and profane knowledge. Birth in the Bharata country is difficult. More difficult is to get manhood (i.e. to be born as a human being). In manhood to be born as a brāhmaṇa is difficult; and extremely difficult is to be born in a good family. There also, due to what did I get a chaste wife, knowing everything, speaking agreeably, endowed with all virtues and difficult to obtain?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>091 Happy End of Devaśarman’s Story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/091/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/091/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. That very wise Devaśarman along with that Sumanī took a bath according to proper rites at the very famous and holy sacred place called Kanakhala in (i.e. on the bank of) Gaṅgā in Vaiśākha when the Sun was in Aries. Observing curbs and restraints, he worshipped Viṣṇu according to the proper rites, and gave something (by way of gifts) according to his capacity. He ate food fit to be eaten during days of fast, slept on the bare ground, and practised the vow of celibacy. He became emaciated by the practice of penance like Kṛcchra (i.e. mortification of the body) and meditated upon Nārāyaṇa in his heart. When the full-moon day arrived, he gave honey, sesamum seeds etc., so also he devoutly gave food, a cow along with other presents, to brāhmaṇas, and requested the brāhmaṇas for the absence of a defect in (the fruit of) bathing there. That beautiful, chaste wife, solely devoted to her husband, every day served her husband, after bathing and worshipping Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>092 Citrās Story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/092/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/092/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Hearing these words of that Nārada, that king, being amazed, saluted him, and thinking of Viṣṇu in his mind, said (to him):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambarīṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ambarīṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. How should we err about it, since by means of little exertion a śūdra behaving sinfully obtained excellent brāhmaṇa-hood? O dear one, to obtain brāhmaṇa-hood, even by means of various acts of religious merit, is difficult. (Then) how is it that the mean one obtained it (merely) by bathing (daily) during the month of Vaiśākha? O lord, even rich kings like me do not obtain the lordship of the earth by (performing) sacrifices, (giving) gifts, (practising) severe austerities, and other acts called (acts of) religious merit. That (Viśvāmitra, the) son of Gādhi obtained it after a long time and with great difficulty by practising continuously for full hundred years various kinds of severe austerities and with many efforts. How is it (then) that that sinful one belonging to the lowest caste, bereft of his own duties, poor and non-giver obtained through this small religious merit done without exertion the essential nature of Rāma?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>093 Divyādevī Is Married to Vīrasena</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/093/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/093/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having heard these wonderful words of Jātūkarṇa, the king having respectfully saluted the learned sage, said:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;divodāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Divodāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2a. O sage, how would she now be free from this affliction?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;jātūkarṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jātūkarṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-4. I shall tell you about a very meritorious (act) by (doing) which she would be happy. Though generally it is not to be disclosed, I shall tell it to you. Though the act is small, it is wonderful (and) so would destroy (the fruit of) hundreds of bad acts. As due to the power of meditation upon Viṣṇu great and full sin perishes, in the same way a formidable (sin) perishes due to the (daily) morning bath and gifts (given) in the month of Vaiśākha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>094 The Means of Destroying Sins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/094/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/094/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambarīṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ambarīṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. O lord, I desire to hear that hymn which destroys sins (and) by merely hearing which the heap of sins melts away. I am lucky; I am favoured, that I was made to hear the auspicious rite by merely hearing which the (fruit of) bad deeds that is earned is lost; then what is wonderful there if (greater merit is earned) by auspicious ablutions in the month ofVaiśākha sacred to god Viṣṇu? By ablutions which are laid down as compulsory the heap of sins perishes. Even by the recital of his name, there would be (i.e. one would reach) his heaven. O sage, I think that which is called Viṣṇu’s name is alone meritorious, great, pure, charming, to be attained in the world by good deeds only, and is present in the month of Vaiśākha. Oh! they are blessed who remember the name of Viṣṇu in the month of Vaiśākha. O (sage), tell me again his account which is pure and which is the friend of all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>095 More Rites and Rituals to be Observed in Vaiśākha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/095/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/095/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then the king joyfully asked the sage, after saluting him who was ready to go for his bath, the rite in brief, proper for bathing, giving (gifts) and other performances.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ambarīṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ambarīṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. O sage, in this month of Vaiśākha which rite (should be performed)? Which is superior penance? Which gift (should be given)? How should a bath (be taken)? How should Viṣṇu be worshipped? O brāhmaṇa sage, please tell it (to me). You know everything, and you are dear to Viṣṇu. Tell (me) in particular about the procedure of worship at a holy place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>096 Deeds Leading to Hell and Heaven</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/096/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/096/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O Sūta, O Sūta, O you very wise one, live for a hundred years, since we were made to hear (i.e. you told us) what is beneficial to the world. Again talk the most. We (shall) drink your words. Again and again drinking those words, we are not satisfied, O Sūta.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6a. In this case also there is known an old account—a dialogue between the prime world among the worlds (i.e. the Earth) and the lord of the world. The height of the Earth was six thousand yojanas and the expanse is three thousand yojanas. Thus making the Earth to have (an area of) nine thousand yojanas, he first held the Earth with his large left tooth and lifted her. He held the Earth for a thousand divine years. In course of the legendary account of religious importance she politely said to the lord:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>097 More Sinful and Meritorious Deeds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/097/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/097/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Even a fool knows that a man doing auspicious deeds does not go to hell; in the same way a man engaged in doing sinful deeds does not go to heaven. By those skilful in (good) conduct is obtained the happiness of heaven by means of various sacrifices, and desired vows, gifts, muttering of prayers and truthfulness. Heaven is obtained by sages who have the wealth of knowledge and (good) conduct and who are the masters of the Vedas, due to religious merit and not by means of sacrifices. By a man who is attached to his family, even though having much wealth, much wealth in charity cannot be given without (i.e. unless he has) liberality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>098 The Greatness of Vaiśākha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/098/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/098/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Having heard these words of that Dharmarāja (i.e. Yama), the brāhmaṇa again asked him about the auspicious rite of Vaiśākha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;O magnanimous Dharmarāja, you have properly disclosed the secret of the religious merit due to a bath in Vaiśākha which gives salvation to men, and is great. Tell me the manner in which a man, being calm and having bathed in the morning, should worship the god (Viṣṇu) and with which flowers in the month of Vaiśākha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>099 Kaśyapa’s Advice to King Mahīratha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/099/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/099/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yama-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yama said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Formerly there was a well-known king named Mahīratha who had obtained great power and wealth due to his former religious merit. He merely connfined himself to amorous play with his wife who subjected him to lust. He was addicted to that vice only, and was not settled in piety. Having transferred (the administration of) his kingdom to his minister, the king enjoyed the objects of senses. He, moving in the company of beautiful women, and averse to royal offices, did not consider (i.e. care for) his subjects, wealth, religious rites, material welfare and (other) acts. He only had desire for the amorous play with beautiful women. After a long time his family priest, Kaśyapa, thinking in his mind that a preceptor who, through folly, does not ward off the king should be known as a sharer in the sin, spoke righteous words to him. (He also thought:) ‘If he disregards the words of the family priest though admonished by him, then the family priest is not at fault. The king shares the entire fault’:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100 Carnal Enjoyment Is Sinful</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/100/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/100/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-king-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The king said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. I have been advised by you with words that are like the water of the milky sea, that have a viewpoint that is cool and pure, that are true and beautiful. O dear one, you have made me drink the nectar which has not come up from the ocean, which is not a substance, which is a medicine for the calamity, and which removes the disease in the form of the worldly existence. O brāhmaṇa, it is said that contact of the good gives delight to men, removes their sins, is a medicine for their life, and destroys old age and death. Due to the association of the good only, those desired objects difficult to obtain, are obtained.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>101 King Mahīratha Goes to Viṣṇu’s Abode</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yama-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yama said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. Then the king, observed by the glance of Death, and with his body emaciated due to consumption caused by extreme sexual enjoyment, died. He was being taken by the attendants of Yama, was repeatedly being beaten, was wailing with loud cries, and remembered his sins. Then Viṣṇu’s messengers, having come, beat my followers, and saying, ‘He is righteous’, they put him into an aeroplane. The king, with his sins exhausted due to the morning bath in the month of Vaiśākha, and being praised by the hosts of celestial nymphs, was taken to Viṣṇu’s city. Then, thinking that he was unrighteous, the king was again put by the divine messengers at the behest of Viṣṇu, not far from the path to hell. While going, he heard the various wailings of beings, being roasted in hell. Hearing the very awful cries of the sinners being boiled, the king was amazed and became extremely afflicted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>102 King Mahīratha Gives Part of His Merit to the Sufferers in Hell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/102/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yama-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yama said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O brāhmaṇa, then the king, the ocean of compassion, afflicted by their grief, spoke politely to Viṣṇu’s messengers: “The good ones look upon the protection of the frightened one as the fruit of affluence, nobility of birth and meritorious deeds. If I have some religious merit (to my credit) then, by means of that let these beings, free from their sins, go to heaven. I shall live in their place.” Having heard these words of the truthful king, they, thinking of his truthfulness and generosity, said these words to the king:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>103 How to Meditate on Kṛṣṇa in Vaiśākha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/103/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/103/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yama-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yama said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. O best brāhmaṇa, I have narrated in brief some importance of the month of Vaiśākha, especially of the full-moon day. He who recites this account dear to Viṣṇu in the month of Vaiśākha, getting purified quickly goes to Viṣṇu’s abode and gets delighted (there) for many kalpas. This (description of the) greatness of the month of Vaiśākha, the life of the king and our dialogue are blessed, give fame, long life, are a great means of securing prosperity, lead to heaven, give prosperity, delight, are praiseworthy and destroy sins. Having heard and recited it duly, and delighting the one dear to the mind, there would be (i.e. take place) devotion, due to which there would be the destruction of sins. O brāhmaṇa go, as you desire, from the world of gods. Your kinsmen, having dropped (i.e. put) your body on the ground, are still weeping. Go, as it were, you have just got up from the sleep, before your body is quickly thrown (i.e. put) into fire by your kinsmen that are weeping. By my favour you have heard this path of religious merit. Do it properly. By doing it, you will be united with gods at the (proper) time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>104 Dialogue between Śambhu and Rāma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/104/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/104/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Om, salutation to Śrī Gaṇeśa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O illustrious one, tell us again the wonderful account of Rāma, which is the all-in-all of Rāma’s greatness and which gives delight to the devotees.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6a. The wise son of Daśaratha, after having performed the excellent horse-sacrifice, engaged himself in the worldly deeds and in acts laid down in the sacred texts. Śaṅkara, the magnanimous one, desiring to go to Ayodhyā, lived with Pārvatī on the bank of Sarayū. Great-souled sages like Kaśyapa approached that Śaṅkara, of a universal form, and asked him of unlimited lustre. (They said:) “O best sage, wherefrom have you come with your wife? For what deed have you come with your wife? For what deed have you come here? Which country are you bent on going to?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>105 The Importance of Sacred Ash</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/105/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/105/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. What did the illustrious Rāma do thereafter? What did the magnanimous sages do after that?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9. When Rāmacandra was seated comfortably, (so also) Bibhiṣaṇa, the lord of monkeys, the best sages said to Śambhu: “Tell us a meritorious tale.” Having heard their words, Śaṃ-kara said to Pārvatī: “This is the extremely beautiful house of a certain brāhmaṇa. It is adorned with a lovely garden, wells and creepers. It has (as it were) invited Cupid by means of the rows of humming bees. The sun is, as it were, proceeding to ascend to the mid-day position. We (shall) have bathed in the water of a beautiful well, and (shall have) put on fine garments. We (shall have) besmeared (our bodies with) thick, excellent sandal paste ground (i.e. mixed) with musk. We (shall) have firmly braided hair ornamented with the wreaths of the sallakī (flowers). Having tasted the tāmbūla that is large and dense and excellent and being glad and delighted, we shall remain comforting each other on a bed that is strewn in an auspicious house furnished with artificial jets, full of notes of peacocks along with sweet songs (sung) outside. If the face having a broad smile and red lips will be kissed, then we shall have enjoyed the fruit of the mundane existence.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>106 A Sinful Brāhmaṇa Becomes an Attendant of Vīrabhadra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/106/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/106/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śucismitā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śucismitā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O great sage, the eating of the sacred ash is seen to prolong life. It is capable of giving a course of the other world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;dadhīca-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dadhīca said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8. In this matter I shall tell you an old and well-known account of what happened between Yama and Citragupta. Formerly a dog wandered through hunger in Mithilā. In a hundredth previous existence he was a brāhmaṇa of sinful resolves. In his youth he was a very intelligent (man) who was endowed with the (knowledge) of Vedas and sacred texts. Having gone to Gaṅgā for bathing, he bathed (in Gaṅgā) and having worshipped his dead ancestors, gods and sages also, went to the city (called) Prāttalikā. He took shelter in a brāhmaṇa’s house. There was staying a daughter of a kṣatriya. She was young. Her lover was killed. She had lost her kingdom. She possessed wealth of six crores of niṣkas. At night, after moonlight, she came near the brāhmaṇa who was asleep and was handsome in all limbs, and seeing him said these words: “O brāhmaṇa, wherefrom have you come? To which country will you go?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>107 Vīrabhadra’s Heroic Deed</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/107/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/107/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śucismitā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śucismitā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O brāhmaṇa, O sage, tell me how formerly the sacred ash protected Kaśyapa, Jamadagni of the gods?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;dadhīca-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dadhīca said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. Formerly gods accompanied by Kaśyapa and others went to a well-known mountain named Śokara. In the middle of the mountain was a very beautiful (forest) which was full of many birds, which was resorted to by various hosts of sages, which was the resort of Vāsudeva, which was charming, which was resorted to by bevies of celestial nymphs, which was crowded with strange trees, which was bright with flowers of all seasons. We and others entered the best mountain (forest) like that and praising Viṣṇu went there to lord Śiva. We saw a great flame there and we entered it. Excepting me that deity (i.e. that flame) burnt (other) sages. After that it (also) burnt me. O auspicious one, we were reduced to ash.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>108 How to Prepare Sacred Ash</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/108/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/108/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O illustrious one, tell about the origin of the sacred ash, the greatness of the sacred ash, and the religious merit (earned) through the application of the sacred ash.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śambhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śambhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8a. O Rāma, I shall tell you about the origin of the sacred ash. (I shall tell you about its effect) by (just) remembering or telling about it. O king, listen to it. He who is that eternal god Sadāśiva, who is saluted by Brahmā, who has three eyes, who is the prop of virtues, who is beyond qualities, who is unchangeable and immutable, had once a desire to create on seeing the three qualities in himself—this triad of qualities should be known as the three Vedas. O dear one, having divided himself and the region there, he created on his right side the son, viz. Brahmā and Hari from his left side. At the back side he created Maheśāna (i.e. Śiva); thus the mighty one created three sons. As soon as they were born they became the three gods—Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Śiva. They distinctly spoke these words: “Who are you? Who are we?” To those sons Śiva said: “You are the sons, (and) I am your father. O sons, resort to these three qualities which are the cause of (all) acts.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>109 Jābāli Recommends Phallus Worship to the Brāhmaṇa Ikṣvāku</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/109/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/109/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śambhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śambhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5a. In this regard I shall tell you a story which destroys sins and hearing which the pious one (i.e. Ikṣvāku) obtained excellent devotion. (There was) the best brāhmaṇa, Ikṣvāku by name. He was very learned, very intelligent, proficient in many sacred precepts and well-versed in the science of ethics. He did not perform a sacrifice; he did not give (in charity); he did not worship deities. He did not teach the Vedas, nor did he explain the sacred texts; so also (he did not teach) the Purāṇas, history, the sacred texts or the Vedas. With difficulty he could (get food to) cat and proceeded only with the embellishment of his body. The life (of the span) of a lakh of years of that brāhmaṇa of that type passed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>110 How a King Became Śiva’s Attendant Agniśikha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/110/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/110/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Tell me, how this fire named Agniśikha became an attendant of Śiva like that. Salutation to you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śambhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śambhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9a. Formerly he was a kṣatriya who was always angry. He had lost his wife, his army and his country. (Therefore) he was extremely afflicted. Having got a couple of buffaloes, he practised agriculture with his sons. He was full of (i.e. had incurred) a great debt, and so was very much unhappy. The king was also unhappy on account of his son being killed by (the bite of) a serpent. The king, though like that, also gave up agriculture. He also abandoned his two sons, and having given up food, wept. Then the two sons came to the father, and said these (words) to him: “O father, why do you weep? What has gone does not come (back) by weeping excessively. Your lamentation today will (only) lead to the parching up of your body. Due to the grief your eyes have been impaired; so also your throat has been impaired. Similarly your practice of religious rites has been harmed. (Then) why do you torment (yourself)? One that has gone does not come (back). Protect the five breaths that have remained (with you). It is meritorious to protect many, especially those that have resorted to (a person). How do you grieve over this enemy who has resorted to someone else?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>111 The Sinner Vidhṛta Goes to Śiva’s Abode</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/111/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/111/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O preceptor, tell me the importance of the name of the great lord, the importance of worship, of salutation, so also the greatness of sight, the importance of giving water, so also the importance of offering incense, so also of lamp and sandal, O best one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śambhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śambhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. It is not possible (to describe) in detail the importance of each of the names. I shall tell (it) to you in brief. O Rāma, listen carefully. Formerly in the Tretā age, there was a powerful king by name Vidhṛta. When his father died, he, even though a child, was consecrated (as the king) on the kingdom. He kept near him all those of his age. He did not like those who were old and learned. He liked the young men who were wicked, who did acts which ought not to be done, who were adept in bringing beautiful women (to the king) and were skilled in acts of stealing. He liked those who were engaged in buffoonery, and who were skilled in dancing. Those who knew the charms of subjugation, also those who knew (the use of) herbs, who were given to singing and dancing, who were rogues, and who knew gambling, were dear to him. That king deserted those who did what his father liked.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>112 The Story of Śoṇa and His Wife Kalā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/112/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/112/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śambhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śambhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. (Now) I shall also tell you another account of a woman. (I shall tell you) what Devarata’s daughter obtained by the utterance of (Śiva’s) name. The young, very beautiful daughter of Devarāta was the wife of the intelligent Śoṇa, the son of Dhanañjaya. The two were restrained, devoted to pious acts alone, and virtuous. When they had gone for a bath in Gaṅga, they found a treasure. (When they had gone) to bring clay on the bank that had fallen due to the current, they took a clod of clay and saw a great silver pitcher having a stone on it (i.e. covered with a stone). Then Śoṇa said these words to his dear wife: “How should we act? What should we do that would be beneficial to us?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>113 The Requirements for Narrating a Purāṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/113/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/113/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. In the sky are seen seated in aeroplanes auspicious ones having many forms, good wives, and hundreds of women. At every step they are honoured by thousands of men and women. Twenty damsels, delicate with (good) figures and beauty, are singing. One is carrying a small box; some have their arms attached with (i.e. are carrying) chowries. (Some) have taken a pair of tala fans and are fanning. Another (man) has made the pillow of her lap. He has given his hand in the hands of one. He is surrounded by many flatterers. His lotuslike face is blooming due to jests of many kinds done (i.e. indulged in). In one aeroplane, he, having the moon’s brightness is seen. In the aeroplanes having hundreds of women, the auspicious lord is seen. Have these done (acts of) religious merit? Or is it (simply) Viṣṇu’s illusion, O sage?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>114 Dialogue between Śiva and Rāma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/114/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/114/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Who is this seen in the sky, who is adorned with all ornaments, seated in an aeroplane, who is, as it were, another sun very brightly shining at mid-day and difficult to be looked at by all mortals? On his lap is a sweet-smiling lady like another Lakṣmī. So also there are five good (i.e. beautiful) women. They are singing a sweet song, accompanied by their glances with knitted eye-brows, gentle smiles and sounds made by clappings. At times they are singing songs in their throats (i.e. singing in subdued tones), by striking on one another’s hands, and by looking at one another’s faces with cupidity preceded by songs. Tell me, due to what religious merit the great meditating sage resembling filaments of lotuses, is sporting like this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>115 Reciting and Listening to Purāṇas Is Meritorious</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/115/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/115/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O best brāhmaṇa, how did (the brāhmaṇa) knowing the Purāṇa explain it to the mean brāhmaṇa to whom heaps of sins had come?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śambhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śambhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. Union takes place in teaching and learning. When they go together, O Rāma, in a year the sin of a sinner goes away. O you descendant of Kakutstha, when the knower (i.e. the reader) of a Purāṇa knows all the essential things, then even repeated heap of sins perishes, as the heap (i.e. column) of smoke perishes when a large fire perishes. A moth is capable of destroying a lamp, (but) not (capable of) destroying fire. As one who frees the mortals seized with the fear of ghosts etc., so a public reader of Purāṇas destroys the sin committed by others. One who knows a spell would send away (the ghost etc.), and not he who is afflicted. Similarly, a public reader of Purāṇas does not receive any sin. One who knows Purāṇas, destroys the sin committed by himself or by others, and even (the fruit of) a very wicked sin.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>116 Narration of the Rāmāyaṇa of a Former Kalpa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/116/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/116/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Rāma said to the sage: “Perform the rite of the (evening) prayer; this sun is setting; this flock of birds is going to the nests.” Having abandoned his conveyance, he himself, desiring to offer his prayers went to the northern direction. Songs were sung by (the gandharvas) Hāhā, Hūḥū. His glory was praised by the chief bards. Rāma went to the bank of Gautamī. His pair of feet was washed by Hanūmat (the son of Vāyu). His hand was supported by Jāmbavat. He reached the excellent river Gautamī. Holding kuśa (i.e. darbha) in both his hands that Rāma went to the excellent quarter of Varuṇa (i.e. the Western direction). Having made a respectful offering to the deity according to the proper rite, Rāma who was delighted, muttered (the hymn) in his mind (i.e. silently).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>117 Fruit of Worship by Justly Procured, Stolen and Impaired Material</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/117/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/117/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-10. Rāmacandra, of a pleased mind, ate along with the best sages, Viṣṇu, the monkeys and the bears at the hermitage of Bhāradvāja. The sky was covered with clouds; breezes were blowing gently; in that forest, there was somewhere the excellent house of Sudeva. It had eight pillars; it was fashioned with golden strips; it was (decked) with gems and pearls; it had silver pitchers in it; it was made fragrant with sandal, camphor, musk and saffron; it had multitudes of mire and was covered with pieces.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Moonlight did not reach the walls in its middle part, and also they could not be seen by the sun (i.e. the sun’s rays also did not reach them), The entire floor in the house was sprinkled with excellent juice of flowers. The entire (portion on) the north was without a construction of a wall (i.e. without a wall). On every pillar there were pictures; its courtyard, measuring a hundred cubits had natural parts and was fashioned with crystal. There was a desire-yielding tree in the courtyard, and it covered a larger part of the courtyard by means of its shadow. There was a dense grove of plantain trees forming the entire hedge. With the grove of the plantain trees there was the hedge of ketaki grove. It was full of the cries of peacocks, and bees were sweetly humming in it. It had the cooing of pigeons and was graced with many parks. It was thronged with hundreds of mansions; it was resounding with the notes of intoxicated cuckoos. It had many trees which were graced with big gems hanging from their branches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>118 Section 6 - Uttara-Khaṇḍa (Concluding Section)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/118/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/5/118/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
