<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;1 on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;1 on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-I&#xA;Sriman Narayana, the Lord Supreme1, Who is all-pervading, all-powerful and all-merciful manifests Himself in five different forms2. They are Paratwa, Vyuha, Vibava, Archa and Antaryamin. He is the Ultimate Reality ever associated with SRI MAHALAKSHMI.&#xA;PARATWA is Sri Vaikunta where the Lord is present as Para Vasudeva with His inseperable Consort Sri Mahalakshmi and &amp;lsquo;Nitya-Suris&amp;rsquo; like Ananta, Garuda and Viswaksena. This is also called Paramapada and this state is said to be His &amp;lsquo;Nitya-Vibuti&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;VYUHA or manifestation is of four forms in which the transcendent (Para) God presents Himself for the well-being of humanity. The four forms are called Vasudeva, Samkarshana, Pradyumna and Anirudda.&#xA;VIBAVA is the Lord&amp;rsquo;s Avataras or divine descents in this world as Sri Narasimha, Sri Rama, Sri Krishna etc.&#xA;ARCHA is His deification in our Temples like Srirangam, Tirupati and Kanchi as Sri Ranganata, Sri Srinivasa and Sri Varadaraja respectively.&#xA;ANTARYAMIN is His presence in our hearts as the inner-&#xA;controller.&#xA;Our Barat (India) is considered to be the most sacred of all the places on the earth. The Lord in His abundant mercy comes down from His Nitya-Vibuti or Sri Vaikunta to this earth (His Leela-Vibuti) through various Avataras to emancipate mankind, to destroy the evil forces and protect the innocent devotees. For the same purpose He is also enshrined in our Temples permanently, in the finitised Archa form. The Archa-murtis are lauded and glorified abundantly by our Alwars and Acharyas since they are more easy of realisation even with our limited physical senses, in this mortal world itself.&#xA;5&#xA;Ayodya, Matura, Maya (Haridwar), Kasi, Kanchi, Avantika (Ujjain) and Dwaraka are the seven sacred salvation- yielding cities of the earth. Our great Acharya, Sri Vedanta Desika has said that among the seven cities, our Kanchi is the most important.&amp;quot;&#xA;Again, there are 108 Vaishnavite Divyadesas or sacred places sanctified by our Alwars through their melodious out- pourings of devotion. Even here, our elders have singled out three as more important. They are&#xA;They are Koil (Srirangam), Tirumalai (Tirupati) and Perumal Koil (Kanchi).&#xA;KANCHI appears under all the above categories. Maha- kavi Kalidasa has praised this city as &amp;ldquo;Nagarishu Kanchi&amp;rdquo;. It is the famous seat of learning and propagation of our Vaishnavite cult and other faiths. Great Seers, Bards, Alwars and Acharyas like Budatalwar, Tirumangai Alwar, Tiruk- kachi Nambikal, Sri Ramanuja, Kuratalwar, Nadadur Alwan, Nadadur Ammal, Appullar, Sri Vedanta Desika, Nayana Varadachariar, Panchamata-Banjanam Tatadesika, Lakshmi- kumara Tatadesika, Mahacharya and many others lived or stayed here worshipping the presiding deity Lord Varadaraja, and propagating the Visishtadvaita philosophy. Side by side the Buddists, Jains and Saivites were also preaching their faiths from this sacred centre. Hiuen-T-Sang, the famous Chinese traveller who visited this capital city in the 7th century A. D., during the time of Narasimha Pallava, acclaims it as a place of scholars erudite in their fields of study and advanced in culture. The first Principal of the Nalanda University started by Emperor Harshavardana in the north, it is said, was one Dharmapala who had his education under a scholar at Kanchi. Kautilya (Chanakya) the author of Arta- sastra, Parimelazhagar the famous annotator of &amp;ldquo;Tirukkural” and many other great scholars belong to this great city of learning where there existed a University of renown in olden days.&#xA;This premier city of Kanchi is one of the most ancient cities of our land, situated fortyfive miles south-west of Madras, the capital of Tamilnadu in South India. It is well-planned&#xA;6&#xA;with broad streets and properly ventilated houses, which has won the admiration of even foreign travellers. The very name &amp;ldquo;Kanchi&amp;rdquo; has been given to it because the Lord of Hastigiri blessed Brahma, the creator, by appearing before him in his Aswameda Yaga&amp;rsquo; here. The Temple is situated at the eastern- most end of Kanchi which is in the form of a bow (Danura- kara). The Lord stands facing the city, showering His blessings on it. The western part is higher in level and the eastern part, lower. River Vegavati flows on the southern periphery of the city. A lake near the Temple towards the north is called &amp;ldquo;Arulala Putteri&amp;rdquo; (now colloquially called Allaputteri) after the name of Lord Arulala. The Lord of Hastigiri&amp;rsquo; is called by several names as Tevapperumal (Tepperumal), Varadaraja (Varada), Arulalan (Perarulalan), Devarajan (Devadirajan), Hastigirinatan etc. The lands irrigated by this lake is called &amp;ldquo;Tiruvidipallam&amp;rdquo;, just on the south of the lake and in between the Temple and the lake. The reason or origin of this name is said to be that the &amp;ldquo;Pallam&amp;rdquo; or depth was caused on account of the earth dug out from there for raising the level of &amp;ldquo;Tiruvidi&amp;rdquo; of the Lord, viz., the Sannidi street with the elevated houses on both sides. The steps leading to the houses serve as a gallery to the vast concourse of worshippers to have the Gopuravasal Darsan&amp;rdquo; of the Lord on the famous Garudotsavam day in the early hours of the morning. The street in front of any Temple is usually called Sannidi street. But it will be prefixed with the name of the Temple before which it runs. For instance, at Kanchi itself, there are Sannidi streets like Yatoktakari Sannidi street, Astabujam Sannidi street,&#xA;Ekamreswarar Sannidi&#xA;66&#xA;street, Kamakshi Amman Sannidi street etc., to denote the name of the Temple for which the Sannidi street stands. But our Temple&amp;rsquo;s Sannidi street is named merely as Sannidi street indicating its fame and prominence in the city.&#xA;The street just north to the Sannidi street is called &amp;lsquo;Vadakku Vasal street&amp;rsquo; (colloquially called Varakuvasal street), though this name with this significance has been now changed. Just like the Sannidi street, the Mada streets are also named without the mention of the Temple&amp;rsquo;s name, as North, East and South Mada streets, whereas the other Mada streets of the city&#xA;7&#xA;are called with the names of the temples concerned. A street just towards the east of the North Mada street is called &amp;lsquo;Tiruchola; street&amp;rsquo; denoting its situation on the side of our Lord&amp;rsquo;s garden (Tottam or Tirucholai).&#xA;A tank towards the north-east of the Temple is called &amp;lsquo;Deva- rajan Kulam&amp;rsquo; after the name of our Lord. One street called Hastigiri street is on the southern side of the Temple. One among the several names of our Lord is&#xA;is &amp;lsquo;Girisan&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;Malayalan&amp;rsquo; in Tamil. There is a street, towards the west of the Temple bearing this name Malayalan, called Malayala(n) street.&#xA;The Easwaran Temple&amp;quot; on the south-western side of our Temple is called &amp;ldquo;Punyakotiswarar Temple&amp;rdquo;, perhaps indicating its situation whence the Punyakoti Vimana&amp;rsquo; of our Lord is visible. Not only at Little Kanchipuram but also at Big Kanchipuram we can find such significant names of places and streets. Our Lord is Varada Raja. The four Raja streets are named after Him. The grand Brahmotsava is celebrated in all its flare and pomp, around here in the Tamil month of Vaikasi. The huge car of our Lord is also dragged round these four Raja streets.&#xA;The Gangai Kondan&amp;rsquo; Mantapa built by the Chola King Rajendra I (Gangai Kondan) is situated at the north-western corner of the Raja street for our Lord&amp;rsquo;s alighting here during the days of the Brahmotsava on the huge Vahanas both in the day and in the night.&#xA;There are some interesting particulars regarding Krishna Devaraya&amp;rsquo;s mediation in connection with some difficulty regarding the routes of the cars of Siva Temple and ours. It seems the trustees and other employees of both the Temples came to an agreement before him as regards the routes to be followed by the Cars and Vahanas of the two Temples during their festive rounds.&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Attiyur &amp;quot; - &amp;ldquo;Tiruvehka&amp;rdquo; - &amp;quot; Ashtabujam &amp;ldquo;.&amp;rdquo; Velukkai” &amp;ldquo;Tirutanka&amp;rdquo; (Toopul) - &amp;ldquo;Uragam&amp;rdquo; - &amp;ldquo;Padagam &amp;ldquo;- &amp;ldquo;Parame- swara Vinnagaram&amp;rdquo; etc. etc. are some of the fifteen sacred localities (Divyadesas) of the city.&#xA;8&#xA;The puranio version of this great city and Avatara of Lord. Hari as Varadaraja before Brahma, the creator, in his Aswameda Yaga (Sacrificial fire) is given in the &amp;ldquo;Hastigiri Mahatmya a part of the Brahmandapurana.&amp;rdquo; This is depicted, as is usual with the puranas, in the form of a dialogue between sage Narada and Brugumaharshi.&#xA;According to it under the behests of an &amp;ldquo;Asareeri &amp;quot; (a voice from an unseen body coming from the skies) Brahma performed the yaga at this place which is called &amp;ldquo;Satyavratha Kshetram in order to get his mind purified. It is said, that a good deed done here is equal to that of one thousand such good deedsR performed elsewhere. Brahma could cleanse his mind only by performing one thousand Aswameda yagas. Since he could not complete so many yagas in his lifetime, he was advised by the Asariri to go to this place for performing the yaga in order to achieve his object.&#xA;Accordingly, when Brahma started the yaga at this place, his consort Saraswati tried to prevent it by assuming the form of a rivulet (Vegavati) and rushing towards the site of the yaga with the object of destroying it. She had a grouse against her husband previously. When she was requested to forget it and come to participate in the yaga as the Darmapatni to the &amp;lsquo;Karta&amp;rsquo; (the performer), she refused, incited by the Asuras&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;Brahma, the Rishis and the Devatas prayed to the Lord for protecting them from the calamitous consequences of the deluge. Bhagavan Sri Narayana, in response to their prayers laid Himself bare before the on-coming fury. of the flood. Vegavati&amp;rsquo; had to subside and turn in a different direction before the Lord who proved to be a dam. This is the Tiru Vehka&amp;rsquo; the Sacred place where the Lord lies and the Deity is called Yatoktakarin. In Tamil He is called &amp;ldquo;Sonnavannam-&#xA;6&#xA;Saitha-perumal.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;After that Brahma successfully completed the yaga, along with his pacified Darmapatni Sri Saraswati, in which the Lord appeared before him in the Punyakotivimana in all His9&#xA;glory and resplendence as Varada (giver of boons). After worshipping the Lord, Brahma returned to Satyaloka, mentally purified. Before he left, he prayed that the Lord may deign to remain in the place everlastingly to bless mankind. Acceding to his request the Lord remains here making this place His abode on the earth (Vaiyamaligai). From that time onwards the place has come to be known as Kanchi&amp;rsquo; since Ka&amp;rsquo; (Brahma) worshipped Hari&amp;rsquo; from here.&#xA;&amp;quot;&#xA;Great seers, Alwars and Acharyas have sung in praise of Sri Varadaraja in ecstatic terms. Sri Vedanta Desika had sworn, that he would prefer stay in this mundane world, worshipping the Lord of Hastigiri to the attainment of Vaikuntavasa (Moksha). Such is the enchanting and soul- stirring beauty and gracefulness of the Lord that our great devotee-saints were completly dazed and captivated when worshipping Him.&#xA;Sriman Narayana also sends His close attendants and devotees the Nityasuris and Sudarsana Panchajanya (discus and conch) etc. to this world whenever he finds it necessary to retrieve mankind. One such devotee was the Sage Satamarshana who was the descendant of Vishnuvardana, one who was deeply immersed in the devotion of Lord Vishnu, as the name itself signifies.&#xA;It is said that Satamarshana came to the world later as Satakopa. Sriman Natamunikal who descended from Satamar- shana worshipped Sri Satakopa who was the manifestation of his great ancestor himself for restoring the Tamil Vedas.&#xA;Later his grandson Sri Alavandar, Sri Tirumalai Nambikal Sri Ramanuja and Sri Pillan spread the Visishtadvaita philosophy handed down to them by Sriman Natamuikal. Side by side with the Sri Bashya pravachanas (interpetation and teaching of Brahma Sutras) these Vaishnavite savants ingratiated the prabandas of Alwars as an inseparable part with their cult. The principle of Ubaya Vedanta thus became the main feature of Vaishnavism. Tirumalai Nambi is stated to have been an authority on both these Vedantas.10&#xA;10&#xA;Sri Peria Tirumalai Nambikal, the grandson and disciple of Sri Alavandar and maternal uncle of the great Vaishnavite teacher Ramanuja was staying at Tirupati (Tirumalai) and doing Kainkaryam to the Lord of the Seven Hills side by side with his teachings of Vaishnavism. He was also one of the Acharyas of Sri Ramanuja, his nephew. It is said that Lord Srinivasa was very much pleased with him for the paternal care he was taking of Him and on one occasion the God is said to have addressed him &amp;ldquo;mama-tata &amp;quot; (my father) and ever since then Peria Tirumalai Nambikal came to be recognised by the name Tatacharya, a title which his descendants also began to assume. &amp;ldquo;There were several branches of the family, many members of which were holding important positions during the period of the Vijayanagara rule &amp;ldquo;.11&#xA;Tirukkurukai Piran Pillan (11th century, AD) was the son of Sri Tirumalai Nambikal. Sri Ramanuja was the sister&amp;rsquo;s son of Sri Nambikal (Srisailapurna). Sri Pillan&amp;rsquo;s keen perception, deep knowledge in the scriptures and devotion to Sri Ramanuja endeared him very much to the latter. He was chosen by Sri Ramanuja as the fit and competent person to translate the Tiruvaimozhi, since he had both the capacity and heredity to undertake the task, as a descendant of Sriman Natamunikal.1 The annotation of Tiruvaimozhi thus brought out by Sri Pillan under the behests of his Acharya is called the famous Aaraayirappadi&amp;rsquo; the first gloss in Manipravala, an elegant mixture of Sanskrit and Tamil expressions of the Divya Prabandas. Further he was made the first and foremost among the seventy-four Simhasanatipatis created by Sri Rama- nuja for propagating the Visishtadvaita philosophy after him,&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; and was also announced by him during his last days that he (Pillan) was his Gjnana Putra and successor. 14&#xA;Srinivasacharya1&#xA;After Pillan, Tirumalai&#xA;may be mentioned in this great line (Vamsa). He was one of the most trusted disciples of Sri Vedanta Desika (13th and 14th Centuries AD). Tradition has it, that Sri Vedanta Desika. who was attending to the worship of Lord Varadaraja, later&#xA;11&#xA;entrusted the responsibility to Sri Srinivasacharya, whom be considered as the best choice for this service. Thus the Srikaryam of the Temple devolved upon him and, later on on his descendants.&#xA;FOOT NOTES&#xA;PART I-CHAPTER I&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;foot-notes&#34;&gt;CHAPTER-II&#xA;&amp;lt;&#xA;Before proceeding further, it may be relevant here to give an account of the history of the Tatacharyas as royal preceptors of the Vijayanagar monarchs. The Vijayanagar Kings from Vira-Sayana Udayar down to Venkata III (the middle of the 17th century), who, notwithstanding their general religious toleration seem to have in later times developed a leaning towards Vaishnavism, and to have made the Varadaraja Temple an object of their special adoration&amp;rsquo;. This is evidently due to the influence their preceptors, the Tatacharyas of Kanchipuram had over them. Ettur Singaracharaya and his brother Ranga- charaya enjoyed royal patronage under Virupaksha. From this, it does not mean that they had lost touch with Kanchi, Temple of Varadaraja, and their kinsmen there. Their interest in this Temple must have been ever-abiding and they should have lost no opportunity to impress upon their patrons of Vijayanagar the need to develop the leanings of the latter in Vaishnavism to take concrete shape in utilising their resources in building the structures and maintaining the worship in the Temple.&#xA;In Saka 1387 (1465 A.D.), according to an inscription&amp;quot; during the reign of the Vijayanagar King, Virapratapa Devaraya Maharaja of the Sangama dynasty, one Kumara Tata Aiyangar of Satamarshana gotra, is said to have contributed 400 panams for offerings to Perarulalapperumal, &amp;ldquo;who was pleased to take his stand at Tiruvattiyur&amp;rdquo;. Devaraya II was the greatest ruler of the Sangama dynasty. He is distin- guished in Inscriptions by the title of &amp;ldquo;GAJÄBETEKARA”, i.e., elephant hunter. He is sometimes called, &amp;ldquo;Immadi Deva- raya&amp;rdquo;. It is significant that this &amp;ldquo;Immadi&amp;rdquo; prefix is also attached to the names of the Tatacharya-preceptors Vijayanagar rulers.&#xA;of the&#xA;King Virupaksha II 1465-85 (A.D.). King Virupaksha II was the next Vijayanagara King whose story may be related here. During his reign two Tatacharya brothers,&#xA;13&#xA;figure prominently by name Ettur Singaracharaya and Ranga- charaya of whom the former was the royal preceptor. They were very proficient in the exposition of the Ramayana. This is a heritage which they inherited from their ancestor Sri Periya Tirumalai Nambikal who was said to have attained to great glory by his mastery in Srimad Ramayana. Sri Ramanuja, his nephew had to make, it is said, eighteen trips to Tirupati to get himself initiated in this sacred treatise*, under him.&#xA;There is also a story regarding the spiritual powers through which the Tatacharya brothers warded off the evil spirit that possessed the King&amp;rsquo;s daughter&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;The genealogy of the members of the Tatacharya family is found given in an inscription&amp;quot;. King Virupaksha according to an inscription made some offerings to our Temple&amp;rsquo;. This connection of the Tatacharyas with the Vijayanagar royal line continued till the last.&#xA;The next prominent King of the&#xA;the Tuluva Dynasty. his guru.&#xA;Prof. K. A.&#xA;Krishnadevaraya 1509-30 A.D. of the line, is Krishnadevaraya He had also a Tatacharya as Nilakanta Sastry describes the Sri Vaishnava leaders in the sixteenth century as &amp;ldquo;able leaders who were men of considerable learning. They were men of great tact and possessed much skill in carrying on religious propaganda. According to the Telugu literary tradition, a Sri Vaishnava teacher, called Tatacharya was the guru or spiritual advisor of Krishnadevaraya”.&#xA;66&#xA;This Tatacharya was Venkata Tatacharya the elder brother of Panchamata-banjanam Tatadesika. Dr. B. A. Saletore describes him in the following words:&#xA;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;the famous dictator, Venkata Tatarya whom as already narrated above, Krishna Devaraya, the great, invested with uncommon religious powers in A.D. 1523, was entitled to receive the first THIRTHA and PRASADHA in all the great Vishnu Temples in Vijayanagra Ghanadri and all the 77 durgas, gutti durga, etc. in all the cities to the east and west of Vijayanagara as far as the sea; in all the durgas to the north and south as far as Madura and all the holy places such as Kanchi, Trisaila and Khadri excepting Srirangam, Ahobila and Ghatikagiri, privileged to get&#xA;14&#xA;the first honours in the assemblies of the Sri Vaishnavas and authorised to make enquiries into the conduct of all castes owing allegiance to Ramanuja and to punish the delinquents in regard to religious and social matters&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Krishnadevaraya was an ardent Vaishnavite as evidenced by his munificence to our Temple in gilding the Punyakoti Vimana with gold and rendering several other acts of benevolence1o. In this he was chiefly guided and influenced by his Tatacharaya- preceptor who was naturally interested in the Temple as its cus- todian. &amp;ldquo;There appears to have fiourished two or three people bearing the name of Tatacharya during the first half of the 16th century.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;A copy of copper plate grant mentions &amp;ldquo;Venkata Tatarya (of Sathamarshna gotra - Apasthamba Sutra - Yajus Sakha, son of Ahobilacharya son of Srirangadesika) on whom Krishnaraya conferred some privileges in 1522 A.D.&amp;rdquo;. This Tatacharya was the elder brother of Panchamatabanjanam Tatadesika as said above. But the father&amp;rsquo;s name is wrongly quoted and the grand father is Sundara Desika and not Sriranga Desika.&#xA;Though an ardent Vaishnavite devotee, Krishnaraya gave due regard and respect to religious heads like Vyasa Tirta of the Madwa Math. He was also impartial in his munificence towards both Siva and Vishnu Temples, as evidenced by his present- ation of a car each to the Vinayaka and Krishna images of the two temples at Kanchi 1*. This is further borne out by the following extract:- &amp;ldquo;.&#xA;18&#xA;The Manucarita gives a brief but poetic description of the Sabha or the royal assembly as it existed during the time of Krishnaraya. To this assembly called Bhuvanavijaya, flocked the Amaranayakas and their repre- sentatives, Chiefs of subordinate states, Princes, Dalavays, Mer- chants, Ambassadors from foreign states, Pandits, Poets, Philosophers, Theologians and all those that depended upon the court for eking out a living. The &amp;lsquo;Amuktamalyada&amp;rsquo; alludes to the Sabha which was attended by the Ambassadors from foreign Kingdoms. It was here that the Emperor gave audience to representatives of foreign rulers and heard the disputations of&#xA;1&#xA;15&#xA;rival Theologians and Pandits. It was here Vallabha, Chaitanya, Vyasathirtha and Tatacharya waxed eloquent over the excellence of their respective creeds&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;..&#xA;Panchamata Banjanam Tatadesika 1509-1591 A.D: One of the luminaries of the renowned Vaishnavite Acharyas in the line of Sriman Natamunikal was Sri Panchamatabanjanam Tatade- sika, son of Kandanur Srinivasachariya who flourished at Kanchi in the sixteenth century, A.D. Born in the Tamil Year Vibava, Masi month and Swati star, corresponding to Kali 4610, he was named &amp;ldquo;Tatadesika&amp;rdquo; by his parents, after Sri Peria Tirumalai Nambikal, their illustrious ancestor and uncle of Sri Bashyakar, whose birth star also happens to be &amp;ldquo;Swathi&amp;rdquo;. He had his education in the Vedas and the Sastras under his father and subsequently he was initiated in the Sri Bashya and other philosophical works, by his maternal uncle, Shashta Parankusa Swami, the sixth pontiff of the Ahobila Math. He attended to the &amp;lsquo;Srikaryam&amp;rsquo; service also under the behests of his uncle, it is said.&#xA;He was a great scholar and a spiritual preceptor to the Vijayanagara rulers, Sadasiva, Ramaraya, Tirumala, Sri Ranga and Venkata. Sri Doddayachar otherwise known as Mahacharya another Vaishnavite scholar and devotee was his contemporary as also the famous Saivite scholar Appayya Dikshita. This Mahacharaya, finding the enormous influence Sri Tatacharya wielded over the Vijayanagar rulers sought his help to restore and establish the worship of Sri Govindaraja at Chidambaram, when there was some trouble over it caused by the Saivites. Sri Tata- charya accordingly, helped in fulfilling the same 1. The works &amp;ldquo;Panchamathabhanjam&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Chandamarutham” 1A were produced by Sri Tatacharya and Sri Doddayacharya respectively as a counter to the Advaitic philosophy expounded in those days by Saivite scholars like Appayya Dikshitar. Regarding Sri Panchamatabanjam Tatacharya, Dr. B. A. Saletore says,&#xA;66&#xA;an equally great name among the Rajagurus was that of the celebrated Tatacharya, the family guru of Ramaraya, Born in the Srisaila Vamsa of the famous Srisailanatha, also known as Peria Tirumalainambi, the maternal uncle of Ramanuja,&#xA;16&#xA;Tatacharya, the son of Srinivasa Guru, learned in all Sastras, was the Acharya of Rama Raja. He accompanied the Emperor to Chandragiri” 1⁄4&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Rama Raya (C. 1550) is said to have preferred Tatacharya to Govinda Desika as his Acharya. A manuscript work of the seventeenth century attributes to Rama Raya anti-brahmanical tendencies. This &amp;ldquo;estimate of Rama Raya seems to be exagger- ated for neither contemporary inscriptions nor the literature and chronicles of the period say anything about his anti-brahmanical tendencies. Further the author of the work appears to have been a Madwa disappointed in his expectations at the fact Govinda Desika was replaced by Tatacharya in the exalted position of being the guru of the King. Obviously the author of the work was a partisan and wanted to paint Ramaraya in black colours, on account of his preference to Tatacharya&amp;rdquo; 1o.&#xA;Ramaraya was completely under the influence of Sri Tata- charya, the Rajaguru. During his times and during the times of the inheritors of the fragment of the empire after the battle of Talikota, mass conversions took place engineered by the Rajaguru under State patronage. Sri Appayya Dikshita in his 66 NIGRAHASHTAKAM &amp;quot; says that the leader of the Vaishnavas had taken a resolute vow to stamp out Saivism from the land. The Prapannamrtam, a work of one Ananta- charya, which purports to record the history of Vaishnavism and the lives of the Acharyas, refers to Sri Appayya Dikshita as living at Chidambaram, resplendent with fame and unassailable by controversialists, sectarian or philosophical and proceeds to state that to refute his great works on Sivadvaita and Advaita, Sri Tatacharya wrote a work called &amp;ldquo;Panchamata- banjanam&amp;rdquo; and Mahacharya wrote a work called &amp;ldquo;Chanda- marutam and thus both of them defended the creed of Sri Ramanuja&amp;rdquo;. The lives of Sri Tatacharya and Appayya Dikshita &amp;ldquo;ran together during the major part of the sixteenth century. During all these years of Sri Tatacharya&amp;rsquo;s supremacy, Sri Appayya Dikshita is not known to have anything to do with the Vijayanagar court. After 1585 when Venkatapathi was re-establishing the glory of Vijayanagar and the younger Tatacharya was the Rajaguru, Sri Dikshita was invited to the court and was held in great honour &amp;ldquo;1&amp;rdquo;&#xA;17&#xA;With his immense power and wealth, he secured from the kings, Sri Tatacharya started many constructional works in our Temple many of which were later completed by his illustrious son, Sri Lakshmi Kumara Tatadesika. During the period of Sadasivaraya he brought one Ramanujayya from Tiruppullani for undertaking these works, whose services are praised in two Tamil verses.1 He is said to have attained to great fame and beautitude&amp;rdquo;. Later, his family settled down at Kanchi itself as there was opportunity for continued work. It is said that &amp;ldquo;the right of supervising the repairs and certain items of service which was then in the hands of one Ramayya was cancelled, perhaps at the instance of Kumara Tatacharya by Venkatapatideva Maharaya, and conferred on this Parankusa Thiruppanippillai1. He is described as a probable partisan of the all-powerful Tatacharya. The right of supervising repairs (Tiruppani Nirvaha Kaniya kshi) was sold by Ettur Tirumalai Kumara Tatachari and other trustees of the same temple to Tiruppani Sri Parankusan and his disciples &amp;ldquo;21. This is attested by Inscriptions at Tiruppukkuli Vijayaraghava- Perumal Temple during the time of Srirangadeva Maharayaa2. We learn that Sri Tatacharya was the Guru of Venkata even when he was a Viceroy in 1582 A.d** and that Sri Tatacharya was managing the temple affairs**.&#xA;Thus we find the major constructions and improvements that took place during the sixteenth century viz., the gopuras, prakaras, mantapas, like Abhisheka mantapa, Hundred pillard Mantapa containing beautiful pieces of architecture, Vimanas, etc. were all started, managed and completed by the Tata- charyas who had the full support, backing and patronage of the Vijayanagar Kings from Krisnadevaraya down to Venkatapati Deva Maharaya (Venkata I) and Venkata II.&#xA;From the inscriptions of the Yatoktakari Temple, we are informed that in all the inscriptions of the King, Ettur Kumara Tatacharya figures prominently&amp;rsquo;.&#xA;Every member of this family styled himself as Tatacharya of Ettur and hence arises the confusion in clearly identifying persons bearing this name. This is certainly true, in that it&#xA;2&#xA;18&#xA;requires, some clarification, So let us be excused for a small digression here. Because of the same names and appellations attached to the members of this family, even historians and epigraphists had to give conflicting opinions. For instance, while giving the genealogy of the Tatacharya family of Kanchi, S. I. T. I. III states that &amp;ldquo;Panchamatabanjanam Tatacharya 1509-91 A. D. (otherwise known as Kotikanyaka- danam Tatacharya whose name was Lakshmi Kumara) is the same as Lakshimikumara Tatacharya&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; This is not correct. Lakshmi Kumara Tatacharya was the son of Panchamata- banjanam Tatadesika by adoption. Sri Lakshmi Kumara&amp;rsquo;s natural father and younger brother of Panchamatabanjana, was Tirumalirumcholai Aiyangar of Kumbakonam2&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;One thing should be clearly borne in mind. Sri Lakshmi- kumara Tatacharya was born at Kumbakonam in 1572 A. D., and lived upto 1632 A. D. Records or inscriptions mentioning the name Kumara Tatacharya prior to 1572 A. D., therefore, should be that of his father Panchamatabanjanam Tatacharya or his ancestors. The titles Lakshmi Kumara and Kotikannika- danam belong to Sri Tatacharya who flourished between 1572-1632 A. D. He officiated at the Pattabisheka ceremony of Veera Venkatapati Deva Maharaya at a very young age of fourteen or fifteen when his father was alive and very old. Evidently because of his old age (nearing eighty) he had the coronation done through his young adopted son &amp;ldquo;Aparyapta- mrta&amp;rdquo; who later became the illustrious Lakshmi Kumara Kotikannikadanam Tatadesika.&#xA;Venkatapatidevamaharaya (1585-1614 A.D.) Now, we come to Vira Venkatapatidevamaharaya (Venkata I), the fourth son of Hiri Timmaraja (Tirumala) who ruled for 29 years, after having been crowned by his royal guru, Sri Lakshmikumara Tata- desika in 1585 A.D. His reign witnessed vast improvements in the construction of temples as well as the expansion of his empire to its original greatness after the battle of Talikota. Though the whole empire devolved upon him after the death of his brothers Sri Ranga and Rama Raja, Venkata chose to remain at Chandragiri, his original seat of Kingdom. This was perhaps in deference to the wishes of his preceptor, Sri Tatacharya, who19&#xA;desired that he should remain near the sacred Tirupati. Because of this, he is sometimes called as the &amp;ldquo;Raja of Chandra- giri&amp;rdquo; and his Acharya as Venkataraya Tatacharya, the Tatacharya whom King Venkata revered. A good number of inscriptions mentioning Sri Tatadesika during the reign of this monarch have been found on the walls of &amp;ldquo;Arulala Perumal&amp;rdquo; Temple at Kanchi and in several other places of the Empire.&#xA;29&#xA;Venkata is said to have been a subordinate of Sadasivaraya in Saka 1489 (1567 A.d.) 2*, He was referred by his title alone, viz., &amp;ldquo;Viravasantaraya&amp;rdquo; in two epigraphs from the Salem and North Arcot Districts&amp;quot;. During the reign of his father Tirumala and his elder brother Sriranga II he governed the Chandragiri Rajya as its Viceroy as indicated in the Telugu Kavya &amp;ldquo;Vasu- caritamu&amp;rdquo; 1 and next held &amp;ldquo;Charge of the Udayagiri, Kondavidu and other outlying hill fortresses&amp;rdquo;. He had married five queens, one of whom Krishnamamba or Krishnajiamma ** is mentioned in the T.D.E. Report.&#xA;On his accession to the Karnataka throne after his brothers, he transferred the capital of Vijayanagara from Penugonda to Chandragiri as aforesaid. &amp;ldquo;Having been initiated by his GURU Kumara Tatacharya, he became an ardent Vaishnava and encouraged the propagation or Vaishnavism. He was a staunch devotee of Sri Venkateswara. As a memorial of his Bhakthi, a copper statue of his, with folded hands and palms joined in a prayerful aspect is found placed on the south side within the inner front Mantapa adjoining the entrance PADIKAVALI GOPURAM of the temple of Sri Venkateswara at Tirumala with the name &amp;ldquo;Venkatapathirayulu&amp;rdquo; incised in Telugu characters on the right shoulder. The figure appears to be muscular in form and ordinary stature, but the warrior in the King is not prom- inent as in the statue of Krishnaraya placed in a group with his two queens on the north side of the same Mantapam &amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo;.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Although himself a staunch Vaishnava, yet Venkatapati- devamaharaya welcomed the Jesuit fathers to his Court at Chandragiri in 1598 and granted them complete freedom to preach their religion and erect churches&#xA;churches throughout his dominions. He held disputations on God, Philosophy, and&#xA;20&#xA;Mathematics with the teachers or Philosophers almost everyday. The protagonist of Vaishnavism, Saivism and Christianity vied with one another to convince him of the superiority of their respective creeds and he gave them all a patient hearing. Himself a great scholar, he was devoted to the protection of the learned. Eminent philosophers like Tatacharya and poets like Chenna- maraju, Matla Ananta and Tarigoppula Mallanna adorned his Court. With a view to foster learning he and the Nayaka of Madura endowed several colleges for the maintenance of pro- fessors and students who were supplied with victuals, cloths and everything they needed&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;. &amp;hellip;..His copper statue in the Tirupathi Temple is another proof of his artistic taste&amp;rdquo;. Though he is styled here as Venkata II, he is Venkata I according to us and many other authorities we have quoted elsewhere.&#xA;•&#xA;It is thus seen that in the spread of Sri Vaishnavism in Vijayanagar from the days of Mallikarjuna the members of the Srisailapurna family played an important role. This should lead to the conclusion that although Mallikarjuna (1447-1465) and Virupaksha II (1465-1485) became convinced of Tatacharyas&amp;rsquo; greatness as spiritual leaders they did not openly change their faith in favour of Vaishnavism. But that they had special and exclusive leanings towards Vaishnavism cannot be questioned. Saluva Narasimha (1468-1491) ** Vira Narasingha (1505-1509) 86 Krishnadevaraya (1509-1529) Achyutaraya (1529-1542) Sada- sivaraya (1542-1570) ** and Sri Ranga I (1572-1585) ** were Vaishnavas of course not of the bigoted kind. An inscription of Devaraya dated 1465 records a grant of money to Kumara Tatayyangar, son of Tiruvenkadayyangar and grandson of Sottai Tozhappayyangar of Sathamarshana gotram, evidently belonging to the family of Srisailapurna,. The money was given for specific Naivedya in Arulalaperumal Temple. This is a clear proof for recognising the role of the members of Srisailapurna family played in our Temple and the honoured position they held in the court of the rulers of Vijayanagar.&#xA;PART I-CHAPTER II&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;89&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-III&#xA;Sri Lakshmi Kumara Tatadesika 1572-1632 A-D. Sri Koti- kannikadanam Lakshmikumara Tatadesika (1572-1632 A.D.) was the son of Sri Tirumalirumcholai Aiyangar and the adopted son of Sri Panchamatabanjanam Tatadesika. Born at Kumba- konam (Tirukkudandai) in the Tamil Year of Prajotpati (Kali 4673 1572 A.D.), Karthikai month, Anusham Star (Nakshatram) he was later taken to Kanchi, by his adopted father, for initiating him in the line of spiritual preceptorship (Acharya Sthanam). Elders have considered him as the incarn- ation of Viswaksena (Senainathan) the commander-in-chief of Lord Sriman Narayana.&#xA;At the time of his birth, he remained still and did not cry. The parents thought that the child was still-born. Just then a noble lady appeared there, took the child in her lap and after suckling it with her milk, left the child on a piece of cloth torn from her saree. The child revived and began to cry. Some time after this incident when they went to worship Sri Komalavalli Tayar in the Temple, they observed to their great surprise the torn saree worn by her. Realisation dawned at once that the lady who brought life to their child was no other than Sri Komala- valli Tayar. Subsequently when the first birthday was celebrated at Kanchi to the child, Sri Perundevi Tayar also showered Her blessings on the child similarly when the child had an attack of high fever. Thus from his very birth he was endowed with the grace of Sri Tayar (Lakshmi Devi) which earned him the name of Lakshmikumara.&#xA;Out of the sacred and precious heritage he inherited from his ancestors, Sri Tatadesika not only maintained the daily worship and management of the Temple, but also developed it further by his vast and huge constructions with big rampart walls, mantapas, prakaras, etc. Some of the works were started during the time of his father, as said earlier. One such monumental piece of his works is, the granite hundred&#xA;24&#xA;pillared mantapa containing skilful pieces of architecture like the stone chains on the corners and the cat and the pigeons all made of a single &amp;lsquo;stone, with its monolithic pillars and exquisite cary- ings, which is even today the great attraction of tourists and foreigners at Kanchipuram.&#xA;Sri Tatadesika was the Manager-general of the temple affairs (Sri Karya Durandara) from and during the time of the Vijayanagara King Venkatapatideva Maharaja, to whom he was the spiritual guru and officiated on the occasion of his&#xA;coronation.&#xA;It may be of interest to note here that the Kings of Vijaya- nagar were all invariably crowned by their spiritual preceptors, the Tatacharyas at the time of the coronation, just as we see in the days of Ramayana, Sage Vasishta, the royal guru of the Kings of &amp;ldquo;Surya Vamsa&amp;rdquo; performing the Pattabishekam cere- mony of the Kings including Sri Rama. To quote again, Dr. B. A. Saletore, &amp;ldquo;we may disgress a little in order to form an idea of the coronation scene at the courts of Vijayanagar. Rajanatha, in his well known work mentioned above, gives us an admirable picture of the coronation of Achyutaraya, when, so we are told, the Queen Varadhamba was also anointed to the House&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.. The most prominent person on such occasions was the Raja guru or Royal Priest. We are told that Venkata- pathideva Maharaya was anointed to the throne by Thathacharya, &amp;ldquo;the guru of his own gotra and other chief Brahmins&amp;rdquo; in a cop- per plate grant dated A.D. 1589 and again in A.D. 1602-3&amp;rdquo; 1.&#xA;(From the copper plates examined during 1917-18 by the Ephigraphical Department of the Government of Madras, another piece of information that Sriranga was crowned by Tatacharya, is got. This Sriranga is evidently Sri Ranga III, who was crowned in or about 1642 A. D., and the Thathayarya mentioned here is evidently the son of the great Laxshmikumara Tatadeshika, either Sri Tirumalai Tatayarya or Venkata Tatayarya).&#xA;Venkatapatideva Maharaja, &amp;ldquo;in his excess of admiration for his Acharya is said to have offered the whole Kingdom to&#xA;目&#xA;T&#xA;The Hundred Pillared Mantapa&#xA;(P. 24)&#xA;A Front Portion of Peria Tirumadil&#xA;(Prakara Wall)&#xA;(P. 24)&#xA;A View of the Aiyangarkulam and the Temple&#xA;(P. 26)&#xA;The Nadabavi Well&#xA;(P. 26)&#xA;25&#xA;him&amp;rdquo; According to the Prapannamrtam Venkata entrusted the whole kingdom to Thathacharya and himself led a life of retire- ment. It was thus he happened to achieve his object of construction of temples all over India, spend huge amounts on establishing Agraharams, build tanks, provide capital for the maintenance of the temples, secure valuable jewels, gold coverings, etc. to the deities and give gifts towards marriage expenses to bachelors and unmarried girls in abundance. Since he was responsible for innumerable marriages, he acquired the title of &amp;ldquo;Koti Kannikadanam&amp;rdquo;. In a sloka in praise of him, it is said humorously that even Hanuman and Vigneswara, the legendary bachelors, shuddered at this marital munificence, lest their bachelorism may also be affected one day.&#xA;&amp;ldquo;கலயதி விபுதார்யே தாதயாசார்யவர்யே ஸபதி&#xA;கடிததாராம் வர்ணின ஸ்வர்ணஜாலை: அவிரதமிஹகாஞ்ச்யாம் வீக்ஷ்ய கல்யாண கோடீம்- ஹநுமதி கணநாதே கம்பதே பிரம்ஹசர்யம்.”&#xA;&amp;ldquo;He weighed himself against gold and silver and used all that wealth in the service of God Varadaraja of Kanchi in erecting the &amp;ldquo;Kalyanakoti Vimana&amp;rdquo; in gold for the Goddess Lakshmi in that famous temple&amp;hellip; The Kalyana Koti Vimana was finished about 1614 A. D. and was evidently built in emula- tion of the Punyakoti Vimana set up by Krishnadevaraya. The latter was repaired by Tatacharya and regilded by him as it had decayed&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;He was a great Rama Bhaktha and so with the grace and help of Hanuman he was able to ward off the evils that surrounded him at times. &amp;ldquo;There is also a record registering the Hanumat Vimsati, a poem of twenty verses composed by him in honour of God Hanuman whose image he set up in the tank now known familiarly as the Aiyankarkulam dug by him. According to an inscription on the bund of the Tenneri Tank, Chingleput District, it seems to have been dug by Tatacharya&amp;rdquo;. He is probably identical with the Tatacharya mentioned in a record dated 1590 A. D. as the grandson of Ettur Srinivasa Tatacharya and son of Srinivasa. This record registers the grant of a village called Vekatesapura in his favour. His&#xA;26&#xA;forebears have been connected with the spread of Vaishnavism and the family claimed descent from Srisailanatha, the uncle of the great reformer, Ramanuja&#xA;Aiyangar&amp;rdquo; is a term generally used to denote a Vaishna- vite Brahmin. Since he was an outstanding figure of this community, he is exclusively termed as &amp;ldquo;Aiyangar&amp;rdquo;. Just as we find streets, places, etc., nowadays being named after big leaders, certain streets, places and villages in and around Kanchi, were named after him and his consort, &amp;ldquo;Ammangar in those times. &amp;ldquo;Aiyanpettai&amp;rdquo;, Aiyangarkulam &amp;ldquo;, &amp;ldquo;Aiyangarpalayam Street&amp;rdquo;, Ammangar Street&amp;rdquo;, etc. of Kanchipuram are some of the standing examples, even now.&#xA;66&#xA;66&#xA;In Aiyankarkulam, a village named after him as said above near Kanchipuram, he built a huge tank and temple to Sri Rama and His Bakta Sri Hanuman. It is said that as he was returning with huge riches to Kanchipuram from one of his wide tours, it grew dark and he was forced to camp at this place for the night for performing his daily evening chores. Just then he was surrounded by a band of robbers. Sri Aiyangar was inside the tent uttering Rama Nama. As Hanuman is an unfailing attendant wherever Rama Nama is uttered, he came to the spot and stood guard at the entrance of the tent. When the looters approahed the tent, Sri Hanuman gave vent to a &amp;ldquo;Humkara (wrathful exclamation) out of which there sprang a band of men greater in number than the &amp;rsquo;looters. They surprised the looters by their sudden appearance, wrested the torches from their hands, beat and drove them away. All this took place in such a swift and sudden manner that Sri Tatadesika who was in his trance was not at all aware of the happenings outside. When he got up next morning, the newly sprung up men with the blessings of Rama Bhaktha paid their obeisance to the Acharya and detailed to him the happenings of the previous night. Thereafter these men placed themselves at the service of the Acharya, who took them into his fold as disciples.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Sri Tatadesika also constructed a huge well nearby with a big cloistered verandah and mantapa underneath-which is now known as &amp;ldquo;Nadapavi.&amp;rdquo; A grand festival to Sri Devaraja27&#xA;is performed annually on Chitra Pournami day in the temple at Aiyankarkulam and the Nadapavi (well). The festival, popularly known as &amp;ldquo;Aiyankarkulam festival&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Nadabavi festival &amp;quot; attracts devotees in their thousands.&#xA;Though he was a staunch Vaishnavite leader, he was tolerant towards other religions. It is said he was responsible for renovating a portion of the Siva temple at Tirukali- kunram, when approached by some Saivaites.&#xA;The gold gilding of the Ananda Nilaya Vimana of &amp;lsquo;Panipathigiri&amp;rsquo; was done in 1630 A. D. by him during the time of Venkata II&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;He was also responsible for establishing 500 Agraharas; performing 99 yagas and making 32 Tulabaras and the cons truction of Tenneri&#xA;Tenneri lake, otherwise known also as Tata Samudram, near Kanchipuram. He had also installed idols of Sri Vedanta Desika in so many &amp;ldquo;Divyadesas &amp;quot; like Thirukkanna Mangai, etc. He had also composed several&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Grantas&amp;rdquo;&#xA;His various life episodes and sevices are inscribed on stone walls all round the Temple of the Lord of Hastigiri and other important Temples of the south. He is also deified along with his consort, Sri Ammangar, in Sri Vedanta Desika&amp;rsquo;s shrine, in our Temple, Kumbakonam, Srirangam and other places.&#xA;Sri Devaraja and Sri Perundevi are brought in a grand procession to his shrine and a very big festival takes place for a full day in his honour on his annual &amp;ldquo;Tirunakshatram&amp;rdquo; day of Kartikai Anusham. In all the perambulations of Lord Varadaraja and Sri Perundevi, Sri Vedanta Desika and Sri Tatadesika and his consort are bestowed with special &amp;ldquo;Satari&amp;rdquo; etc. honours, which is an unfailing feature in the Temple. His life is a true example of how a Vaishnavite grahastha should spend and live for others, immersed deeply in devotion and service to the Lord Almighty.&#xA;Sri Tatadesika was the author of many works like, &amp;ldquo;Lakshmi&#xA;Niyudam&amp;rdquo;, Panchagranthi Nipaharam &amp;quot;&#xA;66&#xA;66&#xA;28&#xA;&amp;ldquo;Sapthagranthi Nipaharanam&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Desika Prabanda Yeedu &amp;quot; Nigama Parimala Arumpadam&amp;rdquo;, etc. He has also brought out a philosophical work by name, &amp;ldquo;Satvikabrahama Vidya Vilasa&amp;rdquo;. Based propably on this work, the Kannada Poet Rangaraja, who lived at the court of Chikka Deva Raja, brought out a work of the same in Kannada. Another work called &amp;ldquo;Panduranga Mahatmya&amp;rdquo; was also made by this great Acharya. This is also to be distinguished from the Telugu work of the same name by Tenali Ramakrishna. A work called, Hanumat Vimsati, composed by him in praise of Hanuman is inscribed on the walls of the temple built by him at Aiyankarkulam, evidently after he was saved by Him from the bandits. &amp;ldquo;He is called in the Dalavai Agraharam grant, as &amp;ldquo;The ornament of the wise&amp;rdquo;. Dr. N. Jagadesan, Ph.D., describes him as a distinguished man of letters and is known for the authorship of a play in five Acts &amp;ldquo;Parijatha Apaharana &amp;ldquo;10.&#xA;In Kali 4733 Prajotpatti (1632 A. D.) Tamil Panguni month (on the day after Sri Rama Navami) This great Acharya attained moksha, on the way to Chandragiri from Tirumala Hills. Thus ended, with him, a golden era in the renaissance and prosperity of our Temple.&#xA;PART I-CHAPTER III&#xA;FOOT NOTES&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-IV&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After the decline of the Vijayanagar Empire in the middle. of the 17th Century A.D. the Tatacharyas continued to main- tain the upkeep of the Temple, as usual, in its usual glory and splendour. The Temple was already well provided for by the munificence of the Vijayanagar monarchs, through the agency of Tatacharyas, who procured vast lands, properties and finance sufficient to last for generations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Subsequently they (the Tatacharyas) were sought after by the Wodeyar kings of Mysore. One of the descendants, Sri Venkata Varada Tatarya, the second son of Lakshmikumara Tatadesika went there as the royal guru of the Mysore Maharaja in the latter half of the 17th century.1 This Tatacharya&amp;rsquo;s influence over the Mysore Wodeyars contributed not a little towards the uplift of the Temple. It is said orginally the Garudotsavam of our Temple was celebrated by the Kings of Mysore, through the instrumentality of their preceptor the Tatacharya and it was stopped only during the middle of the 19th century after nearly a century, on account of a small misunderstanding. We shall speak about this misunderstanding by and by.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 THATHACHARYA TRUSTEESHIP</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/5_THATHACHARYA_TRUSTEESHIP/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/varada-tAtArya-survey/1/5_THATHACHARYA_TRUSTEESHIP/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER-V&#xA;THE HISTORY OF THE HEREDITARY TRUSTEESHIP OF THE THATHACHARYA FAMILY&#xA;In 1842, the Government, in pursuance of their policy to deliver over the temples to the &amp;ldquo;original mirasdars&amp;rdquo; called for applications from the parties who had such claims.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Rayaguru Kotikannikadanam Kumara Kumara Tatacharya, descendant of Lakshmi Kumara Tatadesika claimed the hereditary right to trusteeship. Tenkalais and others also claimed likewise.&#xA;1&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Collector Mr. Freeze after enquiry, made a proposal for appointing a committee, consisting of the representative; of all the four claimants for entrusting the management in its hands. Sri Kumara Tatacharya objected to this and preferred a petition to the Board of Revenue against the proposal of the Collector.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
