<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;ए।एम्। श्रीनिवासाचार्यः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/e.em._shrInivAsAchAryaH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;ए।एम्। श्रीनिवासाचार्यः on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/e.em._shrInivAsAchAryaH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>श्रीमद्भागवतम्</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/e.em._shrInivAsAchAryaH/shrImadbhAgavatam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/e.em._shrInivAsAchAryaH/shrImadbhAgavatam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[श्रीमद्भागवतम्&#x9;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ebharatisampat.in/readbook3.php?bookid=Mjg1MzY4OTE1MDU5MDU2&amp;amp;pageno=MjI0MjQyNjk5NTk=&#34;&gt;EB&lt;/a&gt;]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[TABLE]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOREWORD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;______&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;T&lt;/strong&gt; has been the ambition of Mr. G. A. Natesan to popularise the three most important poems in the sacred literature of India by bringing out abridgments of the original Sanskrit texts with an English translation. He first brought out an abridgment of Valmiki&amp;rsquo;s Ramayana, the most famous Kavya in the classical literature of India. This was immediately followed by the abridgment of the Mahabharata, the greatest Itihasa. His latest venture is the abridgment of the Srimad Bhagavata which may be justly described as the greatest and most popular of the Puranas. Every Purana has necessarily to deal with a certain number of topics according to traditional conventions, and the manner of treatment of these topics is more or less on similar lines. But each Purana is further intended to serve a special purpose. The Puranas generally contain a strange medley of fables and fairy tales, philosophy and religion, myth and legend. It is not easy for a Western reader to appreciate to appreciate the teaching and value of our Puranas without a knowledge of the methods employed by the ancient&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
