<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;२ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;२ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>001  The Story of Śivaśarman</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Om, salutation to Śrī Gaṇeśa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O glorious Sūta, O you who know the significance of the essence of everything, (please) listen to the terrible doubt, destroying understanding, that has occurred to us. Some describe in the Purāṇas that when Prahlāda was five years old he pleased Keśava (i.e. Viṣṇu).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. How did (the war) between gods and demons come about? How did the demon fight with Viṣṇu? He, killed by Viṣṇu, entered his body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>002  Life is Restored to Vedaśarman</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Then taking it the virtuous one quickly left. By his devotion for his father, his austerities, and the power of his truthfulness and straightforwardness, Dharmaśarman attracted Dharma (i.e. Yama).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-3a. Attracted by the penance of that intelligent (Dharmaśarman), Dharma, who had come (there), said these words to Dharmaśarman:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4a. “O Dharmaśarman, why did you invite me? I have&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;come. Then tell me about your work. I (shall) do it. There is no doubt about it.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>003  The Heroic Deed of Viṣṇuśarman</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Proceeding along that path, he entered the heaven. He was seen by the intelligent Indra, the lord of gods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4a. Knowing his exertion, the king of gods put in an obstacle. He said to that (nymph) Menikā: “Go by my order; O you of beautiful waist, going quickly create an obstacle (in) his (way). Well-being to you. Do that to the son of that excellent brāhmaṇa Śivaśarman by which he would not come to my house.” Hearing these words of him, Menikā started quickly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>004  Somaśarman’s Devotion Put to Severe Test</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;l. When they had gone to the Goloka of Viṣṇu, beyond darkness, the very wise Śivaśarman said to his youngest (son):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. O very wise Somaśarman, you are very much devoted to (me) your father. Now protect this pitcher of nectar given by me. With this wife I shall go on a pilgrimage.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“O glorious one, let it be so. I shall protect the auspicious (pitcher)”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>005  The Consecration of Indra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śivaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śivaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O good son, today I am pleased with your penance, restraint, purity, and with your service to the elders and your devotion and resolution.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. I (shall) abandon this deformed body; obtain happiness from me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Saying so to the son, he showed that (former) body.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. He saw both the elders (i.e. his parents), who became as they were before, who were bright, who were magnanimous and who resembled the orb of the sun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>006  Diti’s Wailing</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. The other miserable wife of Kaśyapa, named Danu, being tormented by the grief due to the son (of Aditi) came to Diti’s house. She was weeping, she who was reached by (i.e. was of) great grief, saluted the two lotus-like feet of Diti. Diti advised her.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;diti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Diti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O glorious one, what is the cause of your weeping? Women are (said to be) ‘Putriṇī (i.e. endowed with sons) (even though) they have (only) one son. O beautiful, auspicious one, you are the mother of even a hundred magnanimous sons like Śumbha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>007  Account of the Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;diti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Diti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O Lord, you have spoken all the truth; there is no doubt about it. Abandoning love for my husband, I entertained rivalry (with my co-wife), O brāhmaṇa. (Now) being tormented by pride, agony, humiliation and great grief, I shall, O best one, give up my life.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kaíyapa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kaíyapa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. (Please) listen, I shall tell (i.e. explain) you in such a way that there will be (i.e. you will have) peace (of mind). O auspicious one, nobody is anybody’s son, or mother or father. Nobody has a brother or a relative. None has kinsmen and friends. In the mundane existence such is the relation, affected by illusion and infatuation. O respectable lady, one is one’s own mother, one’s own relatives and kinsmen. One is oneself the eternal moral virtue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>008  Account of the Soul</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kaśyapa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kaśyapa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. He, being afflicted day by day, became bewildered in the womb. The rightenous one, harassed by all kinds of suffering, was overcome with grief.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. With his face turned down he remained in the womb. He was overcome with mental agonies and physical diseases; he was lamented over; he was senseless.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3a. He was full of great grief. Being (thus) tormented, he said to Jñāna:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ātman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ātman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4. O you very wise one, at that time I did not do what you told me (to do). In spite of being prevented by Dhyāna, I fell into the danger caused by delusion. Therefore, O you highly intelligent one, protect me from this very fearful stay in the womb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>009  Instructions to Diti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kaśyapa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kaśyapa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. The intelligent Ātman, thus addressed by Dhyāna and others, desiring to give up the product of the five-natured ones, and finding out motives, abandoning his aimless body, which he did not notice when it fell down, went to them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. There is no connection between life and body that were brought up together. For what reason is there a relation with wealth, sons or wife?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-13a. O you very dear one, realising thus, be calm; do not be weak-minded. He alone is the highest Brahman; he alone is eternal. This Ātman lives in demons and gods in his own nature. He is Brahmā; he is Rudra; he is the eternal Viṣṇu. He creates all things; he protects the beings. This (Ātman) Janārdana (i.e. Viṣṇu), the pious one and of the nature of virtue withdraws (all). O you very dear one, he has created gods and demons. Gods are liberated due to their piety (while) your sons are wanting in piety. This virtue is Viṣṇu’s body, preserved by all gods. O respectable lady, one (i.e. a man) should think about proper conduct and follow proper conduct only. The meritorious Viṣṇu always favours him. Gods always lived with piety, truth and penances. Those, with whom Viṣṇu is pleased, have practised virtue here (i.e. in this world). This proper conduct is the body of Viṣṇu and truth is his heart. Viṣṇu is pleased with him who always practises them. He, who would defile truth and piety would always have sin. The very powerful Viṣṇu would be angry with him and would destroy him. Viṣṇu’s devotees, abiding by truth and penance practised piety. The virtuous one is pleased with them and protects them thus.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>010  The Practice of Penance by Demons (Dānavas)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O you very intelligent one, what effort did all the demons, who were accompanied by Hiraṇyakaśipu and had fled from the battle, do? Tell us in detail their excellent account. O brāhmaṇa, we all now desire to hear it from you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. All the demons who had fled from the battle, who had become powerless, prideless and distressed with grief, went to their father.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>011  The Story of Suvrata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. You, the omniscient one, have narrated (to us the account of) the war between (the gods and) the demons. Now we desire to hear (the account) of the noble Suvrata.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Of whom was he—the very intelligent one—the son? In whose family was he born? What (kind of) penance did the brāhmaṇa have (i.e. practise)? How did he propitiate Hari (i.e. Viṣṇu)?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. O brāhmaṇas, I shall tell you the account of the noble Suvrata as I had heard it due to the power of my intelligence. I shall tell you, with Viṣṇu’s favour, the divine, purifying account bringing the Viṣṇuite merit (to the narrator and the listener).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>012  Dialogue between Somaśarman and Sumanā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. (Now) hereafter I shall describe to you the son who is related through debt. He, from whom a man takes a loan dies—i.e. the creditor, being (i.e. is born as) the son or the brother or the father, or might be (born as) a friend (and) is always very cruel, O dear one. The cruel one of a rough form, does not notice the virtue (in others), and always utters harsh words among his relatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>013  Sumanā Explains Ten Basic Virtues</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;somaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O beautiful lady, tell me in detail the characteristics of Celibacy if you know them. Of what nature is Celibacy?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. (He is a true celibate) who is always interested in truth; he the righteous one would (i.e. is) always be satisfied; and being free from faults would approach (i.e. cohabit with) his own wife when she menstruates.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. He never gives up the good practices of his family. O best brāhmaṇa, I have told you this (i.e. these characteristics) of a householder. I have indeed explained to you the celibacy of (i.e. as observed by) householders.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>014  Sumanā Describes the Death of the Virtuous</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;somaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O good lady, how do you do such an excellent and highly meritorious exposition of Dharma? From whom did you learn this?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O you very intelligent one, well-known Cyavana, well-versed in all (branches of) knowledge, and born in the family of the Bhārgavas was my father.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. I was his dear daughter, dearer to him than his own life.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Always playing, I used to go with him wherever he went—to sacred places, groves, assemblies of sages and temples of deities, O you of a good vow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>015  The Death of Sinners</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;somaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O good and beautiful lady, tell me, if you know it, in detail, what characteristics appear at the death of sinners.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4a. O my dear husband, listen; I shall tell you what I learnt from the Siddha about the death of the sinners and what its marks are. I (shall) also tell you about the place and actions of great sinners. A very wicked man reaches a region which is inauspicious due to its being impure on account of excretion and urine; and has a painful death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>016  The Death &amp; Post-mortem State of Sinners</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. That wicked man being burnt and struggling again and again is taken along a path full of a heap of charcoals.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Being tormented by the sun’s rays, he is taken along that path on which the sun’s heat is intense and which is heated by twelve suns.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. The wicked-minded one is taken along the path, on mountains, inaccessible and shadow-less places, while he is very much tormented by hunger and thirst.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>017  The Story of Somaśarman’s Previous Birth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;somaśaman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somaśaman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O respectable lady, you have told (me) the excellent form of Dharma. O you noble one, O you of a good vow, tell me if you know how I would get a son endowed with all virtues. There is no doubt that good acts like charity (are fruitful) in this and the next world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sumanā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sumanā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Go to Vasiṣṭha who knows (what) virtue (is). Request that great sage. From him you will (learn how to) obtain a son knowing piety and loving it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>018  The Account of Somaśaman’s Birth in a Brāhmaṇa Family</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;somaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O sage, you told me about my sin in the former birth. O best brāhmaṇa, in what way was I forsaken by śūdrahood and did I obtain brāhmaṇahood? O you well-versed in spiritual and worldly knowledge, tell me all about it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vasiṣṭha-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vasiṣṭha said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. If you think (like listening to them) listen; I shall explain to you, O brāhmaṇa, what religious deeds you did in the former birth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>019  Somaśarman’s Eulogy of Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. The very intelligent, the best (brāhmaṇa) Somaśarman, having bathed, with (his wife) Sumanā, at the auspicious (sacred place called) Kapilāsaṅgama,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on the bank of Revā, causing great merit, he, the intelligent one, and of a good vow, having gratified (with oblations) gods and manes, practised penance there, with a very calm mind and with meditation, muttering with the hymn of twelve syllables (the name) of auspicious Viṣṇu—that Vāsudeva, the magnanimous god of gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>020  The Birth of Suvrata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;hari-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hari said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O brāhmaṇa, I am pleased by this meritorious penance of yours, and also by your truthfulness; and I am also pleased by the holy hymn of praise. Choose a boon. O you illustrious one, I shall grant you the boon that you have (i.e. cherish) in your mind. I shall fulfil (i.e. satisfy) whatever desire you entertain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;somaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Somaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O Kṛṣṇa (i.e. Viṣṇu), first, with a pleased mind, grant me a boon much desired by me, if you have good (i.e. great) pity for me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>021  Suvrata’s Devotion to Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Once that resplendent Vyāsa, being extremely amazed, asked Brahmā, the lord of the world, (about) the entire account of Savrata.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O soul of the worlds, O you in whom the worlds are deposited, O god of gods, O great lord, I now desire to hear the life-account of Suvrata.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahmā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O you noble Pārāśarya (i.e. son of Parāśara), listen to the meritorious, excellent account, full of practice of penance, of the brāhmaṇa Suvrata.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>022  Dharmāṅgada Born as Suvrata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O noble one, I shall put one question to you. Now speak (i.e. answer) it; you yourself had formerly said that Suvrata meditated upon lord Nārāyaṇa Anāmaya, due to former practice. In which caste was Suvrata born in his former birth? Now tell that to me (and also) how Hari was propitiated by him. O lord of gods, who is he that is full of merit?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahmā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-13. In the auspicious city (called) Vaidiśa, full of all prosperity, (lived) a very lustrous, powerful king, the son of Ṛtadhavaja. His very intelligent son was well-known as Rukmabhūṣaṇa. His loyal wife was the glorious Sandhyāvatī. The king&amp;rsquo;s son (i.e. Rukmabhūṣaṇa) having produced a son on her like himself, named him Dharmāṅgada. This (Dharmāṅgada), the most fortunate son of Rukmāṅgada, was endowed with all auspicious marks and was intensely devoted to his father; and he, for the happiness of his father, even gave his own head to Mohinī. Hṛṣīkeśa (i.e. Viṣṇu) was pleased by his Viṣṇuite way of life and devotion to his father; and took him physically to Viṣṇu’s position. He, who knew all codes of conduct, who was a devotee of Viṣṇu, who was best of the Sātvatas, he—Dharmāṅgada, who was very wise, who was well-versed in judgement and knowledge, who was an ornament of piety, living there only gladly enjoyed all divine pleasures according to his desire. When a full thousand yugas were over, he who was piety (himself) and an ornament of piety, dropped from that position, and due to the favour of Viṣṇu, was born as the eldest and most fortunate and intelligent son of Somaśarman, increasing the delight of Sumanā, and named Suvrata. The intelligent one practised penance and was intent upon meditation on Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>023  The Slaying of the Demon Bala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O you best among speakers, you have told us this wonderful, meritorious, excellent tale, bringing about glory, and destroying all sins. Please tell us the propriety of the creation. O son of Sūta, tell us in detail, as to how the creation (took place) formerly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. I shall tell in detail the cause of creation and destruction, merely by hearing which a man would become omniscient. Hiraṇyakaśipu occupied the three worlds. Having propitiated Brahmā by penance, he obtained a boon, difficult to obtain, and also immortality from that noble god. He, having pervaded gods and the worlds secured mastery (over all).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>024  Vṛtra Duped</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Having heard that her very powerful son Bala was killed, Diti piteously wept saying: “Oh, I am facing a great misery.” Having thus very piteously wept for a long time, the miserable, glorious one went to Kaśyapa, her husband, and said to him:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. “Seeing your son who had gone to the ocean, the very sinful Indra, the lord of the host of gods, with his thunderbolt killed him having the characteristics of a brāhmaṇa and just practising &lt;em&gt;sandhyā&lt;/em&gt; (i.e. the daily prayer).”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>025  The Killing of Demon Vṛtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I. (Vṛtra thought:) ‘Who is this woman with charming eyes, singing in graceful modes? This attractive woman shines all round. She would delude people with full emotions.’&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. Seeing that Rambha, of large eyes like lotuses, of plump breasts, with her body smeared with sandal, with her face resembling a lotus, (he thought) ‘Is she the abode of my sexual desire or is she charming and attractive Rati? Sent here only by Cupid, I shall certainly approach her, who is full of emotion, endowed with good form, disposed to sex, and of an extremely good disposition.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>026  The Origin of Maruts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O best brāhmaṇas, that Diti, hearing that her son was killed, was afflicted with pain and tormented with grief due to (the death of) her son. She again said to that noble, best sage Kaśyapa: “O best brāhmaṇa, to kill that very wicked Indra, give me, O lord, a son having Brāhmaṇic lustre, strong and unbearable to all deities, if I am very dear to you, O my beloved husband.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>027  Coronation of the Kings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/027/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/027/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. That lord, Brahmā, the master of all worlds, having then consecrated on the entire kingdom (i.e. as the king of all the kingdom) that great lord, king Pṛthu, Vena’s son, of large arms and a huge body, and resembling Indra, the lord of gods, and taking into account (other) kingdoms one by one, proceeded to give each one that kingdom, which he deserved.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4. The highly intelligent one consecrated Soma (i.e. the Moon) as the king of the trees, brāhmaṇas, of planets and stars, of all pious acts, of religiously conducted sacrifices, of merits and of those of an auspicious lustre.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>028  The Story of Pṛthu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/028/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/028/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. O noble one, (please) tell us in detail (about) the birth of that magnanimous Pṛthu. We desire to hear it. (Tell us) how that noble king formerly milked this cow (i.e. the earth); how gods, manes, sages knowing the truth, demons, serpents, Yakṣas, trees and mountains, goblins and Gandharvas, brāhmaṇas doing auspicious acts, and how other magnanimous ones (did so). O you highly intelligent one, tell us especially how they held the pot of milk and the manner in which she was milked. O Sūta’s son, tell us why formerly the very meritorious and angry sages churned the hand even of that noble king Vena. This is a strange account which destroys all sins. We are desirous of hearing it; O noble one, (it is so interesting that) we are not at all content with (i.e. even though we hear) it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>029  The Story of Pṛthu (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/029/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/029/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pṛthu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pṛthu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;l-13a. If a very sinful one is killed, O you of sinful conduct, good people rich in merit live happily. Therefore one that is most sinful and of a wicked mind should be killed. Now you have suppressed all seeds by devouring them. Where will you go by being stable after having destroyed the beings? When a sinful one of a bad conduct is killed, the good live happily. Therefore sin should be destroyed; this is the truth; there is no doubt about it. That from which merit proceeds, should be carefully preserved. You have committed a great sin causing the destruction of the beings. He who for himself or for someone else kills one who torments the world, does not incur sin. O auspicious Earth, when many people become happy by a wicked one having been killed, there is neither a (major) sin nor a minor sin. There is no doubt that (i.e. certainly) I shall kill you. If, O Earth, for the good of this world (i.e. these beings), you do not act according to these meritorious and good words of (i.e. uttered by) me, I shall kill you with sharp arrows, if you are averse to my words. There is no doubt that I shall sustain, by means of my lustre and merit, the virtuous beings living in the three worlds. Accepting my meritorious rule, and obeying my order always rejuvenate these beings, O Earth. If, O you good one, you today obey this order of mine, then I shall be pleased with you, and will always protect you, and also other best kings (will protect you); there is no doubt about this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>030  Sulobha and Śapharahā; Suśaṅkha and Sunīthā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/030/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/030/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O brāhmaṇa, what was the course of conduct of that sinful Vena, whom you mentioned as behaving sinfully, and what fruit did he get? O you wisest and very intelligent one, tell us in detail the account of that Vena (as it) formerly (took place).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-9a. I shall properly tell you the story of that Vena and also the very meritorious account of his noble son, as I have heard it before. When that magnanimous son, Pṛthu, was born, the king (Vena) became spotless and again became religious. All the major sins earned (i.e. committed) by mean persons vanish with their close contact with the sacred places. There is no doubt that merit alone is produced in the company of the good; and sin alone is produced in the company of sinners. Sin would spread around by talking with, seeing, touching, sitting and taking food with and by the company of sinners. In the same way merit alone would spread in the company of the meritorious. The sinners are purified by their contact with great sacred place (only) and in no other way; and ultimately, with all their sins completely washed, they obtain a holy status.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>031  The Account of Suvrata</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/031/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/031/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. Then Aṅga, the very lustrous one, seeing noble Indra’s wealth, enjoyment of amorous pleasures and sports (thought:) ‘How shall I have a son, endowed with piety, like Indra?’ Aṅga, the best among the righteous, thinking like this, came to his own home. Bowing down and with his neck (i.e. head) bent down (in respect) he asked Atri, his father: “Who enjoys this high position of Indra by doing pious deeds? Of what merit is this the result? What deed did he do? And of what kind was it? What kind of penance did he have (i.e. practise)? Whom did he propitiate formerly? O best among the truthful ones, tell me in detail (about) this.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>032  Aṅga Gets a Boon from Vāsudeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/032/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/032/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-20. The best mountain (i.e. Meru), with its regions very bright with various gems and gold on all sides, shone like the Sun with his rays. All the meditating saints, seated on firm seats after resorting to very pleasing, cool, comfortable shades, meditated. At some places the sages practised penance; at some places Kinnaras sang (songs). Gandharvas, being delighted, (sang songs), beating time with their hands. Delightful songs were presented by them, who were engrossed in beating (and) measuring time in music, and with the seven musical notes; and with melody and closed fists. On that greatest mountain, Gandharvas, knowing the essential nature of songs, and being intent on singing, sang them, after having resorted to the shades of sandal-trees. The divine women danced there on the excellent mountain. The sound (of the recitation) of the Vedas, which destroyed sins, gave religious merit, which was divine, which bestowed great bliss, and which was very sweet, was heard on the best mountain. The excellent mountain shone with (trees like) sandal, Aśoka, Punnāga, Śāla, Tāla, and bunyan, resembling clouds. The lord of mountains shone at every place with Santānaka&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; trees, desire-yielding trees crowded with Ambhā (?) trees and well-blossomed divine trees. The mountain was full of many minerals and full of heaps of gems. It was full of many wonders and of various auspicious things. It was resorted to by groups of Vedas and was full of the groups of celestial nymphs. It shone with sages, ascetics, Siddhas and Gandharvas. It looked beautiful with elephants resembling mountains and with the roars of lions. It was adorned with Śarabhas&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, with furious tigers and cunning beasts. Everywhere it looked charming with wells, pools and tanks containing spotless water and crowded with swans and ducks. It looked beautiful with golden, white and red lotuses. The lord of mountains looked charming with groups of rivers and streams having clear water, with Śāla and Tāla trees, and with crystal forms and elephants, and with slabs of stone which were extensive, golden, divine and which resembled the sun and fire. It was adorned with the mansions of deities, and palaces (resembling) excellent mountains, and with golden staffs resembling swans and the moon. It was also decorated with pitchers, chowries and palaces. It was also adorned with hosts of gods delighted by various excellences (of the mountain). That holy, best mountain Meru shone all round with many hosts of gods, Gandharvas and bards. That great river, which is very holy, which contains sacred water, which is rich with holy places, which is crowded with swans and lotuses, and which is resorted to by ascetics and hosts of sages, has risen from it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>033  Sunīthā’s Story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/033/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/033/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. She (i.e. Sunīthā) was cursed by that Suśaṅkha, the noble son of a Gandharva. Due to his curse how did she become (i.e. what happened to her)? What deeds did she do?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O best brāhmaṇa, what kind of son did she obtain due to his curse? (Please) narrate to us in detail the account of Sunīthā also.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-14a. That Sunithā, of a slender waist, who was cursed by him, being tormented by grief, went to her father’s place. She disclosed her deeds to her father, Mṛtyu, the best among the truthful and the righteous ones. He spoke to Sunīthā, his daughter, who was cursed by that magnanimous one: “You committed a sin that destroys merit and lustre. O you noble one, why did you beat him, who was very tranquil? You did that which is contrary to (the ways of) all the world. Listen, what sin is committed by him who would kill him who is free from desire and wrath, who is very tranquil, who loves piety, who is fully engrossed in the path of penance, and is settled in the highest Brahman. His son is born wicked, and gets (i.e. accumulates) much sin. There is no doubt that he who beats a person who beats him and makes him cry who is crying, suffers for his sin (i.e. of the other person). He (alone) is tranquil, he (alone) is one who has conquered (i.e. controlled) his mind, who does not beat him (i.e. the person) who beats him. O you (my) daughter, he who has beaten an innocent person, would (thus) later beat, through delusion and in sin, even an innocent man(?). He, the sinner, who, without any reason, causes anxiety to an innocent man or would later beat an innocent man through delusion or some sin, obtains the sin produced in the body of the innocent one. If the innocent person would beat the wicked-hearted person that beats him rashly after suddenly getting up, the sin of the sinner goes to the innocent person.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>034  Sunīthā’s Problem</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/034/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/034/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. She, the noble one, who was very much afflicted with grief, told her friends how she was formerly cursed by the magnanimous Suśankha, and all that she did.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunīthā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sunīthā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-5. O friends, listen now; I shall tell you something else. Seeing my wealth of beauty and excellence in age (i. e. youth) and good qualities, my father became worried about me. The very glorious one desired to give me (in marriage) to (one of the) gods or sages. Holding me by the hand, he said these words to them all: “This is my young daughter, full of good qualities and having charming eyes. Well-being to you, I desire to give her (in marriage) to a virtuous and very magnanimous (god or sage).”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>035  Rambhā Helps by a Suggestion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/035/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/035/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;rambhā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rambhā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6a. Brahma was born from the Unmanifest one, and from him was born the lord of created beings, viz. the religious-minded Atri. O good lady, his son, viz. this Aṅga of a noble mind, came to Nandanavana. Seeing Indra’s glory excellent with graceful lustre, he too longed for a position similar to that of Indra: ‘If I would have such a son endowed with righteousness, (then) my existence, endowed with fame and glory, will be very blessed.’ Then he propitiated Hṛṣīkeśa with austerities and restraints. When Hṛṣīkeśa was very much pleased, he asked for a boon: “O Madhusūdana, give me a son who resembles Indra, whose lustre and valour are like that of Viṣṇu, who is a devotee of Viṣṇu, and who destroys all sins.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>036  Sunīthā Gets Married and Vena is Born</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/036/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/036/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunīthā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sunīthā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I-2a. O good lady, you have spoken the truth; I shall do like this. I shall allure the brāhmaṇa with this incantation, and not in any other way. Give me help so that I shall go to the meritorious one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b. Ramhbā, who was thus addressed by her, said to the high-minded one (i.e. Sunīthā):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5a. “O you beautiful young lady, tell me what kind of help I can give (you).” (Sunīthā said:) “O good lady, now go to him as my messenger.” Thus she spoke to that Rambhā of charming eyes. That celestial nymph Rambhā promised (her) like this only: “I shall help you; give me instructions.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>037  A Heretic Meets Vena</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/037/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/037/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. (If) thus was the creation of the noble Vena, how is it that giving up righteous conduct he would be (i.e. became) (a man) of wicked mind?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Sages endowed with spiritual and worldly knowledge, and knowing the truth, tell what is good and what is bad; that would never become otherwise in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O brāhmaṇas, how can the curse, given by that noble Suśaṅkha, who was practising penance, not turn true?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>038  The End of Vena’s Reign</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/038/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/038/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Vena, thus advised by that very sinful Jina, and deluded by him, attained to a sinful attitude. Abandoning the Vedic faith and rites of a truthful conduct, he saluted the feet of that very wicked one.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5a. There was cessation of good sacrifices, and also of the Vedas. Religious practices full of holy scriptures (i.e. as told in the holy scriptures) did not proceed at that time. As a result of his (bad) rule, the world became full of all sins. When that king ruled, there were no sacrifices, no (recitations of) the Vedas, no excellent purport of the holy texts, no charity and no study, O brāhmaṇas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>039  On Gifts and Worthy Recipients of Gifts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/039/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/039/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-sages-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The sages said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you best among the truthful ones, tell us in detail, how Vena casting off his sin went to heaven.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6a. O best brāhmaṇa, by the contact of the merit of the sages, by their concurrence, the sin went out of his body as a result of the churning of his body. Then that Vena of a righteous mind obtained eternal knowledge. O brāhmaṇas, free from desire and anger, he practised penance for a full hundred years in the hermitage of the sage Tṛṇabindu, which destroyed sins, and (which was situated) on the right bank of Reva. O glorious ones, god (Viṣṇu), the holder of the conch, disc and mace, was pleased with the sinless king due to his severe penance. Being pleased with him, he said to him: “I am pleased. Choose an excellent boon.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>040  The Fruit of Occasional Charity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/040/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/040/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vena-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vena said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O god, I have heard from you the fruit of regular charity. By your grace (i.e. be gracious and) carefully tell me that fruit which is the fruit of occasional charity. I am not getting great satisfaction; my faith prompts me to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8a. O best king, I shall explain to you (gifts given called) the occasional. Listen to the fruit of the gifts given to worthy recipients by a person with faith, on a great parvan day. O best king, he, the best man, who gives an elephant, a chariot or a horse (to a brāhmaṇa) becomes the best king, accompanied by servants, in a holy country, O great king; there is no doubt about this. The religious-minded, powerful and very intelligent one becomes a very lustrous king and is unconquered by all beings. O great king, he, who gives a gift of land or a cow when the great parvan (day) arrives, would become the lord of all enjoyments. One should give a gift to a very meritorious brāhmaṇa with great care.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>041  The Story of Sukalā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/041/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/041/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vena-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vena said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Tell me how the son (or) the wife (or) the father (or) the mother is a holy place. Tell me also in detail how one’s preceptor is a holy place.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8. There was a great city (named) Vārāṇasī along with (i.e. on the bank of) Gaṅgā. In it lived a vaiśya by name Kṛkala. His wife, named Sukalā, was very chaste, devoted to her husband, always engaged in religious practices, and loyal to her husband. Her limbs were auspicious. She had a good son and she was charming and auspicious. She spoke the truth, she was always pure, she had a lovable form, and was dear to her husband. She, endowed with these qualities, was fortunate, and performed good deeds. The vaiśya (i.e. Kṛkala) was an excellent man; he knew various religious practices, was wise and virtuous. He was always intent upon listening to the Purāṇas and religious practices as told by the scriptures. With faith he set out, with the caravan of brāhmaṇas on a pilgrimage, meritorious and auspicious. He proceeded on the religious path (of the pilgrimage). The chaste wife (i.e. Sukalā), being stupefied by her love for her husband, said (these) words to her husband.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>042  Ikṣvāku Goes Ahunting</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/042/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/042/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-friends-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The friends said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Who is that Sudevā about whom you talked? Tell us as to how she behaved. You have told (about her). Tell us the truth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7a. The great, glorious king, Manu’s son, Ikṣvāku by name, lived in Ayodhyā. He knew the rules of conduct; he was exclusively devoted to religious ends; he knew everything, and he honoured gods and brāhmaṇas; his wife was ever meritorious and devoted to her husband. With her he performed many sacrifices and (visited) various holy places. Sudevā, devoted to truthful conduct, was the daughter of Vedarāja, the brave and illustrious king of Kāśī. King Ikṣvāku married her. Sudevā was beautiful in all limbs, and was devoted to the vow of truth. With her, his beloved,the best king, the meritorious leader of people, enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>043  The Boar Gives a Tough Fight to Ikṣvāku</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/043/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/043/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. Thus those boars stood up for fighting. The hunters stood by the king standing before them. O best king, the great hog resorted to the mountain-peak. He stood after arranging his great herd in an array. The tawny, fat, plump-bodied, irresistible hog having large fangs and mouth, roared very fearfully, O king. The great king saw them resorting to the groves of śāla and tāla. Hearing those words of them the brave son of Manu (said): “Seize the brave hog, kill him who is proud of his strength.” Thus the hero, the brave son of Manu, spoke to them. Then all the hunters, fascinated by the rapture of hunting became ready and furnished with armours, and proceeded with the dogs. The great and very mighty king was full of great joy. Mounted upon a horse, he was ready with his army having four constituents. He came to the bank of Gaṅgā on the best mountain Meru, full of gems and minerals and adorned with various kinds of trees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>044  The Boar Dies Fighting</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/044/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/044/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Seeing his own irresistible army completely vanquished by him (i.e. by the hog) who was difficult to be stopped, the king got angry with the cruel, unbearable hog. He, mounted upon a horse, and taking a bow and an arrow resembling the destructive fire at the end of the world, speedily moved in front of him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-7. When the lord of the herd of boars saw the king, the killer of his enemies, mounted upon the back of a horse and endowed with excellent valour, he went forth to him on the battlefield. The best hog, when struck with a sharp arrow of (i.e. by) the king, went to the soles of the feet of the horse. With a quick mind (i.e. decision) he overstepped him with a very sharp speed. The horse was afflicted by the hog. The hog did not go to (i.e. fall on) the ground. The horse, with his movement checked, and struck on the face,.fell down on the ground. Then the king just went to (i.e. got into) a small chariot. He roared with sounds of (i.e. befitting) the species of a hog. The hog, who was in the midst of the battlefield, was speedily struck with a mace by the Kośala-king seated in his chariot; and then giving up his body, he just went to the excellent abode of Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>045  The Female Hog Fights Back</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/045/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/045/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then all the hunters with nooses in their hands went to the female hog. Also the brave, fearful, terrible (dogs) came (to her).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8. Seeing her dear (husband) killed along with the family in the great war, the female hog took her four children (i.e. young ones) and remained (there). (She thought:) ‘My husband got what he had thought (i.e. desired). He is honoured by sages and gods. The noble one has gone to heaven by means of (having performed) this act. I too shall go along the same path to heaven. The lord (i.e. my husband) waits (there for me).’ Having well determined (like this) she thought about her sons: ‘When my four sons, sustaining (i.e. continuing) our race live here, the noble, very brave hog also will have (the best position in heaven). By what means shall I protect my sons?’ Thus being engrossed in thinking, and seeing the narrow passage on the mountain, she tried to find out an extensive (i.e. wide) path to go out. Having made up her mind about her sons, O great king, she said to those sons who were very much confused: “O sons, as long as I am (alive), go (away) quickly.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>046  The Story of Raṅgavidyādhara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/046/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/046/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. Seeing the female hog, who loved her sons, panting and fallen (on the ground), Sudevā, who was full of pity, went to her, who was afflicted, and having (first) sprinkled cold water over her face, she then sprinkled holy water over the entire body (who was) afflicted and resplendent with fighting. She (i.e. the female hog) spoke to her who was sprinkling.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4. She spoke to the beloved (wife) of the king in a melodious human voice: “O respectable lady, may you be happy. When you sprinkled (holy water) over me, the heap of my sins left (me) by your contact and by my seeing you.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>047  The Story of Vasudatta and His Daughter Sudevā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/047/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/047/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Sudevā, whose entire body was beautiful, said to the female hog: “How is it that you, who are born in a species of beasts, speak Sanskrit?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Tell me wherefrom you had such great knowledge. O you auspicious one, how do you know the account of your husband and of yourself?”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-female-hog-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The female hog said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-7. Due to my being a beast I was enveloped by delusion, O you of an excellent complexion; and struck with swords and arrows, I fell on the battlefield. I was overpowered by swoon, and was unconscious, O you of an excellent face. O beautiful lady, with your pious hand you sprinkled (water on me). When my body was sprinkled over with the holy water by your hand, swoon left me and disappeared. As the darkness disappears due to lustre (i.e. light), similarly, O auspicious one, my sin disappeared due to your having sprinkled (over my body). O you of a charming body, by your favour I obtained old knowledge (i.e. knowledge of previous existence). O you auspicious one, I realised that I shall reach a holy position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>048  The Story of Padmāvatī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/048/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/048/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇas-wife-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa’s wife said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. In the charming region of Māthura, in (the city of) Mathurā, lived the best Yādava king, the killer of his enemies, and well-known as Ugrasena.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. The king knew the meaning and essentials of the whole religion; he knew the Vedas; he was learned and powerful; he was a donor, an enjoyer, an appreciator of virtues and a virtuous one. He, the intelligent one, ruled (over Mathura) and protected his subjects justly. Thus was that very lustrous and valorous Ugrasena. In the holy country of Vidarbha there lived a dignified (king named) Satyaketu. His glorious daughter, having eyes like lotuses and face like a lotus, and devoted to truthful behaviour, was Padmāvatī by name. That (Padmāvatī, the) daughter of the Vidarbha (-king) was endowed with feminine qualities and by means of her virtues based on truthfulness, she shone like another one born from the sea (i.e. like Lakṣmī). Ugrasena (the king) of the Māthura country married her, of beautiful eyes. O glorious one, with her the valorous one enjoyed himself happily. Being very much pleased with her qualities, he became happy with her (i.e. in her company).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>049  Padmāvatī Succumbs to Gobhila’s Fraudulent Approach</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/049/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/049/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇas-wife-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa’s wife said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-9a. O you glorious one, once on the best mountain she saw a beautiful grove, adorned with groups of plantain-trees, with the śāla trees, tala trees, tamāla trees, coconut trees, with big betelnut trees, mātuliṅga (i.e. citron) trees, orange trees, and charming jambu trees, with auspicious campaka trees and pāṭala trees that had blossomed, and also with kuṭaka and bunyan trees; it was full of aśoka and bakula trees, and was adorned with various other kinds of trees. She saw that holy mountain with trees that had blossomed. Everywhere it appeared beautiful, as it was full of many kinds of minerals. She also saw an excellent lake full of holy water on all sides, shining with fully developed lotuses and other fragrant golden lotuses, with white lotuses and fully developed red lotuses, with blue lotuses, white lotuses and with waterfowls, with other aquatic birds, and was full of various minerals. The lake was white all round, and was full of groups of many kinds of birds. The mountain was graced everywhere by auspicious and sweet cooings of cuckoos and was everywhere agreeable due to the sounds (produced) by madhura trees. It looked lovely by the excellent humming of the bees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>050  Padmāvatī is Grief-stricken</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/050/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/050/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-12. Hearing her words, Gobhila said (these) words: “Tell me the reason for which you desire to curse me. By what blemish am I defiled that you are ready to curse me? O auspicious one, I am a demon by name Gobhila, a warrior of Paulastya (i.e. Rāvaṇa). I act like a demon, I know excellent lore. I know the meaning of the Vedas and branches of knowledge, I am also skilled in arts. All this I know. (Now) listen about my demonish behaviour. I enjoy per force the wealth and the wives of others, and do so in no other way. Listen, we demons properly follow the demonish ways and do so knowingly. I am telling you the truth (and) the truth (only). Everyday we observe the loopholes of brāhmaṇas. By (putting in) difficulties we destroy their penance; there is no doubt about this. Finding a loophole in the brāhmaṇas we destroy them, O respectable lady. There is no doubt about this. O you of a beautiful face, listen. We destroy a sacrifice in honour of gods, (other) sacrifices and religious rites. There is no doubt about this. There is no doubt that we live by keeping far away excellent brāhmaṇas, the god Lord Nārāyaṇa, and a chaste, illustrious lady of a good mind and devoted to her husband. O respectable lady, demons cannot bear the lustre of a good brāhmaṇa, of glorious Hari (i.e. Viṣṇu), and of a lady loyal to her husband. The demons, the best evil spirits flee away due to the fear of a chaste lady, of Viṣṇu and of a good brāhmaṇa. I am roaming over the earth, according to the way of life of a demon. Why do you desire to curse me? What do you think my fault is?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>051  Padmāvatī Returns to Her Husband’s Place</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/051/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/051/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-wife-of-the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The wife of the brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. When that wicked-hearted Gobhila of a bad conduct had left, Padmāvatī, being full of great grief, wept. O best brāhmaṇa, hearing her weeping, all her beautiful friends asked the princess.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. (They said:) “Well-being to you, why are you weeping? Tell us your story (i.e. what you did). Tell us where the great king, your (husband) the lord of Māthura, who had invited you by addressing you (as) ‘O dear one’ is”. Weeping again, again she spoke with grief.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>052  Sudevā Goes to Heaven</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/052/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/052/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śivaśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śivaśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Maṅgalā, if you are now asking, then listen to (my) words. O you of an excellent face (i.e. O you beautiful one), know that for which you have asked (me).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. O you of charming eyes, this miserable one who has now come in the form of a beggar, is the daughter of the brāhmaṇa Vasudatta. O good one, this one is Sudevā, my wife, always dear to me. Leaving her (father’s) country for some reason, she has come (here). O you beautiful one, she is scorched by grief due to me and separation from me. Recognising me, she has come to you in the form of a beggar. Realising this, O good one, you, desiring what is very dear to me, should show her good hospitality. There is no doubt about it (i.e. you should certainly show her good hospitality).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>053  Sukalā’s Sickening Description of the Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/053/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/053/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukalā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukalā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Formerly, at that time I thus heard (about) the Dharma from the Purāṇas. How shall I, of a sinful resolve, enjoy pleasures without my husband? I cannot sustain my life with (i.e. in) my body without that husband.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-9. She thus narrated the excellent, great Dharma of the chastity of a wife; and those friends, excellent women, having heard the very meritorious Dharma for women, giving a great position (i.e. salvation) to women, praised that glorious Sukalā devoted to virtue. O king, all brāhmaṇas, gods and all virtuous women call her to mind due to her prowess caused by love for her husband. Indra, the lord of gods, having given a great (i.e. serious) thought to the firmness of Sukalā, and he, the lord of gods, having well pondered over her great devotion (thought): ‘I shall certainly shake her fortitude and her love for her husband.’ The lord of gods hurriedly recalled to mind god Cupid. He, the fish-bannered (god), holding his flowery bow came there. The very powerful one was seen to be accompanied by his beloved Rati. Joining the palms of his hands, he said to the thousandeyed (Indra): “O you lord, O you eminent one, O you who cut off the pride (of your enemies), why have you remembered me now? With all your heart give me an order today.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>054  Sukalā Gets Prepared For the Showdown</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/054/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/054/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. When the female messenger was thus addressed by that Sukalā she went (to Indra). Indra, having understood those significant and truthful words of her, well spoken in a brief manner, and having perceived her boldness, courage and knowledge (thought:) ‘Who, (even) being a woman, would speak on the earth, words that are of the form of (i.e. endowed with) propriety and that are well-ordered and washed with the water of logic? This magnanimous one is pure and of a truthful nature. There is no doubt that she is capable of bearing the yoke (i.e. responsibility) of all the three worlds?’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>055  Indra Tries to Dissuade Kāma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/055/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/055/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Knowing her mind, the lord of gods said to Cupid standing before him: “O Cupid, she, who is well-equipped with the armour of meditation with truth as its soul, cannot be conquered by you. With a desire to conquer, and taking in her hand the bow called piety and an excellent arrow named knowledge, she has stood on the battlefield, like a hero proud of his valour, to fight (with you). (This is her) valour only. Now do (i.e. show) your valour. She is today capable of conquering you in the battle. What is going to happen should be thought just now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>056  Satya &amp; Dharma Come to Sukalā’s Help</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/056/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/056/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-11a. Cupid, with the lord of gods, started to go to Sukalā to bring about a genuine destruction of her. At that time Satya (i.e. Truth) said to Dharma: “See, O very intelligent Dharma Cupid’s misdeed. I create (i.e. have created) a great place, an excellent house, of the nature of an abode, causing (i.e. giving) happiness, and called Satya (truth), Supriya (very dear) and Sudeva (with good deities), for the sake of you, the righteous and magnanimous one, and for my sake. This wicked Cupid, of a blundering mind, and of an inimical nature, would go to it and certainly destroy that excellent house of us. There is no doubt that a Brāhmaṇa with penance as his wealth as the husband, a very poius chaste woman, and a very truthful king, are, O Dharma, my abodes. There is no doubt about it. You would reside there where I am nourished with prosperity. Pu Q.ya (i.e. Merit) comes there and sports with Śraddhā (i.e. Faith). Kṣamā (i.e. Forbearance) accompanied by Śānti (i.e. Tranquility) comes to my abode. Real Dama (i.e. Restraint), and Dayā (i.e. Pity) and Sauhārda (i.e. Good-heartedness), Nirlobha (i.e. Absence of greed), along with Intelligence are there where I live. Śuci Svabhāva (i.e. Pure Nature) (stays) there only. These are my kinsmen. Non-stealing, Harmlessness, Endurance and Prosperity have come to my house. O king Dharma, listen to my blessedness. Service of preceptors and elderly persons, Viṣṇu accompanied by Lakṣmī, gods led by Agni, come to my house. Jñāna (i.e. Knowledge) accompanied by Brilliance, that would illumine the path to salvation (has come to my house).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>057  The Trap Is Laid For Sukalā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/057/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/057/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Rati, taking up the form of a chaste lady, went to the house of the charming loyal wife. She (i.e. Sukalā) the blessed one, endowed with a truthful nature, respectfully spoke to her (i.e. Rati). Rati, the chaste lady, well-honoured with very auspicious words, smiled and spoke to Sukalā, words full of deceit, alluring all and containing a truthful topic: “(Please) listen, my husband, my lord, who is very strong, who appreciates virtues, who is wise and learned, who is endowed with greatness, who has a holy name, left me who am more (i.e. very) sinful and has gone away.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>058  Sukalā Wins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/058/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/058/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Prompted by Rati, Sukalā, the beautiful wife of the vaiśya entered the beautiful grove. The chaste lady saw all the charming grove and then she asked her friend. (She said:) “O friend, to whom does this excellent, very meritorious, divine and charming grove, which is furnished with all excellent pleasures, belong?” Sukalā joyfully asked her friend (Rati).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;krīḍā-ie-rati-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Krīḍā (i.e. Rati) said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. This grove is endowed with all divine qualities of well-known inherent properties and decorations of flowers and perfumes; it is full of flowers and desired fruits; see, it is of (i.e. it belongs to) Cupid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>059  Religious Observances Without One’s Wife Are Fruitless</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/059/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/059/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Having finished (i.e. having visited) all sacred places, Kṛkala, full of great joy, started for his house along with the leader of the caravan. He always thought like this: ‘My worldly existence is fruitful. My dead ancestors, when gratified will go to heaven; not otherwise.’&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5a. Just then having bound his grandsires (Dharma) spoke to him: “You do not have excellent religious merit.” (Dharma) of a divine form and of a huge body said (these) words to Kṛkala: “You do not have the fruit of (your visits to) holy places. In vain have you exerted. You alone are happy (i.e. you have not gratified your dead ancestors etc.); (therefore) you do not have excellent religious merit.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>060  Sukalā’s Story Ends</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/060/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/060/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kṛkala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kṛkala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Dharmarāja, now tell me in detail how I would have final beatitude and how my dead ancestors would be liberated.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;dharma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dharma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. O you noble one, go home. She (i.e. your wife) is experiencing grief without you. Inform your wife, Sukalā practising piety, (of your arrival). Having gone home, offer śrāddha with her hands. Win over the best gods by remembering the holy places. You will have the salvation obtained through pilgrimages to holy places. He who desires to accomplish religious merit without his wife (i.e. all alone), loses (the fruit of) the stage of the householder and would wander alone in a forest. He is unsuccessful in the world, (and) the deities do not respect him. The sacrifices become successful¹ (only) when the housewife remains in the house. All alone (i.e. without his wife) he is not able to accomplish (the fruit of) piety and worldly prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>061  Pippala’s Penance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/061/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/061/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vena-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vena said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. You have described the holy place in the form of wife, the best of all holy places. Now tell about the sacred place in the form of dead ancestors, which is a great emancipater of sons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. In the great sacred region (called) Kurukṣetra (there lived) a brāhmaṇa named Kuṇḍala. That noble Kuṇḍala had a good son by name Sukarman. His parents were very old, knew religious practices, and were proficient in sacred precepts. Both the noble ones were afflicted with old age. He, who knew piety, and who was full of sincerity, devotedly and continuously served them night and day. He, intent on (following) all (good) practices, knowing piety and a lover of knowledge, learnt from that (i.e. his) father, many sacred treatises; and he himself massaged the bodies of the two. He also washed their feet, bathed and fed them with devotion and naturally became thoughtful about them. O best king, he (thus) served his mother and father.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>062  Parents As Sacred Places of Pilgrimage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/062/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/062/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. (Pippala) having gone to Kuṇḍala’s hermitage, full of truthful practices, saw (there) noble Sukarman, greatly devoted to his father and mother, serving (them), possessing great prowess born of truth, of great form and lustre, having great knowledge, engaged in serving his parents and seated at their feet, tranquil, endowed with great devotion and the great treasure of all knowledge. That high-souled Sukarman, the son of Kuṇḍala, seeing the very intelligent Pippala who had come to the door, quickly got up from his seat and honoured him, (and said to him): “O you glorious, very intelligent Vidyādhara, (please) come.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>063  Merit Resulting from Service of Parents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/063/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/063/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6a. O best brāhmaṇa, the son properly gets (the religious merit of) a bath similar to the one in all the holy places when the drops of water, (falling from the bodies) of the mother and the father who have bathed, fall on the entire body of the son. I shall (now) tell you about the religious merit of the son who serves his father who is fallen, who is maimed, who is old, who is weak (in doing) all acts, who is ill, who is suffering from leprosy, and also his mother like that (i.e. in such a condition). There is no doubt that Viṣṇu has his mind pleased with him. He goes to Viṣṇu’s heaven, unobtainable by (even) the meditating saints. That son of a sinful mind who abandons his parents who are maimed, helpless, old, or are suffering from a serious disease, obtains (i.e. goes to) a terrible hell, full of worms.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>064  Mātali’s Discourse on Old Age</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/064/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/064/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pippala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pippala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Tell me in detail, how, by the grace of his father, Yadu obtained happiness and enjoyed well. O son of Kuṇḍala, tell me also in detail how Ruru suffered as a result of his sin, O best brāhmaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-11a. Listen, I shall tell you the account of the very meritorious Nahuṣa, and the noble Yayāti, (the account) which destroys sin. Nahuṣa, the lord of the earth sprang from (i.e. was born in) the Soma dynasty. He made many matchless gifts. He performed an excellent century of the horse-sacrifices (i.e. performed a hundred excellent horse-sacrifices). He also performed a hundred Vājapeya sacrifices and many kinds of (other) sacrifices. By the power of his religious merit he obtained (i.e. went to) Indra’s world. He made his very intelligent son Yayāti, endowed with truthfulness, having piety as his valour, the protector of his subjects (i.e. the king). The king (Nahuṣa) went to (i.e. obtained) Indra’s position. His son Yayāti, endowed with truthfulness, who (occupied) his place (i.e. the throne), would protect (i.e. protected) the subjects religiously. He himself would look (i.e. looked) after his subjects and the respective duties. Having learnt about excellent duty, he, who knew righteousness got sacrifices performed. He did everything like performing sacrifices, (visiting) holy places, giving gifts (giving) religious merit. The intelligent son of the king (Nahuṣa) ruled truthfully for eighty thousand years in those days. The glorious Yayāti passed that much time (in truthfully ruling his subjects).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>065  Mātali on Why the Body Is Left Behind</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/065/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/065/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yayāti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yayāti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Mātali, tell me the reason, why this body, the protector of Dharma, does not go to heaven with the soul.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mātali-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mātali said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9. The five elements do not go together (with the soul); in the company of the soul, O king. All of them come together in the village of the body. All of them, afflicted by old age, go to their respective abodes. Since the earth is created with a preponderance of fluid, it being wet due to the fluids becomes soft, O king. It is pierced by ants and rats. Holes are formed into it, and also anthills with large interiors. In the same way inflammation of the glands of the neck and itch are produced in the body. O best of men, this body is also cleft by worms. Enlargements (of parts like the spleen), instantly troubling, are also produced in it. O son of Nahuṣa, this body is full of such defects. How will it go to heaven with the life, O lord of men? The earthly part is settled in the body for the vital air essential to digestion. The body does not come (i.e. go) to heaven. It remains here as the earth does. I have told you all this along with a heap of earthy blemishes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>066  Mātali on the Universality of Suffering</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/066/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/066/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yayāti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yayāti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O Mātali, listen, (we see that) the body falls due to sin and also due to religious merit. On the earth I do not see what difference religious merit makes. The body is produced again (just) as it fell before. Tell me in detail how the body is produced.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mātali-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mātali said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-16. In the case of the hellish beings, just in a moment, the (hellish) body is produced from the (five) elements due to impious acts only. In the same way, due to religious merit, a divine body (in the manner of that) of the gods is instantly produced from the essences of the elements. That body of the magnanimous ones, (which is produced) due to the mixture of the (fruits) of deeds should be known to be of four kinds according to the transformation of deeds. The immobile ones in the form of grass and bushes should be known as the ones born by sprouting up. Worms, insects and moths should be known to be born from the sweat of living beings. O king, all birds, serpents and crocodiles are oviparous. Human beings and quadrupeds should be known to be viviparous. When the earth is ‘cooked’ by heat, it is moistured by water and is scattered by wind (into loose particles). Then the seed approaches the soil in such a way that the seeds that are sown and are watered, become soft and attain the state of roots. From the root there is the rise of a shoot. From a shoot a leaf springs up. From a leaf a hollow stock comes up; from that a stem comes up; and from that the &lt;em&gt;prabhava&lt;/em&gt; (power). From it would be (produced) &lt;em&gt;Kṣīra&lt;/em&gt; (the sap), and from the sap there is the rise of &lt;em&gt;tandula&lt;/em&gt; (the gram?), from the gram come up the ripened &lt;em&gt;oṣadhayaḥ&lt;/em&gt; (herbs). They are said to be seventeen—the best ones—beginning with barley and ending with rice. The herbs are rich with the wealth of fruits. The remaining ones are said to be trifling. These were first cleansed and cut and crushed by the sages with winnowing baskets, mortars and (other) vessels. With water in a pan and fire, they, which have six varieties, undergo alteration, have many tastes due to the combinations of their respective tastes. O king, they have six varieties like that which is consumed, eaten, drunk, licked, sucked and bitten (and eaten). They have six tastes like the sweet (taste) etc. That food which is eaten by living beings through (i.e. in the form of) balls and mouthfuls, settles all the vital airs in the stomach one by one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>067  Mātali on Three Kinds of Sin</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/067/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/067/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yayāti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yayāti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O you charioteer of Indra, due to my good luck I have been able to see you. This gives me immense merit. Even in the mortal world human beings commit a terrible sin. O Mātali, now tell me about the ripening of their actions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mātali-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mātali said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-12. Listen, I shall tell (you) the characteristics of a sinful behaviour. In this world great knowledge is produced when (things) are heard. People condemn the Vedas and censure brāhmaṇic practices. Those who are learned should also know what great sin is. He who causes harm to all the good persons (has committed) a major sin. It would go (i.e. its effect would be nullified only) by expiation. People give up the customs peculiar to their own family and practise those of others. Those who know what should be done (i.e. what is proper) have described this to be a major sin. Reviling one’s mother and father, beating one’s sisters, and abusing one’s father’s sister is certainly a sin. The dead ancestors of him, who, when the time for offering a śrāddha has come, proceeds (to offer the śrāddha and) feeds someone else through lust or anger or fear, ignoring his son-in-law living at a distance of five kośas, his daughter’s son, his own sister and her son, do not enjoy (the oblations offered by him), nor do the gods enjoy (the offerings made to them). This sin, committed by him, is equal to patricide. When the time for giving gifts has come, and when a brāhmaṇa (-group) has come, he avoids giving gifts to many, and gives them (only) to a few. That a gift is given to one, and no gift is given to another, is also a terrible sin, and is said to destroy (the merit acquired from) gifts.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>068  The Fruit of Righteous Deeds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/068/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/068/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yayāti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yayāti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;l. O charioteer, O lord, I have heard everything about the fruit of unrighteousness. Tell me also about the fruit of righteousness. I have a curiosity to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;mātali-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mātali said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-12. These four kinds of all the embodied ones, being helpless, go to Yama’s world which causes fear and which is terrible, due to their sins. All beings, that remain in the womb, that are born, and children, young men, middle-aged men, old men, men, women and eunuchs have to go (to Yama’s world). There the auspicious or inauspicious fruit (of the deeds) of human beings is decided by all like impartial and omniscient Citragupta and others. There are no beings (in the world) that do not go to Yama’s abode. (The fruit of) the deed done (by a being) has to be enjoyed as decided by them. Those men, who do auspicious deeds, who have soft hearts, who are endowed with pity, go to Yama’s abode along a pleasing path. A man who would give (i.e. who gives) shoes, wood or sandals to brāhmaṇas, happily goes to Yama’s abode in a great aeroplane. By giving umbrellas (as gifts to brāhmaṇa) human beings go (to Yama’s abode). By giving a palanquin (as a gift to a brāhmaṇa) one would happily go (to Yama’s abode) along a path in the sky. Those who give garments (as gifts to brāhmaṇas), go, wearing divine garments (to Yama’s abode). By giving a palanquin (as a gift to a brāhmaṇa) one would happily go (to Yama’s abode) in an aeroplane. By giving a comfortable seat (to a brāhmaṇa) (human beings) happily go to Yama’s abode. One who has constructed groves would go happily (enjoying) very cool shadows. Those who give gardens (with trees full of) flowers go to Yama’s abode in the Puṣpaka aeroplane. He, who builds a temple, or a hermitage for ascetics, or pavilions for the helpless, playfully goes, due to (having constructed) best dwellings (to Yama’s abode). So also he, who worships deities, fire, preceptors, brāhmaṇas, and his father and mother, (playfully goes to Yama’s abode).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>069  Righteous Acts Enjoined by Śiva (Śivadharmas)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/069/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/069/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mātali-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mātali said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Acts of righteousness have been told by Śiva (in) the excellent scriptures of the Śiva cult. Due to the difference in the manner of performance of acts they should be known to be many. The ancient acts as (told) by Śiva are free from blemishes like harming (others), are without suffering and exertion, are beneficial to all beings, are pure, involve little effort and give great fruit. They have many branches, but resort to (i.e. are supported by) the root (in the form) of Śiva. They have good flowers like knowledge and meditation. Since they sustain Śiva and are supported by the sayings of Śiva, they that help (human beings) to cross the ocean of the worldly existence, are known to be acts (liked) by Śiva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>070  Sinners in Hell</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/070/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/070/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;mātali-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mātali said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I shall (now) tell (you) about the very poignant and very terrible torture caused by Yama (which) all the cruel, sinful killers of brāhmaṇas experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-10. Sometimes the sinful ones are roasted with the fire of dry cow-dung; sometimes they are eaten up by fierce lions, wolves, tigers, gad-flies and worms. Sometimes (they are eaten up) by great leeches, or by huge cobras, and by terrible flies or sometimes by serpents with strong poison. (Sometimes they are eaten up) by great intoxicated and torturing herds of elephants, (or) by great bulls with sharp horns, scratching the path, and by buffaloes with big horns harming the bodies of the wicked, and by fierce female goblins and by terrible demons. Mounted on a great balance and being tormented by very terrible diseases and being burnt in a wild fire, they go (to Yama). They are very speedily shaken by very violent wind, and are shattered all round by the shower ofgreat (slabs of) stone, and by the terrible falls of meteors having a sound like that of thunderbolt. Being struck by the shower of burning charcoal they go (to Yama). Being filled (i.e. covered) with a great shower of dust, they go to Yama. Men who are sinful experience terrible pain. Thus, the most sinful ones, who commit sins, experience, due to their particular sin, hell, full of many tortures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>071  Identity of Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Śiva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/071/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/071/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yayāti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yayāti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. The faith of me, to whom you have excellently explained everything about merit and demerit, has been all the more stimulated by it. Tell me the number said to be that of the gods staying in the (various) worlds (i.e. tell me about their position in the various worlds), O Mātali, and also (tell me that) by whose contact with religious merit and by whom it (i.e. that position) is reached.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>072  Yayāti’s Reluctance to Part with the Body</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/072/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/072/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pippala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pippala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O you highly intelligent one, tell me in detail, what the king, the son of Nahuṣa said on hearing the words of Mātali. O wise one, this is an all-meritorious story which destroys sins. I desire to hear it. I am not at all being satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Yayāti, the best king, the greatest among those who practised piety, said to the messenger Mātali, Indra’s charioteer, who had come (to him):&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>073  The Efficacy of Viṣṇu’s Name</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/073/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/073/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pippala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pippala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. When that illustrious messenger had left (for heaven), what did that religious-minded Yayāti, the son of Nahuṣa, do?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. When that messenger of the best god (i.e. Indra) had left, the son of king (Nahuṣa) thought (to himself). Having immediately called his excellent messengers, he instructed them with words of propriety: “The excellent messengers should go to an excellent city, to all regions and islands in the world. They should carry out my words (i.e. order) which is full of virtue. May people go along the good path of Viṣṇu, by means of devotional and very meritorious (acts), meditations resembling nectar, knowledge, sacrifices and austerities. Abandoning the worldly objects of sense, may they worship Viṣṇu alone with sacrifices and gifts. May they see only the enemy of the demons and of the nature of the soul everywhere—at dry places, wet and immobile places, in the clouds, on the earth, in mobile and immobile (objects) and even in their own bodies. With hospitality and rites in honour of their dead ancestors may they offer gifts dedicating them to that god. May they offer sacrifices to that best god Nārāyaṇa (i.e. Viṣṇu); you (i.e. they) will soon be free from blemishes. That shameless man who through greed or folly would not obey these words of me right now, would certainly be punished like a vile thief.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>074  Popularity of Viṣṇu Cult during Yayāti’s Rule</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/074/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/074/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. All the messengers said (i.e. proclaimed) in the islands, regions and cities: “O people, listen to the command of the king. With all their glory may they worship Viṣṇu. May people with (devoted) minds desiring merit, reflect on Viṣṇu, by means of many gifts, sacrifices; austerities, and sacrificial rites.” Such is the order of that king.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. The people heard all these meritorious (words) thus well-proclaimed on the earth (by the messengers). Since then only the human beings sacrificed (in honour of) Viṣṇu, reflected on him, sang (in praise of) him, and muttered (prayers to him). All human beings, giving up the blemishes due to their bodies, minds and speech, by means of vows, fasts, restraints and gifts, and with their hearts gone to (i.e. set upon) him, worship that Śrī Keśava, Śrī Vāsudeva, the abode of Lakṣmī, and the habitation of the worlds, with well-recited, very meritorious and nectarlike hymns taught by the Vedas and with eulogies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>075  Yayāti’s Subjects became Deathless by the Grace of Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/075/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/075/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. All men, children, old people, unmarried girls always uttered names (i.e. recited the various names of Viṣṇu like) Viṣṇu, Kṛṣṇa, Hari, Rāma, Mukunda, Madhusūdaṇa, Nārāyaṇa of the form of Viṣṇu, Narasiṃha, Acyuta, Keśava, Padmanābha, Vāsudeva, Vāmana, Varāha, Kamaṭha, Matsya, Hṛṣīkeśa, Surādhipa, Viśveśa, Viśvarūpa, Ananta, Anagha, Śuci, Puruṣa, Puṣkarākṣa, Śrīdhara, Śrīpati, Hari, Śrīnivāsa, Pītavāsa (i.e. clad in a yellow garment), Mādhava, Mokṣada (i.e. giver of salvation) and Prabhu. Women, engaged in domestic work always profusely sang (i.e. recited the names of) Hari, Mādhava, (so also when they were seated) on a seat, (when they were lying) in bed, (while they were going) in a vehicle and in meditation. Similarly children (while) playiṇg saluted Govinda (i.e. Viṣṇu).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>076  Dharmarāja Rendered Jobless</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/076/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/076/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4a. The son of the Sun (i.e. Yama) went with all his messengers to heaven to see there Indra, surrounded by groups of gods. Then that king of gods (i.e. Indra) saw Dharmarāja in his assembly. Quickly getting up he presented excellent respectful offering to him, and asked him (the reason for) his arrival (saying:) “Tell me (why you have come).” Hearing the weighty words uttered by the king of gods, Dharmarāja narrated (to him) all the great account of Yayāti.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>077  Yayāti Yields to Passion</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/077/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/077/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. The king of kings was allured by the charm of Cupid’s music and his charming smile and his appearance as an actor, O Pippala. Having urinated and evacuated his bowels, the king, Nahuṣa’s son, sat on his seat without having washed his feet. Having reached (i.e. seized) that opportunity, Jarā (i.e. old age) moved on to the king. Cupid also accomplished the act, beneficial to Indra, O best king. When the drama was over, and they had left, the religious-minded king was overcome with old age, had his mind attached to lust, was allured by the delusion (caused) by Cupid, was perturbed, had his organs weakened; the virtuous (king) was very much stupefied, and was driven away by objects of sense.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>078  Pūru Gives His Youth to Yayāti</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/078/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/078/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;yayāti-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yayāti said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O my noble sons, the wise one among you should take this my old age which is giving me pain, and should give his own youth and excellent form (to me); (so that) I shall behave as I like. Today my very fickle mind is inflamed, and is attached to a woman. As fire whirls round the water in a pot, similarly, O (my) sons, my mind is very much shaken by the fire of passion. O (my) sons, one (of you) should take this my old age which is giving me pain, and should give (me) his youth; (so that) I shall behave according to my will.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>079  Youthful Yayāti Enjoys with Aśrubindumatī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/079/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/079/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viśālā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viśālā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. There (i.e. in that king) only, whose wife is Śarmiṣṭḥā and whose wife is beautiful Devayānī, good fortune is seen. This cannot be false, O king; then O glorious king, how are you fascinated by (the beauty of) this maiden’s body&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; since you are known as a husband having two wives?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. Like sandal, O king, you are with serpents (around) you. O king, as a great sandal-tree is surrounded by serpents, so you are surrounded by serpents called co-wives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>080  Yadu Refuses to Kill His Mothers</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/080/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/080/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pippala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pippala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O best brāhmaṇa, when the king (Yayāti) married the daughter of Cupid, what did his two former, very auspicious, wives, viz. the noble Devayānī and Śarmiṣṭhā, the daughter of Vṛṣaparvan do? Tell me the entire account of the two.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-9a. When that king took home Cupid’s daughter, that high-minded Devayāni very much entered into rivalry (with her). “For her he, with his mind overcome with anger, cursed two of his sons (viz. Turu and Yadu).” The renowned one, having called Śarmiṣṭhā, said these words to her. Śarmiṣṭhā and Devayānī vied with her in beauty, lustre, charity, truthfulness and holy vows. Then Kāma’s daughter knew their wickedness. Just then only she told everything to the king, O brāhmaṇa. Then the great king, getting angry, called Yadu and said to him: “Go and kill Śarmiṣṭhā and also (Devayānī) the daughter of Śukra. O son, if you care for felicity then do what is very dear to me.” Having heard those words of his father, Yadu then replied to his father, the lord of kings:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>081  Destiny is Irresistible</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/081/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/081/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. This very intelligent Indra, always afraid of the noble Yayāti, seeing his valour and many meritorious acts like (giving) gifts, sent the celestial nymph Menakā to act as a messenger. (He said to her:) “O good and illustrious one, go-and tell (i.e. convey) my order. Going from here tell Cupid’s daughter the words (i.e. the order) of (me), the lord of gods: ‘Bring the king here by any means (i.e. somehow).’”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>082  Yayāti Takes Back His Old Age</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/082/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/082/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. When the king was thus absorbed in thinking, that beautiful daughter of Rati said: “O you very intelligent king, what do you think just now? There is no doubt that mostly women are fickle. I am not leading you away through fickleness. I am not making use of a fraudulent expedient today, O best king, (by speaking) as other greedy women speak, something that cannot be done, through greed and delusion. A strong desire to see all the worlds is produced in my heart. Seeing deities is meritorious, and is very difficult to be had even by good men. Say to me, O king, that you will cause (i.e. help) me to see the deities. Like another ordinary man, afraid of a great misery and fallen into the ditch of delusion, you are thinking if there would be a great sin due to my company now. Give up your anxiety; you should not go to heaven. I shall never do that which gives you pain.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>083  Yayāti Visits the Divine Worlds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/083/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/083/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5a. Having called all the subjects from all parts (of the world), the lord of the earth, full of great joy, said: “O best ones my subjects—brāhmaṇas, kṣatriyas, vaiśyas and śūdras, along with this lady I am going to Indra’s heaven, Brahmā’s heaven, Rudra’s heaven and then to Viṣṇu’s heaven, destroying all sins and causing salvation. There is no doubt about it. With (your) families (you) should stay happily on the earth. O people, I have appointed this glorious and wise Pūru as your guardian and king with the sceptre.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>084  Glorification of Devotion to Parents</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/084/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/084/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sukarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sukarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-10. I have narrated to you this entire account, which removes sins, which emancipates sons, which is divine, and which gives great religious merit. The well-known deeds of Yayāti are actually seen in the world. Pūru obtained the great kingdom as it was brought into existence, and Turu was reduced to a bad plight, due (respectively) to the father’s favour and anger. It emancipates sons, gives glory and wealth and grains. Both Turu and Yadu were under the influence of a curse. There is no other giver of desirable fruits like the father or the mother. A father may call his son through love, and a mother (may call him saying:) ‘O son, O son.’ Listen to its meritorious fruit. When a son, who is called by his mother, goes to her with affection, he would get the fruit of having bathed in the Ganges. A very glorious son, who would wash the feet (of his parents) enjoys, through their grace, the fruit of (having visited) all the sacred places; and by shampooing their bodies he would obtain the fruit of a horse-sacrifice. In that son, who would nourish his father (and mother) with food, covering, and bath, merit equal to that obtained by the gift of the earth is produced. The Ganges is full of (the merit of) all sacred places. A mother is like that (only). There is no doubt about it. The ancient poets know that as the ocean is established as full of much merit, similarly is the father in this world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>085  The Story of Cyavana, Kuñjala and Divyādevī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/085/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/085/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vena-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vena said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O venerable lord of gods, through your grace towards me, you have told me about the sacred place (in the form of) a wife, so also about the excellent holy place (in the form of) the father and (in the form) of the mother, giving great religious merit. Being gracious to me (now) tell me about the holy place (in the form) of the preceptor.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-10. O king, I shall tell you about the matchless holy place (in the form) of the preceptor, which is declared as the remover of all sins and the giver of happiness to the disciples, which being of the nature of ancient Dharma (i.e. religious merit) gives great virtue to the disciples, which is the highest sacred place, highest knowledge giving a visible fruit, (and) O lord of kings, by whose favour (the disciple) gets the fruit here (i.e. in this world) only; and O lord of kings, by the favour of the glorious preceptor he enjoys happiness and would obtain glory and fame in the next world. O prince, (by the preceptor’s favour) the disciples actually see the three worlds along with the mobile and the immobile, so also the dealings and practices of the people. A disciple obtains wisdom and goes to salvation. As the sun illumines all the worlds, so the teacher enlightens his disciples and is the best refuge of them. O best king, the king Soma (i.e. the Moon) would shine at night only, and would keep a watch over the mobile and the immobile. O best king, a lamp would illumine a multitude (of objects) in the house, and would dispel the entire dense and impure darkness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>086  Divyādevī As Citrā in Her Former Birth</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/086/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/086/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O boy, I (shall) tell you all the acts of that Divyādevī. Listen to all that she did in the former birth as I am telling you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7a. There was an auspicious city named Vārāṇasī, the destroyer of sins. In it lived a very intelligent man named Suvīra, who was born in the Vaiśya caste and who possessed wealth and grains. O you very intelligent one, his wife was Citrā by name, who was well known. She, abandoning the family-practices, behaved improperly. She did not care for her husband, (and) behaved wantonly. Bereft of piety and merit she would act (i.e. she acted) sinfully only. She always reviled her husband, and always loved quarrelling. She always stayed in the house of another (person), and wandered from house to house. She would observe (i.e. she observed) the weak points of others, and was always wicked to beings. She was very much given to condemning the good, and always laughed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>087  A Hundred Names of Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/087/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/087/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. I shall explain to you the kinds of vows by which Hari (i.e. Viṣṇu) is propitiated. O good son, there are many kinds of Ekādaśī: Jayā, Vijayā, and Jayantī, Pāpanāśinī, Trispṛśā, Vañjulī; the next is Tiladagdhā, then the other one is Akhaṇḍā, Cārakanyā, and Manorathā. There is (the vow of) Aśūnyaśayana (i.e. not sleeping on a bed), and there is the great vow of Janmāṣṭamī. There is no doubt that the sin of beings goes away due to these very auspicious vows. I am telling you the truth (and) the truth (only).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>088  Divyādevī Goes to Viṣṇu’s Heaven</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/088/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/088/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4a. O good son, I have told you the vow, the hymn, the great knowledge and the meditation of Viṣṇu which destroy sins. When she (i.e. Divyādevī) would practise these auspicious four, she will go to Viṣṇu’s world, difficult to be obtained even by gods. O child, going from here, teach the vow to Divyādevī. Tell (i.e. teach) her the king of vows called Aśūnya-śayana. Emanicipate the glorious princess from a great sin. You asked me (and therefore) I told (you about the vow) giving religious merit and destroying sins. O glorious one, go, (do) go.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>089  The Miraculous Bath in the Water of Mānasa Lake</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/089/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/089/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. Then Kuñjala said (these) words to his very bright son: “O son, tell me what you saw earlier. Tell me that. I am now very much pleased to listen to it.” Thus ordering his son, that Kuñjala ceased speaking. The son, bending with modesty replied to the father:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;samujjvala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Samujjvala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-14. O father, for your and my food, I go to Himālaya, the best mountain, attended by hosts of gods. I saw a wonder there, not seen or heard of before. (I saw) a region crowded with groups of sages, adorned with celestial nymphs, rich in many beautiful things creating curiosity, auspicious, and endowed with auspicious things, attracting the mind with many curious things, full of many auspicious fruits. There, near the Mānasa (lake), O father, I saw a wonderful thing. A swan accompanied by many swans came there. In the same way, O glorious one, other black swans with white beaks and feet (also) came there. At other places their bodies were white (i.e. other parts of their bodies were white). They were black like that, and, O you very intelligent one, others were white. There were four females of formidable figures and fearful, fierce and cruel due to their fangs, with their hair erect and causing fear. Later they also came there to that Mānasa lake. O father, in front of me the black swans bathed in the Mānasa (lake). Others roamed around; they did not bathe there in the Mānasa (lake). Later the females also came there to that Mānasa (lake). O father, the women laughed loudly and fiercely. From that lake a swan of a huge body came out. Then three went out; they neglected the swan. Discussing wiṃ each other, they went along the aerial path. Those very fearful women wandered on all sides.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>090  The Powers of the Holy Places</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/090/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/090/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;l. Having heard all that Samujjvala said, that pious Kuñjala said in reply:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. O dear one, I shall explain it to you. Listen with a steady (i.e. attentive) mind to the account removing all doubts and destroying sins. In the assembly of that noble god Indra a debate, producing curiosity, was going on. (At that time) Nārada hurriedly came to see Indra. Indra, having seen him, with lustre like that of the sun, who had arrived, became glad and the very intelligent one, with his mind humble through devotion, offered him material of worship and water for washing his feet. Joining the palms of his hands, he saluted him. Seating the best brāhmaṇa on an auspicious, soft seat, and bowing down, he, full of great reverence, asked him: “Tell me now the reason for your arrival today.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>091  Vidura, Candraśarman, Vedaśarman and Vañjula</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/091/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/091/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-16a. Formerly when Indra was affected by (the sin of) killing a brāhmaṇa, he committed a great sin of having an illicit intercourse with Gautama’s wife. He was abandoned by gods and brāhmaṇas. Indra, propless and shelterless, practised penance. At the end of his penance all deities, sages, yakṣas, kinnaras started a religious bath to honour the lord of gods. O best son, O noble one, having taken the lord of gods to the Mālavaka country they gave him a bath with (the water from) the pitchers filled with water. Then he was first taken to Vārāṇasī to give him a bath; then Indra (was taken) to Prayāga and then to Arghatīrtha. O best of brāhmaṇas, the noble one was given a bath by the magnanimous Puṣkara itself; he was also given a bath by all gods like Brahmā, by hosts of sages. Hallowed with Vedic hymns destroying all sins by sages, the lord of gods was given a bath by elephants, trees, serpents, snakes along with kinnaras. When that noble Indra was purified, his (sin of) killing a brāhmaṇa and (that of) illicit intercourse were gone. On the earth Indra’s (sin of) the murder of a brāhmaṇa along with that terrible sin of illicit intercourse perished. Indra who was well-pleased granted a boon to the Holy Places: “Since, you, who, are pure, freed me from this very terrible sin, therefore, by my favour you will be holy and the lords of sacred places.” Giving such a boon to them he gave a boon to (the) Mālava (country): “Since today you bore my dirt causing distress, therefore you will be adorned with food, drink, wealth and grains. There is no doubt about it. By my favour you will surely be very holy and free from bad times (like drought etc.).” After Indra, the lord of gods, had given him (i.e. the Mālava country) such a boon, all the Holy Places and also the Mālavaka country went to their respective places along with Indra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>092  The Greatness of Revā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/092/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/092/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Reaching Kālañjara (the four) very much afflicted, tormented by great sins, lamenting and senseless lived there; and there came a very glorious siddha. He asked them who were afflicted with great grief: “For what reason are you unhappy?” He the very wise one, and proficient in all (branches of) knowledge was told by them (the cause of their grief). The very meritorious one having known their great sin, showed compassion to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>093  Vijvala Narrates His Experience</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/093/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/093/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O Vijvala, what thing not seen before and full of wonder did you, while wandering on the earth, see? Tell me that, O you of a good vow. O best son, tell me which country did you go to with a strenuous effort for (obtaining) food; (tell me) what wonder you noticed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vijvala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vijvala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6. On the surface of mountain Meru there is a forest by name Ānanda. It is abounding in divine trees, always full of fruits and flowers; it is crowded with groups of gods, and is attended by sages and siddhas, and also by beautiful celestial damsels, gandharvas, kinnaras and serpents; (it is full of) wells, ponds, lakes, rivers and streams. The holy forest Ānanda shines with divine objects, aeroplanes numbering in crores and resembling swans, kunda flowers and the moon. It is full of the mixed and sweet sounds of songs, and resounds with the thunders of clouds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>094  In Praise of Making Gift of Food</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/094/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/094/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O son, listen, I shall tell you the reason why the two became the eaters of their own flesh.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-12a. There is no doubt that everywhere (i.e. for everything) auspicious or inauspicious act is the cause. O son, a man enjoys happiness due to a meritorious deed; and due to a sinful deed he suffers. A man should undertake a deed after having pondered over the subtle path by means of the eye of the knowledge of scriptures, and also after having repeatedly well thought over the coarse path of conduct with an accurate mind (i.e. thought), as, O son, an artist, fashioning images, produces elegance (in them) by means of the lustre of the fire and flames all round. A metal, heated by fire would slowly turn into a liquid. O child, undoubtedly the kind of form produced is similar to the kind of food, perfect with taste, that is poured down. A deed is enjoyed in the same way as it is done. It is the deed that is the principal thing and that alone proceeds in the form of rain. O child there is no doubt that the farmer enjoys (i.e. reaps) the fruit as he sows the seed in the fields. (A man) enjoys in the same way as he performs a deed. Deed is the cause of his destruction. All of us are controlled by (the fruits of) our deeds. We are the heirs of our deeds and the kinsmen related to our deeds in the world. It is the deeds that prompt a man to pleasure or pain. As gold or silver is poured down (in a liquid form) as the form is (desired), in the same way a being is conceived in accordance with his former deeds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>095  Deeds Which Lead to Heaven</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/095/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/095/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;subāhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subāhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O best brāhmaṇa, now explain to me the merits of heaven. O greatest brāhmaṇa, I shall do all this naturally.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-13a. There (i.e. in heaven) are various divine, meritorious, charming pleasure-gardens, full of all objects of desire and beautiful with trees satisfying all desires. (There are) everywhere aeroplanes attended by bevies of celestial nymphs. They are variegated; they move according to the desire (of the occupant); they are controlled (by the occupant). Their colour is like that of the young sun, and they have windows (decked) with pearls. They are white like the moon’s orb, and have golden beds and seats. In them meritorious men, richly endowed with all objects of desires, and free from all griefs move as on earth. Non-believers do not go there. Those who have not conquered their senses do not (go there). Wicked, cruel, ungrateful and proud (people) do not (go) there. Men that are truthful, that remain in penance, that are brave, kind, forgiving, that perform sacrifices, and are given to giving gifts go there. There nobody suffers from a disease, old age; nobody meets with death; nobody suffers from cold or heat. Nobody has hunger, thirst or exhaustion. O king, there are many merits like these and others of heaven. Now listen to the defects that are there. The entire fruit of an auspicious deed is enjoyed there only. The great defect that is said to be (present) there is that much (activity) is not done (i.e. undertaken by the residents). Also there is dissatisfaction on seeing the bright glory of others. There is a sudden fall of them whose mind is full of happiness. The fruit of that deed which is done here is enjoyed there. O king, this is known to be the land of deeds and that the land of fruits.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>096  Good and Bad Deeds and the Fate of the Performer</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/096/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/096/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;subāhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subāhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Please tell me by (performing) which deeds men go to hell after death, (and) by (performing) which deeds they go to heaven after death.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. Those brāhmaṇas who give up (leading) a brāhmaṇa’s life and deluded by greed live on bad deeds go to hell. Atheists, those who have violated the norms of (good conduct), those who are intent upon (satisfying) sexual pleasures, religious hypocrites, and who are ungrateful go to hell. Men who do not give wealth to brāhmaṇas after having promised them, and also those who take away a brāhmaṇa’s wealth go to hell. Wicked men, those who insult others, who tell lies and talk irrelevantly go to hell.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>097  Subāhu Eats His Own Flesh</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/097/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/097/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The king, having heard all the result of good and bad conduct as told by the sage at that time, said to the sage:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;subāhu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subāhu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O best brāhmaṇa, that I (who am thus advised by you) will practise righteousness; I shall (do) meritorious (acts); O sage, I shall very much worship Vāsudeva (i.e. Viṣṇu), the source of the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6. The king would worship (i.e. worshipped) Madhusūdana (i.e. Viṣṇu) by performing sacrifices and muttering prayers. He, having performed a sacrifice, and having practised penance, and being endowed with all desired objects gladly and quickly reached Viṣṇu’s heaven (along with the queen). Having gone there he did not (i.e. could not) see the lord of gods in that great world. Great hunger arose in them, and great thirst proceeded (i.e. they felt extremely hungry and thirsty) which very much troubled their soul. The king too oppressed by hunger and thirst along with his wife and full of great grief did not see Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>098  The Vāsudeva Hymn</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/098/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/098/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. When the glorious Vijvala uttered these auspicious words, Kuñjala, the best among speakers, told him the auspicious hymn. The hymn in honour of Hari (i.e. Viṣṇu) is recited after meditating upon and saluting Hṛṣīkeśa, who destroys all sufferings and gives entire religious merit. The hymn is called (the hymn in honour of) Vāsudeva; it gives all virtue; it is the gate to salvation; it is possessed of happiness; it gives peace; it enhances nourishment; it gives all desired objects; it gives knowledge and increases knowledge. (Kuñjala) manifested to Vijvala the hymn of Vāsudeva. (The hymn) is called Vāsudeva (-hymn); it is boundless and increases nourishment. Vijvala, the best among birds, having learned it from his father, started to go there (and) asked (the permission of) his father. The religious minded (Kuñjala) said to his son Vijvala who had decided to go, who. had mastered knowledge and who was intent upon obliging (others).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>099  God Viṣṇu Appears to Subāhu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/099/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/099/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. The king, on hearing the hymn which was pure, very ancient, which removed sins, which was full of merit and auspicious, which was blessed, which contained good words, which was greatly fit to be muttered, became happy. His great thirst, along with his hunger, vanished. The lord of the earth became like a god. His wife also shone. Both of them, freed from the bondage of sin, became endowed with good form. That god, the holder of the auspicious conch, disc, lotus, mace and sword, surrounded by great gods, brāhmaṇas, great siddhas full of the devotion of Hari came to the king whose sins had vanished. The holy Nārada, Bhārgava, Vyāsa (came there). The son of Mṛkaṇḍa (also) came there. The sage Vālmīki, Viṣṇu’s devotee, (so also) Vasiṣṭha, the son of Brahmā, came there. The illustrious Garga, full of devotion for Viṣṇu, Jābāli and Raibhya, so also Kaśyapa, (all) dear to Viṣṇu, and best among the followers of Viṣṇu, came there with Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100 Vena Asks to Hear More about Kuñjala</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/100/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/100/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8a. (Vijvala’s) father (Kuñjala) lived on a bunyan tree on the beautiful bank of Narmadā. Vijvala too came there, and the very intelligent, religious-minded one narrated to his father the greatness of the hymn called Vāsudeva(-hymn). With a very much pleased mind he told him as to how Viṣṇu came there and gave him (i.e., Subāhu) an auspicious boon. Kuñjala also, having heard the account of that king, was full of great joy, and having embraced his son said: “O child, by narrating the very auspicious (hymn) of Vāsudeva (to the king) you have done a meritorious deed and an obligation to the noble king.” Having thus spoken to his godlike son, having congratulated him with blessings, and having repeatedly praised him, he remained on the beautiful bank of the river, while Cyavana was beholding. O great king, I have told you all this account of those devotees of Viṣṇu. What else should I tell you?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>101 Kapiñjala’s Narration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/101/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/101/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Viṣṇu, the god of gods, told the best king, the son of Aṅga, the very meritorious account that destroys sins. Listen, I shall narrate to you the meritorious account, and also the account of the noble Kuñjala.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. And the pious Kuñjala with joy called his fourth son Kapiñjala, and said to him: “O son, tell me what wonder you saw. O best son, to which (forest) did you go for your food from here? Tell me, O blessed one, what very meritorious (event) you have seen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>102 Aśokasundarī is Born</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/102/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/102/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O child, now I shall explain to you all that you said: as to what their splendour originated from, O you best twice-born. Once the great goddess Pārvatī, the best among women, while sporting, said (these) words to the lord: “O great god, in my mind a great longing has sprung up. To me (please) show a grove that is best among groves.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-mahādeva-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Mahādeva said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4. Let it be so, O great goddess. I shall show you the Nandana, crowded with gods and resorted to by brāhmaṇas and siddhas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>103 Aśokasundarī is Saved and Āyu Gets Boon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/103/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/103/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. At that time Aśokasundarī was born as the best woman. She, of a charming smile, skilled in singing and dancing and enjoying all pleasures along with the very beautiful daughters of gods sported in the excellent, meritorious Nandana endowed with all desired objects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. Vipracitti’s son Huṇḍa, who was always violent, impetuous and very lustful entered Nandana. After seeing Aśokasundarī, endowed with all ornaments, he was, at her sight, pierced by the arrows of Cupid.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>104 Indumatī’s Dream</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/104/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/104/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. When that illustrious great sage Dattātreya had left, that great king Āyu came (back) to his own city. Being delighted, he entered Indumatī’s house endowed with glory, rich with all desired objects and resembling Indra’s house. O best brāhmaṇa, like Indra in heaven, the intelligent one ruled with Indumatī, the daughter of Svarbhānu, over his kingdom. By the words of Dattātreya, that queen Indumatī conceived a child endowed with divine lustre as a result of eating the fruit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>105 Nahuṣa is Born</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/105/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/105/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. With her friends she went to Nandana garden to sport (there). There she heard significant words, not wholesome to her father, of the bards and siddhas talking delightfully, viz. ‘In the house of Āyu, the best son, of great might, resembling Viṣṇu in valour will be born; he will kill Huṇḍa’.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4. Having heard such significant, unwholesome, painful words, she went (to her father) and told the painful words to her father in brief.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>106 Indumatī’s Lamentations on the Loss of Her Child</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/106/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/106/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. The glorious wife of Āyu, Svarbhānu’s daughter of an excellent complexion, not seeing that excellent, matchless child, resembling a god, wept, making a loud wailing: “Who has taken away may son of excellent marks, endowed with good characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. I had obtained the son by penance, charity, sacrifices, and vows difficult to practise, and with hard efforts. Who has kidnapped the son given to me by the magnanimous, pious Dattātraya, (after) being pleased.” (Thus) she wept piteously.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>107 Nārada Assures of Nahuṣa’s Return</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/107/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/107/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Then that Nārada came from heaven to king Āyu. Having come he said to him: “O king, why are you bewailing? O great king, O very intelligent one, knowing that the kidnapping of your son is beneficial to gods and others, do not bewail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. Being omniscient, virtuous, and equipped with all worldly knowledge, and full of (i.e. endowed with) all arts, your son wilt come (back). O great king, he who has taken away the boy, having virtues like those of a god, to his house, has certainly taken Death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>108 Vasiṣṭha’s Instruction to Nahuṣa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/108/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/108/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Brahmā’s son Vasiṣṭha, of great lustre and the best among the speakers, called that Nahuṣa and spoke these words (to him).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. “Quickly go to the forest, and bring many sylvan products.” Hearing the words of the sage, Nahuṣa came (i.e. went) to the forest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. There that mighty Nahuṣa heard some good (i.e. agreeable) account: “This is that pious and mighty Nahuṣa, the very wise son ofĀyu, separated from his mother (right) from his childhood. Due to a great (i.e. painful) separation from him, the wife of Āyu is weeping.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>109 Vidvara, a Kinnara, Dispels Aśokasundarī’s Apprehensions</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/109/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/109/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Having saluted, having propitiated and having taken the leave of Vasiṣṭha he, an archer, with arrows in his hand, went out (to the forest). Having well cooked the flesh of a black antelope that child, the good, virtuous, handsome son of Āyu, resembling a god, and endowed with godly qualities, was cleverly protected by her (i.e. that female attendant). With that meat which was well cooked, well dressed, boiled and tasty, the cook very gladly fed that wicked (demon) after talking to him. The demon ate that tasty and sweet meat. He was full of joy also. He went to Aśokasundarī.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>110 Nahuṣa Gets Divine Weapons from Gods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/110/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/110/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Having taken leave of all the sages and of Vasiṣṭha, the best of the ascetics, Nahuṣa being eager desired to go to the demon. Then all the sages like Vasiṣṭha, with penance as their treasure, congratulated the very mighty son of Āyu with blessing. All the deities in the sky joyfully beat drums and showered flowers on Nahuṣa’s head.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. Then the thousand-eyed god (i.e. Indra) came there with gods and gave him weapons and missiles resembling the sun’s lustre. O best twice-born, the best king took those divine missiles from the god, and due to that he became one of a divine form.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>111 Nahuṣa Enters Mahodaya, the City of Huṇḍa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/111/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/111/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. When that brave Nahuṣa, comparable to the lord of gods, was going out to fight (with Huṇḍa), all women out of curiosity and with (i.e. singing) auspicious songs went there. The excellent women of gods, and kinnarīs, (all) eager through curiosity sang melodiously, O best one. Also the gandharva women endowed with beauty and ornaments went there where the king stood, through curiosity. The city of that wicked Huṇḍa was Mahodaya by name; it was everywhere adorned with divine groves (like) Nandana. It looked pleasant with houses having seven apartments and with pitchers. The best city shone with great staffs with banners. The best city shone with (mansions) shaped like the peaks of Kailāsa, lofty, reaching the sky, divine and endowed with all glory.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>112 Aśokasnudarī has a Glimpse of Nahuṣa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/112/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/112/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Hearing that song sung by the celestial women and being affected by the songs and their introductory stanzas, that beautiful daughter of Śiva, pondering, quickly getting up from her seat, and being full of great enthusiasm, possessed of penance and devotion, and seeing the prince who resembled a god, whose lustre was like that of a divine form, whose body was besmeared with divine sandal (-paste), who was adorned with divine garlands, who was graced with divine ornaments and garments, who was bright like the sun, who was having divine marks, (thought:)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>113 Rambhā Acts as Aśokasundarī’s Messenger</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/113/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/113/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;rambhā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rambhā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O auspicious one, abandoning the penance, what are you looking at? By pondering over a man your penance would perish.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;aśokasundarī-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aśokasundarī said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. My mind was completely absorbed in penance. Gods, demons or serpents could not lead me away (from it). (But) O you glorious one, on seeing this one my mind becomes very uneasy. Going to him I desire to dally with him. It has become thus (i.e. so much) eager. O you beautiful one, such a change was (there) in my mind. Therefore, tell me its cause, if you know it well. The magnanimous gods have created me as the wife of Āyu’s son. Why is my mind eagar to dally (with this man)?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>114 The Fight between Nahuṣa and Huṇḍa Starts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/114/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/114/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Then all the demons, Huṇḍa’s attendants, told Huṇḍa, the lord of demons, the good words—the conversation—between Nahuṣa and Rambhā as they had heard them. Having heard them, he got angry and said (these) words to his messenger: “O hero, go and know that man who converses with that daughter of Śiva.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-8. Hearing the order of his master the demon left quickly. In a solitary place he said these words to Nahuṣa: “You stand round with a chariot along with horses and the charioteer, and with a bow and divine arrows, and you are fearful in an assembly. To whom to you belong? By whom are you sent, and for what purpose? Tell clearly to me all that this Rambhā and the other (one i.e.) Śiva’s daughter told you today. How is it that you are not afraid of Huṇḍa, the destroyer of gods? If you desire to live, tell me all this. Leave quickly, do not remain (here). The lord of the demons is difficult to put up with.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>115 Huṇḍa is Killed in the Battle</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/115/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/115/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then that great soul, holding a bow, ready to fight and shining in the battle, like Death that was angry and desired to destroy the worlds, desired to kill the great demons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. He killed the demons with a number of mighty weapons resembling the sun’s lustre and very bright. As the wind uproots trees, he killed the demons. As the wind shakes the divine mass of clouds, the king destroyed theintoxicated demons with very sharp excellent arrows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>116 Nahuṣa Marries Aśokasundarī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/116/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/116/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. That devout Aśokasundarī, auspicious and joyful, reaching, along with Rambhā, the powerful Nahuṣa, said to him: “I am your legal devout wife, as ordained by the gods. O hero, if you desire merit here (i.e. in this world, then please) marry me. Always thinking of you, I remained in penance. O best king, by virtue of my merit I have obtained you.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nahuṣa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nahuṣa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5a. If you, O good lady, are directed to be my wife, and for that you remained in penance, then after a short time, in accordance with the words of my preceptor, I shall be your husband. O you beautiful lady, we two shall go with this Rambhā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>117 Nahuṣa’s Consecration</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/117/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/117/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-10. Nahuṣa with his wife and Rambhā came in that excellent, divine chariot of Indra to the city called Nāga which was endowed with all beauty, divine auspicious objects, which was adorned with mansions, which possessed golden portals, which was beautified with banners, and with the sounds of many musical instruments, and with panegyrists and bards. It was also adorned with auspicious men resembling gods in form, with women of divine forms and, with elephants, horses and chariots. It was full of many auspicious sounds and sounds (of the recitation) of the Vedas, the sounds of music and musical instruments, and of flutes and lutes. He entered the best city full of all (kinds) of beauty. The hero honoured with the auspicious Veda recitation by brāhmaṇas saw his father and very meritorious mother. Being full of great joy, he saluted his father’s feet. That beautiful Aśokasundarī devoutly saluted the feet of both of them again and again. That Rambhā also saluted them and expressed her affection (for them). The prince having saluted his father and having talked to him inquired about the health of his mother and father. With horripilation due to joy the illustrious one (i.e. Āyu) spoke thus:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>118 The Story of Kāmoda</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/118/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/118/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kapiñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kapiñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. O father, a beautiful lady was formerly weeping at the mouth of the Ganges. From her eyes tears fell into the great water. They sank into the Ganges and became lotuses. (These) flowers were of a divine nature, great, and fragrant. O father, O illustrious one, why did the pure tears fall from her beautiful eyes into the water of the Ganges? A bearded man, having but bones and skin left (on his body) and clothed in a long strip of cloth, collected those fragrant lotuses. Taking those divine (lotuses) of golden colour, he would worship Śiva with them. O you very intelligent one, tell me who that lady is and who that man is. Why does he lament after having worshipped Śiva? If I am dear to you tell all this to me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>119 The Birth of Kāmodā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/119/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/119/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kapiñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kapiñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O father, from her laughter are produced very charming, divinely fragrant flowers, difficult to be obtained (even) by gods and demons; but, O you very intelligent one, why do all&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;deities long for them? Śiva is pleased when he is well-worshipped with the flowers (produced) from her laughter. Tell me in detail as to what merit the flower possesses. Who would be (i.e. is) that Kāmodā? Whose daughter is that excellent lady? (Tell me how) from her laughter good flowers are produced. Tell me about the merit. Tell me in detail her complete story.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>120 Nārada on Dreams</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/120/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/120/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kuñjala-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kuñjala said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Then Nārada saw the divine city called Kāmodā, which was crowded with gods and rich objects satisfying all desires. Reaching Kāmodā’s house, the best brāhmaṇa (i.e. Nārada) entered it. Then he saw Kāmodā, possessing all desired objects. She honoured the brāhmaṇa with good words like ‘Welcome (to you).’ The best brāhmaṇa, seated on a divine seat asked her: “Are you living happliy, O good lady, sprung from Viṣṇu’s lustre?” Having greeted her with blessings he (also) asked her about her well-being.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>121 The End of Vihuṇḍa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/121/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/121/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;kāmodā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kāmodā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. He is said to be soul, whose limit or form (even) all deities do not know, and in which all this is merged; and the expansion of whose illusion is this worldly existence. Listen, O Nārada. For what reason does my lord, the master of the world go to the worldly existence? A man, who is bound by sinful and even meritorious acts, moves to the worldly existence. O brāhmaṇa, tell (me) why Viṣṇu would go to worldly existence?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>122 Dharmaśarman’s Account</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/122/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/122/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;viṣṇu-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viṣṇu said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-5. That righteous and very intelligent bird Kuñjala, having thus spoken to his sons, ceased speaking. He did not say anything to them. The best brāhmaṇa remaining under the bunyan tree said to that great parrot: “Who are you, explaining Dharma while remaining in the form of a bird? Are you a god, or a gandharva, or are you a vidyādhara? Due to whose curse did you obtain this very sinful birth in the form of a parrot? O parrot, due to what do you possess such knowledge which is beyond the reach of senses? Of what great religious merit or penance is it the fruit? O you very intelligent one, why are you staying here in this disguise? Tell me the origin: whether you are a siddha or a god.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>123 Kuñjala’s Story: A Preceptor Is a Holy Place</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/123/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/123/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-siddha-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The siddha said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-16. Listen, I shall tell you the nature of knowledge. Knowledge has no body, no hands, no feet, and no eyes. It has no nose, no ears. Knowledge does not have the collection of bones. Who indeed has seen knowledge? What are its characteristic marks? It is without any form, it is eternal. The omniscient one knows everything. The sun illumines by day; the moon illumines at night; a lamp would illumine (i.e. illumines) the house. These remain in the world. O best one, listen, (I shall tell you) by what lustre is that place seen? Fools, deluded by Viṣṇu’s Māyā do not obtain it. Knowledge remaining in the body is inflamed by concentration and is matchless. That (highest) place will be seen through that (knowledge) and not by means of the moon, the sun etc. Knowledge is without hands and feet. It is eyeless, and is without ears. It moves everywhere. It grasps and sees everything. O best brāhmaṇa, it smells everything; it does hear; there is no doubt about this. There is no lamp like knowledge for the destruction of all darkness (of ignorance). It is seen in the heaven, on the earth, in the nether world—at every place. Those of wicked minds are not conscious of the knowledge that remains in the body. I shall explain to you the place of knowledge, from which knowledge springs up. O brāhmaṇa, it has always been kept in the hearts of beings. He who always desires to bum with the fire of discrimination the great sensual pleasures like sex and great allurements, becoming full of all tranquility, would crush objects of senses. Then would knowledge be born manifesting the full truth. This knowledge has the first principle as its basis; it is spotless and it manifests everything. Therefore have tranquility which enhances all pleasures. Be equanimous towards your enemy and your friend; and always restrict your food and control your senses. You should not form friendship (with anyone); enmity should be cast at a distance. Being without attachment, being desireless, and having resorted to a solitary place, you will possess spiritual knowledge, explaining everything. O child, there is no doubt that by my grace you, remaining at one place, will know the account of what is taking place in the three worlds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>124 Pṛthu’s Righteous Rule</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/124/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/124/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. When Viṣṇu disappeared, that very intelligent king Vena became anxious as to where the lord of gods had gone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3a. Being full of great joy and having pondered the best king having called the greatest king with sweet words, then said to that magnanimous one with great joy.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-6. “O son, you my son have emancipated me from a great sin in the world. O Pṛthu, now you have made bright my dynasty. I ruined it with my faults; you have illumined it with your virtues. I shall perform a horse-sacrifice and shall give many presents. Due to your graciousness I shall today bodily go to Viṣṇu’s heaven. O you best and very prosperous king, gather the necessaries (for the sacrifice). O you blessed one, invite brāhmaṇas who have mastered the Vedas.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>125 The Merit of Listening to or Reciting This Purāna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/125/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/125/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4a. Having well received the order of Vena that very religious prince, Pṛthu, collected all auspicious necessaries (for the sacrifice). Having invited all brāhmaṇas born in various countries, king Vena performed a horse-sacrifice. He gave various kinds of gifts to brāhmaṇas. The lord of the earth physically went to Viṣṇu’s heaven. The religious-minded one eternally lives with Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4b-12a. I have thus told you the entire account of that king, which terminates all sins and destroys all misery. That religious-minded king Pṛthu ruled the earth. The best king milked the earth with the three worlds. He pleased his subjects with virtuous and religious deeds. I have narrated to you the entire Bhūmikhaṇḍa. The first is the Sṛṣṭikhaṇḍa and the second is Bhūmikhaṇḍa. I shall again tell you the greatness of Bhūmikhaṇḍa. The sin of the best man who (just) listens to one verse of this Khaṇḍa everyday, perishes. O best: brāhmaṇas, listen to the religious merit of him who, the wise one, listens devoutly to a chapter (of this Khaṇḍa). He gets that fruit which is obtained by a gift of a thousand cows to brāhmaṇas on an auspicious parvan-day; and Viṣṇu is pleased with him. A man who everyday reads this Padma Purāṇa, will not meet with difficulties in the Kali Age.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>126 Section 3 - Svarga-khaṇḍa (section on the heavens)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/126/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/2/126/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
