<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;तिरुपति-मन्दिरम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;तिरुपति-मन्दिरम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>KRShNa-svAmI history</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/kRShNa-svAmI_history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/kRShNa-svAmI_history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the statements made and the views expressed the author alone is responsible.&#xA;A&#xA;HISTORY OF THE&#xA;HOLY SHRINE OF SRI VENKATESA&#xA;IN&#xA;TIRUPATI&#xA;VOLUME&#xA;श्री वेङ्कटाद्रि शृङ्गार मङ्गलाभरणाङ्घये । मङ्गलानां निवासाय श्रीनिवासाय मङ्गलम् ॥&#xA;தேனோங்குசோலைத் திருவேங்கட மென்றும் வானோங்கு சோலைமலை யென்றும் - தானோங்கு தென்னரங்கமென்றுந் திருவத்தியூரென்றும் சொன்னவர்க்குமுண்டோ துயர்.&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;CHAPTER&#xA;PAGE&#xA;I. General Geographical Features &amp;hellip; 1 II. Founder of Tirupati-A Toṇḍaman. 30 III. Tirupati and the early Alvars IV. Tirupati in Śilappadhikāram&#xA;V. Tirupati in Tirumalisai Alvar&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;Works&#xA;VI. Tirupati and Nammāļvār VII. Tirupati and the other Alvārs VIII. Bhakti, the dominent Feature&#xA;of the Age&#xA;IX. History of Tonḍamandalam&#xA;X. Inscriptions of the Chōla&#xA;Dynasty in Tirupati&#xA;XI. The age of the Vaishnava&#xA;Acharyas and Tirupati&#xA;XII. Organisation of Worship at&#xA;Tirupati by Rāmānuja&#xA;XIII. The last Chōlas and their&#xA;successors&#xA;XIV. The Yadavarāyas and Tirupati XV. Tondaman Chakravarti-The&#xA;52&#xA;96&#xA;&amp;hellip; 101&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;134&#xA;156&#xA;&amp;hellip; 185&#xA;&amp;hellip; 200&#xA;&amp;hellip; 235&#xA;256&#xA;&amp;hellip; 288&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;&amp;hellip; 312&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;342&#xA;Human Founder of Tirupati. 375&#xA;XVI. Tirupati under Vijayanagar XVII. Tirupati under the Sāļuvas&#xA;&amp;hellip; 393&#xA;&amp;hellip; 453&#xA;PRINTED AT&#xA;ANANDA PRESS, MADRAS.LIST OF ILLUSTRATIONS.&#xA;I. The procession image of&#xA;Śrī Venkatesa&#xA;Page.&#xA;Frontispiece&#xA;3&#xA;II. Tirupati hill and surroundings &amp;hellip; III. Śrī Venkatesa-Seshavāhana&#xA;(Serpent vehicle)&#xA;IV. The Sri Venkatesa shrine&#xA;V. The sanctum of Sri Venkatesa&#xA;VI. Tiruchanur-Temple and tank&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;68&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;114&#xA;197&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;229&#xA;23&#xA;VII. Padikaval Gopuram, Tirumalai&amp;hellip; 239&#xA;VIII. Town of Tirupati&#xA;IX. Pāpanāśa-Tirtham&#xA;X.&#xA;Varāhasvāmi-Tirumalai&#xA;XI. Ākāśaganga-Tīrtham&#xA;XII. Svami Pushkarini&#xA;293&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;294&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;302&#xA;303&#xA;306&#xA;XIII. Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s discus at the fresh water&#xA;tank at Tirupati town&#xA;XIV. Kapila Tirtham&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;324&#xA;646&#xA;336&#xA;345&#xA;&amp;hellip;&#xA;349&#xA;13&#xA;425&#xA;XV. Shrine of Govindaraja, Tirupati.&#xA;XVI. Anandanilaya Vimāna&#xA;XVII. The emblem of Vijayanagar&#xA;THE PROCESSION IMAGE OF SRI VENKATESA&#xA;(Frontispiece)&#xA;THE&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;HE cluster of hills which goes by the name Venkatachalam hills, and the small group in it called the Tirupati hills, have long been the most famous pilgrim spots in South India and the latter has enjoyed an eminence equalled but by a few even up to the present time. It is in the fitness of things that the management, recently constituted for carrying on the administration of the affairs of the temple on the hill and its large properties and income, should have thought of getting a history of the shrine written for the information of the public. The first Committee had this question before them for consideration. Śri Dewan Bahadur T. A. Ramalingam Chettiar&amp;rsquo;s suggestion that I be invited to write the history was readily accepted by the Committee. The Committee&amp;rsquo;s invitation was quite acceptable to me, as it has long been my wish to bring to a conclusion the enquiry, in regard to the history of the temple, which I started so long ago as 1904 in writing a life-history of Rāmānuja, which publication came in for important public consideration in connection with the Govindaraja shrine in Chidambaram. The time was rather propitious also, as the large number of inscriptions&#xA;i&#xA;collected by the Devastanam Department of epigraphy during the last decade had at last been printed and was likely to become available to the public. The history of the shrine in the following pages is based upon these inscriptional records for the latter period, as they furnish an amount of information for that period, not inferior to that of any other important shrine for the corresponding period. This period has reference to that following the life activity of the Vaishnava teacher, Rāmānuja, whose connection with the temple and his actual services to it had long been a fruitful subject of controversy.&#xA;For the period relating to Rāmānuja himself and his active work of reorganising the temple worship and ritual and putting these on a footing of permanence, we are driven to such information as the material for his life-history would provide. That material is hardly ample enough to give us any detailed information in regard to the details of his organisation. But luckily for us, we have a Sanskrit work composed just a few generations after Rāmānuja which bears specifically upon this work. The Committee was so good as to sanction the republication in good form of a critical edition of this work, of which there was an unsatisfactory Telugu edition, and even that had for some time been out of print. The then Commissioner, Śrī A. Ranganatha Mudaliar, deserves all thanks for having enabled&#xA;11&#xA;me to&#xA;to bring out the edition, in Devanagari characters, of the work, Sri Venkatachala Itihasamala, which gives a detailed account of what took place under Ramanuja, and how that arrangement was allowed to continue since then.&#xA;For the period anterior to Rāmānuja, the sources of information are not as ample as for the period following. For about three centuries preceding Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s activity in Tirupati, we have some inscriptions, not many, though some of them do throw much light upon the history of the shrine and the locality surrounding it. For the period before the 8th century, we have to depend entirely upon other sources of information, of which the dominent sources are literature, Tamil and Sanskrit, bearing upon the temple. The classical literature of the Tamils, the so-called Sangam works, have just a few references to Vengaḍam, which formed the northern boundary of the Tamil land according to them, and just a few which would support the existence of the temple at the time, and even of the establishment of the annual festivals for worship in the temple. Proceeding therefrom we have the work of the twelve Vaishnava Āļvārs, whose age and active work occupied the period from the most brilliant period of the Sangam age on&#xA;age on to the last years of the 8th century. These works necessarily have a great deal to say about the temple, as it was one of&#xA;it&#xA;their holy of holies and came in for elaborate description from their point of view.&#xA;While these last sources do have but oblique references in regard to the origin of the temple, they do not supply us with a satisfactorily detailed account. We have to go to the Paurāṇic sources for this, and these are all brought together in a Sanskrit work, Venkatachala Mahatmyam, of which there are numbers of editions, several of them not quite satisfactory. A recent edition brought out for the Devastānam and not published, I have been enabled to look through along with the other editions. This work is mainly a collection of what is said in celebration of this holy place in the various Purāṇās, of which eleven have extensive passages connected with the temple. In their own way, they give us a full exposition of how the self-existing shrine had come to notice, and what services it received from various people from time to time. This account, partaking as it does of the character of all the Pauranic accounts, still seems to let us into the secret of its origin, and the time when it acually came to be recognised as a human institution.&#xA;I have made use of all these sources of information with the care that a work like this deserves, and have adopted deliberately the method of letting the sources speak as far as&#xA;iv&#xA;they could, as in a controversial matter like this, it is much the best thing to set out the facts clearly and place them upon an indubitable footing, quite distinct from such inferences, etc., that one may have to deduce from these facts. I have done so, and the facts are there quite distinctly stated followed by such inferences I have been enabled to draw therefrom. I need hardly add that the responsibility for these inferences and such views as are expressed in the book is entirely my own. The account presented therefore is more or less the bare facts of the history of the holy shrine interspersed with such necessary explanation and clear statement of what the sources by themselves do not make quite clear. It is for readers to judge how well or ill it has been done, and to what extent it carries conviction in regard to the whole history of the shrine.&#xA;I have been able to carry the history of the shrine from its probable date of foundation about the beginning of the Christian era down to practically the end of the 18th century. The account given for the period beginning with the Carnatic Wars right on is not quite as full as it should be owing to the absence of sources of information directly bearing on the period. The records of the British Government may contain information of an important character bearing upon the period; but the records are not as&#xA;yet made open to the public. What is more, the Government have declined to give me access to the records for the purpose. In the circumstances, I could do no more than to leave it as it is.&#xA;I must in the first instance acknowledge my obligation to my friend, Śrī T. A. Ramalingam&#xA;Chettiar and the other Members of the first Dēvastānam Committee, as also the succeeding Dēvastānam Committee with its Chairman Sri Venkata Ranga Rayaningaru. The two Commissioners, Messrs. Sitarama Reddiyar and Ranganatha Mudaliar were no less helpful in regard to the matter, as also the staff of the Dēvastānam Office on the occasion of my visit to Tirupati in the course of the work. I acknowledge with particular pleasure the assistance rendered in the course of my writing the book to Sahitya Sirōmani Pandit S. Rajagopalacharya and Dr. P. Srinivasacharya, M.A., Ph.D., in the earlier stages of the work. The index to the book is the work of Śrī T. V. Mahalingam, M. A., till recently University Research Student, who offered to do the work with alacrity. My grateful thanks are due to all of them for the assistance. The printing work has been entrusted to the Ananda Press. I am very much obliged to its Proprietor, Śrī B. Madhava Rau, M. A., for much accommodating assistance in the course of printing the work, which, as will be seen, has been&#xA;viexcellently done. The illustrations are taken, about one half from the Dēvastānam Archæological photo negatives, and the other from photographs taken by Messrs. G. K. Vale for the Devastanam Committee.&#xA;I am really gratified that I have been able to carry the work to completion without break through the grace of Sri Venkatesa, to whom I dedicate this in token of my devotion.&#xA;THE DASARA 1939,&#xA;S. KRISHNASVAMI AIYANGAR.&#xA;Mylapore, Madras.&#xA;vii&#xA;A HISTORY OF THE HOLY SHRINE OF&#xA;SRI VENKATESA AT TIRUPATI&#xA;CHAPTER I&#xA;GENERAL GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;Tirupati, or far rather the group of hills lying in a confused coil called the Tirumalai hills, forms a feature of the region of South India between the 13th and 14th degrees of north latitude. The Eastern Ghats which, from the northern extremity of the Presidency, run close to the coast, turn into the interior after passing the river Krishna, and then break up into a number of parallel ranges of hills of which, in the region south of the Krishna and extending southwards to the latitude of Madras, say roughly 13th degree of north latitude, three parallel ranges are distinguishable. The range nearest the coast runs more or less straight in one single range. The second range is an irregular group starting similarly from the Krishna well below Kurnool, and runs down in a semicircle into the Cuddapah District scattering about in a cluster, one group of which is called Śēshachalam hills; the main range however runs southwards till it makes a further approach to the coast, coming down as far as Ponneri a few miles north&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;of Madras. Another range more irregular and much lower in point of height, proceeds northwards from the foot of the Mysore plateau and scatters itself through Anantapur and Kurnool districts. The central group is what is called Nallamalais in the Kurnool District, and, as it proceeds southwards from there, it becomes more definitely something like a single range, and meets the Eastern range round about the group of hills at Tirupati, Kalahasti, etc. These hills therefore form a feature of the frontier half a degree to the north of Madras, extending the whole length from the Mysore plateau and stretching eastwards to almost near the coast at Ponneri, and thus constitute a prominent feature of the northern extremity of the Tamil land. Hence it is that, in defining the boundaries of the Tamil country, they mark Vengaḍam, a prominent feature of this cluster of hills, as the northern boundary, the eastern and western boundaries being formed by the sea, and the southern boundary marked by the promontory of the Western Ghats, ending in Cape Comorin. The earliest Tamil grammar Tolkappiyam defines the boundary of the provenance of Tamil as such. Some of the Puranas dealing with the holy shrine at Tirupati liken the range of hills, the Nallamalais and their continuation, to a buge cobra lying about at ease, of which almost&#xA;2&#xA;TIRUPATI HILL AND SURROUNDINGS&#xA;(To face page 3)&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;the end of the tail is marked by the great Śiva shrine of Srisailam not far from the Krishna river, beyond the 16th degree of north latitude and a considerable way down the river from Kurnool. Coming up on the back of this huge snake one next strikes the Vishņu shrine of Ahōbalam&amp;rsquo; which is at the beginning of the trunk of the snake. At the back of the hood stands the hill of Tirupati, and almost at the opening of the mouth again the great Śiva shrine of Kāļahasti. This Paurāņic description is rather graphic and accurate, although the features marked happen to be only the four holy places of Kalahasti, Tirupati, Ahōbalam and Srisailam. We mentioned already the cluster to the west being called Śēshachalam hills, probably the name is given from this feature of the whole group lying about like a snake, or rather a cobra lying at ease in the sun. This curious feature probably had its own share in creating the peculiar impression upon people journeying from a distance, and is probably responsible for the names given which, at first sight, may seem fanciful.&#xA;THE ACTUAL NAME OF THE HILL. Tirupati which is a Vaishnava sacerdotal name for the shrine there, is generally known to Tamil literature by the name Vengaḍam, which is one of the&#xA;B&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;alternative names in holy parlance as well. Vengadam is generally referred to as a hill, though often the reference is as much to the territory surrounding it, and, when it happened to be the capital, the territory dependent upon it. In Tamil secular literature it figures as the northern borderland of the Tamil speaking country of the south. Tolkappiyam, the classical grammar of the Tamils, popularly believed to be one of the oldest pieces of Tamil literature extant, defines the boundary of Tamil provenance as between the hill Vengaḍam and the southern Comorin (Kumāri) as marking the northern and southern boundaries. In those days the seas marked the extent and the prevalence of Tamil on the other two sides. Therefore northern Vengaḍam (Vaḍa Vengaḍam) is the style in which it is most referred to. To make the position clear, it is possible to quote references in which it is stated quite unmistakably that when one passed Vengaḍam from the south, he passed the bounds of Tamil on the one side and gets into a region where the language actually is different. That is usually referred to as &amp;lsquo;Vengaḍam passing which the language changes.&amp;rsquo; Numbers of instances could be quoted for that from Tamil classical literature. So we might take it that Vengaḍam for Tirupati, is the name of the hill,&#xA;4&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;so familiarly known to the Tamils, more or less as a landmark which characterised the northern border of the Tamil land passing across which one got into a region where the Tamil language was not spoken.&#xA;VENGADAM, BOUNDARY MARKING OFF TAMIL FROM&#xA;VADUKAR. The language that was spoken beyond Tirupati was known to the Tamils as Vaḍuku, and the chieftains who ruled even over Tirupati and the regions to the west of it, were generally known as princes of the Vaḍukas (Vaḍukar Perumakan) in classical Tamil. This Perumakan evolves into Peruman in later Tamil which, in the sense of the great one, prince or king according to circumstances, is used as a title of dignity. Accordingly the language which they spoke is known as Vaḍuku which, in modern parlance, means Telugu. But, in the early centuries of the Christian era, the term Vaduku for the language, and Vaḍukar for the people, applied to all the people along the northern borders of the Tamil land extending from the east coast far into the peninsula, perhaps reaching even to the west Coast. At least there is one chieftain in the interior, the ruler of Erumai, who is referred to as Vaḍukar Perumakan, and the indication is that he held rule in a part of the country which is northern&#xA;Б&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Mysore now, and the territory adjoining it. Certain points in this long boundary, in fact the points on the highway of communication between the north and the south, seem marked off as Vaḍukar-munai, the frontier posts of the Vadukar land, that is, the outposts of the Tamil country, where one came into contact with the Vadukar, the contact in respect of Vaḍukar-munai being generally contact hostile. This term Vadukar seems merely to represent the linguistically analogous&#xA;analogous Baḍagas of the Nilgiris of to-day, and it is possible that that happened to be the common name, at least so far as the Tamils were concerned, for Telugu and Kanarese together, before perhaps the two languages differentiated. We have to go to the 11th or the 12th century for a distinctive reference describing the prevalent language in these regions as Vaḍuku, and locating both the Telugu and the Kanarese behind this Vaḍuku land. That distinction obtained in the days of Nacchinarkiniyar, the great commentator. So then, the whole northern borderland of the Tamils was Vaḍuku, and hence the road leading there to the north was described as Vaduka vali, which may mean only one great trunk road leading into the Vaḍuka-land, although from some of the expressions used in the inscriptions of a later date, it may be possible to infer&#xA;6GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;more than one road, as had sometimes been done. Hence the Tamil land was bounded on the north, across almost the whole length of the peninsula, by the land of the Vaḍukar. A prominent landmark in this northern boundary was undoubtedly Vengaḍam, and Vengadam, according to references in classical Tamil literature, should have lain on the highway leading north from the Tamil land, as it happens to be even now.&#xA;TIRUPATI IN EARLY CLASSICAL TAMIL LITERATURE.&#xA;The body of literature generally known as the Sangam literature consists of a number of collections of poems which at one time must have been more generally current in the Tamil land. These seem, from their nature, poems composed on occasions, exhibiting various modes of composition as a mere exhibition of poetic skill by their respective authors. Some time later it was apparently felt that these fugitive pieces of composition were in danger of being lost, and, as a practicable effort, some one was set to collect the most excellent of such pieces to provide typical illustrations of the various modes of composition. Presumably therefore the collections which have come down to us are composed of pieces considered the most excellent at the time that the collections happened to be&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;made. There is one particular author who is reputed in Tamil literature as one who wrote the Bhārata in Tamil, and therefore was generally distinguished as Perundēvanar who composed the Tamil poem Bharatam. Perundēvanār being a common name in Tamil literature, this distinction was considered necessary as, even in this comparatively narrow field of literature, there were a number of Perundēvans. But this Perundēvan who made the Bharatam must be distinguished from the Perundevan, the author of the Bharatam in Venba verses, whose time we know precisely. This Perundēvan must have been an earlier author. To the well-known eight collections he composed the verses in invocation, and these poems in invocation relate to all the well-known deities of the Tamil land at the time, and not confined to one or the other of these exclusively. A late copper-plate charter datable in the tenth century ascribes the &amp;ldquo;doing of the Mahabharata in Tamil&amp;rdquo; to the Pandyan ruler well-known in this class of literature as the Pāṇḍyan &amp;ldquo;who won the victory at Talaiyalangānam.&amp;rdquo; In this famous battle the young Pandya is said, in this literature itself, to have won a victory against his two rival contemporaries, the Chōla and the Chera, assisted by a number of chieftains of the Tamil land, seven of whom are mentioned by name. It is probably&#xA;8&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;therefore that, it was in his reign or immediately after that, the collections of these poems were made, and the poems in invocation to these collections composed by Perundēvanar, the author of the poem, the Mahabharata. The collections which have been made therefore must all relate to a period anterior to this Pāṇḍyan, victor at Talaiyalangānam. References in this literature therefore must be regarded as having relation to the period before the date of Perundēvanar or the Pandya, victor at Talaiyalangānam.&#xA;THE CHARACTER OF THESE REFERENCES.&#xA;These&#xA;references collected from various pieces in two or three of these collections refer to Tirupati by the name Vengaḍam, and generally to Tirupati as being on the northern borderland of the Tamils, as is made in the Tolkāppiyam. In the actual circumstances in which the references do occur, Tirupati is indicated as in a region passing across which one passes from the land of the Tamils into a land where the language spoken was different from Tamil. Among the authors referring to Tirupati we can distinguish two authors contemporary with the Pandyan of of Talaiyālangānam, Kallāḍanar and Nakkirar. Poem 83 of the Ahananuru refers to the chieftain Pulli of the region surrounding Vengadam. He is described in this poem as Ilaignar&#xA;9&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Perumakan; the latter word Perumakan is a Tamil equivalent of prince which later became Peruman, meaning king. The whole expression therefore would mean the prince of Ilaignar, and this latter term is generally used to indicate hunters by profession. Another attribute which he uses is the Tamil term kalla which would mean uncultivated; in other words, in a comparatively savage state of civilisation. In another poem 209 of the Ahananuru, this same author describes the same Pulli and his Vengadam, and mentions the peculiar feature that there was a narrow passage across the hills, described as a tunnel, through which one had to pass to emerge from the territory of the chieftain Pulli into the land to the northward of the region. Nakkirar does not refer to Vengaḍam as such. But he is undoubtedly referring to the territory dominated by Vengaḍam, where he speaks of Tiraiyan and his capital Pavattiri, Reḍḍipālem in the Guḍur Taluk of the Nellore District. In another poem of the same collection, namely, poem 253, Nakkirar speaks of Vadukar Perumakan, Erumai. This Erumai comes under reference in a number of other poems, and by various authors, as the chieftain of the Vaḍukar but, in this poem, Nakkirar indicates clearly that the territory of this Vaḍukar chieftain lay in the region of the river which he calls Ayiri,&#xA;10&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;and, passing that river, one passes from the Tamil land into the land of the Vaḍukar. Ayiri seems to be the Tamil equivalent of the wellknown Mysore river, Hagari, passing near Kadūr and through the Chitledrug District, falling into the Tungabadra, a well-known frontier region in later history between the Tamils and powers to the north of them. Another poet by name Kaṇakkāyanar, probably the father of Nakkirar, as he is often described as Nakkirar son of Kaṇakkāyanār, refers to the northern Vengaḍam in Aham 27, and of the breed of elephants infesting its forests in the course of a description of a Pandya and his famous port, the pearl-producing Korkai. Other authors referring to Vengaḍam are Tayam Kannan, otherwise Tāyām Tayangannan, who refers to Vengaḍam as belonging to Toṇḍaiyar, and refers to the country of the Vaḍukar across the region. Similarly another poet Kannan son of Kāṭṭūr Kīlār, refers to Vengaḍam as belonging to Tiraiyan, and gives a peculiar feature that the elephants there were being fed with the tender shoots of the bamboo. The last but the most important poet of them all, and, perhaps even the oldest among them, Māmūlanar, has seven poems in this collection in which he might be held to refer to Vengaḍam directly or indirectly. In poem 61 he refers to Vengadam as belonging to Pulli, the&#xA;11&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;chieftain of the Kalvar, and another feature of Vengaḍam which he notes, and which is noteworthy, is that Vengaḍam was famous for its festivals. In two other poems 115 and 281, he does not refer to Tirupati. In the first he refers to Erumai of Kuḍanāḍu, the chief Erumai being the ruler of the western country (Kuḍanāḍu). The other piece refers to the Vaḍukar, and to a hill where there was a tunnel for passing in and out, and these features come under reference in the course of a statement that the Mauryas invaded the south, pressing the Vaḍukar forward before them, passed this tunnel in the hill. In poem 295 however he refers undoubtedly to Tirupati as Pullikunram, the hill of the chieftain Pulli, and refers to the country across as the region of the Vaḍukar entering which the language changes. In other words passing into the region of the Vaḍukar, the language changes from Tamil into another language, obviously Vaḍuku. In poem 311 he refers to the good country of Pulli and the desert past it, and describes the feature that the people were accustomed to eating the rice prepared with tamarind, on teak leaves. In poem 359 he refers to Pulli liberal in gifts. In poem 393 Pulli comes under reference again, and Vengaḍam, and here Pulli is described as one the words of whose speech are long, that is, the words are&#xA;12&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;drawn out, as is the characteristic of some of these languages. There are other references by other authors which would confirm one or other of these features, though they do not specifically refer to Vengaḍam as such.&#xA;TIRUPATI, NOT REFERRED TO AS A HOLY SHRINE AS IT IS. It will be noticed that although a number of authors of eminence in this collection actually refer to Vengaḍam, and give some details of features which in those days were regarded as characteristic of the hill and the region of which it was a prominent feature, there is no reference to the great shrine which now-a-days is almost synonymous with the place name. Tirupati now-a-days means first and foremost, perhaps even almost exclusively, the shrine at Tirupati. The change of word to Vengadam, a synonym, does not make much of a difference. That prominence of the shrine does not appear to be given to Vengaḍam in the references quoted above. There is however one reference in poem 61 of the Mamulanar which seems unmistakable in regard to this. Speaking of Vengadam in this poem, Mamulanar refers to it as Vengaḍam of great prosperity, prosperous because of its having festivals. This may be regarded as an unmistakable reference at least&#xA;18&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;to the celebration of festivals there during the year, and of the place being much resorted to on that account, thereby contributing to its prosperity. This may justify our presuming the existence of the temple there, and the series of festivals which had early been inaugurated in connection with it. But it falls short however of the actual mention of the temple as such. The more so as it gives no indication even inferentially of the character of the temple or of its deity. During the period of the Sangam literature therefore we may take it that the temple may have existed, but it had not quite attained to the importance or the prominence that it attained to in the period following.&#xA;NOTEWORTHY FEATURES OF THE PLACE FROM THIS CLASS OF LITERATURE. There are certain points however in connection with the region which are worth noting with a view to the position of the territory in the age of the Sangam literature. The first point to note is that it is the borderland separating Tamil from a northern language which goes by the name Vaḍuku. The modern equivalent of this Vaḍuku would be Telugu. The people who are on the northern borderland of the Tamil country, almost the whole way across the peninsula are referred to as Vaḍukar, and&#xA;14&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;their rulers as Vadukar Perumakan, prince or chief of the Vaḍukar. The region here referred to would answer to the modern division called Rayalu-Sima to distinguish it from the Andhra country proper, so far as the eastern half of it is concerned. In the earlier period, however, it is not merely the eastern but perhaps even the western half is equally distinguishable, the region of the Vaḍukar having behind it the block of territory which, early in South Indian History, went by the name Karṇāṭaka (Tam. Karu-naḍu for the land, and Karunaḍam for the language), that is, in the period following the age of the Sangam, and judging from the information so far available to us. The distinction is made by certain commentators, at least by one commentator of the Tolkāppiyam. Expounding one of the Sutras of the Tolkappiyam itself, the commentary notes that the region we are concerned with was the region of the Vaḍukar; and behind it were the territories where the languages current were Telugu in the east and Kannada in the west. The next point that comes out from the references is that the people across the border spoke a language different from Tamil. It was, in the judgment of the Tamils at any rate, a language as yet not much cultivated, and, according to them again, the pronunciation of&#xA;15&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;words was drawling at least to the Tamil ear, which, from the point of view of the Tamil, would be true of the Telugu spoken in the Andhra country as distinct from the more southern region. The next point is that the natural character of the region, which was a forest country more or less, made the profession of the inhabitants hunting and cattle rearing. Elephants seem to have been abundant in the forest region, and had been tamed and brought into service. The next point is that the region was under the government of a chieftain by name Pulli ruling over a people who are described as Kalvar, possibly with the variant form Kalavar. Subsequently to him it seems to have come under the authority of a chieftain called Tiraiyan with a capital at Vengaḍam, and perhaps an alternative capital at Pavattiri, a little further north. The next point again is that the territory was included in the region of the Tondaiyar; in other words, it was regarded as a part of what was called in brief Tondaimandalam, or popularly Tondamandalam in Tamil. The last point of importance to note from these references is that, at one time, the Chōlas extended their conquests northwards to bring these Vadukar under their authority. A defeat of the Vaḍukar in the north and of the Paradavar, the fisher-folk, in the south&#xA;16GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;happened to be mentioned in connection with a Chōla ruler; in another poem he is said to have inflicted a defeat on the Vadukar at a place called Pāli. It becomes clear therefore that the region dependent upon Vengaḍam was inhabited by a people called Vadukar who were under their own chieftains, and became subsequently subjected to the authority of the Tiraiyan chieftains perhaps after the defeat inflicted upon them by the Chōla, and the Tiraiyan chieftain referred to here is called Tiraiyan without a qualifying attribute, who had his capital at Pavattiri, and not Ilam Tiraiyan associated with Kanchi as his capital, a famous character in the Sangam literature itself perhaps of a subsequent generation.&#xA;CELEBRATION OF FESTIVALS, A FEATURE OF TIRUPATI IN EARLY TIMES EVEN. Before passing from these texts, there is one particular passage in the poems of Mamulanar which calls for a few remarks. The passage actually occurs in poem 61 of the Ahanānūṛu. * Freely rendered the passage means that &amp;ldquo;the chieftain of the Kalvar&#xA;*&#xA;கழல்புனை திருந்தடிக் கள்வர் கோமான் மழபுலம் வணக்கிய மாவன் புல்லி&#xA;விழவுடை விழுச்சீர் வேங்கடம் பெறினும் பழகு வராதலோ வரிதே.&#xA;Aham. 61.&#xA;17&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;who are in the habit of handing over elephant tusks, bartering them for liquor prepared from paddy, and who wore anklets characteristic of warriors, was Pulli famed for the conquest of the land of the Malavar, and for great gifts to those who went to him. (Your lover) it is rarely possible will reconcile himself to stay away even if he got thereby Vengaḍam, the capital of that Pulli which is prosperous because of the festivals celebrated in it.&amp;rdquo; The actual sense of the passage is that an imaginary lover who had departed from his sweetheart and travelled away in quest of wealth to distant parts, has tarried a little longer than he promised, and the consolation is offered to the heartbroken damsel that he might have delayed, but that he would not stay away under any circumstances. To add emphasis to this statement, it is set down that even if, in his desire for the acquisition of wealth, he got possession of such a prosperous city as Vengaḍam, he would not stay behind. The point for notice here is that the fame of Vengaḍam in the estimation of Mamular was due, at least in part, to the great festivals which were celebrated in the place from time to time, meaning obviously the annual festivals which are now a feature of the great temple-city. The casual statement of this feature has its own tale to tell. According&#xA;18&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;to almost all the Puranas which make references to this shrine at Tirupati, it was a Tondamān ruler who unearthed the shrine, built a temple for the God thus discovered by digging up an ant-hill, housed the God in a shrine and instituted a certain number of festivals to that God. The evidence of the Purāņas therefore is that Tirupati became a human institution with a shrine and all its appurtenances only from the days of the Tonḍaman. The identification of this Toṇḍaman would give us the clue to the actual period in which the temple came into being as a human institution. As a matter of fact, the Purāņas state it that the shrine itself was not a human creation, but is regarded as the divine abode itself come on to the earth by the will of the God abiding there, that is, Vişņu. We noted already that, in these poems alone, we note a change of rulers of the locality, the chieftain whose territory it was, is Pulli, the chieftain of the Kalvar, a section of the Vaḍukar, and from him it becomes included in the territory of the Toṇḍaiyar. Three poets, Tayam Kanṇan in Aham 213, Kāṭṭūr Kilār Makan Kaņṇan in Aham 85, Nakkīrar in Aham 340 speak of the ruler as Tiraiyan instead of Pulli. If these poets were later than Mamular we could take it that the territory dominated by Vengadam passed from the Kalvar chieftain&#xA;19&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Pulli of the Vaḍukar people to the Tiraiyan chieftain. This Tiraiyan is referred to as having for his capital Pavattiri, identified with the village Reḍḍipalem in the Gudur Taluk. The extent of the territory is further indicated by Mamular himself who refers in poem 11 included in the Kurum-togai to the territory as on the borderland of the Vaḍukar (Vaḍukar-munai), and the district is referred to as Vērkkāḍu Naḍu where language changes. This Vērkkāḍu is no other than the latter part of the name Pala-Vērkkādu, now anglisised into Pulicat. The territory therefore forming part of the modern Chingleput, North Arcot and Nellore Districts, constituted the hilly country dominated by Vengaḍam and contained other cities like Pavattiri and Vērkkāḍu; it was in the territory of the people Vaḍukar ruled first by the Kalvar-chieftain Pulli, and then passing from him under the authority of the Tiraiyan chieftain, who at one time had his capital at Pavattiri. The question now would arise as to who this Tiraiyan is and whether he is the same as Ilam Tiraiyan of Kanchi, or different from him. Literary evidence is not quite decisive. The Ahanānuṛu contains a number of poems relating to a Tiraiyan, and the fact that the more famous person associated with Kanchi and the hero of the Tamil Classic Perumbāṇ-&#xA;20&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;arrupaḍai is always referred to as Iļam Tiraiyan would support the view that the Tiraiyan was an older chieftain; and because of his existence the more famous chieftain coming after him has been called Ilam Tiraiyan, so that the two personages may have to be regarded as distinct from one another. That they were distinct seems to be the view of the venerable scholar MM. Dr. Swaminatha Aiyar. The fact that Kanchi is referred to as Toṇḍaman Kanchi in an old quotation, and that, in another similar passage, the chieftain addressed is called Tiraiyan held to be Ilam Tiraiyan, would support this latter view. It is rather strange, however, that in a poem composed to celebrate Ilam Tiraiyan in particular and his capital Kanchi, such as the Perumbāņ-arrupaḍai is, there is no reference to his northern territory or to any one of the cities which seem to be special features of that territory. This omission would perhaps be held to go against the identification. However, for our present purpose we may take it that the various literary references are all of them to one and only one Tiraiyan, Ilam Tiraiyan of Kanchi. That the organisation of festivals in connection with temples we see in his time is in evidence in lines 410 and 411 of the Perumban-arrupaḍai, which, in substance, states, that Kanchi attained to&#xA;21&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;greater fame than the other old cities comparable with it, because of various festivals celebrated there for the spiritual benefit of many peoples, rendered by the commentator, people of various communities in religion. In the days of Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan therefore festivals associated with temples had become an ordinary feature in towns like Kanchi. When the Purāņas state, as they do, that it was a Tondaman who inaugurated festivals in Tirupati, one could very well take it that probably the Toṇḍaman of Tirupati fame is no other than the Tonḍaman associated with Kanchi. Tirumalisai Alvar has a similar reference in verse 41 of his Nan-Mukhan Tiruvandadi where he has a specific reference to the festival of Onam called Ona Vilavu. This festival of Onam (Sans. Śravana) was the earliest festival inaugurated in Tirupati by no less a person than Brahma himself and is as yet the principal festival, the Brahmotsava in Tirupati. The advent of the Toṇḍaman to power therefore, we may take it, marks the beginning of temple festivals, and we could well believe the Purāņas when they state it that it is a Toṇḍaman chieftain, generally called Toṇḍaman Chakravarti in Vaisnava parlance, that instituted these festivals in Tirupati in his time.&#xA;22&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;TONDAMAN ILAM TIRAIYAN. Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan is a great celebrity in Tamil literature, and is celebrated in the poem Perumbāṇarrupaḍai, forming one of the collection called &amp;ldquo;the Ten poems&amp;rdquo; (Pattuppaṭṭu). The author of this poem is described as Kaḍiyalur Rudran Kannan, which would mean Kannan, the son of Rudran of Kaḍiyalur. From what is known of him, he seems to have been a Brahman, but the place from which he came has not so far been satisfactorily located. Though Ilam Tiraiyan is described as a ruler of great influence and importance, he is still not regarded as a crowned monarch, and is placed in a rank inferior to that of the three crowned kings of the south, Chōla, Pandya and Chera. Such rulers are called Kurunilamannar, which literally translated would mean kings or rulers who ruled over land of a smaller extent or of inferior character. In other words it would simply mean kings or rulers of a smaller degree. The Tolkappiyam, the authoritative work on matters like this, classes them as of royal descent, but not of monarchical standing. As described in the poem of Rudran Kaņṇan, he was the ancient ruler of Kanchi ruling over what, in Tamil literature, is generally described as Tondamanḍalam, which included the vast region between the Telugu frontier, the 14th&#xA;28&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;degree of north latitude on the eastern side, extending southwards to the river Pālār, sometimes extending as far south as the northern Vellar. We may take it roughly that the northern Penṇar and the northern Vellar constituted its boundaries north and south. It extended westwards from the coast to take into it all the territory down to the foot of the hills bordering the plateau of Mysore, and from there going across through the middle of the present-day district of Salem. He is regarded as the son of a Chōla ruler, generally described as Killi Valavan, which is more or less a generic name for the Chōla, but is probably identifiable with Neḍu-Mudi-Killi whose name figures in the Silappadikaram and Maņimēkhalai. The Perumbān-aṛrupaḍai describes him as descended of the royal family of Ayodhya, in fact specifically mentioning Tirumal, generally taken to be Rāma; but it carefully distinguishes him at the same time as coming of a younger branch of the family, because the Chōlas claim to belong to the family of Ikṣvāku, and, among their warrior ancestors, figure&#xA;names like Sibi, etc. The actual passage&#xA;under reference is &amp;ldquo;descended from one, the brother who came after him, who has the colour of the sea, who carries on his chest the goddess of prosperity, and who measured out the great&#xA;24&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;earth. &lt;em&gt;&amp;rdquo;&#xA;This would mean that the prince was descended of a younger brother of Vishnu, and therefore equated with the family of the Chōlas who made a similar claim. He bore the name Tiraiyan (belonging to the sea), because he was brought over by the sea and lashed ashore on the Chōla coast, to be taken and brought up by the Chōla ruler as his son. The story in connection with this is that the Chōla ruler in one of his solitary meanderings along the banks of the backwaters of the sea in Kaverippumpattinam saw an extraordinarily beautiful damsel, and fell in love with her at sight. The damsel responded in her turn, and they carried on a love affair which extended to his visiting her in her underground residence as the commentators call it. This was because she was a Naga princess, and the Nagas usually live in the underworld. We shall see that it perhaps means no more than her parents were living in a place access to which could be obtained only by passing through a cavern or a tunnel across the hills. When she became enceinte as a result of this liaison, she expressed&#xA;நீயிரு&#xA;மிரு நிலங்கடந்த திருமறு மார்பின்&#xA;Spear of it QJ Gaur GROT GOT 4 Wishi திரைதரு மரபினுர வோனும்பல்.&#xA;Perumban-arruppadai ll. 29-31.&#xA;25&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;her concern in regard to the child to be born. The Chōla king advised her to put the baby carefully in a box and send it afloat on the sea with a twig of the creeper of the Tondai (coccinia indica) tied round his ankle. If the baby should reach him safe, he would bring him up as a prince and make him king as becoming a prince. Some time after, the baby was born, she did as she was directed, and the baby meeting with an accident on the sea somehow reached the shore, and was brought to the Chōla monarch. The king brought him up as his own child and appointed him to the viceroyalty of Kanchi when the time came. This story figures of course in a Buddhist setting in the Manimēkhalai. We shall come to that detail a little later. He was ruling over the whole of Tonḍamandalam with his capital at Kanchi. The poem Perumbāṇarṛuppaḍai describes him in the conventional style which demands the description of the four classes of land of which one&amp;rsquo;s territory must be composed, the seashore, the forest land, hilly country and agricultural land; and a fifth class has also to be marked in this, as some of these lands had a tendency to become desert land by frequent droughts and by the heat of the sun. This is described as desert land transformed into such either from forest land or&#xA;26GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;from agricultural land. A port is described under the name Nir-Peyartu, from which the Pan or musician, expert in playing on the greater musical instruments, such as the Tamil Yal, and hence called Perum-Pan as opposed to the Šiṛu-Pan, one who played on the smaller musical instruments, passes through various classes of land till he reached the town of Kanchi, the headquarters of Ilam Tiraiyan. This particular poet describes the Vishnu shrine in Kanchi called Veḥ-Ka or Yadōkta-kari, and that is the only shrine, of all the multitudinous shrines that one finds now in Kanchi, which finds mention in this poem actually. Kanchi is described in this poem as having attained to reputation as already an ancient city where religious festivals were celebrated for various classes of people, to each according to its own conviction. Since the author of this poem Rudran Kannan has also celebrated the great Karikāla in another poem of the same collection called Paṭṭinappālai, describing particularly the city of Kaverippumpattinam, the capital of the Chōlas, and is said to have received a very liberal reward from the great Chōla ruler Karikala, and since this poem&#xA;is of almost the same character and must have been presented to the ruler whom it celebrates, we have to take it that Ilam Tiraiyan came in the same generation as the great Chōla Karikāla&#xA;27&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;As a matter of fact we have reason to regard him as coming in the second generation after Karikala and may possibly be even in the third. He was contemporary with the Adiyaman chieftain specifically known by the name Adikan, and the poetess Avvai is said to have gone from him, who was her patron, to the court of Ilam Tiraiyan on an ambassadorial mission and persuaded the monarch into peaceful ways. This would bring him into contemporaneity with the Adiyaman of Tagaḍur, another celebrity in the Sangam literature. There are a number of fugitive pieces of poetry in which he comes under reference either as merely Tiraiyan, or as Tonḍamān, neither of which could be described as a specific name. But these have been held to refer to Ilam Tiraiyan generally, particularly one stanza which is quoted as composed by a Poygaiyar, identifiable with Poygai Ālvār as we shall see later. He was himself an author, and a few poems are ascribable to him in the collections which have come down to us. He is supposed to have been the founder of a town or city which went by the name Tiraiyanur. There is a tank which goes by the name Tiraiyanēri to the south of Kanchi; and the locality where the Mission Hospital and the adjacent buildings are now, is pointed out as the place where the Tiraiyan&amp;rsquo;s palace and other buildings were found in ruins.&#xA;28&#xA;GEOGRAPHICAL FEATURES&#xA;This locality may be considered distinct from the fortress of Kanchi, the part now-a-days called Big Conjeevaram. It may be that this suburb of Kanchi was called Tiraiyanur. We shall see therefore that he is identifiable through and through with Kanchi, and we do not come upon any reference to Vengaḍam, or Pavattiri, or even Vērkkāḍu which we find referred to as in the territory of Pulli first and the Tonḍamān chieftains afterwards, as we have already stated before. There is however the fact that the whole of the territory under reference in these poems is included in the Tonḍamaṇḍalam, or as it is sometimes called Tondainadu.&#xA;29&#xA;CHAPTER II.&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI-A TONDAMAN.&#xA;THE TONDAMAN AND THE EARLY ALVARS.&#xA;From what has been stated above, it is clear that the Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan was undoubtedly ruling over the Tondamandalam so-called which included the territory dependent upon Vengaḍam, and therefore we may take it that he came after the cheiftain Pulli referred to in the&#xA;Sangam literature, particularly in the poems of Māmular. This should be quite in keeping with the trend of evidence in the Sangam literature itself which would bring Ilam Tiraiyan into some kind of a chronological connection with the famous Pandyan, victor at Talaiyalangānam, and the contemporary of Nakkirar. The names of both this Pandyan and the poet Nakkirar are intimately associated in tradition with the third Sangam at Madura. Ilam Tiraiyan therefore comes in at a time when we should expect him from his relationship, again chronologically, with Karikāla, and this is confirmed by Nakkirar&amp;rsquo;s poem Aham 340 where he associates Tiraiyan with Pavattiri, the capital of that part of Tonḍamandalam dependent upon Vengadam. It thus becomes clear that Ilam Tiraiyan of&#xA;30&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Kanchi was probably the Tiraiyan who is referred to in the other poems of the Sangam collections by various authors, and he came in the generation, not very remote from that of the Pandyan victor at Talaiyalangānam. The importance of this position consists in this, that the Vishnu shrine at Vehka finds prominent mention in the poem actually dedicated to him. This is among the oldest shrines of Kanchi, if not actually the oldest. It is mentioned frequently along with Vengaḍam or Tirupati in the poems of the earlier Ālvārs, and is regarded as a shrine of the greatest importance. What is more, the names of two Alvars get associated with the place, namely, Poygai Alvar and Tirumalisai Alvar. In the Vaishnava tradition Poygai Alvar is said to have come and worshipped at Kanchi, which is made just possible by the fact that this Alvar is taken to refer to Tiraiyan in one of the fugitive stanzas already referred to. That particular stanza is quoted as the work of Poygaiyar, not Poygai Āļvār. But a contemporary commentary on a work of the eleventh or twelfth century, Yapparungalakārikai, quotes a few stanzas from Poygai Alvar including the one already referred to. Two of these stanzas are identifiable in the first Tiruvandadi ascribed to Poygai Alvar in the Prabandha collection of 4,000. It therefore&#xA;31&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;seems to leave no doubt that the Poygaiyār referred to is the same as the Poygai Alvar. Poygai Alvar&amp;rsquo;s poems so far known to us are all of them in the Venba metre, and he is quoted along with a number of others who excelled in composing poems in this metre. Poygai Alvar is said to have come to Veḥkā at Kanchi in the course of his pilgrimage along with his two companions Bhutattu Alvar and Pēy Alvar, in the course of which they are said to have met Alvar Tirumalisai. This last Alvar is closely associated with Veḥkā, where he is said to have resided habitually. In the course of his long residence there, he came into contact with a more or less secular disciple by name Kaņikaņṇan through whom he came into contact with the ruler of Kanchi, a Tiraiyan himself, probably Ilam Tiraiyan. The story is merely this. That Kanikaṇṇan was serving the Alvar with devotion, and, in connection with his service, he brought in a woman to assist him. She earned, by faithful service, the favour of the Alvar so much that she was granted by the Grace of God perpetual youth and unfading beauty, with which she was able soon to attract the attention of the ruler of the locality to become ultimately his sweetheart. In the course of his long dalliance he was able to learn from her how she came by the unfading youth&#xA;82&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;and beauty which proved to be such an attraction to him, and, having heard that it was due to the favour of Kanikaņṇan, who served alike the Alvar and the God at Veḥkā, he sent for Kanikannan to see him. Finding out from him that he had not so much part in the matter as the Alvar, the king commanded the presence of the Alvar through Kanikannan. Kanikaṇṇan protested that the Alvar was not likely to go to see him even at the summons of the king. Wild with rage at what he thought was impertinent disobedience, he asked Kanikanṇan to take himself away from Kanchi. Kanikaņṇan in due course went and reported the matter to his master the Alvar, and, through him, wanted to obtain the leave of the God at Veḥkā to go away from Kanchi. Sooner than let him go, the Alvar told him that he would himself follow, and that, if he followed, the God himself was not likely to stay in the place. Saying so, he addressed God in a verse which has come down to us and begged him to follow him as he had decided to leave the place and go along with Kanikanṇan who had been exiled by royal command. The God complied and hence the name for the God Yadōktakari, the God who did as he was directed (by his devotee). The miracle in the story apart, the story itself is evidence of some kind of the contemporaneity&#xA;83&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;which may be accepted as evidence of the contemporary character of Tirumalisi Alvār with Ilam Tiraiyan on the one side, and of his contemporaneity with Poygai Alvar and his reference to Tiraiyan on the other. Ilam Tiraiyan is therefore thus brought into connection with the first Alvārs, namely, the three who are known as such and the fourth, Tirumalisai. That marks the starting point of the history of Tirupati. We shall have to examine the other side of the tradition namely, what the Purāņas have to say about the Tonḍaman chieftains who were responsible for the unearthing of the God at Tirupati, the building of a temple for him and the organisation of worship and festivals in connection with it.&#xA;THE PURANIC ORIGIN OF TIRUPATI. The Purāņa tradition concerning the origin of the temple at Tirupati is varied in character and voluminous. As many as eleven different Puranas refer to this subject, and give the account in circumstantial detail which would strike the ordinary reader as quite legendary in character. Having regard to the character of the subject, and the purpose of edification for which these are severally written, the legendary colour certainly would dominate. It would be surprising if it were otherwise. But, through all this legend,&#xA;34&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;one can still find certain facts standing clear, which may be regarded as not belonging to the realm of pure legend, and may perhaps be regarded historical, though perhaps in a legendary garb owing to association. The basal fact is that God Vishnu had, by his choice, come to live in Tirupati for which an occasion and a stimulating cause alike seem called for. These makers of legend provide both by taking the story of the great Rishi Bhrigu&amp;rsquo;s investigation to find the Supreme in actual fact. Once upon a time there was a discussion among the Rishis, the most devoted to God and nearest in service to him, as to which of the three manifestations of the Supreme, Brahma, Vishņu, Śiva, was really the Supreme. It must be remembered that the Supreme is One, but manifests himself in three forms, with one of the three qualities, Sattva, Rajas and Tamas, dominating in each case, and discharging functions suitable in consequence, which must and necessarily be discharged by the Supreme by his very nature, the three essential functions of creation, protection and destruction. Each one of these functions is allotted to one of the three: Brahma, having charge of all creation, 28 a result of his dominating quality Rajas, energy or activity. Vishnu is given the function of looking after all creation with the dominating&#xA;35&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;quality of Sattva, serene strength. Similarly Rudra or Śiva is allotted the function of destruction, his dominating quality being Tamas, generally regarded as involving unthinking irascibility. But at the back of all this division, there certainly is the notion which makes all the three but manifestations of the One, and, as such, each one of the three being regarded as the Supreme itself. In this notion of unity, there is the possibility of two classes, those who make Rudra the Supreme, and those who make Vishņu the Supreme, Brahma often not coming in for that claim to the same extent. It is this unity in variety that formed the topic of discussion of these wise ones; but they found good reasons for regarding each one of these as the Supreme, and undecided, they induced Bhrigu, the most favoured among the Rishis and the wisest among them, to make a pilgrimage to the various abodes of the trinity and find out by himself and directly by experiment. Naturally he went first to the palace of Brahma in Satyaloka-heaven. He found Brahma seated in full durbar, and treated the guest who entered the durbar after due salutation, somewhat familiarly, and, without the due forms of welcome to which the great sage was entitled, in the belief that Bhrigu was after all Brahma&amp;rsquo;s own son. Bhrigu noted the dominence of self in the mind&#xA;36FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;of Brahma in thus regarding himself as the progenitor of Bhrigu, notwithstanding the height to which that progeny had risen by penance. Having noted that, he passed on next to Kailasa, the abode of Śiva, and found the Lord God disporting himself with Uma, his consort. Resenting the freedom with which Bhrigu entered so familiarly, even into the secret conclave of his own sportive dalliance, and, taking to heart particularly that the Goddess felt very delicate about the matter, he chased Bhrigu out of the palace in anger. Bhrigu noted this incident, and passed on the purpose of his mission to the palace of Vaikuntha, where the other member of the trinity, Vishnu-Nārāyaṇa was in his Yoga sleep, Lakshmi in his chest, the other attendants, ladies and other, each in the appointed place. Affecting disappointment that the God, whose function was protection, should have thus gone to sleep, consulting his own comfort to the neglect of his duties, the Rishi went up to the sleeping God and kicked him on the chest to wake him up. Vishņu woke up from his wakeful sleep, and apologised to the Rishi for having shown himself so careless and wished to know whether his foot suffered by coming in contact with His own hardened chest. So naturally, Bhrigu reported what took place in the three places to the assembled wise people,&#xA;37&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;and they all voted in favour of Vishnu as the really Supreme One, the other two being more or less slaves of their dominating qualities or passions. But for the purpose of the Tirupati story, this gave the occasion for Lakshmi to pick a quarrel with her husband. Bhrigu&amp;rsquo;s kick on the chest of Vishnu fell on her. She therefore was naturally wild that he should have been allowed the freedom to do such a thing, which did her the double insult, of the personal insulting treatment to her, and of the disregard of proprieties which the Rishi should have showed to her Lord. Vishnu pleaded that the sage was justifiably beside himself with anger at Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s apparent neglect of duties, and that it would not do to deal with such people, as otherwise than he did. In a fit of rage Lakshmi declined any more to remain on his chest, which had ceased to give her the protection that it should have, and that she thought she was entitled to have. Lakshmi having gone away from heaven, Vishnu could not go on for long thus bereft of his consort, and wanted to go away somewhere else to spend his time pleasantly and get on alone. After making due enquiries, he discovered that the hill Seshachalam provided a spot which would be quite an ideal place for his residence, pleasant to live in with surroundings which supplied everything that he&#xA;88&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;would want for diverting himself in his serious and light-hearted moods, and so he arranged to come and live there. Knowing this the Rishis went there to perform penance. The Gods and Goddesses each one contributed what he or she could to make the place pleasant, and thus fitted out, God Vishnu came into residence there abandoning Vaikuntha itself. He had been there aeons of time, and when we come to the particular Manvantara (Cycle of Manu) with which we are concerned, he showed himself there in the form of the primeval boar carrying the Goddess of the Earth, redeemed from the deep. This is indicated as the Varaha shrine on the west of bank of the tank on the hill at Tirupati called Vishnu Tirtha now, and after a considerable length of time, and, for the purpose of showing himself to a devotee who had long been performing penance to him, he assumed the form of Srinivasa, God bearing Lakshmi on his chest, for his benefit, and thereafter lay buried in the earth. Ultimately some cowherds discovered the cows that they brought to graze over the hills, going up an ant-hill and milking of their own motion, and returning home dry. The king of the locality whose cows they happened to be, got informed of this phenomenon, and went down to investigate. Digging up the ant-hill, he discovered the God in a small shrine,&#xA;39&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;well within the bowels of the earth. He got the spot dug up, and, unearthing the simple shrine, built a brick temple round it, and provided it with all that would make a temple of it. That is the famous Śrīnivasa shrine at Tirupati, and with this temple we emerge from legend perhaps into history.&#xA;THE TONDAMAN RAJA OF THE PURANAS. The first question that would arise is, who is this Toṇḍaman who laid the foundations of Vishņu worship in Tirupati, in proper form, with the temple and all its appurtenances. We shall have to go a little further into the Puranic story itself to gain the clue to an identification, if an identification for him is at all possible. A Toṇḍaman who was a great devotee of VishņuVishnu at Tirupati and one in whom the God was deeply interested, interested to the extent of lending him his own characteristic weapons of the disc and the conch to bring him success in war, was given by him solemnly the highest teaching that a Vaishnava could desire, directly. We come upon references to a Toṇḍaman who had earned the favour of the Supreme deity so far, as to have had these acts of grace in his favour directly from God himself, in the Prabandha literature. These therefore must have been based upon well accredited tradition,&#xA;40&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;if they do not have a really historical basis. The Purana stories however, continue that, after the foundation of the temple in the manner described above, and providing for worship therein, the God, having been deprived of the company of Lakshmi in the manner previously described, and, having elected to come down and live in Tirupati in consequence,&#xA;was&#xA;accustomed to diverting himself by hunting and such other engagements, habitual to him. In the course of one of these hunting expeditions, he happened to come upon a beautiful damsel in one of the deep glades of the forests round Tirupati. He discovered on enquiry, that the beautiful damsel was no other than the princess, the only daughter, and that, one not born to him, but bestowed on him by divine favour having been discovered by him in the forests. The ruler is known to Purāņic tradition as Akāśa Raja, otherwise described by the synonyms of the word Akāśa, whose queen bore a name synonymous with the earth, as if to give away the secret that the young lady concerned was the daughter, even as the foster-daughter, of the earth and sky, as if to take her away altogether from the human category. We may infer that this Raja belonged to the family of the Tonḍaman chiefs, as he is said to have had a younger brother who went by the name&#xA;41&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Toṇḍaman who assisted the elder brother in sundry acts of administration and seems to have been more or less directly entrusted with the government of the region round about Tirupati itself. The Purāņas certainly display all their resources in describing the marriage that was brought about between this foster-daughter of the &amp;ldquo;sky-king&amp;rdquo; and the God himself, accounting for this strange alliance by the story that when Sīta threw herself into the fire to prove her innocence, at the end of the Rāmāyaṇa, she prayed to be restored to her husband the great God Vishnu himself, and the restoration was brought about in the human fashion in the marriage of Padmavati to God Venkatesa at Tirupati. This is what is generally described as the marriage of Venkatesa or the marriage of Śrīnivāsa, a story much affected by the professional story-tellers who perform Harikathas for purposes of edification. We may pass over these details as of no particular importance to the unravelling of the history of the temple. After the marriage was over and Padmāvatī returned to her original place, Akāśa Rāja ruled for a short while and passed away, along with his queen, leaving only a young son who was born some time after the discovery of the baby Padmavati herself. Since Akasa Raja associated with himself in his administration his younger&#xA;42&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;brother, Toṇḍaman, the uncle and the nephew who was a young prince, went to war to decide who was to succeed Ākāśa Rāja as ruler. Both of them being, each in his own way, a superman, the war proved undecisive; but, in the course of it, the uncle Toṇḍaman felt his physical resources ebbing away and prayed to God for help. It was on that occasion that Venkatesa is said to have parted, with his disc and conch for the use of this ruler. The war terminated however, without being clearly and decisively in favour of either. So ultimately they came to a compromise, and arranged to rule the vast territories of Akāśa Rāja in two parts, the parts nearer Tirupati being given to the uncle, and the rest of it farther away to the nephew. The prince built for himself a capital lower down the river and ruled his kingdom in great prosperity, while the Toṇḍaman ruled&#xA;ruled from the&#xA;from the original capital Nārāyaṇavaram, and did far more service to the temple, and in fact laid the foundations of the organisation and worship that obtain in Tirupati even down to modern times. It is in connection with this Tondaman in the course of his service to the temple that we find mention of a secret passage through the hill leading from his capital up to the temple itself, to which the king could go from his capital unseen of&#xA;43&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;others and quite unmolested. It was he that organised from time to time the various annual festivals, the first of which is the Brahmotsava in the months of September-October of the&#xA;year. The principal festival known is the Brahmotsava, and probably this festival is what is referred to by Tirumalisai Alvar as the Ōna-Vilavu (the Śravana-festival).&#xA;WHETHER TONDAMAN RAJA WAS A HISTORICAL&#xA;CHARACTER. This Tonḍaman ruler seems to be more or less a historical person, although, as we find in the tale recorded in the Puranas, there is much that is said of him which may be legendary, as certainly all that is said of his more illustrious brother, the Akāśa Raja, on the face of it appears to be legendary, even including his own name and that of the queen. It is just possible, notwithstanding the legendary details connected with him, to regard this Toṇḍaman as a historical character from the fact of his building the temple, and his organisation of worship there. Notwithstanding this probability, one might well ask the question whether we have any evidence on which to base a definite statement like that. The legends and the Purāņas themselves appear to give a clue to this. One of the versions tries to define the time when all this organisation took place at&#xA;44&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Tirupati, and states specifically that it took place in the Kaliyuga when the Yuga had advanced sufficiently to have given occasion to the institution of the era which now-a-days&#xA;goes by the name Vikramaditya, and say definitely that the other era known to the Hindus, that of the Saka had not yet come into existence. This would mean a period of time between 57 or 58 B. C. and 78 A. D. the period of time to which we have arrived by our previous line of enquiry, entirely independent of this Purāņic tradition. We found that the region dependent upon Vengaḍam or Tirupati changing hands from the Kalvar chieftain Pulli, and passing into the possession of the Tonḍaman chieftains before the time of the great Pandyan victor at Talaiyālangānam, from references in the Sangam literature. That very literature gives us a Tonḍaman, ruling from his northern capital at Pavattiri, Reddipalem in the Gudur Taluk, and held rule over the northern Tonḍamandalam. We have referred rather more elaborately to another Tonḍaman that literature knows of, namely, the Tonḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan. So we seem to have now three Toṇḍamāns before us, the Toṇḍaman or Toṇḍaman Chakravarti referred to in the Purāņas, the Tiraiyan of Pavattiri or northern Tonḍamandalam and Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan&#xA;45&#xA;of Kanchi.&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;Whether all these three were the same, or how they are to be connected one with the other is a problem which has to be considered now.&#xA;IS TONDAMAN RAJA TONDAMAN ILAM TIRAIYAN?&#xA;We have already seen that some of the literary references seem to leave the question open whether the Tiraiyan of Pavattiri and Ilam Tiraiyan are one and the same. It seems on&#xA;the whole the best course to take it that the two Tiraiyans are different from each other; at least those that were contemporaries of Ilam Tiraiyan and those who wrote of him either as contemporaries or later seem to be under the impression that he was different as they call him distinctly Дam Tiraiyan which would presume an Elder Tiraiyan. If we should therefore take the two to be different, we shall have two rulers coming one after the other-perhaps with an interval of time-it may be a generation or perhaps even a little more. The title Tiraiyan would indicate the family to which they belonged. The name Tondaman would really mean &amp;ldquo;the chief man among the people Tonḍaiyar&amp;rdquo;, at any rate, the person who was ruler of the people called Tondaiyar, the inhabitants of Tondamandalam, in fact, the people who gave the name Tondamanḍalam to&#xA;46FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;the locality. Even some of the Purāņas seem to refer to these Tonḍaman rulers as of the Chōla family. The Tonḍaman who built the temple at Tirupati and organised worship there is the son of a Chōla ruler through a Toṇḍaman princess whom he used to meet in a love adventure, through a secret passage leading through considerable distance. The association therefore between the Tonḍamāns and the Chōlas is thus made clear even in the Purāņas. This connection is specifically stated in the poem Perumbān-aṛṛuppaḍai, mainly to celebrate the liberality of the patron Toṇḍamān Ilam Tiraiyan. Whether this would really warrant our identifying the Tonḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan, with the Tonḍaman associated with the Tirupati temple, is a question which requires careful consideration.&#xA;TONDAMAN RAJA OF TIRUPATI DISTINCT FROM&#xA;TONDAMAN ILAM TIRAIYAN.&#xA;We have already&#xA;noticed that the region round Tirupati passed from the hands of the Kalvar chieftain Pulli to chieftains known as Toṇḍaman, and that at least one Toṇḍaman is referred to as having ruled from Pavattiri over northern Tondamandalam, the country dependent upon Tirupati. We do know of another Toṇḍaman, the famous Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan of whom we have some&#xA;47&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;details of information in the&#xA;poem&#xA;same Tamil classical collections, particularly one exclusively devoted to him by a poet Kaḍiyalur Rudran Kaņṇan, who has also a similar poem on the great ruler Karikāla. A Toṇḍaman is actually referred to in the Purāņas as being specially attached to the God at Tirupati, and rendering great service to the temple there by constructing it for the first time and organising the worship. Of course, we shall have to take it, on the basis of these Purāņic accounts themselves, that this was in all probability the Toṇḍaman to whom the God at Tirupati showed particular favour, by lending him his warlike weapons, and by giving him instruction in the secret of the eight letters (Ashṭākshara). Apart from the personalities named, all the three sources of information collated go to show that there was a dynasty of rulers in northern Tonḍamandalam dominated by Vengaḍam who went by the general name Toṇḍamāns. But there is one aspect of history in regard to these which deserves particular consideration. Speaking of the Toṇḍaman who rendered devoted service to the temple at Tirupati, the Purāņas refer to his having been the son of a Chōla ruler, as the result of his love to a princess of the country, whom he was in the habit of meeting by going through a secret passage&#xA;48&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;which may, in modern language, be described as perhaps a tunnel or a natural cave through the hills. Of course, the Puraņas describe it as a bhilam, a hollow underground going into the depths of the earth. The Toṇḍaman devotee of the God at Tirupati was thus of the Chōla lineage through, of course, a princess of the locality, who might have been a princess of the family of the Toṇḍaman rulers. The Topḍamān Ilam Tiraiyan is described in terms in the Perumbān-aṛruppadai as having been born of a Chōla as well, but by a Naga princess, whom the Chōla king met in the city of the Nagas, Nagapattinam, and with whom he carried on secret love by going to her through an underground passage which would be the equivalent of bhilam of the Purāņas. But this story of a Naga connection for a Chōla ruler and an offspring like this is referred to, in a Buddhist setting, in the Maņimekhalai, and all details concerned being taken together would seem to indicate the Tonḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan, the offspring of a Chōla ruler, successor either immediate, or one degree remote, of the great Chōla Karikala. But the story here differs in this particular. She was a Naga princess undoubtedly, but met the Chōla ruler in the outskirts of his capital at Kaverippumpaṭṭinam at the mouth of the river Kaveri, not Nagapattinam,&#xA;49&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;the city of the Nagas, as Nacchinarkkiniyār explains the passage in the Perumbāṇ-āṛṛuppaḍai which is actually worded much more generally and without specific details which would lead to an identification. The question naturally would arise whether we should identify the Toṇḍaman attached to the God in the temple at Tirupati, with Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan. While there is nothing in the story specifically to lead us to an identification, the circumstantial details given seem to make it possible that the two personages were perhaps the same; but that is hardly enough for a positive identification. The Perumban-aṛruppadai which gives specific details regarding the Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan and mentions the Vishnu temple at Veḥkā at Kanchi, makes no mention whatever of Tirupati, nor of Ilam Tiraiyan&amp;rsquo;s association with Tirupati. This omission on the part of a poet who had laid himself out elaborately to sing the praise of Ilam Tiraiyan is significant, and stands against an identification between the two. We have therefore to take it that the family of the Toṇḍamāns that ruled over northern Toṇḍamandalam had established itself and achieved a certain amount of distinction before Ilam Tiraiyan came into existence and attained to fame, while it may not debar the connection between the family of Ilam Tiraiyan on the&#xA;50&#xA;FOUNDER OF TIRUPATI&#xA;mother&amp;rsquo;s side with the Tonḍaman chieftains of the region round Tirupati. We may therefore have to take the Toṇḍaman devotee of Śrīnivasa referred to in the Puranas as one who came before Toṇḍaman Ilam Tiraiyan, though the possibility of Ilam Tiraiyan&amp;rsquo;s mother being connected with the Toṇḍaman ruler is still made possible. Therefore the Tonḍaman of Tirupati probably came in the generation previous to Tonḍamān Ilam Tiraiyan with whose family the Chōla king could have been brought into contact by the conquest of Tonḍamandalam by the Chōla ruler Karikāla. Ilam Tiraiyan therefore must have been a ruler of Kanchi who came somewhat later than the Toṇḍaman of Tirupati. We shall now proceed to consider how far other evidence supports this position.&#xA;51&#xA;CHAPTER III.&#xA;TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS.&#xA;TIRUPATI IN THE PRABANDHA FOUR THOUSAND: MUDAL ALVARS, THE FOUR THOUSAND,&#xA;ITS&#xA;AUTHORS AND THEIR AGE. The most prominent piece of literature which throws a considerable amount of light upon the early history of Tirupati is &amp;ldquo;the Prabandha Four Thousand &amp;ldquo;, which is a collection of 4,000 stanzas of Tamil poetry, celebrating the 108 places of worship sacred to Vishnu by a certain number of devotees, generally counted twelve, who, because of their single-minded devotion and the consequent nearness to God, are called Alvārs. The general period to which the whole body of this literature is referable happens to be the five centuries 300 to 800 A. D. These did not all of them live at one and the same time, and, if the age of each one of them is not as yet precisely fixed, a broad classification of these into early, middle and later, can well be adopted as a recognised method of classification, and the probable period of time in which each one of these groups flourished seems also ascertainable. Without going into the whole of that question here, we may take it that three among them are known as the first Alvārs, described as the&#xA;52&#xA;we&#xA;TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS&#xA;singers in classical Tamil (Sen Tamil) by Tirumangai Alvar, namely, Poygai, Bhutam and Pey, and one other that follows, namely Tirumalisai. These four constitute the early Alvars. Of these comparatively little is known in the matter of life details, and in consequence are left without much material by way of data for fixing their actual period of life. From the internal evidence of their works, however, it seems possible to come to some fairly definite conclusions in regard to their period of activity, and this, in itself, would throw a flood of light upon the history of a shrine like Tirupati, not to mention other general questions, such as the rise of the cult of Bhakti, and of the school of Vaishnava worship generally known as the Pancharatra, or Agamaic worship more generally. latter class of literature lays down the norms of the life of a devotee, and prescribes the various forms in which worship should be conducted by differing classes of people, with a view to achieving the ends of existence here, and attaining to a permanent one hereafter. It is this form of religion which postulates the existence of a personal god with attributes, capable of being pleased by service and of accepting devotion with a view to secure His grace ultimately and attain to salvation thereby.&#xA;53&#xA;This&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;These Alvars are devotees of Vishnu in that sense, and their works contam in them how exactly they devoted themselves to the service of God and attained ultimately to His grace, thereby providing, at one and the same time, not only an account of their edifying achievement, but also lays down a course of conduct which a devotee might follow with advantage to achieve the same supreme purpose.&#xA;THE FIRST THREE OF THESE AND THEIR LIFE AND&#xA;WORTH. Coming down to their earthly history, we know almost nothing historically of the first three except that they were men who were born in different places and on different dates not much removed from each other either in point of place or in point of time. They led a single wandering life going from place to place, and visiting Vaishnava holy places. The detail bringing the three together happens to be that they all met on a rainy night in the narrow vestibule of a small house in Tirukkōvilür with a view to protection from the inclemencies of the weather. The first one who came there went in, and finding the platform that is generally found in village houses between the front door and the interior door leading into the house to one side of the passage, vacant, lay down there for the night. The second one came there seeking refuge similarly from the inclemencies of the&#xA;54&#xA;TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS&#xA;weather, and he knocked at the front door. The one that was already there answered that all the room that there was, was enough for one to lie down. Finding that the second one was a Vaishnava in distress, he added that, if there was room for one to lie down, certainly it would be room enough for two to sit on, and opened the door; and the two determined to sit out the night on the narrow payal. A short time after the third one came and knocked at the door similarly, and the two replied, as the one in the former case, that the place had just room for two men to sit on, and that, if two men could sit, it would be possible for three men to stand, and so the third one got admitted; and all the three resolved to stand out the whole night, and save themselves from the violence of the weather. It is said that God Vishnu, installed in the temple in the locality, was pleased with their devoted service to him, and, wishing to show himself to them, came with his consort Lakshmi, without whom he does not usually proceed, particularly where acts of grace are intended, and, seeking admission as the others did before, almost squeezed the three out of their place by extending his body gradually and pressing them out. In the course of this process it dawned upon them that they were being tested by no less than God himself,&#xA;55&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;and they broke out into song in praise of God,&#xA;each one of them his own way. Each one of these is the author of one centum or a hundred of the Prabandha referred to above, and these, along with certain other pieces of literature of this school, constitute one main division named Iyarpa in the Prabandha.&#xA;THE GENERAL CHARACTER OF THEIR WORKS.&#xA;Of&#xA;these the first, and by far the most interesting, is Poygai Alvar. Poygai is the author of the first centum of the last thousand of the Four Thousand in the Prabandha. The first part of the word Poygai means a tank, a bathing tank, attached to the temple at Veḥka in Conjeevaram. Alvar is the sacerdotal honorific given to this class of Vaishnava devotees, holy ones in near association with God himself. He seems to be the person referred to by commentators, particularly by one commentator on the Alankāra grantha named Yapparungalam belonging to the 11th or 12th century A. D., to which a commentary was written by a disciple of the author himself. This commentator quotes two stanzas from this centum, namely 40 and 51, as extracted from the author Poygaiyar. The latter part of the word in Tamil is a respectful honorific meaning a person belonging to or born in Poygai. So the difference of this designation&#xA;56TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS&#xA;from that of the previous one consists merely in this that the person so referred to is not given the Vaishnava sacerdotal name, but still the quoting author feels that he ought to be referred to, or quoted with, due respect as the esteemed one coming of Poygai, the place. He is referred to by others as one who composed principally in the Venba metre, and is counted as a model in that kind of composition along with other ancient Tamil classics famous for that. So this Alvar was not only a Vaishnava devotee, but one who occupied a high place among the celebrities in Tamil literature. The question whether he is the same as the one who composed the Kalavali Forty, celebrating the victory of the Chola king Semkan over a contemporary Chera ruler, Kapaikkal Irumporai, is more open to doubt. The first centum ascribed to him was sung by him when the idea dawned upon him that it was God Vishnu himself that was practically elbowing them out of the narrow payal where he and his two companions had found shelter from the inclement weather. This idea is said traditionally to have risen in the three simultaneously, and each broke out, in his own characteristic way, into praising Vishnu in a hundred verses. The first Poygai made the whole universe, the lamp vessel, the oceans, the ghee for feeding the lamp, the sun himself, the burning wick, and, lighting such a lamp, he placed, at the lotus feet of the One with the&#xA;57&#xA;8&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;blazing disc, his garland of verse in order that the great ocean of evil besetting him may leave him. The second in his own way made his own loving devotion (anbu) the lamp vessel, his ardour (dravam) for service the ghee for feeding the lamp, and his mind melting with goodness, the lamp wick. He lighted the lamp of true knowledge (gñāna) and dedicated it to God Nārāyaṇa, as one capable of incorporating his divine knowledge in Tamil verse. The third on the contrary broke out &amp;ldquo;Lo, I see the Goddess Śrī. I see the golden body, I see the colour of the rising sun. I see the glorious disc. I see the dextral conch. I see all this in Him of the colour of the ocean, dear to me. The upshot of all the three is that the unlooked for and the ununderstood incommoding of these people by a pressure for which they could not divine a cause, put them in mind of the Supreme, and this community of thought runs through and through the three centums, though of three separate authors.&#xA;&amp;quot;&amp;rdquo;&#xA;REFERENCES TO TIRUPATI IN THE FIRST CENTUM.&#xA;Our concern in regard to these three centa of verse is not so much their import or philosophy, but merely their bearing upon the history of the shrine at Tirupati. The first of these Poygai has as many as 12 to 15 direct references to Tirupati in the centum ascribed to him. He refers to the place incidentally as one of the&#xA;58&#xA;TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS&#xA;places in which Vishnu in his grace has shown himself to mortal eyes for purposes of devotion and worship, so that people in this sin-promoting world might find it possible to realise the Supreme, and, by that means, shake off the shackles of the results of their deeds and attain to ultimate salvation. These references are of the utmost importance as they give us an insight into some of the characteristic features of the shrine, and have also been in a way responsible for certain false theories as to the actual character of the temple itself. The first point, a point perhaps of the greatest importance, is certain peculiar features in the image of the God at Tirupati which made it possible for raising a doubt whether the image enshrined in the temple is actually an image of Vishnu or Śiva or some other manifestation. Without going into the claims set up and adjudicating as between rival claims, we shall have to consider what exactly these authors have said about the temple. Stanzas 5 and 74 *&#xA;241 687 15 17 17 6007 GOT IT LOLD OUT GOT 4 GT 265 IT உரை நூல் மறை யுறையும் கோயில் வரை நீர் கருமம் அழிப்பு அளிப்புக் கையது வேல் நேமி உருவம் எரிகார் மேனியொன்று.&#xA;(5)&#xA;ஏற்றான் புள்ளூர்ந்தான் எயிலெரித்தான் மார்விடந்தான்&#xA;நீற்றான் நிழல் மணி வண்ணத்தான் - கூற்றொருபால் மங்கையான் பூமகளான் வார்சடையான் நீள்முடியான் கங்கையான் நீள் கழலான் காப்பு&#xA;(74)&#xA;59&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;of the first centum run like this. &amp;ldquo;His name, Aran (Hara) and Naraṇan (Nārāyaṇa), His vehicle, the bull and the bird; His word, the book (Tam. Nul equiv. Sans: Tantra, the Agamas), and Marai (Veda); the house of residence, the hill (Kailasa) and the waters (the ocean); His function, destruction and protection; the weapon in hand, the trident-spear and the disc; His form, though one, is fire and dark cloud. &amp;quot; This is almost repeated in a somewhat different form in stanza 74 where it is said &amp;ldquo;He rides the bull and the bird. He burnt the castle (the three castles in the air) and broke open the heart (tore up Hiranya&amp;rsquo;s chest with his claws as man-lion (Narasimha); He is smeared over with ash (Vibhuti); He is of the saphire blue colour. Part of His body is a lady (Parvati), and in one part is the lady born of the lotus, Śrī or Lakshmi. His coiffure, the long matted locks; His head covered by a tall crown; He wears the Ganga (Ganges) on His head (Siva), and on His lengthening foot (Vishnu Trivikrama)&amp;rdquo;. Here it will be clear that God is described as though he were possessed of a twin form, each with its own characteristic set of features and weapons; and, superficially interpreted, it might be held to mean that the form of the image is, to say the least, Hari and Hara in one, Vishnu-Śiva; and so it has been&#xA;60&#xA;TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS&#xA;seriously held on this evidence, and the contention raised that the temple was actually a Śiva temple. These two stanzas of which a translation is given above have certainly no reference to Vengaḍam or Tirupati in either of them. But it may not be so baseless to regard it as applying to Tirupati, because Tirupati is under reference in this author in a number of places, and, on the whole, some of the less usual and more recondite features of the image at Tirupati seem to lend colour to this interpretation. Before proceeding to draw the important conclusion whether it is a Siva shrine or a Vishņu shrine on the statement of this author, we are bound in simple fairness to interpret the author of the centum as a whole, first of all to ascertain whether the deity having the greatest appeal to him is really Śiva or Vishnu, doubtful details notwithstanding. The Vaishnava holy places are 108, and the Śiva holy places are supposed to be 1,008. In all the works of these it would be difficult to trace a&#xA;reference to any one of the Saiva holy places as such, while all the holy places referred to by their specific names happen to be Vaishṇava holy places. The first is Srirangam in stanza 6, Vengaḍam itself in a number of others, Viņņagar, Veḥkā, Tirukkōvilūr (in 77). Of these places mentioned by him, it is doubtful&#xA;61&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;if Vinnagar has reference to a place on earth, as in this place God Vishnu is said, in that stanza, to be seated which is taken to be only in heaven (Vaikuntha). There are places called Viņņagar, one very prominently near Kumbhakoņam, where the posture of the image representing God is not that. The other places are within comparatively easy reach of Kanchi, which is the birthplace of this Alvār. Veḥkā is in Kanchi itself. Tirukkōvilur is not at any great distance from it, and so Vengaḍam. Śrirangam may be counted a little farther, but perhaps the great reputation of the shrine may have brought it within his reach. These three Alvārs are said to have been moving from place to place on pilgrimage bound, although we do not find them mentioning the more distant places as the other Alvārs do. But what is really more useful for our purpose is that Poygai was associated with the town of Kanchi directly, the more so than even Tirukkōvilür, and the details that he gives of Tirupati would perhaps warrant an equally intimate acquaintance. The reference to Srirangam is however only a single reference, and that says actually nothing more about the place than that he saw and worshipped God enshrined there. The most therefore that we&#xA;could say about it is that he visited Śrīrangam. In regard to Tirupati, however, stanza 26 refers&#xA;62&#xA;TIRUPATI AND THE EARLY ALVARS&#xA;to Tirupati, the saving grace of which is enjoyed by the Gods themselves. In stanza 37 there is a more explicit reference. It refers to Vengaḍam again as &amp;ldquo;a place acceptable to the God who blew the beautiful white conch, which receives constant worship from people of great learning who offered daily worship with incense, lamp, holy water, and proceeded to offer the worship from all directions.&amp;rdquo; There is a similar reference to Vengaḍam in stanza 39 where the God &amp;ldquo;who lies on the deep blue sea, who lifted the earth, and who killed Kamsa by striking fear into him, is in a standing posture.&amp;rdquo; Stanza 40 refers to Vengaḍam as well, but gives only a secular feature of the place where elephants are referred to as if threatened by the falling stars in the belief that they were torches held by the Kuravars of the place. There is another reference in stanza 68. This reference again is rather more general, that &amp;ldquo;the God Vishnu is in the heaven on earth&amp;rdquo; in Vengaḍam, and in the four Vedas. Stanza 76 refers to Tiruvengaḍam describing the God there as the one who measured the earth (Vishņu-Trivikrama). Stanza 77 similarly refers to Vengaḍam where the image of God stands along with the other three places, Vinnagar, Veḥkā, and Kovalur in which respectively He sat, He lay in bed and He walked. In stanza 82 there is a reference to Vengadam, but the&#xA;68&#xA;HISTORY OF TIRUPATI&#xA;description of the place given here is worth noting for more reasons than one. Vengaḍam is here described as the hill of him who on a former day shot effectively the deer (Rama killing the deer Maricha). But the description of the hill is interesting. It says that on Dvadasis (the 12th lunar day) ladies were accustomed to offer worship with garlands and incense, which latter sent up so much smoke which made the sky itself clouded and the stars indistinct.&lt;/em&gt; It must be noticed here that ladies were accustomed to offering worship, naturally with incense and flowers. It happened to be particularly on the 12th day of the fortnight. This Dvadasi festival is counted the holiest among the large number of annual festivals organized in connection with the shrine at Tirupati, and the 12th day is described in the Purāņas as peculiarly holy in respect of Vishņu and that in Tirupati. Stanza 86 does not refer to Tirupati but refers to Tirukkōvilūr, and to the incident of the meeting of the three Alvars that took place at the vestibule of the house there. The last reference to Tirupati is in stanza 99 where Vishnu is spoken of as Eternal, and being&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NanditA</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/nanditA/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/nanditA/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-etymological-roots-of-the-word-are-hard-to-find-in-sanskrit-the-nearest-words-in-sanskrit-are-vyamah-kata-which-mean-enveloping-different-kinds-of-sins-and-the-earliest-appearance-of-the-name-is-in-medieval-puranic-literature-after-the-10th-century-ad&#34;&gt;BALAJI - VENKATESHWARA Lord of Tirumala – Tirupati&#xA;An Introduction&#xA;Nanditha Krishna&#xA;BALAJI — VENKATESHWARA Lord of Tirumala - Tirupati&#xA;An Introduction&#xA;To&#xA;Venkateshwara,&#xA;who has given me every happiness and helped me through times of stress and sorrow,&#xA;and to&#xA;Chinny, Prashanth and Rudra,&#xA;my most accommodating and encouraging family, whose pilgrimages on foot from Madras to Tirumala have reaffirmed my faith.&#xA;00&#xA;BALAJI - VENKATESHWARA Lord of Tirumala - Tirupati&#xA;An Introduction&#xA;Nanditha Krishna&#xA;FS&#xA;Vakils, Feffer and Simons Ltd.&#xA;Hague Building, 9, Sprott Road, Ballard Estate, Mumbai 400 001&#xA;Copyright with the author&#xA;All rights reserved&#xA;First printing 2000&#xA;Price in India Rs. 295/-&#xA;Published by Mrs. Jean Trindade&#xA;for Vakils, Feffer and Simons Ltd.&#xA;Hague Building, 9, Sprott Road, Ballard Estate Mumbai 400 001, India&#xA;Printed by Arun K. Mehta at Vakil &amp;amp; Sons Ltd. Industry Manor, Appasaheb Marathe Marg, Worli, Mumbai 400 025, India&#xA;ISBN 81-87111-46-1&#xA;Contents&#xA;Acknowledgements&#xA;Preface&#xA;1.&#xA;The Lord of Tirumala&#xA;2.&#xA;Legends of Venkatesha&#xA;3.&#xA;The Sacred Hill&#xA;4.&#xA;The Sacred Tank and Holy Waters&#xA;vi&#xA;vii&#xA;1&#xA;7&#xA;17&#xA;21&#xA;5.&#xA;Vishnu&#xA;—&#xA;Narayana&#xA;31&#xA;6.&#xA;Incarnations and Manifestations of Vishnu - Narayana&#xA;35&#xA;7.&#xA;Origin, History and Administration of the Temple&#xA;49&#xA;8.&#xA;Images of Lord Venkateshwara and Other Deities&#xA;63&#xA;9.&#xA;The Temples of Tirumala, Tirupati and Tiruchanur&#xA;71&#xA;10.&#xA;Rituals and Offerings&#xA;93&#xA;11.&#xA;Prayers to Balaji Venkateshwara&#xA;—&#xA;105&#xA;12.&#xA;The Relevance of Balaji - Today&#xA;107&#xA;Glossary&#xA;113&#xA;Bibliography&#xA;114&#xA;V&#xA;vi&#xA;Acknowledgements&#xA;To Dr. I. V. Subba Rao, I.A.S., Executive Officer, Mr. A. Subhas Goud P.R.O., Mr. V. Chandrasekhara Naidu, Superintendent, P.R.O. Office, Mr. P. N. Jayasekhar, Assistant Photographer, and Mr. V. Ramachandra, Assistant in the P.R.O.&amp;rsquo;s Office, of the Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanam, who gave me access, information, photographs and whatever help I asked for, and to Mr. Surendra Babu of the Indian Express, Tirupati, for introducing me to these wonderful people,&#xA;To the artist Y. Venkatesh, who learned to draw in the traditional style of Tirupati art to produce the beautiful drawings in this book, and to the staff of the C.P. Ramaswami Aiyar Foundation and its constituents Y. Rushendra Kumar, H. Manikandan, M. Amirthalingam, Christina Isaac, K. Shantha,&#xA;—&#xA;S. Sumathra, S. Gowri, Malathi Narasimhan,&#xA;S.P. Vijayakumari, R. Shiva, S. Ravi and V. Shanmugam&amp;ndash; who helped me in so many ways,&#xA;To Mr. V.K. Rajamani, for the cover and other colour photos, Mrs. Sharada Rajamani who shared her&#xA;knowledge of the God of Tirumala, to&#xA;Mr. M. Parthasarathi who gave me the photograph of the original image and to Mr. P. Sudhakar&#xA;who provided some of the other photos,&#xA;To Mr. Arun Mehta, who suggested the book, and&#xA;Mrs. Sudha Mehta, of Vakil &amp;amp; Sons Ltd., both wonderful&#xA;friends and people, who were so helpful and co-operative,&#xA;To Mrs. Rajeshree Sabnis, Mr. S. Sivagurunathan,&#xA;Mr. Satish Nagwekar, Mr. M. Annamalai and&#xA;Mr. Parag Chemburkar for their competence and enthusiasm in scanning and correcting the photographs and laying out the text,&#xA;To my mother Shakunthala Jagannathan, an eminent&#xA;writer herself, for proof reading the book, and, to&#xA;my father A.R. Jagannathan, who taught me to have faith and belief in Venkateshwara,&#xA;To Chinny, Prashanth and Rudra, who encouraged me through times of creativity and frustration,&#xA;Thank you very much.&#xA;Preface&#xA;Balaji&#xA;—&#xA;Venkateshwara has been by my side from the moment I entered this world. As our family deity,&#xA;he received the hair from my first tonsure, my two sons&amp;rsquo; several tonsures, and every vow and pilgrimage was made in his name. My husband and sons have frequently walked to Tirumala from Madras and I, myself, have walked up the hill and visited Tirumala several times. After every wedding in the family, including my own, we would perform a kalyana utsavam at Tirumala. Venkatesha has been so intricately woven into my life that his picture adorns every room in my house.&#xA;Thus when Mr. Arun Mehta of Vakil and Sons Ltd. called and asked me to write a book on the Lord of Tirumala- Tirupati, I was ecstatic, for I believe that it could only have been Venkatesha himself who wanted me to write it. Thereafter, things began to happen. I had no material to start with, except my grandmother&amp;rsquo;s tales and a few children&amp;rsquo;s comics on the subject. Suddenly, I started receiving gifts of old and new books on Venkateshwara and Tirumala-Tirupati from unexpected sources, from people I hardly knew and had not met for years, and who did not know I was writing a book on the subject. Today I have one of the best libraries on Balaji, a veritable cornucopia of material which has made it possible for me to write this book. This is one of the many miracles of Balaji. For the rest I went to Tirupati, where the Executive Officer and staff were most helpful.&#xA;Although this is the story of one God and his temple, his mysterious origins, the miracles and legends associated with him, the sanctity of the hill, peaks and lakes, the elaborate rituals and festivals, his beautiful jewellery, his renowned powers to do the impossible, all provide a wealth of material about the God and attract millions of pilgrims to the temple. The various images in the temple, the temple itself and the sculptures which adorn it pale, in contrast, into insignificance. In spite of the inaccessibility of the temple, pilgrims flock in large numbers to have darshan and to participate in the daily, weekly and seasonal festivals. His popularity knows no bounds. All these have made Venkateshwara into one of the most popular Gods of 20th century Hinduism, definitely the wealthiest. What makes the temple so popular, and what are the beliefs of the people, are questions that I have tried to answer.&#xA;I have tried to present to the reader the flavour of Tirumala, a curious combination of myth and reality, a remnant of geological, historical and legendary events of the past preserved in a remote sanctuary atop a hill, and&#xA;vii&#xA;viii&#xA;how it finds relevance in the present day. The story of creation, the appearance of the hill and the clearing of the forests, as narrated in this book, are legendary accounts of geographic and historic events, known to our people several millennia ago.&#xA;To re-create the atmosphere of Tirumala-Tirupati, the legends associated with the God and the temple have been illustrated in the Tirupati style of drawing, a school of art synonymous with Kalamkari painting and executed with vegetable colours. It is still extremely popular in the region of Tirupati-Kalahasti in Chitoor district of Andhra Pradesh.&#xA;A little-known fact is that the temple is a source of so much charity and education, keeping contemporary requirements to the forefront. Every coin dropped in the hundi goes to help a worthy cause.&#xA;Tirumala also represents the cultural unity of India : It is a Tamil deity and tradition situated in Andhra Pradesh, a God with a name (Balaji) of North Indian origin, a manifestation of a pan-Indian deity (Vishnu) and his incarnation, whose feminine aspect&#xA;resides in Maharashtra.&#xA;While the material in this book has been well researched, I have presented it in, I hope, a reader-friendly way for the layman, the devotee and the curious who wish to know more about this phenomenon. Folk stories and oral traditions have been woven into Sanskrit traditions to present popular perceptions. Diacritical marks over Sanskrit and Tamil words have been omitted as they are unknown to the lay reader.&#xA;As we move towards the new millennium, one&amp;rsquo;s thoughts turn to the future what does it have in store for us, how will it be different? The answers lie in the past, in the antiquity and continuity of Indian culture, and in the strength and resilience of the Hindu religion which provides eternal values and belief systems which have stood the test of time.&#xA;January 2000 Chennai 600 018&#xA;Nanditha Krishna&#xA;Vinaa Venkatesham na naatho na naathah&#xA;Sadaa Venkatesham smaraami smaraami&#xA;Hare Venkatesha prasiddha prasiddha Priyam Venkatesha prayachchha prayachchha&#xA;There is no Lord for me other than Venkatesha&#xA;I think of Venkatesha all the time&#xA;May Venkatesha be happy with my prayers May Venkatesha be pleased to bless me forever&#xA;ixBell&#xA;ינשס&#xA;The Lord of Tirumala&#xA;Chapter 1&#xA;The Lord of Tirumala is like a magnet, drawing people to his temple on the hill. Every day, thousands of devotees flock to his shrine in reverence and love. The stories of his miracles and compassion are legion. Who is this God? Why is he so beloved of all? To know and understand this phenomenon, we have to go back in time to the ancient Varaha Purana, a book which contains the story of the manifestation of Lord Vishnu as Balaji or Venkatesha, Lord of the Tirumala hill.&#xA;Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva - the Trinity of Creator, Preserver and Destroyer are, themselves, manifestations of the formless, all-powerful and omnipresent Supreme Being. Vishnu, as the protector of the cosmos, preserves life, making sure that all creatures enjoy a meaningful existence. Whenever Dharma or the Righteous Law is threatened, he appears on earth as an incarnation or a manifestation, to protect the good and his devotees.&#xA;Venkateshwara or Balaji is one such manifestation, and the sanctum sanctorum which houses the Lord on the Tirumala hills is known as Shri Vaikuntham, the heavenly abode of Vishnu.&#xA;This, then, is the story of Balaji Venkateshwara, Lord of Tirumala-Tirupati.&#xA;Brahma, Shiva and Vishnu, the Hindu Trinity of Creator, Destroyer and Preserver.&#xA;1&#xA;2&#xA;Varaha rescues the earth&#xA;For eight thousand yugas - a day and night of the Creator Brahma - Surya the sun belched fire, burning the hills and forests to ashes. There was no rain, so the holy sages left the earth and sought refuge in the heavens. Then Vayu the wind blew with all his might for many years till huge clouds were formed, which rained incessantly and caused a great flood. The Earth sank into Patalaloka, the nether world, where she remained for a thousand yugas, a part of the night of Brahma. It was the pralaya, the primeval flood, which submerged the entire earth under water.&#xA;On that huge sheet of water, Vishnu lay on a ficus leaf as the eternal child, Vatapatrashayi. Seeing the plight of Mother Earth at the bottom of the waters, he assumed the frightening form of Shweta Varaha, the White Boar, and descended into the nether world to search for her. The evil demon Hiranyaksha attacked him, and they fought a long and violent battle, at the end of which Varaha destroyed the demon with his mighty tusks. He then lifted up Mother Earth on his tusks and emerged from the waters. Placing a foot on the divine snake Adishesha, with Mother Earth on his tusks, he dazzled the whole world with his majestic appearance. The holy sages recited the hymns from the ancient books of wisdom and knowledge, the Vedas, and requested Varaha to bring Mother Earth back to her original glory.&#xA;Varaha then re-established Mother Earth, delineated the limits of the seven seas (sapta sagaras) and the seven continents (sapta lokas), and requested Brahma to re-create life on earth. To protect his devotees, he decided to live on earth and asked Garuda, his vehicle, the man- eagle, to bring the divine hill Kridachala from Vaikuntha, his heavenly abode, to establish his new home on earth.&#xA;Varaha selected a location which was sixty yojanas (960 kilometres) south of the river Gomati, five yojanas (80 kilometres) west of the eastern sea (Bay of Bengal) and adjoining the Swarnamukhi river. Here Garuda brought Kridachala, a sacred hill three yojanas (48 kilometres) wide and thirty yojanas (480 kilometres) long. As its shape resembled Sesha, Lord Narayana&amp;rsquo;s&#xA;thousand-hooded snake, it was called Seshadri. It was heaven on earth, with flowering plants and fruit-bearing trees, with peaks of gold and precious stones, where birds sang and kinnaras (celestial musicians) sang and danced, a veritable paradise.&#xA;Varaha occupied a temple on the western side of the sacred pool, the Swami Pushkarni. But his appearance with the tusks and weapons was so frightening, that Brahma, the Gods, the Saptarishis (seven sages) and other celestials prayed to Vishnu, requesting him to assume a more peaceful form and live on the hill to protect his people.&#xA;Thereafter, the supreme, lotus-eyed Vishnu, holding the shankha (conch), chakra (discus) and gada (mace), descended to the Seshadri hill. With Bhudevi (Mother Earth) and Lakshmi (the Goddess of Prosperity), two aspects of the Supreme Mother Goddess, by his side, he settled under the divya vimana (dome) to grant the prayers of the people.&#xA;Brahma promised the gods and the sages that Varaha would stay on Seshadri hill till the end of the Shweta&#xA;Varaha kalpa (the present age), as it was as wonderful as heaven or Vaikuntha.&#xA;www&#xA;3&#xA;4&#xA;Vishnu as Balaji, the child floating on the waters of the great flood; calendar painting&#xA;Thus goes the narration in the Venkatachala Mahatmyam of the Varaha Purana by sage Suta, when requested by Saunaka and others to enlighten them on the places sacred to Lord Vishnu.&#xA;Vishnu of the Tirumala or Venkatadri hills is known as Venkatesha or Venkateshwara (Lord of Venkata), the destroyer of sins and the giver of prosperity.&#xA;Another name by which he is revered is Srinivasa, in whom the Goddess of Prosperity, Sri or Lakshmi, dwells.&#xA;In the north of India he is known as Balaji because when the world was immersed under the waters, Vishnu, as a newborn child, floated on a leaf on the waters. He is Narayana, the Creator, Destroyer and the Refuge. Another meaning for Balaji is Universal Mother.&#xA;He is addressed as Perumal (the Great Lord), Malaiyappa (Lord of the hill) and Govinda (a name of Lord Krishna) by his devotees as they inch forward through the temple, calling out to the holy image of their Lord.&#xA;Venkateshwara with Sridevi and Bhudevi - bronze utsava murtis.&#xA;The Pilgrimage&#xA;The Tirumala hill forms the southern end of the Eastern Ghats. It rises to a maximum height of 1104 metres above sea level and consists of seven peaks or ridges, whence the name Saptagiri or seven hills. It covers an area of about 250 square kilometres and resembles a massive serpent or dragon, giving it the name Seshadri or the hill of the snake. The head of the serpent is Tirumala, the body is Ahobilam to the north and the tail is Srisailam, even further north.&#xA;The temple is approached from the town of Tirupati by a ghat road. Once upon a time, the only way to reach the temple was by a footpath eleven kilometers long, crossing thick jungles and the seven peaks. It is a charming and breath-taking walk through a thickly forested hill, commencing at the entrance tower or Alipiri (Adipadi or steps). The difficult sections are at the beginning, from Alipiri to the Gali Gopuram, and at the end, near the top, known as the &amp;ldquo;knee breaker&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;The nearest railhead, bus terminus or airport, to reach the temple, are at Tirupati, the town at the foot of the hills, in the southern Indian state of Andhra Pradesh. From Tirupati there are regular bus and taxi services, managed by the Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanam, to go up the hill. The temple can either be approached by road - there are two separate roads for uphill and downhill traffic - or by foot along the lovely eleven kilometer-long footpath with canopied steps traversing the hills. Walking up the hills is more difficult but confers great merit, for the hill is nearly as sacred as the temple.&#xA;Accommodation of all varieties is provided by the Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanam, from free to low-cost to air-conditioned and expensive rooms and cottages. Free meals are also provided to all who desire it. It is a miracle how well organized the arrangements are, considering&#xA;The Tirumala hill&#xA;A view of the hill from the beginning of the footpath at the Alipiri tower&#xA;5&#xA;6&#xA;Padmavati Devi, Tiruchanur&#xA;the millions of pilgrims who visit Tirumala every day. In spite of the crowds, the hilltop is kept scrupulously clean.&#xA;No visit to Tirumala is complete without a visit to the temple of Padmavati, the consort of Venkateshwara, at Tiruchanur, formerly known as Tiruchokinur or Tiruchukanur. The story of their divine union is deeply entwined with the story of the hills.&#xA;Pilgrims flock in millions to the temple of Venkateshwara in the Tirumala or Venkatadri hills, above the town of Tirupati, to be rid of their sins and to be blessed with prosperity. He is probably the most popular God of contemporary Hinduism and is credited with innumerable miracles and immense spiritual power.&#xA;A sizeable number of his devotees are Muslims,&#xA;for a former Nawab of Gandikota in Cuddapah district, Andhra Pradesh, was an ardent devotee of Lord Venkateshwara. His daughter refused to marry, and died dreaming of her beloved Lord Balaji who, she believed, would marry her after her death. Between 5 and 10 percent of the devotees are Muslims.&#xA;This is the story of how Vishnu came to reside on Venkatadri hill, to look after his devotees and to save good from evil during Kali yuga, the age we live in.&#xA;Legends of Venkatesha&#xA;There are many stories associating Vishnu with the Tirumala or Venkatadri hills.&#xA;Vishnu comes to Venkatadri hill&#xA;—&#xA;Krita,&#xA;According to the Bhavishyottara Purana, Vishnu remained on Venkatadri for the first three yugas Treta and Dvapara. At the beginning of the present yuga -the Kali yuga he decided to leave for Vaikuntha, his heaven, with his spouse Sri or Lakshmi, the Goddess of Prosperity.&#xA;Learning of this, sage Narada went to Brahma who, also, felt that while Vishnu remained on earth people were pious and meritorious. Accordingly, he raised a tamarind tree on Venkatadri hill, beneath which he formed an anthill. Narada was instructed to bring Vishnu back to Venkatadri, to reside in the anthill.&#xA;Narada went to the banks of the river Ganga where the rishis or sacred sages were performing rituals. He asked them to whom they would dedicate the fruits of their prayers. The rishis discussed the matter, but could not arrive at any decision.&#xA;Chapter 2&#xA;7&#xA;8&#xA;Lakshmi, Kolhapur temple, Maharashtra.&#xA;Bhrigu rishi first went to Satyaloka. Here he met Brahma. Bhrigu behaved rudely and was ignored. Angered, he went to Kailasa, where Shiva was in the company of his consort Parvati. Disapproving, Bhrigu left for Vaikuntha where he saw Vishnu reclining on the serpent Adishesha, with Lakshmi by his side. Bhrigu went up to Vishnu and kicked him on the right chest, the abode of Lakshmi. Vishnu got up, bowed to the rishi, washed the latter&amp;rsquo;s hands and feet and pressed them. He apologized for his inactivity and gratified Bhrigu so much that Bhrigu returned to the banks of the river Ganga and informed the other rishis that they should pray to Vishnu for salvation.&#xA;Meanwhile Lakshmi was very angry that Vishnu had pacified and apologized to the rishi who had kicked her abode on his chest. She would no longer live on his chest but go to Karaveera Kshetram (Kolhapur in Maharashtra) where she would henceforth reside.&#xA;The unhappy Vishnu then left Vaikuntha to return to Venkatadri, where he lived incognito in the anthill. During this period, Dvapara yuga came to an end and Kali yuga began.&#xA;Lakshmi knew that Vishnu was living in an anthill on Venkatachala. She took the appearance of a milkmaid and Brahma and Shiva that of a cow and calf respectively. She sold them to the Chola queen who ruled over the Venkatachala region, knowing that the cow would take care of her Lord.&#xA;Every day, the cow and calf accompanied the Chola king&amp;rsquo;s head of two thousand cattle to graze on the hillside. But unknown and unnoticed by the others, she would go up the hill and empty her milk on the anthill, over Vishnu. Noticing the lack of milk, the cowherd followed the cow up the hill and observed it emptying its milk over the anthill. Furious, he threw his stick at the cow, but Vishnu took the blow and saved the cow. Amazed at the phenomenon, the cowherd fell dead.&#xA;The Chola king went to Venkatachala to investigate, and was cursed by Vishnu to become a demon to expiate his servant&amp;rsquo;s sin. The king prayed for mercy, so Vishnu relented and informed him that he would have&#xA;to suffer the curse till he was reborn as Akasha Raja, and would gain merit when his daughter&#xA;Padmavati married Venkatesha.&#xA;As Vishnu searched the hill for the herbs recommended by Brihaspati to cure his head-wound, he came across Varaha, his own incarnation. As he narrated the story of his return to Venkatadri, Varaha told him that he had hunted out and defeated the demon Vrishabhasura. He was very happy to see Vishnu back at Venkatadri.&#xA;uummmmnu&#xA;ዘጠ&#xA;לגנובן ענק:&#xA;Thereafter, Vishnu requested him for some place to live in till the end of Kali yuga. Varaha said that if Vishnu paid the price, he would measure out some land.&#xA;Vishnu replied that if Lakshmi, the Goddess of Wealth, was still living with him, he would have been affluent enough to pay the price, but since she had left and gone to Kolhapur, how could he earn the money? Since Varaha had rescued the earth from Patalaloka, he could mark out a space where the Lord would live. In return, Varaha would receive the first prayer and offering of food from Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s devotees.&#xA;Varaha agreed and assigned a plot for Vishnu, as well as Vakulamalika to serve him food mixed with honey and to apply medicine on his wound, which healed in response to her devotion. Vakulamalika was actually Yashoda, the mother of Krishna in a previous life, now reborn to take care of Vishnu as Venkateshwara on Venkatachala and to see him as a Kalyana murti (divine bridegroom) in the Kali yuga.&#xA;Vakulamalika&#xA;9Marriage of Venkatesha and Padmavati&#xA;10&#xA;After the Mahabharata war, the land of Thondaimandalam was ruled by Akasha Raja, whose capital was situated at Narayanapuram, near the Venkatachala hill range. As he was childless, he decided to perform a great sacrifice and, when the land was ploughed for the sacrifice, a thousand-petalled lotus containing a baby was discovered. She was an incarnation of Goddess Lakshmi and was named Padmavati, as she was born in a lotus.&#xA;The baby grew up into a beautiful young girl. One day, sage Narada appeared in court, read her palm and predicted that she would be the bride of Vishnu. The same day, Venkateshwara was chasing a wild elephant in the Venkatachala forest, and followed it into the royal garden where he met Padmavati, who fell in love with him. He returned home and enlightened Vakulamalika about his past birth as Rama and Lakshmi&amp;rsquo;s as Sita, and how they would both be united in Kali yuga as Srinivasa and Padmavati.&#xA;Vakulamalika was keen on seeing Vishnu as a Kalyanamurti, and immediately offered to leave for Akasha Raja&amp;rsquo;s city, and arrange, the sacred marriage alliance.&#xA;Crossing the river Swarnamukhi, she reached the Shiva temple where she learned of Padmavati&amp;rsquo;s encounter with a handsome young man. Vakulamalika requested for an audience with Padmavati&amp;rsquo;s mother, Dharunidevi. Meanwhile, Venkateshwara disguised himself as a female Pulinda astrologer and entered the city, announcing her sooth-saying abilities. The astrologer then informed queen Dharunidevi that Padmavati, her daughter, had fallen in love with a handsome young man who was Srinivasa, the Lord of Venkatachala. She should be married to him immediately, or would collapse in three days. Also, as&#xA;proof, an old woman would soon arrive to discuss the marriage, he told the queen, and left.&#xA;As predicted, Vakulamalika soon approached the queen for the hand of Padmavati for Srinivasa. Dharunidevi. discussed the subject with the king and the royal couple announced their approval. Sages Brihaspati and Shuka fixed up the auspicious time for the wedding and predicted auspiciousness and happiness for the young couple and the world through this marriage.&#xA;All the gods and the sages arrived at Venkatachala to witness the marriage. Vishwakarma, the divine architect, constructed a beautiful city on the hill and Lord Indra a beautiful mandapa (pavilion) for the wedding ceremony.&#xA;As the Goddess Lakshmi had left him, Venkatesha had no money to perform his wedding. So Venkatesha took a loan from Kubera, the God of Wealth, promising to repay him within a thousand years. To help him repay his dues, pilgrims still shower him with money. By helping their Lord, the devotees believe that their Lord will help them in return.&#xA;Invitations to the wedding were sent to all the inhabitants of the fourteen worlds, the Gods, Goddesses and the celestial beings. It was to be a grand affair, and all the celestials, accompanied by the apsaras, gandharvas and kinnaras descended on earth to perform the wedding of Venkatesha and Padmavati.&#xA;11&#xA;20&#xA;12&#xA;Then, riding his eagle-vehicle Garuda, Venkatesha set out in a glorious procession to Narayanapuram, accompanied by Lord Shiva on his bull and the other deities on their vehicles, preceded by the divine dancers and musicians, the Gandharvas and Apsaras, and followed by musical bands, while sages and seers recited the Vedas. As they passed the hermitage of Sukha Maharishi, the sage sang in wonder at the fantastic procession. He invited Venkatesha to come in and accept his offering of food. In return, the sage was asked how he expected to feed the vast procession. The sage replied that if he could satisfy the Lord, everyone else would automatically be satisfied. Pleased by the sage&amp;rsquo;s devotion, Venkatesha entered the hermitage and accepted his offering of fruits. And all the processionists had a strange feeling of having had a good feast, without having eaten a single morsel of food.&#xA;They soon arrived at Narayanapuram where they were received by King Akasha Raja with music, flowers and sandalwood paste. Riding an elephant, Venkatesha entered the marriage hall where the wedding was performed according to Vedic rites by the sages Vashishtha and Brihaspati. Then, to the chanting of Vedic hymns by the sages and the singing of auspicious songs by the women, Srinivasa tied the mangala sutra around the neck of Padmavati, and the celestials rained flowers on the holy couple.&#xA;Later, Lakshmi, the consort of Vishnu, also joined Venkatesha on the hill. The Lord told her of his debt, to be paid with interest, to Kubera. To help him, she should enrich his devotees who would give him contributions of money and wealth. This would help him redeem his debt. Lakshmi agreed, and returned to live in his heart, whence his name Srinivasa, or the dwelling place of Sri or Lakshmi.&#xA;1000&#xA;That is why pilgrims offer money and precious jewels to Srinivasa, to help him pay off his debt to Kubera and, in return, earn great merit.&#xA;The Temple for Venkateshwara&#xA;After the death of Akasha Raja, his brother Thondaimaan and son Vasudasa battled each other for the succession. On the request of Padmavati, Srinivasa intervened and divided the kingdom into two regions, leaving thirty two villages for Padmavati, who was Akasha Raja&amp;rsquo;s daughter. But Srinivasa and Padmavati continued to live in sage Agastya&amp;rsquo;s hermitage.&#xA;One day, Thondaimaan came to Srinivasa and told him of his desire to see the Lord frequently. Srinivasa then suggested the construction of a shrine on the hill, on the place allotted to him by Varaha on the banks of a beautiful lake. Being an ardent devotee, Thondaimaan built a temple with a tower, prakaras, cattle sheds, storage space and more, added a foot path through the seven peaks and renovated the flower well (Pushkarini). The entire hill became a reconstruction of Vaikuntha, Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s heaven. Consecrated with Vedic hymns by the Gods and the sages, the temple tower was named Ananda Nilayam, the abode of happiness.&#xA;Venkatesha with Sridevi and Bhudevi - bronze kalyana murtis.&#xA;00:00&#xA;13&#xA;14&#xA;The Annual Festival of Tirumala&#xA;During the celebrations, Brahma took a promise from Srinivasa, that he would redeem the sins of all the pilgrims who came to the temple. Srinivasa agreed, and the Seshadri hills were renamed as Venkata (Vem = dire sins, kata = power of immunity). Srinivasa came to be known as Venkateshwara or Venkatesha, Lord of the Venkata hills.&#xA;Brahma lit two lamps with the instructions that they should burn continuously and that Srinivasa should live on the Venkata hills, granting boons to his devotees who came there. And to this, too, did Srinivasa agree.&#xA;Brahma then decided to arrange a grand celebration. He called Vishwakarma and ordered the preparation of chariots, vehicles, temple umbrellas and diamond ornaments, and gave Thondaimaan the work of making all other arrangements. All the kings of India were invited to this grand celebration.&#xA;The celebration began on the first day of the New Moon, in the month of Bhadrapada (Tamil Purattaasi) and went on for ten days. People came from every part of the country to witness it. They desired that it should be repeated every year. Thus it became an annual festival — the Brahmotsavam, the festival of Brahma.&#xA;After the celebration, Brahma returned to heaven, having fulfilled his mission of leaving Vishnu on the Venkata hills for the duration of Kali yuga.&#xA;800&#xA;007&#xA;1177427&#xA;161111&#xA;300&#xA;ood&#xA;Srinivasa turns into stone&#xA;With the progress of Kali yuga, the world was plunged into chaos and evil. Lord Srinivasa announced that with the chaotic rule of the human race in Kali yuga, he no longer wished to talk directly to the unworthy. He would become a stone statue and communicate only with his dear devotees.&#xA;Saying this, he transferred himself into a statue, now the stone icon of Venkateshwara, on Tirumala hill.&#xA;Once Srinivasa was no longer available to him, Thondaimaan lost interest in ruling. He handed over his kingdom to his son and left for Venkatadri. There he chanted the thousand names (sahasranaama) of the Lord with offerings of tulasi (sacred basil) leaves till he attained moksha or final liberation.&#xA;Miracles of Venkateshwara&#xA;Venkateshwara is credited with countless miracles performed to save and redeem his devotees.&#xA;Vasu, a great devotee of the Lord, was a tribal hunter. One day he went to the forest to collect honey to mix with the food he wanted to offer the Lord. Meanwhile, his only child, a twelve year old boy named Suveera, offered the food to Venkatesha and then ate it. When Vasu heard of this on his return, he was furious and wanted to kill his child. But Venkatesha appeared and stayed his hand, saying that Suveera too was his devotee, and he had happily accepted the offering without the honey.&#xA;CONS&#xA;15&#xA;A pious lady prayed to Venkatesha to save her sick husband&amp;rsquo;s life, in return for which she would gift her mangal sutra (thaali), her wedding symbol which&#xA;she wore around her neck, into the hundi (collection box). When the husband became well, she decided,&#xA;instead, to buy another mangal sutra as her offering, and dropped it in the Lord&amp;rsquo;s hundi. But when she came out of the temple, the thaali around her neck was missing. Venkateshwara, who had saved her husband&amp;rsquo;s life, had redeemed her pledge.&#xA;16&#xA;Hathiram Bhava was a Bengali devotee who came to the hill to worship Venkatesha. He built an ashram where he lived alone, and was known as Sevadasji. As his mode of worship was mystical and different, he was avoided by the others. So the Lord visited him every night and they would play a game of chess together. One night the Lord left his pearl necklace in the house of Sevadas. When Sevadas took it to the temple in the morning, his story was not believed, and he was imprisoned for theft. Sevadas prayed to the Lord to prove his innocence. At midnight, a white elephant entered the prison cell. The terrified jailers ran and brought the temple authorities. When they opened the prison doors, the elephant vanished before their eyes, leaving them dumbfounded. Sevadas ran to the temple shouting &amp;ldquo;Hathiram&amp;rdquo; (hathi-elephant). His innocence was established and he came to be known as Hathiram Mahant.&#xA;A poor man had nothing to offer the Lord except the two rupees left in his pocket. He put that in the hundi, and came home to find that he had won a gold ring in a chit fund.&#xA;The stories of Venkatesha&amp;rsquo;s miracles are endless and a few appear in some of the following chapters. Venkateshwara is the fountainhead of compassion, and the true devotee is never denied his Lord&amp;rsquo;s grace.&#xA;The Sacred Hill&#xA;Chapter 3&#xA;The Tirumala hill is believed to be Kridadri or Kridachala, as sacred as Vaikuntha, Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s heaven, having once been situated in heaven. Known by different names in the different yugas, it was called Vrishabhadri or&#xA;Vrishabhachala in Krita yuga, Anjanadri or Anjanachala in Treta yuga, Seshadri or Seshachala in Dvapara yuga and Venkatadri or Venkatachala in Kali yuga. The stories of the hill establish its sanctity in every age. The word Tirumala itself means sacred hill: Tiru (pronounced thiru) = Shri, meaning sacred, and mala (Telugu, pronounced malaa), or malai (Tamil) means hill. Achala and adri are suffixes meaning hill.&#xA;Vrishabhadri: During the Krita yuga, a wicked asura named Vrishabhasura captured the Kridadri hill where he performed a terrible penance for five thousand years, frightening the holy men living there. Every day he would cut off his head and offer it along with a flower to Lord Narasimha, while his head would grow back again.&#xA;Finally, Narayana appeared before him and asked him what he wanted. Vrishabhasura replied that he wanted no boon but wished to fight with the God. Thus began a terrible battle between the two till Narayana wielded his Sudarshana chakra, the mighty discus. Vrishabhasura believed that since those who were killed by the Lord&amp;rsquo;s discus always attained final moksha or liberation, he too would now achieve it. He requested that the hill be named Vrishabhadri, a boon which Vishnu granted for the Krita yuga.&#xA;The sacred hill of Tirumala. Early 20th century photograph&#xA;17&#xA;18&#xA;Seshadri : Once Vayu, the God of the Wind, went to Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s heaven Vaikuntha. As Vishnu was resting with his consort Lakshmi, Adishesha, the divine serpent, was guarding the doorway and refused him entry. The two began to quarrel, till Narayana came out and heard each boasting of his strength and prowess. The Lord suggested a way for them to determine who was more powerful : Adishesha should circle the Ananda mountain and Vayu should try to blow and dislodge him. Several days and nights of furious combat passed by, with neither winning nor yielding, while all the worlds trembled. Finally Brahma and the other Gods told Adishesha that Vishnu and Shiva knew of his strength, so he could loosen his hold and allow Vayu to win. So the serpent loosened his hold and was immediately blown away, with the hill, to the region north of the Swarnamukhi river. As he was very dejected, Brahma assured him that he would be merged with the Venkata hill and Vishnu would reside on him. Then Adishesha fell at Lord Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s feet and was blessed to become the Seshadri range, by which name it was known in the Dvapara yuga. His hood is located at Venkatadri, his body at Ahobalam where Vishnu lived as Narasimha, and his tail at Srisailam where Vishnu was manifested as Mallikarjuna.&#xA;M&#xA;R&#xA;Anjanadri Anjanadevi, the wife of tribal chief Kesari who lived on the banks of the Pampa river near Hampi, had no children and consulted Rishi Matanga on what she should do to conceive. He advised her to go to the Akasha Ganga stream on the Venkatachala hill and meditate for twelve years, after which she would conceive a son. She lived on water for the first year and on a sweet fruit given to her by Vayu, the God of the Wind, each day for the next twelve years, till she gave birth to a son named Anjaneya (later known as Hanuman), who helped Lord Rama and the Gods.&#xA;In honour of Anjanadevi&amp;rsquo;s penance, the hill was named Anjanadri in the Treta yuga.&#xA;When Rama was on his way to Lanka, he was invited to the hill by Anjana, mother of Hanuman. As he and his monkey army bathed here before proceeding to Lanka, their victory over Ravana is attributed to the sacred Anjanadri hill, according to the Vayu Purana.&#xA;1920&#xA;D&#xA;رده&#xA;Venkatadri : Brahma took a promise from Vishnu that he would redeem the sins of all the pilgrims who came up the hills to the temple. Vishnu agreed, and the Seshadri hills were renamed as Venkata (Vem = dire sins, kata = power of immunity) in the Kali yuga.&#xA;The story goes that Madhava, the son of a learned Brahmin named Purandara Somaiyaji, was infatuated by another woman. He abandoned his parents, wife and child and went to live with her till her death twelve years later. Meanwhile, he contracted leprosy and wandered around as a mendicant till, one day, he met a group&#xA;of pilgrims who were singing in praise of the Lord as they walked on a pilgrimage to Tirumala. Madhava followed them up the hills till he stood in front of the image of Venkateshwara. He realized the enormity of his sin of abandoning his parents, wife and child. Suddenly his body was consumed by flames, the leprosy left him and his body became beautiful once more. So the hill came to be known as Venkatadri, the hill which destroys all sins.&#xA;Other names of the hill are&#xA;Vaikunthadri, for it was brought from Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s heaven, Vaikuntha;&#xA;Simhachala, because it was here that Vishnu took his Narasimha form for killing the demon Hiranyakashipu;&#xA;Varahadri, as it was the home of Varaha;&#xA;Srisaila, for it was the home of Goddess Sri (Lakshmi);&#xA;Anandadri or Kridadri, for it was the site of Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s divine sport;&#xA;Pushkaradri, where the red lotus grew in plenty on the hill;&#xA;Gnanadri, for it confers knowledge on the devotee;&#xA;Chintamani, since it grants the object of one&amp;rsquo;s desire;&#xA;Teerthadri, after the many sacred watering spots which are situated here;&#xA;Dharmadri, for Dharmadeva, the God of Righteousness who performed penance on the hill;&#xA;Kanakadri, where gold and precious stones were once found;&#xA;Narayanadri, after a Brahmin named Narayana who did severe penance on the hill and was granted his desire to have the hill named after him;&#xA;Nilagiri, for the Vanara chief Nila who once lived here;&#xA;Srinivasagiri, where the Lord Vishnu once lived as Srinivasa and married Padmavati;&#xA;Garudadri, since it was brought from Vaikuntha by Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s vehicle Garuda.&#xA;The Sacred Tank and Holy Waters&#xA;Tirumala hill is a vast area dotted with peaks from which rise lakes and waterfalls. Of these, 108 are believed to be sacred and associated with various epic characters and miracles of Lord Venkatesha.&#xA;Swami Pushkarini: The Swami Pushkarini was Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s tank in Vaikuntha, and was brought to the earth by Garuda for Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s use. It is the sacred tank in front of the temple of Tirumala, even regarded as equivalent to the Ganga and other sacred rivers. A dip in the tank cleanses the bather of all sins. The performance of the daily rites or even occasional rites on the banks of the Swami Pushkarini is said to cure deformities of the body and ensure the avoidance of all types of hell. It grants the wishes of those who bathe in it. Like the hill, all the tanks and lakes of Tirumala are sacred and known as &amp;ldquo;teerthas&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;There are seventeen teerthas (holy waters) whose waters are believed to combine in the Swami Pushkarini.&#xA;Chapter 4&#xA;Swami Pushkarini,&#xA;the sacred tank of Tirumala&#xA;21&#xA;22&#xA;According to the Bhavishya Purana, King Shankhana, a scion of the lunar race, lost his kingdom to Samantha Raja. He therefore left his kingdom and went with his family on a pilgrimage to Sethu in the south and on his return, reached the Swarnamukhi river. He was feeling very sad at having lost his kingdom when a voice directed him to go to Venkatachala, where the Lord is like Kamadhenu, the celestial cow which satisfies all wishes, the Chintamani, the divine stone which grants all prayers and Suradruma, the wish-granting tree. The king was instructed to build his hermitage on the banks of the tank and worship the Lord. The king did as instructed, till one day Lord Vishnu, holding the conch, discus and mace, and flanked by Sridevi and Bhudevi, arose from the Swami Pushkarini on a divine air vehicle. Shankhana praised the Lord and bemoaned the loss of his kingdom. Vishnu blessed him and assured him that whoever bathed in the Swami Pushkarini would get his heart&amp;rsquo;s desire. Shankhana was very happy and started his return journey home. Meanwhile, Shankhana&amp;rsquo;s enemies had been fighting among themselves. The people rose in revolt and threw them out and had set out in search of Shankhana. They met him near the Godavari river and requested him to return and assume his throne. Thus his penance on the banks of the Swami Pushkarini regained King Shankhana his kingdom.&#xA;It is believed that the Swami Pushkarini rewards those who bathe in its waters by granting their heart&amp;rsquo;s desire.&#xA;Vajra kavacha, a jewelled covering presented by King Krishnadevaraya&#xA;23&#xA;24&#xA;Coronation of Rama.&#xA;Kalamkari painting from Kalahasti&#xA;Another story from the Vamana Purana associates Markandeya with this tank. The Rishi Markandeya did severe penance to Lord Brahma who appeared before him. Markandeya asked to be blessed with the opportunity to visit all the sacred teerthas. Brahma replied that it would take a very long time and even Rudra could not undertake and finish such a pilgrimage. However, he added that the reward for bathing in all the holy waters could be obtained from a dip in the Swami Pushkarini on&#xA;when the one day in the year- the Mukkoti day waters from all the sacred teerthas merged with the tank. Markandeya did so, and was rewarded accordingly. Other visitors to the Swami Pushkarini were Indra, Chandra, Kubera and the other gods.&#xA;―&#xA;Bathing in the Swami Pushkarini is therefore considered to be equivalent to bathing in all the sacred waters.&#xA;Rama, son of Dasharatha and an earlier incarnation of Vishnu, visited the hill at the request of Anjana, mother of Hanuman. He and his army, consisting of his brother Lakshmana, his devotee Hanuman, the monkey king Sugriva and the monkey army bathed here, before continuing on their journey to Lanka. They fought and vanquished Ravana, king of Lanka, and his army and Rama returned in triumph to Ayodhya where he was crowned king. The Varaha Purana attributes their success to the bath in the Swami Pushkarini, as it grants success to all those who bathe in it.&#xA;25&#xA;25&#xA;The Rishi Narayana, after whom the hill was named Narayanadri, bathed regularly in the tank and meditated on its banks.&#xA;The Skanda Purana narrates the story of Dharmagupta, the son of king Nanda. One day, Dharmagupta went out on a hunting expedition when it became dark. He decided. to stay in the forest when he was chased up a tree by a lion. There he found a boar who had also taken refuge. Dharmagupta and the boar decided that each would stay awake half the night while the other slept. The boar was on the first shift and, as the king slept, did not yield to the lion&amp;rsquo;s entreaties to throw down the sleeping man. Then it was the king&amp;rsquo;s turn to stay awake. As the boar slept and the lion cajoled, the untrustworthy king decided to push down the boar as the lion&amp;rsquo;s prey. But the boar woke up in time, assumed the form of a sage and saved himself by holding on to a branch. Dharmagupta was cursed to become a lunatic. When his retinue saw him, they rushed to king Nanda who took him to Rishi Jaimini for advice and help. The sage, whose divining powers made it possible for him to find out what had happened, advised the king to take his son to the Venkatachala hill and make him bathe in the Swami Pushkarini to rid himself of his sin. The king did so, and Dharmagupta was cured. He returned to rule his kingdom wisely and well.&#xA;1)&#xA;B&#xA;Kapila teertha and waterfall at the foot of the hill&#xA;26&#xA;Similarly, the Rishi Kashyapa, who was an expert in curing snake bites, was persuaded by the snake king Takshaka to go back to his village, as a result of which Takshaka bit king Parikshit, who immediately died. He went to his guru, Sakalya Maharishi, who advised him to go to Venkatadri, bathe in the Swami Pushkarini and then worship the Lord. Kashyapa did so, and was absolved of his sins.&#xA;The river Saraswati prayed long and hard and, when Vishnu appeared before her, said she wished to be regarded as the most sacred. He told her that while it was not possible for her to be more sacred than the Ganga, she (Saraswati) would reside beside his temple on his hill at Venkatadri in the Swami Pushkarini. Once a year, all the sacred waters, including the Ganga, merge with the Swami Pushkarini to wash off their sins.&#xA;The sacred Mukkoti or parva day of the Swami Pushkarini tank takes place on dvadashi (the twelfth day of the waxing moon) in the month of Dhanur (December-January) when Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s chakra or discus is taken in procession and immersed in the Swami Pushkarini, when all the Gods bathe in the tank. A bath at the same time, it is believed, washes away all sins.&#xA;—&#xA;There are seventeen sacred lakes - teerthas whose holy waters mingle with the Swami Pushkarini. They are&#xA;Kapila teertha, a sacred pool in front of which sage Kapila worshipped the Linga;&#xA;Shakra or Vajra teertha, situated on the hill above the Kapila teertha, where the God Indra (Shakra) was released from the curse of Gautama Rishi;&#xA;Vishvaksena saras, where Vishvaksena, the son of Varuna, meditated and became the commander of the divine forces;&#xA;Agnikunda teertha, situated above the Panchaayudha teertha, which is inaccessible;&#xA;Brahma teertha, that which cleanses great sins&#xA;(even those such as murder);&#xA;Panchaayudha teerthas, five pools named after the five weapons of Vishnu : shankha (conch), chakra (discus), gada (mace), sharanga (bow) and khadga (sword);&#xA;Saptarishi teertha, seven water sources named after the seven rishis or sages Kashyapa, Atri, Bharadwaja, Vishwamitra, Gautama, Vashishtha and Jamadagni.&#xA;The seventeen teerthas are put into seven groups, each possessing greater merit than the other. A pilgrimage to the sacred teerthas on Venkatadri is equivalent to visiting all the other holy waters. Apart from these, there are many other teerthas on Venkatachala, such as&#xA;Akashaganga teertha : Situated to the north of the temple, this is the site where Anjanadevi performed penance for twelve years and Hanuman was born. Every day silver potfulls of water from this teertha are brought by one of the seven families of Acharyas, for the daily ceremonial bath (Abhishekha) of the Lord.&#xA;Vaikuntha teertha: Situated in a cave to the&#xA;north-east of the temple, a few members of Rama&amp;rsquo;s monkey army saw Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s Vaikuntha inside the cave, hence the name.&#xA;Sanaka-Sanandhana teertha: Once the home of saints and yogis, it is believed that a dip in this lake will confer yogic powers. A bath in the month of Maargali or Dhanur (December-January) will liberate a person from earthly bondage.&#xA;Jabali teertha: This was the site of the hermitage, first of Jabali Rishi and his disciples and, later, of Agastya Rishi and his disciples, and is located two miles to the north of the temple. It is believed to have miraculous powers to relieve bodies possessed of spirits and ghosts.&#xA;Pandava teertha: Situated a mile away from the temple, to the north east, it is named after the five Pandava brothers who lived on the Venkatachala hill for a year. At the end of the year, Yudhhishthira dreamed that as they had lived here for a year, they were now absolved of their sins, and would be victorious in the war to regain their kingdom from the Kauravas. Thereafter, the Pandavas left for Hastinapura, and the teertha was named after them.&#xA;Papavinasha teertha: A low waterfall three miles from the temple, a bath in its holy water on the seventh or twelfth day of the waxing moon in the month of Ashada (July-August) will wipe out the sins of previous births.&#xA;Papavinasha teertha and waterfall&#xA;27&#xA;28&#xA;Chakra teertha : To rid the world of the demons&#xA;—&#xA;who were a menace to life, a devotee named Padmanabha meditated on Lord Venkatesha for twelve long years at this teertha, till the Lord sent his chakra Sudarshana to destroy the demons. Images of Lakshmi Narasimha and Sudarshana chakra are installed here. On the twelfth day of the waning moon in the month of Kartika, an offering of payasam (sweetened milk and rice pudding) is offered to the images from the main temple, and then distributed to those who bathed in the teertha.&#xA;Kumara teertha: An elderly Brahmin lived alone on the hill, meditating on Lord Venkatesha. One day, when he had lost his way, a young boy appeared before him, led him to a lake and asked him to take a dip in the lake. The old man did so, and was transformed into a sixteen year old youth. The young boy revealed himself to be Lord Balaji, blessed the old man and disappeared. From then on, the lake was known as Kumara (youth).&#xA;Kumaradhara teertha: In order to absolve himself of the sin of Brahmahatya (killing a Brahmin) when he killed the wicked Tarakasura, Kumara or Kartikeya performed penance at this teertha which was named after him. According to another story, a blind old man with a decrepit body was told by Lord Venkatesha to bathe here. On doing so, he became a youth&#xA;of sixteen years. In honour of this miracle, the teertha was named Kumaradhara.&#xA;Rasayana, Valighna and Jarahara teerthas are three teerthas not visible to the human eye.&#xA;Thotti teertha Situated in the sanctum sanctorum, the sandal and saffron-mixed abhishekha waters used for the ritual ceremonial bath of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s image are collected on Fridays in this teertha. Drinking these waters will destroy all sins.&#xA;Kayarasayana teertha or ashthi saras: Also hidden from view, the waters of this teertha, if drunk, purify the body immediately. Thondaimaan had been entrusted by a Brahmin with the care of his pregnant wife when the latter went on a pilgrimage to Kashi. Unfortunately, the woman died. Venkateshwara instructed Thondaimaan to dip her corpse in this water. He did so, and she came back to life.&#xA;Ramakrishna teertha: Six miles to the north of the Venkatesha temple, a person named Krishna excavated this pool. Later, a rishi named Ramakrishna meditated here for centuries till an ant hill grew around him. To test his concentration, Indra sent down thunder, lightening and rains, but Ramakrishna did not budge. But the crest of the anthill broke, and Lord Venkatesha appeared before&#xA;20&#xA;})))))&#xA;)))))))&#xA;him, with the promise that whosoever bathed in the teertha on full moon day would be released of all sins.&#xA;Tumba, Tumburu kona: Gandharva Tumburu cursed his lazy wife to become a toad and live in this lake till rishi Agastya arrived at the teertha and described its merit to his students, after bathing in its waters. On hearing his words, she would regain her form. It happened thus, and she became a Gandharva again. The teertha is thus named after the Gandharva Tumburu.&#xA;Viraja teertha The divine Viraja river is supposed to flow under the feet of Lord Venkateshwara. The water is collected in a small tub at the entrance to the temple store room.&#xA;Deva teertha: Located in a thick forest to the north-west of the temple, a bath in this teertha on a Thursday combined with the constellation pushya or on a Monday combined with the constellation shravana will destroy all sins and confer longevity and happiness.&#xA;Phalguni teertha: Arundhati, wife of the Rishi Vasishtha, meditated on the banks of this lake till Goddess Lakshmi appeared and blessed her with immortality. A bath in this teertha on a full moon day in the month of Phalgun (March-April) will release the bather from the cycle of birth, death and rebirth.&#xA;2930&#xA;Vishnu resting on Ananta-Sesha, surrounded by his consort Lakshmi, the personifications of his weapons, and the Devas, 5th century A.D., Gupta; Deogarh, Madhya Pradesh.&#xA;Vishnu&#xA;Narayana&#xA;Balaji or Venkateshwara is a form of Vishnu, the Protector of popular Hinduism, who manifests himself on earth whenever Dharma righteous duty and good conduct — are in danger.&#xA;Shiva destroys evil and Brahma creates life, while Vishnu preserves all that is good. He is the Preserver, the sustenance of all life. Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva form the Trinity of popular Hinduism and, as Creator, Preserver and Destroyer, represent the cycle of birth, life and death.&#xA;Vishnu, the all-pervading, the Preserver&#xA;The earliest reference to Vishnu is in the Rig Veda, the most ancient and sacred Hindu text which is of divine origin, ageless and eternal. The name Vishnu means all-pervading and reflects his solar nature. He is called an Aditya, or solar deity, or even the sun itself. He is responsible for the solar year and the seasons.&#xA;Chapter 5&#xA;Vishnu, 8th century A.D., Pallava bronze; Thanjavur, Tamilnadu&#xA;Vishnu Trivikrama and his vehicle&#xA;Garuda, 8th century A.D.;&#xA;Rajavalochana Temple,&#xA;Madhya Pradesh&#xA;31&#xA;Vishnu, 8th century A.D.; Sultanpur, Uttar Pradesh.&#xA;Vishnu on Adishesha,&#xA;6th century A.D., Chalukya;&#xA;32 Badami, Mysore&#xA;chaturbhih saakam navatim cha naamabhishchakra na vrittam vyateera veevipat.&#xA;(He, like a rounded wheel, sets in motion his ninety racing steeds together with the four — Rig Veda, I. 155.6).&#xA;His three strides (trivikrama) through the earth, firmament and heaven represent the three stations of the morning, evening and midday sun.&#xA;idam vishnurvichakrame tredha nidadha padam samoolhamasya paamsure.&#xA;(Through all this world strode Vishnu; thrice his foot he planted. The whole was gathered in his footstep&amp;rsquo;s dust- Rig Veda, I. 22.17).&#xA;The dust raised by his steps envelop the world and is symbolic of the all-embracing sun&amp;rsquo;s rays. While the first two places where he keeps his foot - the rising and the setting sun are known to man, no mortal can discern the highest limit.&#xA;paromaatrayaatanvaa vrudhaan na tai mahitvamanvashnuvanti. ubha te vidam rajasi prithivyaa vishno deva tvam paramasya&#xA;vitse.&#xA;na te vishno jaayamaano na jaato deva mahimnah paramantamaap.&#xA;udastamnaa naakamrushpam bruhantam daaghartha praacheem kakubham prithivyaah.&#xA;(Men come not near your majesty who grows beyond all bound and measure with your body. Both your regions of the earth, O Vishnu, we know you, Lord, know the highest also. None who is born or being born, God Vishnu, has reached the utmost limit of your grandeur. The vast high vault of heaven you have supported, and fixed the eastern pinnacle securely - Rig Veda, VII. 99.1)&#xA;tadasyapriyamabhi paatho ashyaam naro yatra devayavo madanti.&#xA;urukramasya sa hi bandhuritthaa vishnoh pade parame madhva utsah&#xA;(May I attain to that his well-loved mansion where men devoted to the gods are happy. For there springs, close akin to the wide-strider, the well of nectar in Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s highest footstep — Rig Veda, I. 154.5)&#xA;This third step, or Vishnupada, is described by the Katha Upanishad as the goal of spiritual attainment of the human soul.&#xA;In the Rig Veda, Vishnu, the all-pervading sun, partners Indra, the god of thunder and rain, to fight Vritra, the demon of drought, who is finally killed by Indra. This is the story of the sun and rain wiping&#xA;out drought, an eternal Indian preoccupation, and ushering prosperity.&#xA;This aspect is reflected in the story of Balaji. The sun is the source of life and sustenance on earth and Vishnu as the all-pervading Aditya preserves life on earth.&#xA;The Rig Veda also refers to Vishnu as Girikshit and Girishtha, associating him with the mountains and hills. Again, Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s residence on the Venkatadri hills reflects this aspect.&#xA;Finally, Vishnu, in the Veda, is the protector of the sacrifice and, in this form, obtains the earth, the aerial expanse and the sky for the sacrificer. Venkatesha is the beneficial, the giver of boons who is worshipped by his devotees for his munificence.&#xA;The Rig Vedic descriptions of Vishnu are important in that they are manifested in various forms in the later incarnations of Vishnu. All the incarnations are of solar lineage. His all-pervading nature makes him manifest himself everywhere, in every age. He is the giver of boons and prosperity, the munificent god, the destroyer of famine, whose home is the life-giving waters themselves. He is the destroyer of evil, who manifests himself on earth whenever Dharma, or the divinely-ordained righteous order, is threatened, and who has taken several incarnations to save the earth and righteousness. He is the final refuge of all human beings.&#xA;The images of Vishnu are generally four-armed, holding the conch, discus, mace and lotus, although they may also be two, eight or sixteen-armed, holding the sword and bow and arrow in addition. His vehicle is Garuda the eagle, on whom he often sits, and his couch is Adishesha, the many-hooded serpent. His consorts are Sri (Lakshmi), the Goddess of prosperity and Bhu, Goddess Earth.&#xA;It is the all-pervading Lord Vishnu who resides on Venkatadri hill as Venkateshwara, Balaji or Srinivasa, for the benefit of the world.&#xA;Narayana as Padmanabha resting on Adishesha, surrounded by the&#xA;waters. Lakshmi is at his feet,&#xA;Brahma is seated on a lotus issuing from Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s navel&#xA;33&#xA;34&#xA;Vishnu reclining on the cosmic waters on the coils of Adishesha with the lotus of life on which sits Brahma, the Creator, rising out of his navel; Pahari miniature painting&#xA;Narayana, the refuge&#xA;At the time of the dissolution of the world, following the great flood, there was only water everywhere and the sage Markandeya was wandering, lost, when he met a male child lying on the branch of the nyagrodha (banyan) tree. The child introduced himself as Narayana, the creator and destroyer of the universe, saying,&#xA;aapo naaraa iti puraa sangyaakarma krutam mayaa tena naaraayano apyukto mama tattvayanam sadaa&#xA;(Formerly I gave the waters the name nara. Because the waters have always been my abode, I am therefore called Narayana Mahabharata, III. 189.12952.)&#xA;―&#xA;The later Manusamhita, Vishnu Purana and Harivamsha add the information that the waters were called nara because they were the resting place of the Supreme Lord Narayana.&#xA;Narayana is represented variously as Narayana, the refuge of all souls, as Ranganatha, with Sridevi and Bhudevi, and as Vata-patra-shayi, the child lying on the leaf of the Ficus krishnae plant. In the first two forms he lies on the many-hooded serpent Adishesha. All these forms are aspects of Vishnu the all-pervading, resting on the waters, the refuge of all souls, the destroyer of evil and saviour of good.&#xA;Narayana, as he rests on the eternal waters, becomes the Creator who brings forth life from the ocean. The Rig Veda tells us that &amp;ldquo;the waters, they received that germ primeval wherein the gods were gathered all together. It rested upon the Unborn&amp;rsquo;s navel, that One wherein abide all things existing&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;His creative powers are represented by a lotus issuing out of his navel, bearing Brahma the Creator. Narayana is &amp;ldquo;older than the oldest ones&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;Lord of life&amp;rdquo;. And creation comes from the life-giving waters.&#xA;As Narayana rests on the waters, there is tranquility on earth. When the world is denuded and barren, or in danger from an evil power, Narayana incarnates himself on earth, first to destroy evil and then to re-create a new and better world order. As the Preserver, he protects the world for the good, for his devotees. Thus he combines in himself the three qualities of Destroyer, Creator and Preserver.&#xA;Images of Narayana generally show the God resting on his couch, the many-hooded serpent, Adishesha, holding the conch, discus, lotus and mace. Sometimes a lotus, on which Brahma is seated, is shown&#xA;coming out of his navel.&#xA;Incarnations and Manifestations&#xA;of Vishnu&#xA;—&#xA;Narayana&#xA;Although Vishnu has taken several incarnations on earth, as and when Dharma or the divine law was in danger, there are generally ten accepted incarnations&#xA;corresponding with the various stages of evolution of life on earth. With the exception of Krishna who was a full incarnation of Vishnu, the others were part incarnations who even met with other incarnations or Vishnu himself during their sojourn on earth.&#xA;The images of the incarnations may be two, four, eight or sixteen-armed, holding the conch, discus, mace, lotus and sword. Or they may hold none of these, such&#xA;as Parashurama with the battle-axe or Rama with the bow and arrow or Krishna with the flute.&#xA;Matsya, the fish : At the end of the last age or kalpa a great flood devastated and destroyed the world. Vishnu the Preserver commanded Rishi Satyavrata to collect the seven great sages and samples of every animal, bird, plant and seed in a boat. Lord Vishnu then appeared in the form of a gigantic fish and dragged the boat through the turbulent oceans all through the long night of Brahma, till the deluge ended and Brahma created the present world. Thus was born Manu, the progenitor of the human race. This story resembles the tale in the Bible&amp;rsquo;s Book of Genesis, a story which first appeared on the tablets of ancient Babylon and probably goes back to an actual flood which took place in the ancient past, probably in the sixth millennium B.C. Another version is that an evil demon stole the four Vedas and hid them beneath the ocean. Vishnu took the form of a giant fish and retrieved them.&#xA;Chapter 6&#xA;Vishnu as Matsya; Kondapalli, Andhra Pradesh&#xA;Matsya killing Damanaka, the demon who stole the Vedas and hid in a conch-shell; Pahari Painting&#xA;35&#xA;36&#xA;Vishnu as Kurma; Kondapalli, Andhra Pradesh&#xA;In the story of evolution, the fish represents the earliest form of life on earth, a form of life which lived under water. In iconography, Matsya is represented with the upper torso of a man and the lower torso of a fish.&#xA;Kurma, the tortoise: The wicked demons performed austerities and obtained strengths with which they harassed the Gods and constantly fought with them. The Gods then implored Vishnu to deliver them from this evil. Vishnu advised the Gods to make peace with the demons and unite with them to churn the ocean for amrita, the nectar of immortality. So the Gods lifted the mountain Mandara, used it as a churning rod, and the snake Vasuki as the rope. But the earth sank under this weight. Vishnu assumed the form of a giant tortoise and went beneath the mountain, serving as a base on which the mountain could pivot. When the nectar of immortality was churned, the demons again started fighting for it. Now Vishnu assumed the form of a beautiful woman, Mohini, to distract the demons and give the nectar to the Gods, who now attained immortality. The incident of the churning of the ocean is known as the samudra manthana. This incarnation was extremely popular in South East Asia. The story is beautifully carved in relief on the walls of the temple of Angkor Vat in Cambodia. The entrance to Angkor Thom is made up of five gates consisting of the mountain Mandara crowned by four-faced heads, variously described as Brahma, Vishnu, Shiva and Lokeshvara. However it is obviously Vishnu who appears atop Mandara during the samudra manthana on the beautifully carved reliefs on the walls of both Angkor Vat and Angkor Thom. On either side of the gates unfold the coils of the serpent Vasuki held by larger-than-life demons and Gods churning the ocean in unison.&#xA;The tortoise represents the next stage of evolution, the amphibian who could live in and out of water. In iconography, he is generally represented with the upper torso of a man and the lower of a tortoise.&#xA;Gods and demons churning the ocean of milk; temple carving&#xA;Vishnu as the mighty boar Varaha, raising the earth, goddess Bhudevi, from the ocean floor; Halebid, Karnataka&#xA;Varaha, the boar: During the great flood, the earth was submerged under water. The wicked demon Hiranyaksha abducted Goddess Earth- Bhudevi - and took her away under water. So Vishnu took the form of a boar, dived deep into the water, fought and killed the demon and rescued Earth. The rescue of the Earth represents the Supreme saving the world from evil.&#xA;This incarnation is generally represented as an enormous boar carrying Goddess Earth in a human form on his tusks. Varaha may be represented in three ways:&#xA;Bhu Varaha, holding Goddess Earth or Bhudevi - seated on his tusks or in his hand or on his lap and holding the blue lotus in her hand.&#xA;Adi Varaha, standing with one foot on Adishesha, representing the life-giving waters and carrying Bhudevi holding the blue lotus and seated on his tusks or in his hand or on his lap.&#xA;Pralaya Varaha, sitting on a throne which he shares with Goddess Earth holding the blue lotus.&#xA;Yagnya Varaha, seated on a throne with Lakshmi and Bhudevi on either side holding the lotus&#xA;and blue lotus respectively.&#xA;Varaha represents the land animal who no longer lives in the waters, an important step in evolutionary history. He is intimately connected with the land which he rescues from the waters.&#xA;Vishnu as Varaha, the guardian of the earth-goddess Bhudevi; calendar art&#xA;37&#xA;Vishnu as Narasimha, the man-lion; Halebid, Karnataka&#xA;38&#xA;Narasimha, the man-lion: Hiranyaksha had a brother Hiranyakashipu who now began harassing the Gods. Actually the two were Jaya and Vijaya, the gate-keepers of heaven, who had incurred the displeasure of Vishnu and were cursed to be born as demons and Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s enemies in three births. Hiranyakashipu performed severe penances and obtained several boons from Brahma which made him invincible: he could be killed by neither man nor animal nor weapon, neither inside nor outside a building, neither in the day nor in the night, neither on earth nor in the sky. Now Brahma was helpless when the demon turned against the Gods who, in turn, turned to Vishnu for help.&#xA;Hiranyakashipu&amp;rsquo;s son Prahlada was a devout worshipper of Vishnu, making Hiranyakashipu very angry. In one of his fits of anger, Hiranyakashipu asked Prahlada where Vishnu was and kicked a pillar. And out came the terrible form of the man-lion Narasimha, neither man nor animal. Sitting on the doorway, neither inside nor outside, at dusk, which was neither day nor night, Narasimha tore apart the wicked demon.&#xA;There are three types of Narasimha images :&#xA;Sthauna Narasimha, with Hiranyakashipu stretched out on his lap, his belly ripped open by the man-lion;&#xA;Girija Narasimha, a Yogic figure sitting on a lotus seat with his legs tied in place by a belt called&#xA;the yogapatta.&#xA;Yanaka Narasimha, sitting either on his vehicle Garuda, the eagle, or on his couch Adishesha, the serpent.&#xA;There are several Narasimha shrines in the Eastern Ghats, of which the Venkatachala hill is a part. In fact, he is probably the most important incarnation of Vishnu in this region.&#xA;Narasimha represents a transitional stage on the&#xA;evolutionary ladder, the transition from animal to man.&#xA;Vamana, the dwarf : The roots of the Vamana incarnation are to be found in the Vedic Vishnu who, as Trivikrama, traversed the universe in three steps.&#xA;Bali was the grandson of Prahlada. He performed many austerities which won him control over the earth, heavens and the nether regions, all of which he ruled with his demon hosts. Seeing her son Indra lose his heavenly kingdom, Aditi, the mother of the Gods, went to request Vishnu to restore them their kingdom. So Vishnu took the form of a young Brahmin boy, a dwarf, and approached Bali, who was performing a sacrifice. Against the advice of his guru Shukracharya who recognized Vishnu in the dwarf, Bali said he was honoured by Vishnu&amp;rsquo;s presence and offered Vamana whatever he wanted. Vamana asked for the space covered by his three paces, a request which Bali acceded to at once. Immediately, the dwarf became the giant Trivikrama. With his first step he covered the heavens, with the second the earth. As there was no place for the third, Bali offered his head. Pleased with Bali, Vamana allowed him to return to rule the nether worlds with his demons, and the heavens were returned to the Gods.&#xA;The artistic representations of this incarnation are of two extremely different forms :&#xA;In one, Trivikrama is a gigantic figure with one foot on the ground and the other lifted high across the heads of all the attendant deities. He is generally multi-armed and surrounded by several Gods and holy men.&#xA;In the other, Vamana is represented as a short Brahmachari holding an umbrella, water pot and book and wearing a ring made of kusha grass on his third finger.&#xA;On the evolutionary scale, Vamana is the early Homo sapiens, short in stature and still growing.&#xA;Narasimha, the man-lion incarnation&#xA;of Vishnu, whose fury was restrained by his gentle consort Lakshmi; calendar art&#xA;Vishnu as Vamana; Kondapalli, Andhra Pradesh&#xA;3940&#xA;Vishnu as Parashurama; Kondapalli,&#xA;Andhra Pradesh&#xA;Parashurama, with the battle axe: The Kshatriyas&#xA;(warrior caste), goes the story, had become arrogant and quarrelsome. So the world had to be saved from them.&#xA;Vishnu was born as Parashurama, the son of Renuka and Jamadagni, a holy sage. One day, King Kartavirya, while out hunting, visited the hermitage of the sage who entertained the royal entourage with the help of his cow Surabhi who could fulfil any wish. The king asked for the cow, but Jamadagni refused, upon which he was killed by Kartavirya&amp;rsquo;s son. Parashurama learned of this on his return to the hermitage and swore vengeance on the entire Kshatriya race. He first killed Kartavirya and his son. Thereafter, he pursued all Kshatriyas, who trembled. at his name and tried, unsuccessfully, to hide themselves from the avenger. Parashurama killed every Kshatriya and wiped out the entire race from this earth. His incarnation came to an end only when he met the next incarnation Rama, after which Parashurama retired to the hills. Images of Parashurama show a man in a deer skin, unshaven, holding a battle-axe.&#xA;Parashurama resembles the Neolithic cave man of popular imagination, wielding a battle-axe, representing an age of hand-to-hand warfare. This is also his position on the evolutionary scale.&#xA;Rama: Rama was born the son of Dasharatha, the king of Ayodhya. The story of his marriage to Sita, his banishment to the forest by his step-mother for fourteen years, the abduction of Sita by the wicked king Ravana of Lanka, Rama&amp;rsquo;s killing of Ravana, his triumphant return to Ayodhya and coronation as king make up the Ramayana, an epic familiar to every Indian and which forms the basis of Indian social and moral&#xA;Rama, Sita, Lakshmana and Hanuman; contemporary illustration.&#xA;values. Rama represents perfection, a fountainhead of goodness and justice, upholding his father&amp;rsquo;s promise even when it is unfair to him, faithful to a single wife and a role model for all times.&#xA;Images of Rama are invariably a part of a group consisting of Rama holding a bow and arrow, his brother Lakshmana holding the same weapons, Rama&amp;rsquo;s wife Sita and his devotee Hanuman, the monkey faced god, loved by all.&#xA;In evolution, Rama is early man as we know him, part of a social order and fulfilling his duties, the provider and protector. His weapon, the bow and arrow also portray the development in weaponry from the hand-to-hand fighting equipment of the previous incarnation.&#xA;The coronation of Rama; Thanjavur painting&#xA;41&#xA;42&#xA;Krishna playing the flute in Vrindavan; North Indian Miniature painting&#xA;Krishna&amp;rsquo;s advice to Arjuna (the Bhagavad Gita)&#xA;Krishna Unlike the other incarnations, Krishna is regarded by his devotees as a full manifestation&#xA;of Vishnu. Born to Vasudeva and Devaki, he is taken away to the home of the cowherds Nanda and Yashoda by his father to be saved from death at the hands of his uncle Kamsa, king of Mathura, who, it was predicted, would be killed by their eighth child, Krishna. He grows up in Brindavan and the stories of his childhood there make up the legends of the child-god Krishna who kills several demons and his wicked uncle. He is Arjuna&amp;rsquo;s charioteer in the war of Kurukshetra between the Pandavas and the Kauravas, and is the author of the Bhagavat Gita. The story of the Kurukshetra war and of Krishna makes up the great Indian epic, the Mahabharata. Krishna is represented with his flute in one hand and flanked by his wives Rukmini and Satyabhama, manifestations of Sri (prosperity) and Bhu (earth). He is often represented with the conch, discus and lotus or mace the first two were obtained by Krishna as he killed the evil demons.&#xA;Krishna is the thinking man, the philosopher, statesman and intellectual who plans with his brain rather than fight with his hands. This is the beginning of the evolution of modern man.&#xA;Buddha : According to the Bhagavata Purana, Vishnu, as Buddha, was born to deceive the enemies of the Gods. Buddha advised the Asuras (demons) to renounce the Vedas, making them lose all their power. Thus the Gods were able to establish their supremacy.&#xA;Born Prince Siddhartha, he renounced all his worldly possessions and became a mendicant. He rejected sacrifices and rituals, and taught his devotees to be free of desire, lead a disciplined life and search for the answers to the riddles of the world within oneself. The Buddha is an example of Upanishadic philosophy in action. He is represented sitting in the lotus pose on a lotus seat, blessing the worshipper, after attaining enlightenment.&#xA;Buddha is the enlightened man, a step up the ladder of evolution, a man of peace preaching non-violence in preference to war.&#xA;Kalki : This incarnation of Vishnu has yet to arrive. In Kali yuga, the present age, people will not follow the Vedas and dharma, foreign barbarians will rule and there will be so much evil that Vishnu will arrive on a white horse to destroy the evil. The world will go up in flames and peace, purity and righteousness will be restored on earth. Kalki is represented either with a horse face or riding a horse.&#xA;This is the future of man, destroyed in an apocalypse sent to destroy the earth.&#xA;The Buddha; bronze from Nagapattinam, Tamil Nadu&#xA;Vishnu as Kalki, the horseman of doom, who dismantles the corrupt world so that it can be reassembled in purity; temple carving, Gujarat&#xA;43&#xA;44&#xA;Vishnu as Balarama, the lord of farmers bearing a plough; Mysore painting (left) and as Hayagriva, the horse-headed Vishnu, sometimes mentioned in the list of avataras; Mysore painting (right)&#xA;Other Forms of Vishnu :&#xA;Vishnu incarnates himself on earth whenever Dharma or the divinely ordained laws and duties are in danger. The number of incarnations varies from text to text, from seven according to the Vishnu Purana to twenty four according to the Bhagavata Purana and twenty six according to the Devi Bhagavatam. However, ten is the most popular and frequently-used number and the incarnations are invariably known as the Dashavatara (ten incarnations) of Lord Vishnu.&#xA;Although Vishnu has ten official incarnations on the evolutionary scale, he manifests himself from time to time in various other forms. Venkateshwara is one such form. Some of the others are&#xA;Balarama, the brother of Krishna, who is regarded by some as the incarnation in place of the Buddha. Others regard him to be an incarnation of Adishesha. He is represented by the plough;&#xA;Dhanvantari, the father of Indian medical systems, particularly Ayurveda;&#xA;Hamsa, the mythical wise swan;&#xA;Hayagriva, a horse-headed human figure, regarded as the God of learning;&#xA;Dattatreya, a representation of Vishnu as the Trinity, with the three heads of Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva, and accompanied by four dogs representing the four Vedas, and the sacred cow;&#xA;Jagannatha, Lord of the Universe, a common name&#xA;for Vishnu and a form which is sanctified in the&#xA;temple at Puri, along with his brother Balarama and sister Subhadra;&#xA;Dattatreya; contemporary illustration&#xA;OO&#xA;Jagannatha with Balarama and Subhadra; wood carving, Orissa&#xA;45&#xA;46&#xA;Vishnu and Lakshmi on Garuda the eagle, the vehicle of Vishnu (right) and Vishnu as Mohini (below); Halebid, Karnataka&#xA;Lakshmi- Narayana, a composite figure of Vishnu seated with Goddess Lakshmi on his lap, the merging of the male and female principles;&#xA;Mohini, the form of a beautiful woman assumed by Vishnu to distract the asuras or demons from the amrita, the nectar of immortality;&#xA;Varadaraja, the giver of boons, whose most famous temple is the Varadaraja Perumal temple of Kanchipuram in Tamilnadu;&#xA;Padmanabha, the lotus-navelled One, a reference to&#xA;Narayana lying on the ocean with the lotus issuing out of his navel. Brahma sits on the lotus, signifying the&#xA;beginning of all creation;&#xA;Ranganatha, or Vishnu resting on his great serpent couch Adishesha, with Sridevi and Bhudevi at his feet. He is represented thus at Srirangam near Tiruchi, where the great Vaishnava philosopher Ramanuja spent most of his life;&#xA;Vitthala, a form of Krishna accompanied by Rukmini, the deity of the temple of the same name at Pandharpur in Maharashtra.&#xA;Ranganatha; contemporary soapstone carving, Pondicherry&#xA;Stone-carved image of Vitthala;&#xA;Pandharpur, Maharashtra&#xA;47&#xA;Vaikunthanatha in bronze at the Hari Rai Temple, Chamba, Himachal Pradesh&#xA;Vaikunthanatha, combining the heads of a man, woman, lion (Narasimha) and boar (Varaha), a form popular in the early medieval art of Kashmir, and the Himalayan region; Shreenathji, a form of Lord Krishna originally installed by his grandson Vajranabha in ancient Vraja on the Yamuna and later reinstalled in Nathdwara during the period of Muslim vandalism;&#xA;There are many more, impossible to list fully. Nearly every temple of Vishnu, Shiva and Shakti has a local name or manifestation of the deity, running into several million forms of the Supreme Being.&#xA;In the Bhagavat Gita or the Song Celestial, Vishnu, as the divine incarnation Krishna who is performing the role of the charioteer of Arjuna, tells the latter that whenever Dharma, the divine code of moral and religious duty, is in danger, he will be reborn again and again, in many different forms. Apart from the main incarnations, Vishnu has manifested himself time and again, whenever Dharma was in danger, and will be manifested many more times in the future, as the world of human beings plunges into greater evil and chaos.&#xA;Shreenathji, a form of Lord Krishna, 48 Gujarat; contemporary illustration&#xA;Origin, History and Administration of the Temple&#xA;Origin of Balaji - Venkateshwara&#xA;Who was Venkateshwara? Today the devotee accepts him unquestioningly as a manifestation of Lord Vishnu, but his identity has been a subject of bitter debate for centuries. The origins of the God are shrouded in a mystery which will probably never be solved. We can only discuss some of the theories.&#xA;The name Venkateshwara&#xA;The name Venkata is exclusive to the Lord of the hill. It does not appear anywhere else, either in literature or in religion, it is not used for any other deity anywhere, except in recent temples built to replicate the Lord of Tirumala. Venkata has two differing meanings, according to Sanskrit texts :&#xA;The first is &amp;ldquo;Destroyer of sins&amp;rdquo;. The Brahmanda and Bhavishyottara Puranas, both medieval Sanskrit works, say that &amp;ldquo;vem&amp;rdquo; means dire sins and &amp;ldquo;kata&amp;rdquo; is the immuning power. Brahma took a promise from Vishnu that he would redeem the sins of all the pilgrims who came up the hills to the temple. Vishnu agreed, and the Seshadri hill was renamed as Venkata. Thus Vishnu came to be known as Venkateshwara or Lord of Venkata.&#xA;The second meaning, according to the Vayu Purana, another medieval work, is &amp;ldquo;giver of worldly wealth&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Vem&amp;rdquo; is derived from amrita or nectar and &amp;ldquo;kata&amp;rdquo; from aishwarya or affluence, says the Purana. This meaning relates more to the God&amp;rsquo;s qualities than to the actual etymology of the word.&#xA;The etymological roots of the word are hard to find in Sanskrit. The nearest words in Sanskrit are &amp;ldquo;vyamah kata&amp;rdquo; which mean &amp;ldquo;enveloping different kinds of sins&amp;rdquo; and the earliest appearance of the name is in medieval Puranic literature, after the 10th century A.D.&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;songs-of-the-alvars&#34;&gt;On the other hand, the word Venkatam, describing the hill, first appears in the Tamil grammar Tholkaappiyam, belonging to the pre-Christian era (about 200 B.C.). Venkadam means &amp;ldquo;burning debts&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;ven&amp;rdquo; = burning and &amp;ldquo;kadan&amp;rdquo; debts), a reference to Venkatesha&amp;rsquo;s loan from Kubera. Another meaning in Tamil is &amp;ldquo;burning mountain slopes&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;kadam&amp;rdquo; also means a mountain slope), a meaning with interesting anthropological connotations. The latter could either refer to the forest fires, which used to be very frequent (and which are still a problem on these dry deciduous hills), or to the act of clearing the forests, an important event in local history which was&#xA;Chapter 7&#xA;Venkateshwara, the Lord of the hills&#xA;49Balaji smeared with sandalwood&#xA;50 paste and turmeric&#xA;carried out by Thondaimaan, who is closely involved with the legends of Venkatesha and is credited with the construction of the temple.&#xA;In popular perception in South India, Venkatesha is collecting money to pay off his debts. Pilgrims flock to Tirumala to pour money into the hundi, in the hope that he will reward them in return. The branches of the banks situated in the Tirumala hills probably receive the largest daily collections of money in the whole country, from the amounts deposited by the devotees in the hundi or given by them for the performance of various rituals and special offerings.&#xA;However, the name Venkata still remains a mystery. Venkateshwara is the Lord (Ishwara) of Venkata.&#xA;Skanda? Shakti? Shiva? Vishnu?&#xA;The biggest mystery of all is which God could he be Skanda, Shakti, Shiva, Vishnu, all or none? This has consumed scholars and been the subject of bitter debate for centuries.&#xA;Hindu deities are generally identified by their attributes, vehicles and distinguishing marks. Venkatesha has no attributes. The original stone image has a crescent mark on the forehead and holds nothing, the jeweled conch and discus being later detachable additions. There are some distinctly Shaivite features such as the hair, which consists of matted locks (jata juta), the God&amp;rsquo;s snake-shaped ornaments and the cobra slung over his right arm.&#xA;Skanda&#xA;In the Tamil tradition, Skanda or Kumara is the God of the hills and nearly all his temples are situated on at least a hillock. Also, there are frequent references in early Tamil literature to festivals on the Venkadam hill, including the hunting festival. Kumara is the God of the hunters and hill festivals are conducted in his honour all over South India. Further, the sacred tank or teertha is named the Swami Pushkarini, Swami being an appelate of Skanda (Kumaraswami). But Swami could also mean God in general. Finally, his attributes, described above, are also undoubtedly Shaivite in nature. He is the son of Shiva.&#xA;Shakti&#xA;Another view is that it is a form of Durga or another Shakti. The drapery of the Lord resembles a sari. The ceremonial bath (abhisheka) is performed only on Fridays, the day of the auspicious bath (mangala snana) for women, with sandal paste and turmeric, both women&amp;rsquo;s cosmetics, to the chanting of the Shri (Lakshmi) Sukta. The Thomala Seva is also known as Bhagavati aradhana. Above, on the vimana of the temple, crouches Devi&amp;rsquo;s symbol, the lion. The Devi Bhagavatam describes the Lord of Tirumala as Shri Venkateshwari, the only deity for Kali yuga. And finally, according to North Indian tradition, he is known as Balaji, derived from &amp;ldquo;Bala&amp;rdquo; the Universal Mother, a woman&amp;rsquo;s name.&#xA;Shiva&#xA;The Shaivites maintain that the matted hair, the cobra on one arm, the snake ornaments and the crescent on the head are undoubtedly marks of Shiva. Significantly, the pooja is done with the leaves of the bilva (Bengal quince or Aegle marmelos) tree : bilva leaves are used only in Shiva temples, never in those of Vishnu. The earliest Tamil Vaishnava saints - Poygai Alvar, Bhutat Alvar and Pey Alvar who lived between A.D. 500 and 650 — as well as Nammalvar, regarded as the most important and the greatest of them all, have conceded that the deity is both Shiva and Vishnu, an admission they would not have made if there was no trace of Shiva in the Lord of Tirumala. Finally, the Purusha Sukta and Shri Sukta are&#xA;51&#xA;52&#xA;recited by Smarthas (Dikshitas or Aiyars), just as it is a Smartha who performs the sacred abhishekha for the main deity on Fridays. The Vaishnavas recite the Tamil Divyaprabandham, the passion songs of the Alvars who sang of their divine Lord.&#xA;Vishnu&#xA;The Silappadikaaram (8th century A.D.) refers to the deity as Vishnu. The author, a Jaina who would not have been concerned with the rival claims of the various sects, says, &amp;ldquo;Lord Vishnu&amp;hellip; is seen in a standing posture on the top of Vengadam hill&amp;hellip;adorned with a brilliant cloth of gold round his loins and&amp;hellip;a beautiful garland on his chest and (he) holds in his lotus-like hands the invincible discus and milky white conch&amp;rdquo;. The later Alvars have referred to the deity as a manifestation of Vishnu in their songs. The Brahmanda, Bhavishyottara and Vayu Puranas describe Venkatesha as a manifestation of Vishnu.&#xA;The arguments for identifying the God exclusively with Vishnu were first made by the Vaishnava philosopher and missionary Ramanuja, who lived between 1017 and 1137 A.D., and who is credited with the establishment of the temple as a Vaishnava shrine. Ramanuja is believed to have participated in a great debate over whether the image was of Shiva or Vishnu.&#xA;The Yadava king, who was a Vaishnava himself, ruled in Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s favour. Thereafter, Ramanuja reconsecrated the image as a manifestation of Vishnu. While there is no historical evidence for this, it seems fairly certain that the cult of Venkatesha as a manifestation of Vishnu gained prominence at this time.&#xA;The Verdict&#xA;The arguments for and against each identification have been going on for over a thousand years, if not more. There is no clear answer, except some likely inferences. The discovery by Thondaimaan, while ascending the hill with a hunter, of a half-buried image &amp;ldquo;standing under a tree, with the lower part of the body hidden in an anthill&amp;rdquo;, as well as the references in literature to unspecified but famous festivals in the hills, suggest a folk or tribal origin for the deity. Even today, there are several ambivalent images of deities all over India who are identified with either Shiva or Vishnu but are actually neither, nor any of their subsidiaries, and who combine within them male and female, Hari (Vishnu) and Hara (Shiva). Also, Hindu deities generally carry some attribute the original stone image, it is believed, carries none.&#xA;The answer probably lies in the work of the earliest Vaishnava saints who saw both Shiva and Vishnu in their&#xA;Lord, even though they were diehard Vaishnavas. Poygai Alvar says&#xA;&amp;ldquo;His name is Aran (Hara or Shiva) and Naranan (Narayana)&#xA;His vehicle is the bull (Nandi) and the bird (Garuda)&#xA;His word is the book and marai&#xA;His residence is the hills (Kailasa) and in the waters&#xA;His function is destruction and protection&#xA;His weapon is the trident and the disc&#xA;His form, though One, is fire and dark cloud.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Can there be a more beautiful description of the Oneness&#xA;of Shiva and Vishnu?&#xA;53&#xA;Nammalvar, 16th century bronze, Tamilnadu&#xA;Pey Alvar sings&#xA;&amp;ldquo;He has in his form the flowing matted locks and the high peaked crown&#xA;The shining dagger and the disc&#xA;The snake coiling around him and the golden string around his waist&#xA;In him, my father on Tirumalai,&#xA;The two forms have gracefully blended into One&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;Bhutat Alvar also visualises the Lord as a combination of Shiva and Vishnu, while Nammalvar, writing in the 8th century, concedes that Vishnu, as the Lord of Tirumala, has merged in himself Rudra, Brahma and Lakshmi, accepting all three forms of the Supreme.&#xA;The attempt to identify him exclusively as Vishnu and deny the Oneness of the various forms of the Lord took place only during the period of Ramanuja, who is well-known for his missionary zeal to convert temples, Gods and people to Vaishnavism. As Ramanuja had the support of his rulers, the Yadava kings, and their successors, the powerful Vijayanagara emperors who were worshippers of Vishnu, the Lord of Tirumala became irrevocably identified with Vishnu.&#xA;In Balaji - Venkatesha, the devotee sees his personal God, be it Shiva or Vishnu, Skanda or Shakti. There can be no greater proof of the Universal Nature of&#xA;the Lord than that he combines within himself the main deities of Hinduism.&#xA;Ramanuja, founder of the&#xA;Vishishtadvaita school of Vaishnava&#xA;philosophy; stone carving,&#xA;54 Tirumala Temple&#xA;2400&#xA;2012&#xA;Origin of the stone image&#xA;Our sources of information about the hill temple range from literature to oral traditions to epigraphs. The earliest reference to the hill is by the Tamil grammarian&#xA;Tholkaappiar in the second century B.C. who refers to the hill as the northern boundary of the Tamil world:&#xA;vada vengada then kumari yaayida thamil kurum nal ulaham&#xA;(the tract between vengadam in the north and (Kanya) Kumari in the south is said to be the good world of the Tamils).&#xA;The next references are in Tamil Sangam literature. Poet Maamoolanar refers to the Vengadam hills in the second century A.D. The Ahanaanooru mentions Pulli, chieftan of the region around Vengadam, the narrow passage across the hill which one had to cross to come out of Pulli&amp;rsquo;s territory and the festivals for which Vengadam was famous. Nakkirar and Kanakkanayanaar are two Shaivite saints who refer to Vengadam, the latter also mentioning the hosts of elephants in the forests.&#xA;Although none of these writers speak of the God of Vengadam, the references to Thondaimaan, the name of the hills - Venkatadri — which is associated with the destruction of sin, and the festivals for which the place was famous make it very likely that the God was known by 200 B.C. itself.&#xA;The first actual reference to a deity appears in the Silappadikaaram, a Jaina epic of the 8th century A.D. which defines Vengadam as one of the three Vaishnava temples. The author says that &amp;ldquo;Lord Vishnu of the lotus eyes is seen in a standing posture on the top of Vengadam hill which is full of waterfalls and where the effulgent rays of the sun and the moon fall on the image. The Lord is adorned with a brilliant cloth of gold round his loins and he wears a beautiful garland on his chest and holds in his lotus-like hands the invincible discus and milky white conch. He looks like a black cloud with a streak of lightning and a rainbow&amp;rdquo;. What is interesting about this stanza is the author&amp;rsquo;s assertion that the sun and the moon shone on the image, indicating that it either stood out in the open or under a tree (which was and still is very common) or under an open-sided pavilion. Obviously, no temple had been built as yet.&#xA;The statue is, visually, pre- or early Pallava, the identification coming from its style and attribute-less state (it is believed that the original stone figure does not hold any weapons, these were added much later by Ramanuja). It is also likely that there was an earlier image made of a perishable material like wood or clay.&#xA;The tradition of an image of worship, as described&#xA;in Tamil literature, is much older than the present stone&#xA;55&#xA;Utsava murti of Balaji decorated with pearls&#xA;Venkatesha&#xA;56 A Vaishnava Alvar or saint&#xA;figure which, at the earliest, belongs to about the sixth century. When stone sculpture became popular in the South, many of the earlier wooden or terracotta figures were replaced. The Vishnu temple of Varadaraja Perumal at Kanchipuram is one such example where the original figure made of fig wood has been preserved in the temple tank and is taken out only every twelve years, while the main deity under worship, today, is made of granite.&#xA;Songs of the Alvars&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vaishnava saints of Tamilnadu — the Alvars — have sung extensively about the Lord of Vengadam. Ten out of twelve Alvars visited Tirumala and composed songs in his praise. The first three - Poygai Alvar, Bhutat Alvar and Pey Alvar-lived in the early years of the eighth century and sang of the Lord of Vengadam. The Thiruvaimoli of Nammalvar, who lived in 798 A.D. and is considered to be the greatest of the Alvars, contains several stanzas describing the God. While the existence of the temple is not known, the hill was held in high esteem as the annihilator of sins. In 1803, the then Collector of Chittoor, G. Stratton notes that &amp;ldquo;In such veneration is even the hill held that pilgrims resorting to the pagoda prostrate themselves to the ground (on) first getting a sight of the range of hills connected with it.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;The Alvars also describe the thick jungles, interspersed with streams and waterfalls, surrounding the hills which abounded with elephants, snakes, monkeys and boars, and where the Korava tribes lived. In fact the later Yadava rulers of the region are known to have originally belonged to the Kurumba tribe who overthrew the Vedars and Ventari hunting tribes of the hills. In 1804, the existence of Yanadis &amp;ldquo;who collected honey and bees&amp;rsquo; wax and sandalwood, fruits and roots&amp;rdquo; is mentioned.&#xA;Kamban, the author of the Tamil Ramayana, refers to Vengadam as a sacred hill where holy men live, who do good deeds without any thought of reward and who have attained a state of bliss.&#xA;There are several references to the Venkata hill in&#xA;medieval Sanskrit literature, as the earlier references from the Puranas testify. Telugu and Kannada literature are also replete with references to the God, indicating his widespread worship.&#xA;The Puranas ascribe the construction of the temple to Thondaimaan, the ruler of Narayanavanam, who discovered the image of the God &amp;ldquo;standing under a tree, with the lower part of the body hidden in an ant-hill&amp;rdquo; when he ascended the hill with a local hunter, and who constructed the prakara and gopuram, maybe even the original temple complex. Although Thondaimaan&amp;rsquo;s role in the Venkatesha legend is obviously exaggerated, he was actually a historical figure who probably lived around 550 A.D., the pre-Pallava period to which the style of the main stone statue corresponds. He is reputed to have cleared the jungles around Kalahasti and established the kingdom of Thondaimandalam. The region between the Vengadam hills and as far south as Chidambaram is known as Thondaimandalam even today. There are some villages around Tirupati which still bear traces of Thondaimaan, such as Thondamaanaadu and Thondavaada. He is described as the illegitimate son of Kulottunga Chola of Thanjavur and was probably related to the Pallavas, who were also known as the &amp;ldquo;Thondaiyars&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Kattu Vettigal&amp;rdquo;, meaning &amp;ldquo;those who cleared the forests&amp;rdquo;, an appropriate appellate for Thondaimaan. According to the Tamil text Perumpanatruppadai, the Pallavas are so-called because their ancestor Vishnu came floating on the leaf (&amp;ldquo;pallava&amp;rdquo; means leaf) of a &amp;ldquo;thondai&amp;rdquo; creeper, and that is why the name Thondaimandalam was given to their kingdom.&#xA;Recorded history&#xA;While the origin of the image is shrouded in the mists of time, the temple has a far more certain history. The recorded history of the temple begins in the small village of Tiruchanur, once known as Tiruchchokinur, where there is an inscription regarding the gift of a perpetual&#xA;Thondaimaan, Pallava ruler of Thondaimandalam which included Tirumala-Tirupati&#xA;57&#xA;58&#xA;Krishnadevaraya, Vijayanagara emperor, Tirumala temple&#xA;light to the hill God Tiruvengadattu Peruman Adigal by Vijayaditya, a local ruler of the Bana dynasty who&#xA;lived between 830 and 850 A.D. An inscription dated 970 A.D. on the north wall of the hill shrine records the gift of a silver image (now placed in the Tiruvilankovil), a necklace and other ornaments and lands in Tiruchanur by Samavai, daughter of a Pallava chieftan and wife of a Kadava chief. In 1000 A.D., we are told, the wife of the Chola king Parantaka II presented a gift of a gold plate studded with precious stones to Venkateshwara. There are several subsequent records of grants made in the Chola and subsequent Pandya periods.&#xA;But it was the Yadava Rayas, Chola feudatories of the region between 1184 and 1355, who contributed greatly to the development of the temple. They gifted several lands, villages, cows, ornaments and images to the temple. It was during their rule that Ramanujacharya established the temple as a Vaishnava shrine. Ramanuja visited the area two or three times. The first occasion was when he lived at the foothills for a year, to study the Ramayana from his maternal uncle Tirumalai Nambi. The second occasion was as the leader of the Sri Vaishnava community of Srirangam. The third occasion was in his old age.&#xA;In 1303, Allauddin Khilji tried to invade Andhra desha, but was repelled. In 1309 he sent his general Malik Kafur on a military expedition to the south. Malik Kafur ravaged the kingdoms of the Kakatiyas, Hoysalas and Pandyas, plundered and took away their wealth and destroyed their temples.&#xA;In the Koil Alagu, the history of the famous temple of Srirangam at Tiruchirapalli (Trichi), it is said that on hearing of the approach of Malik Kafur, the local people who were celebrating the annual festival took some urgent measures to save the deity from destruction by the Muslim general. They walled up the sanctum sanctorum which housed the main deity, hid the jewels and smuggled the bronze processional image away to Tirumala which, fortunately, was too inaccessible for Malik Kafur.&#xA;The Tirumala-Tirupati region was taken over by the Vijayanagara empire, founded in 1336 A.D. by Harihara and Bukka of the Sangama dynasty, two brothers who were inspired by their philosopher friend and guide, Saint Vidyaranya, to establish a kingdom to protect the religion and culture of the Hindus. An important event of this dynasty was the return of the processional image to Srirangam. Devaraya II of the Sangama dynasty was devoted to the Lord and made several benefactions.&#xA;The Sangamas were followed by the Saluva, Tuluva and Aravidu dynasties of the Vijayanagara empire, all of whom were great devotees of Lord Venkateshwara. The temple structure evolved in this period. Saluva Narasimha&#xA;Raya endowed the village of Durgasamudram in 1482 A.D. for the purpose of constructing gopurams (gateways) in Tirumalai and gave several gifts to the temple. But the greatest patronage was received during the reign of Krishnadeva Raya of the Tuluva dynasty, who visited the temple on all important occasions, and his brother Achyuta Raya. The two kings and their queens made costly gifts of gold, jewels and lands, and instituted and supported several festivals.&#xA;The rule of the Aravidu, the last dynasty, was one of constant war, culminating in the ultimate destruction of the capital Vijayanagara (modern Hampi) and the empire. From 1650 to 1800 the Tirumalai-Tirupati region was ruled by the Muslims as the Sultans of Golconda and&#xA;who extracted tribute and taxes&#xA;the Nawabs of Carnatic&#xA;from the temples.&#xA;The management of the temple was in the hands of the Sthaanathaar, the traditional managers, and there is no record of any fees being collected from the pilgrims. In 1724, Asaf Jah, Nizam of Hyderabad, appointed Daud Khan as the Nawab of the Carnatic. The latter demanded an annual tribute of rupees two lakhs to leave the temple alone. To make up this amount, several levies were introduced which the pilgrims had to pay, fees for reciting the mantras, tonsuring the head, lighting camphor, attending the archana, presenting a cloth, offering a food item and so on. In 1753, Muhammad Kamal marched towards Tirupati to plunder the temple, so the British sent a detachment to ward off the attack. Thereafter, the British took over the revenues of the temple, away from the Nawab.&#xA;The revenues passed to the East India Company in 1801, who continued the practice. In 1843 the Company handed over the temples to the mahants (priests) who managed them till the Government of the erstwhile Madras Presidency took them over in 1933 and put them under the management of a Board of Trustees.&#xA;Two well-known English officials who were devotees of the temple, although as non-Hindus they were never permitted to enter, were Sir Thomas Munroe and Lord Williams. The former suffered from an acute and incurable stomach pain. He was advised by a devotee of Lord Venkatesha to take a vow that he would visit Tirumalai and worship Lord Venkatesha if he was cured. Sir Thomas agreed and was cured. He visited Tirumala, although he was not permitted to enter the temple, and created an endowment for a daily offering of a gangalam (a huge vessel) of pongal (a rice and lentil dish), and gifted the village of Kotavayulu in Chittoor district for this purpose. His gift is still known as Munroe gangalam. Similarly, Lord Williams, who was cured of an incurable chronic illness, instituted the Lord Williams chali pandili&#xA;Sir Thomas Munroe, Governor of Madras and devotee of Balaji, statue at Chennai&#xA;5960&#xA;Vaikuntham queue complex; Tirumala&#xA;(drinking water service) at Mokalametta, along the footpath to Tirumala, a charity continued even today.&#xA;With the formation of the state of Andhra Pradesh, the control and management of the temples passed on to the new state. Today the Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanam manages Tirumala and all the associated temples. The revenue goes to maintain the properties, staff and the many charities and educational institutions of the Devasthanam.&#xA;Administration and facilities at Tirumala-Tirupati&#xA;The Tirumala Tirupati Devasthanam (TTD) is administered by a Board of Trustees appointed by the Government of Andhra Pradesh. The administration&#xA;is carried out by the Executive Officer, generally an I.A.S. officer, although the legendary Dr. C. Anna Rao, who held the position for several years and was responsible for many of the present facilities for pilgrims, did not belong to the cadre. The administration can be divided into two sections - general administration and temple administration - the former managing the Devasthanam&amp;rsquo;s properties, finance and staff, and the latter involving the maintenance of the temple and facilities for pilgrims. The main offices of the Devasthanam are at Tirupati, with camp offices on the hill and information&#xA;centres in various parts of India. The average annual income is about Rs. 300 crores, most of the money coming from hundi offerings.&#xA;Accommodation is available for all purses, from free choultries for the poor to cottages for families and air conditioned suites for the very rich. A lot of money is spent on providing civic amenities in Tirumala and Tirupati, for widening and maintaining roads and supplying water to the town of Tirupati, including the construction of a canal from Srikalahasti to Tirupati in order to bring the Telugu Ganga water to the temple town. Free bus facilities are available from the railway station to the top of the hill. The Devasthanam also provides several services such as religious propogation, education, afforestation, medical facilities and succour for the poor and disabled.&#xA;Free food is provided to the devotees, with an average of 30,000 people fed every day. The Sri Venkateshwara Nithya Annadanam Trust makes it possible for the devotee to contribute his mite to this scheme.&#xA;The Dharma Prachara Parishad promotes religious knowledge among young people, propogates the basic ideals of Hinduism and runs two Veda pathashalas at Tirumala and Hyderabad. The Devasthanam runs five institutions for Sanskrit and Vedic learning, four colleges, two for the Fine Arts, a new training centre for sculpture, one polytechnic, one Ayurvedic college, one institute for Yoga and allied sciences and ten schools in Tirupati and elsewhere in Andhra Pradesh. The Publications Department and Press bring out several publications about the temple and religious tenets, as well as regular journals. The Oriental Manuscripts Library is a storehouse of manuscripts. Two Museums - the Hall of Antiquities at Tirumala and the Sri Venkateshwara Museum of Temple Art at Tirupati - provide a feast of art. Several kalyana mandapams (wedding halls) have been constructed or are under construction 170 in Andhra Pradesh, 3 in Karnataka, and 1 each in Kerala (at Guruvayoor, a famous temple town), Orissa and Tamilnadu - which are made available at very low rates or even free of charge.&#xA;―&#xA;3025 hectares of land covering the slopes of the hill have been afforested and restored to their original biodiversity by the TTD&amp;rsquo;s Forest Department. The Garden. Department has developed beautiful ornamental and flower gardens on 455 acres of land on the hilltop. The Sri Venkateshwara Vanaabhivriddhi Scheme provides several opportunities, through the Vriksha&#xA;Samvardhanam, Vriksha Prasadam, Smaraka Vanuly and Vana Samrakshana Bhagaswayam schemes, for the public to participate in the Devasthanam&amp;rsquo;s afforestation programmes and earn great merit.&#xA;61&#xA;Hundi, early 20th century photograph&#xA;The Devasthanam runs the Ashwini Hospital at Tirumala and the TTD Central Hospital at Tirupati, besides several clinics and dispensaries to provide free medical aid to the pilgrims. A speciality hospital Sri Venkateshwara&#xA;Institute of Medical Sciences - has made advanced technology available for diagnosis and treatment for the poor. Philanthropists wishing to contribute for health services can donate to the Sri Balaji Arogyavaraprasadini Scheme.&#xA;Several facilities have been provided for the&#xA;disadvantaged. The Sri Venkateshwara Poor Home is the largest asylum in the country for leprosy patients. There is a Venkateshwara School for the Deaf and a Technical cum Production Centre for the Handicapped. The Balaji Institute for Research and Rehabilitation of the Disabled (BIRRD) provides advanced surgical techniques for poor and needy orthopaedic patients free of cost, while the Artificial Limb Fitting Centre provides aids and appliances for the poor free of cost. The Venkateshwara Balamandir is an orphanage established in 1943, while the Sri Venkateshwara Karunadhanam is a home for beggars.&#xA;Every pilgrim who visits Tirumala and puts money in the hundi or collection box can be satisfied that he is contributing to helping the poor and the needy, the young and the handicapped. This is one place where the Lord answers the prayers of all his devotees.&#xA;Venkateshwara carved out of&#xA;62 sandalwood; Karnataka&#xA;Images of Lord Venkateshwara and Other Deities&#xA;Venkateshwara : His image is regarded as a swayam vyakta murti, or one which is self-manifested. He is an &amp;ldquo;eka beralaya&amp;rdquo;, where only one form of God receives all the worship.&#xA;Carved out of black granite, Balaji stands on a high lotus pedestal. The image is about nine feet tall from the base of the pedestal to the tip of the crown. Every Friday the deity is given a ceremonial bath (abhishekha), when he is visible without his jewels or the huge Vaishnava caste mark on his forehead. His eyes look directly at the devotee and he smiles with an expression of inner tranquility and outer happiness. His crown or makuta, also sculpted in stone as a part of the image, is over twenty inches high. His flowing hair or jata juta is curled and rests on his shoulders.&#xA;The image is four-armed: two arms at the back are held up and curled into fists, ready to hold weapons. The conch and discus are attached separately. The front right hand is in the varada mudra (boon-giving hand posture), while the front left hand rests lightly on the hip in the katya vilambita hasta indicating that the Lord protects and blesses his true devotees. A seated Lakshmi is carved on the right side of his chest. The sacred thread (yagnyopavita), four necklaces, a thick girdle around the waist, snake-shaped armlets and a pair of anklets adorn the figure. On his shoulders are marks resembling the scars made from carrying a bow. The deity is a typical image of the Pallava or pre-Pallava period.&#xA;Chapter 8&#xA;Gold surya kathari or sword&#xA;Gold waist band sculpted with the ten Avataras&#xA;63&#xA;2&#xA;GOLD JEWELLERY&#xA;5&#xA;3&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
