<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;03 Modern period 18CE to date on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/03_Modern_period_18CE_to_date/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;03 Modern period 18CE to date on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/03_Modern_period_18CE_to_date/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>25 (xxv) TIRUMALA UNDER THE MAHANTS OF TIRUPATI</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/03_Modern_period_18CE_to_date/25_xxv_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_MAHANTS_OF_T/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/03_Modern_period_18CE_to_date/25_xxv_TIRUMALA_UNDER_THE_MAHANTS_OF_T/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the decline of the Vijayanagar Empire, there is a dearth of inscriptions in the Temple. When the British established themselves in South India, they took over the management of all the temples within their territorial jurisdiction in 1801 A.D., and credited the income under the general revenues of the State. Later on, during the middle of the 19th century, when they desired to relinquish their connection with the religious institutions, they conferred the administration of the temple of Sri Venkatesvara, together with those of Tirupati and Tiruchanur to the then Mahant Sri Sevadasuji of Sri Hathiramji Muth in 1843 A.D. through a sanad from the Collector of the North Arcot District.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 (xxvi) TIRUPATI IN MODERN TIMES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/03_Modern_period_18CE_to_date/26_xxvi_TIRUPATI_IN_MODERN_TIMES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/03_Modern_period_18CE_to_date/26_xxvi_TIRUPATI_IN_MODERN_TIMES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Subsequently the administration by the Mutt came to an end in 1933 when the Committee system of management replaced the Vicharana Karta Mahants. Later on by the Hindu Religious Endowments Act of 1951 and the Andhra Pradesh Hindu Religious and Charitable Endowments Act of 1966, were enacted, made the administration of the temple had been handed over to a Board of Trustees representing all shades of public opinion. In 1979 the Tirumala Tirupathi Devasthanam bill was passed, under which the management of the temple became autononous with a committee of management and also a Board. This self contained legislation has enabled the administration of the temple to be run on efficient lines.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
