<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 GEOGRAPHICAL BASIS on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 GEOGRAPHICAL BASIS on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>25 Location</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/01_Location/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/01_Location/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE group of hills lying in the shape of a coil called the Tirumala hills,  forms a feature of the region of South India between the 13th and 14th degrees  of north latitude and east longitude 79 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Tirumalai range has seven principal peaks, each of them sacred,  and each of them bearing a separate name accounted for by a fable. Near  one of them, namely Seshachalam, stands the Tirumala temple and the whole  range is often called after this principal peak.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 Topography</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/02_Topography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/02_Topography/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The physical geography of Tirumala, like its social economy, typifies  the interaction of the Tamil and Telugu cultures of South India. The dominant  topographical feature of Tirumala is the secluded hill top on which the temple  is built. As a matter of fact this has been referred to in the following words  used in Silappadhikaram:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot; Venkadamennum Enguyar Malaiyath thuchimimisai&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This notion that the Lord was named as &amp;quot; Uchchiyilninran&amp;quot; (He who  stands on the summit) appears to have persisted as a legacy of the tradition  till the middle of the 13th Century. The realisation that the temple was  actually on a much lower level than its surroundings became more general  in later days.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 Climate</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/03_Climate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/03_Climate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The climate is on the whole dry and agreeable. The year is divided  into four seasons. December to February is dry and cool. March to  May is summer followed by the South West monsoon from June to September.  October and November is the post monsoon retreating period, the average  rainfall being 8 to 7.5 mm. (32.58&amp;rsquo;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 Rainfall</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/04_Rainfall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/04_Rainfall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The annual rainfall is between 34 and 35 inches. The rainfall during  the monsoon period from June to September constitutes only 44% of the  annual normal rainfall. During May there is some significant amount of  rainfall mostly in the form of thunder showers. During the post monsoon  season as much as 35 % of the annual rainfall is received. The period from  August to November is the chief rainy season, October being the rainiest  month. The variation in the rainfall from year to year is very large.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Temperature</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/05_Temperature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/05_Temperature/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The annual temperature ranges from 18° to 42° C. The period from about  the middle of November to the middle of February is the coolest part of the  year. In December when the mean temperature is the lowest, the mean  daily maximum temperature is 25.3°C (77.5°F) and the mean daily minimum  is 15.4°C (59.7°F). After February the temperature begins to rise rapidly.  April and May are the hottest months with a mean daily maximum  temperature of 34.5°C (94.6°F). The nights are slightly hotter in May than  in April, the mean daily minimum in May being 23.9°C (75.0°F). Thunder  showers which occur on some days during the afternoon of April and May  bring welcome relief. With the onset of the SouthWest monsoon by about  the first week of June, day temperature decreases a little and the weather  in the whole of the south west and post monsoon season is more agreeable  than in the summer season. Night temperature decreases after October.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 (VI )Humidity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/06_VI_Humidity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/06_VI_Humidity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The relative humidity is about 70% to 80% in the morning and about  60% to 65% in the afternoons during the period from July to December.  It decreases thereafter. The driest part of the year is the period from February  to May when the relative humidities in the afternoons are between 25 % to 40 %.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 Cloudiness</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/07_Cloudiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/07_Cloudiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the period from June to November, skies are moderately and  heavily clouded and overcast for a few days. During the rest of the year  the skies are clear or highly clouded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 Winds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/08_Winds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/08_Winds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Winds are generally light and blow mainly from directions between  south-west and north-west during the period from May to September; for  the rest of the year, winds are light and variable in the morning. Afternoon winds are stronger, and in the period from October to January, they are mainly  north westerly or easterly; in the next three months, afternoon winds are mostly  from direction between east and north&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 Geological Formations</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/09_Geological_Formations/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/09_Geological_Formations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The geological formation of the area is of three kinds. The Jewadis,  the Eastern Ghats, and the spurs passing from them-belong to the gneissic  or metamorphic series, and this formation underlies, and occasionally crops  up from beneath, the level plains of the south-east. The hills present a bare  and rugged appearance, being rarely covered with more than a stunted scrub  jungle. Long coarse grass grows everywhere among the rocks, affording  pasturage to the miserable village cattle during the cool season, but during  the dry months the rocks are parched and useless. The villagers then set fire to  the grass, and the conflagrations rapidly spreading destroys the withered blades  and form a fresh soil, from which at the advent of the rains new shoots spring  up. The stunted jungle naturally suffers from such rough treatment, and  wood sufficiently large for building purposes can only be cut in a few localities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 Minerals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/10_Minerals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/10_Minerals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Among the gneissic hills, iron ore of Dharwarian age in the form of  hematite is found in considerable quantities and is in some places, exported.  The product is poor in quality and the percentage of iron is less than 60%,  Steatite barytes, gold and lead are found in small quantities in the area. Copper  mines, once profitably worked in the Kalahasti Zamindari, have long been  abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 Flora</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/11_Flora/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/11_Flora/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The flora of the tract is a measure of the general state of its progress  on the whole, although the ecological succession is rather hampered by biotic  influences mostly. In spite of the heavy influence of a biotic nature the district  still presents unique flora to a botanical explorer. The climate, topography  and geology have played a great role in presenting the flora of the tract. The  climate is on the whole salubrious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 Forest</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/12_Forest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/12_Forest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Forests cover about 27.4 % of the total extent of the area of the Chittoor  district in which Tirumala lies. In view of conserving and increasing the  land under forests the Government has taken over several estate forest blocks  paying due compensations during the past one decade.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The floristic composition in the forests vary from dry mixed deciduous  to thorny scrub with occasional patches of dry evergreen growth and can  be assumed to have reached the climatic climax of the region. The forests  of Bhakarapet and Tirupati Ranges and these in their vicinity, mainly confined  to imposing Seshachalam hills were assumed to be part of Dandakaranya  of antiquity, as expounded in the famous epic Ramayana. Dandakaranya,  as implied in its name, was impregnable and was replete with a great variety  of birds and animals, besides its luxuriant and varied vegetative forms. Such  remarkable vanams are too far deteriorated physically, as to be easily  reclaimable, and in fact, tending to be an assemblage of bald and barren  mountains and hills.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 Fauna</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/13_Fauna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/13_Fauna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The forests of the district, especially those of Tirupati and Bhakarapet  ranges even before their reservation, were reported to be rich, both in flora  and fauna. Legions of birds and animals were reported to have found in them a good abode and lived an unbridled and poised life. Mr. Jean Baptiste Travernier a French traveller and jewel merchant who passed through these forests on 27-8-1652 has written in his chronicles that the &amp;ldquo;place  is very pleasant and derives its coolness from numerous streams and fountains &amp;quot;  and that elephant capturing operations were then being conducted in these  hills by one of the captains of Mir Jumla&amp;rsquo;s army. This may appear rather  difficult to believe to those acquainted with the present condition of the forests and the fauna existing therein now, but it may not be far from truth, if we  can visualize the amount of havoc which could have been caused by man  to the once dense forests during the past three centuries. Not only have the  big game like elephants, bison etc , disappeared, but even carnivora like tigers and panthers, not to speak of Cheetahs, are greatly depleted and  almost extinct. Other common forms of wild life such as sambhurs and  spotted deers are also frightfully reduced and one rarely sees them in herds.  The opening of extensive unreserves around all forest reserves for cultivation, forming new highways passing through or along Nagapatla, Bhakarapet,  Tirupati, Mamandur and Napier RF. and the advent of fast moving vehicles  and the jeeps that can cruise the rugged forest tracts, the proliferation of  unlicensed weapons and coming of cheap and poisonous poison drugs like  endrine etc , and man&amp;rsquo;s unsportive desire for ruthless destruction of wild  beasts, have all cumulatively contributed to the present sad state of affairs  of reduction in the rate and varied fauna in the forests. Today even the  harmless peacocks are reduced in numbers. To give the much harassed  wild life a chance to recoup, all the forests in the district were closed to shooting  from 1962.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 Birds</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/14_Birds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/14_Birds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The bird life in general may be considered to be in much better shape  in the tract as the poachers had not concentrated much in their destruction  and the birds protecting themselves better by their flight and smallness in  size than quadrupeds. A number of species exist in the tract whose number  swells in the winter by swarms of migratory birds. Among the Babblers, the  Large Grey Babbler &lt;em&gt;(Tindoides malcolmi&lt;/em&gt;) is the common one. The Shrikes,  like the Large Grey Shrike &lt;em&gt;(Lanis excubitor&lt;/em&gt;), can be seen hawking insects among the main highways in the district and help to keep down the insect  population that crop-up during and after rains. The king-crow, Mynas  and Crows are always attendant on cattle snapping up insects. These and a  host of other birds like the Warblers, Bee-eaters, Hoopoes, Swifts etc., all  help in keeping down the insect population which would otherwise cause  untold harm to the crops. Vultures like the White-Breasted and Long-billed  keep the countryside clean of carcasses and are to be found practically all  over the area. The other predatory birds are the Eagles, Kites and owls  which keep the rodent population under check. Among the game birds,  mention may be made of Sandgrouse, Quails, Partridges, green pigeons and pigeons, which are trapped by local villagers and Yenadis. A large number  of water fowl visit the numerous tanks in the district in the winter season.  Mention may be made of various ducks like spot-bills, pintails and pochards.  The Chinnagottigallu tank in winter is always found with these ducks. Among  the teals, the whistling teals are found in all seasons while the cotton and  Blue-winged teals are found in other seasons. The paddy fields attract a number of Herons and Egrets at all times. The peacock (&lt;em&gt;Pavo cristatus&lt;/em&gt;)  is present still in Tirupati, Bhakarapet, Madanapalli and Palamaner Ranges,  and quite often it may be seen crossing the Tirumala ghat road in the evening  between the 6th and 7th mile. Parakeets, grey jungle fowls, and Weaver birds are also found in plenty in all the class-I reserves in the district.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 Reptiles</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/15_Reptiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/01_GEOGRAPHICAL_BASIS/15_Reptiles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A number of poisonous as well as non-poisonous snakes are found in  the district. Most common among the poisonous are the cobra which is often  revered by Hindus and milk offered into the anthills during Nagulachavithi  festival. Russell&amp;rsquo;s viper (&lt;em&gt;Vipera russelli&lt;/em&gt;) and Krait (&lt;em&gt;Bungarus fasciatus&lt;/em&gt;) are also common in the area. The python (&lt;em&gt;Python molurus&lt;/em&gt;) is reported to be  present in the interior Class-I forests though it is seldom seen: The other  non-poisonous snakes like rat snake (&lt;em&gt;Ptyas mucosa&lt;/em&gt;), sand boa (&lt;em&gt;Eryx johni&lt;/em&gt;), the Green snake (&lt;em&gt;Tropidonotus&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;stolatus&lt;/em&gt;), water snake (&lt;em&gt;Tropidonus&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;coton&lt;/em&gt;)  etc., are to be found commonly in and around the villages performing the  very useful function of keeping down the rodent population.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
