<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०५ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०५ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how King Priyavrata enjoyed royal opulence and majesty and then returned to full knowledge. King Priyavrata was detached from worldly opulence, and then he became attached to his kingdom, but finally he again became detached from material enjoyment and thus achieved liberation. When King Parīkṣit heard about this, he was struck with wonder, but he was somewhat bewildered as to how a devotee with no attachment for material enjoyment could later become attached to it. Thus in astonishment he questioned Śukadeva Gosvāmī about this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, the character of Mahārāja Āgnīdhra is described. When Mahārāja Priyavrata went off for spiritual realization, his son Āgnīdhra became the ruler of Jambūdvīpa, in accordance with Mahārāja Priyavrata’s instructions, and maintained its residents with the same affection a father feels for his sons. Once Mahārāja Āgnīdhra desired to have a son, and therefore he entered a cave of Mandara Mountain to practice austerity. Understanding his desire, Lord Brahmā sent a celestial girl named Pūrvacitti to Āgnīdhra’s hermitage. After dressing herself very attractively, she presented herself before him with various feminine movements, and Āgnīdhra was naturally attracted to her. The girl’s actions, expressions, smile, sweet words and moving eyes were fascinating to him. Āgnīdhra was expert in flattery. Thus he attracted the celestial girl, who was pleased to accept him as her husband because of his mellifluous words. She enjoyed royal happiness with Āgnīdhra for many years before returning to her abode in the heavenly planets. In her womb Āgnīdhra begot nine sons — Nābhi, Kiṁpuruṣa, Harivarṣa, Ilāvṛta, Ramyaka, Hiraṇmaya, Kuru, Bhadrāśva and Ketumāla. He gave them nine islands with names corresponding to theirs. Āgnīdhra, however, his senses unsatisfied, was always thinking of his celestial wife, and therefore in his next life he was born in her celestial planet. After the death of Āgnīdhra, his nine sons married nine daughters of Meru named Merudevī, Pratirūpā, Ugradaṁṣṭrī, Latā, Ramyā, Śyāmā, Nārī, Bhadrā and Devavīti.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the spotless character of King Nābhi, the oldest son of Āgnīdhra, is described. Wanting to have sons, Mahārāja Nābhi underwent severe austerities and penances. He performed many sacrifices along with his wife and worshiped Lord Viṣṇu, master of all sacrifices. Being very kind to His devotees, the Supreme Personality of Godhead was very pleased with the austerities of Mahārāja Nābhi. He personally appeared before the King in His four-handed feature, and the priests who were performing the sacrifices, began to offer their prayers unto Him. They prayed for a son like the Lord, and Lord Viṣṇu agreed to take birth in the womb of Merudevī, the wife of King Nābhi, and incarnate as King Ṛṣabhadeva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Ṛṣabhadeva, the son of Mahārāja Nābhi, begot a hundred sons, and during the reign of those sons the world was very happy in all respects. When Ṛṣabhadeva appeared as the son of Mahārāja Nābhi, He was appreciated by the people as the most exalted and beautiful personality of that age. His poise, influence, strength, enthusiasm, bodily luster and other transcendental qualities were beyond compare. The word &lt;em&gt;ṛṣabha&lt;/em&gt; refers to the best, or the supreme. Due to the superexcellent attributes of the son of Mahārāja Nābhi, the King named his son Ṛṣabha, or “the best.” His influence was incomparable. Although there was a scarcity of rain, Ṛṣabhadeva did not care for Indra, the King of heaven, who is in charge of supplying rain. Through His own potency, Ṛṣabhadeva sumptuously covered Ajanābha with ample rain. Upon receiving Ṛṣabhadeva, who is the Supreme Personality of Godhead, as his son, King Nābhi began to raise Him very carefully. After that, he entrusted the ruling power to Him and, retiring from family life, lived at Badarikāśrama completely engaged in the worship of Vāsudeva, the Supreme Lord. To follow social customs, Lord Ṛṣabhadeva for a while became a student in the &lt;em&gt;gurukula,&lt;/em&gt; and after returning, He followed the orders of His &lt;em&gt;guru&lt;/em&gt; and accepted a wife named Jayantī, who had been given to Him by the King of heaven, Indra. He begot a hundred sons in the womb of Jayantī. Of these hundred sons, the eldest was known as Bharata. Since the reign of Mahārāja Bharata, this planet has been called Bhārata-varṣa. Ṛṣabhadeva’s other sons were headed by Kuśāvarta, Ilāvarta, Brahmāvarta, Malaya, Ketu, Bhadrasena, Indraspṛk, Vidarbha and Kīkaṭa. There were also other sons named Kavi, Havi, Antarikṣa, Prabuddha, Pippalāyana, Āvirhotra, Drumila, Camasa and Karabhājana. Instead of ruling the kingdom, these nine became mendicant preachers of Kṛṣṇa consciousness, following the religious precepts of the &lt;em&gt;Bhāgavatam.&lt;/em&gt; Their characteristics and activities are described in the Eleventh Canto of &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam&lt;/em&gt; during the talks between Vasudeva and Nārada at Kurukṣetra. To teach the general populace, King Ṛṣabhadeva performed many sacrifices and taught His sons how to rule the citizens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter there is a description of &lt;em&gt;bhāgavata-dharma,&lt;/em&gt; religious principles in devotional service that transcend religious principles for liberation and the mitigation of material misery. It is stated in this chapter that a human being should not work hard like dogs and hogs for sense gratification. The human life is especially meant for the revival of our relationship with the Supreme Lord, and to this end all kinds of austerities and penances should be accepted. By austere activities, one’s heart can be cleansed of material contamination, and as a result one can be situated on the spiritual platform. To attain this perfection, one has to take shelter of a devotee and serve him. Then the door of liberation will be open. Those who are materially attached to women and sense gratification gradually become entangled in material consciousness and suffer the miseries of birth, old age, disease and death. Those who are engaged in the general welfare of all and who are not attached to children and family are called &lt;em&gt;mahātmās.&lt;/em&gt; Those who are engaged in sense gratification, who act piously or impiously, cannot understand the purpose of the soul. Therefore they should approach a highly elevated devotee and accept him as a spiritual master. By his association, one will be able to understand the purpose of life. Under the instructions of such a spiritual master, one can attain devotional service to the Lord, detachment from material things, and tolerance of material misery and distress. One can then see all living entities equally, and one becomes very eager to know about transcendental subject matters. Endeavoring persistently for the satisfaction of Kṛṣṇa, one becomes detached from wife, children and home. He is not interested in wasting time. In this way one becomes self-realized. A person advanced in spiritual knowledge does not engage anyone in material activity. And one who cannot deliver another person by instructing him in devotional service should not become a spiritual master, father, mother, demigod or husband. Instructing His one hundred sons, Lord Ṛṣabhadeva advised them to accept their eldest brother, Bharata, as their guide and lord, and thereby serve him. Of all living entities, the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; are the best, and above the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; the Vaiṣṇavas are situated in an even better position. Serving a Vaiṣṇava means serving the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Thus Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes the characteristics of Bharata Mahārāja and the sacrificial performance executed by Lord Ṛṣabhadeva for the instruction of the general populace.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter tells how Lord Ṛṣabhadeva left His body. He was not attached to His body even when it was being burned up in a forest fire. When the seed of fruitive activity is burned by the fire of knowledge, the spiritual properties and mystic powers are automatically manifest, yet &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga&lt;/em&gt; is not affected by these mystic powers. An ordinary &lt;em&gt;yogī&lt;/em&gt; is captivated by mystic powers and his progress checked; therefore a perfect &lt;em&gt;yogī&lt;/em&gt; does not welcome them. Because the mind is restless and undependable, it must remain always under control. Even the mind of the advanced &lt;em&gt;yogī&lt;/em&gt; Saubhari created such a disturbance that he lost his yogic mystic powers. Due to a restless mind, even a very advanced &lt;em&gt;yogī&lt;/em&gt; can fall down. The mind is so restless that it induces even a perfect &lt;em&gt;yogī&lt;/em&gt; to be controlled by the senses. Therefore Lord Ṛṣabhadeva, for the instruction of all &lt;em&gt;yogīs,&lt;/em&gt; showed the process of quitting the body. While traveling in South India, through the provinces of Karṇāṭa, Koṅka, Veṅka and Kuṭaka, Lord Ṛṣabhadeva arrived in the neighborhood of Kuṭakācala. Suddenly there was a forest fire that burned the forest and Lord Ṛṣabhadeva’s body to ashes. The pastimes of Lord Ṛṣabhadeva as a liberated soul were known by the King of Koṅka, Veṅka and Kuṭaka. This King’s name was Arhat. He later became captivated by the illusory energy, and in this condition he set forth the basic principles of Jainism. Lord Ṛṣabhadeva set forth the principles of religion that can free one from material bondage, and He put an end to all kinds of atheistic activities. On this earth, the place known as Bhārata-varṣa was a very pious land because the Supreme Lord appeared there when He wanted to incarnate.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, the activities of King Bharata Mahārāja, the emperor of the whole world, are described. Bharata Mahārāja performed various ritualistic ceremonies (Vedic &lt;em&gt;yajñas&lt;/em&gt;) and satisfied the Supreme Lord by his different modes of worship. In due course of time, he left home and resided in Hardwar and passed his days in devotional activities. Being ordered by his father, Lord Ṛṣabhadeva, Bharata Mahārāja married Pañcajanī, the daughter of Viśvarūpa. After this, he ruled the whole world peacefully. Formerly this planet was known as Ajanābha, and after the reign of Bharata Mahārāja it became known as Bhārata-varṣa. Bharata Mahārāja begot five sons in the womb of Pañcajanī, and he named the sons Sumati, Rāṣṭrabhṛta, Sudarśana, Āvaraṇa and Dhūmraketu. Bharata Mahārāja was very rigid in executing religious principles and following in the footsteps of his father. He therefore ruled the citizens very successfully. Because he performed various &lt;em&gt;yajñas&lt;/em&gt; to satisfy the Supreme Lord, he was personally very satisfied. Being of undisturbed mind, he increased his devotional activities unto Lord Vāsudeva. Bharata Mahārāja was competent in understanding the principles of saintly persons like Nārada, and he followed in the footsteps of the sages. He also kept Lord Vāsudeva constantly within his heart. After finishing his kingly duties, he divided his kingdom among his five sons. He then left home and went to the place of Pulaha known as Pulahāśrama. There he ate forest vegetables and fruits, and worshiped Lord Vāsudeva with everything available. Thus he increased his devotion toward Vāsudeva, and he automatically began to realize further his transcendental, blissful life. Due to his highly advanced spiritual position, there were sometimes visible in his body the &lt;em&gt;aṣṭa-sāttvika&lt;/em&gt; transformations, such as ecstatic crying and bodily trembling, which are symptoms of love of Godhead. It is understood that Mahārāja Bharata worshiped the Supreme Lord with the &lt;em&gt;mantras&lt;/em&gt; mentioned in the &lt;em&gt;Ṛg Veda,&lt;/em&gt; generally known as Gāyatrī &lt;em&gt;mantra,&lt;/em&gt; which aim at the Supreme Nārāyaṇa situated within the sun.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Although Bharata Mahārāja was very elevated, he fell down due to his attachment to a young deer. One day after Bharata Mahārāja had taken his bath as usual in the river Gaṇḍakī and was chanting his &lt;em&gt;mantra,&lt;/em&gt; he saw a pregnant deer come to the river to drink water. Suddenly there could be heard the thundering roar of a lion, and the deer was so frightened that it immediately gave birth to its calf. It then crossed the river, but died immediately thereafter. Mahārāja Bharata took compassion upon the motherless calf, rescued it from the water, took it to his &lt;em&gt;āśrama&lt;/em&gt; and cared for it affectionately. He gradually became attached to this young deer and always thought of it affectionately. As it grew up, it became Mahārāja Bharata’s constant companion, and he always took care of it. Gradually he became so absorbed in thinking of this deer that his mind became agitated. As he became more attached to the deer, his devotional service slackened. Although he was able to give up his opulent kingdom, he became attached to the deer. Thus he fell down from his mystic &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt; practice. Once when the deer was absent, Mahārāja Bharata was so disturbed that he began to search for it. While searching and lamenting the deer’s absence, Mahārāja Bharata fell down and died. Because his mind was fully absorbed thinking of the deer, he naturally took his next birth from the womb of a deer. However, because he was considerably advanced spiritually, he did not forget his past activities, even though he was in the body of a deer. He could understand how he had fallen down from his exalted position, and remembering this, he left his mother deer and again went to Pulaha-āśrama. He finally ended his fruitive activities in the form of a deer, and when he died he was released from the deer’s body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Bharata Mahārāja’s attainment of the body of a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; is described. In this body he remained like one dull, deaf and dumb, so much so that when he was brought before the goddess Kālī to be killed as a sacrifice, he never protested but remained silent. After having given up the body of a deer, he took birth in the womb of the youngest wife of a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa.&lt;/em&gt; In this life he could also remember the activities of his past life, and in order to avoid the influence of society, he remained like a deaf and dumb person. He was very careful not to fall down again. He did not mix with anyone who was not a devotee. This process should be adopted by every devotee. As advised by Śrī Caitanya Mahāprabhu: &lt;em&gt;asat-saṅga-tyāga — ei vaiṣṇava-ācāra.&lt;/em&gt; One should strictly avoid the company of nondevotees, even though they may be family members. When Bharata Mahārāja was in the body of a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa,&lt;/em&gt; the people in the neighborhood thought of him as a crazy, dull fellow, but within he was always chanting and remembering Vāsudeva, the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Although his father wanted to give him an education and purify him as a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; by offering him the sacred thread, he remained in such a way that his father and mother could understand that he was crazy and not interested in the reformatory method. Nonetheless, he remained fully Kṛṣṇa conscious, even without undergoing such official ceremonies. Due to his silence, some people who were no better than animals began to tease him in many ways, but he tolerated this. After the death of his father and mother, his stepmother and stepbrothers began to treat him very poorly. They would give him the most condemned food, but still he did not mind; he remained completely absorbed in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. He was ordered by his stepbrothers and mother to guard a paddy field one night, and at that time the leader of a dacoit party took him away and tried to kill him by offering him as a sacrifice before Bhadra Kālī. When the dacoits brought Bharata Mahārāja before the goddess Kālī and raised a chopper to kill him, the goddess Kālī became immediately alarmed due to the mistreatment of a devotee. She came out of the deity and, taking the chopper in her own hands, killed all the dacoits there. Thus a pure devotee of the Supreme Personality of Godhead can remain silent despite the mistreatment of nondevotees. Rogues and dacoits who misbehave toward a devotee are punished at last by the arrangement of the Supreme Personality of Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Bharata Mahārāja, now Jaḍa Bharata, was successfully accepted by King Rahūgaṇa, ruler of the states known as Sindhu and Sauvīra. The King forced Jaḍa Bharata to carry his palanquin and chastised him because he did not carry it properly. A carrier of King Rahūgaṇa’s palanquin was needed, and to fulfill this need the chief carriers found Jaḍa Bharata as the most likely person to do the work. He was therefore forced to carry the palanquin. Jaḍa Bharata, however, did not protest this proud order, but humbly accepted the job and carried the palanquin. While carrying it, however, he was very careful to see that he did not step on an ant, and whenever he saw one he would stop until the ant had passed. Because of this, he could not keep pace with the other carriers. The King within the palanquin became very disturbed and chastised Jaḍa Bharata with filthy language, but Jaḍa Bharata, being completely freed from the bodily conception, did not protest; he proceeded carrying the palanquin. When he continued as before, the King threatened him with punishment, and being threatened by the King, Jaḍa Bharata began to talk. He protested against the filthy language used by the King when the King chastised him, and the King, hearing the instructions of Jaḍa Bharata, was awakened to his real knowledge. When he came to his consciousness, he understood that he had offended a great, learned and saintly person. At that time he very humbly and respectfully prayed to Jaḍa Bharata. He now wanted to understand the deep meaning of the philosophical words used by Jaḍa Bharata, and with great sincerity he begged his pardon. He admitted that if one offends the lotus feet of a pure devotee he is certainly punished by the trident of Lord Śiva.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; Jaḍa Bharata instructs Mahārāja Rahūgaṇa in detail. He tells the King: “You are not very experienced, yet you pose yourself as a learned person because you are very proud of your knowledge. Actually a person who is on the transcendental platform does not care for social behavior that sacrifices spiritual advancement. Social behavior comes within the jurisdiction of &lt;em&gt;karma-kāṇḍa,&lt;/em&gt; material benefit. No one can spiritually advance by such activities. The conditioned soul is always overpowered by the modes of material nature, and consequently he is simply concerned with material benefits and auspicious and inauspicious material things. In other words, the mind, which is the leader of the senses, is absorbed in material activities life after life. Thus he continuously gets different types of bodies and suffers miserable material conditions. On the basis of mental concoction, social behavior has been formulated. If one’s mind is absorbed in these activities, he certainly remains conditioned within the material world. According to different opinions, there are eleven or twelve mental activities, which can be transformed into hundreds and thousands. A person who is not Kṛṣṇa conscious is subjected to all these mental concoctions and is thus governed by the material energy. The living entity who is free from mental concoctions attains the platform of pure spirit soul, devoid of material contamination. There are two types of living entities: &lt;em&gt;jīvātmā&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Paramātmā,&lt;/em&gt; the individual soul and the Supreme Soul. That Supreme Soul in His ultimate realization is Lord Vāsudeva, Kṛṣṇa. He enters into everyone’s heart and controls the living entity in his different activities. He is therefore the supreme shelter of all living entities. One can understand the Supreme Soul and one’s position in relationship with Him when one is completely freed from the unwanted association of ordinary men. In this way one can become fit to cross the ocean of nescience. The cause of conditional life is attachment to the external energy. One has to conquer these mental concoctions: unless one does so, he will never be freed from material anxieties. Although mental concoctions have no value, their influence is still very formidable. No one should neglect to control the mind. If one does, the mind becomes so powerful that one immediately forgets his real position. Forgetting that he is an eternal servant of Kṛṣṇa and that service to Kṛṣṇa is his only business, one is doomed by material nature to serve the objects of the senses. One should kill mental concoctions by the sword of service to the Supreme Personality of Godhead and His devotee (&lt;em&gt;guru-kṛṣṇa-prasāde pāya bhakti-latā-bīja&lt;/em&gt;).”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Because Mahārāja Rahūgaṇa was still doubtful about his enlightenment, he asked the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; Jaḍa Bharata to repeat his instructions and clarify ideas he could not understand. In this chapter, Mahārāja Rahūgaṇa offers his respectful obeisances to Jaḍa Bharata, who was concealing his real position. The King could understand by his speech how exalted and advanced he was in spiritual knowledge. He very much regretted his offense against him. Mahārāja Rahūgaṇa was bitten by the serpent of ignorance, but was cured by the nectarean words of Jaḍa Bharata. Later, because he was doubtful about the subjects discussed, he made further inquiries, one question after another. First he wanted to be released from the offense he had committed at the lotus feet of Jaḍa Bharata.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; Jaḍa Bharata became very kind to King Rahūgaṇa, and to disassociate him from the material world, he spoke figuratively of the forest of the material world. He explained that this material world is like a great forest in which one becomes entangled due to association with material life. In this forest there are plunderers (the six senses) as well as carnivorous animals like jackals, wolves and lions (wife, children and other relatives) who are always anxious to suck the blood from the head of the family. The forest plunderers and the carnivorous blood-sucking animals combine to exploit the energy of a man within this material world. In this forest there is also a black hole, covered by grass, into which one may fall. Coming into the forest and being captivated by so many material attractions, one identifies himself with this material world, society, friendship, love and family. Having lost the path and not knowing where to go, being harassed by animals and birds, one is also victimized by many desires. Thus one works very hard within the forest and wanders here and there. He becomes captivated by temporary happiness and becomes aggrieved by so-called distress. Actually one simply suffers in the forest from so-called happiness and distress. Sometimes he is attacked by a snake (deep sleep), and due to the snakebite he loses consciousness and becomes puzzled and bewildered about discharging his duties. Sometimes he is attracted by women other than his wife, and thus be thinks he enjoys extramarital love with another woman. He is attacked by various diseases, by lamentation and by summer and winter. Thus one within the forest of the material world suffers the pains of material existence. Expecting to become happy, the living entity changes his position from one place to another, but actually a materialistic person within the material world is never happy. Being constantly engaged in materialistic activities, he is always disturbed. He forgets that one day he has to die. Although he suffers severely, being illusioned by the material energy, he still hankers after material happiness. In this way he completely forgets his relationship with the Supreme Personality of Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The direct meaning of the forest of material existence is given in this chapter. Merchants sometimes enter the forest to collect many rare things and sell them at a good profit in the city, but the forest path is always bedecked with dangers. When the pure soul wants to give up the Lord’s service to enjoy the material world, Kṛṣṇa certainly gives him a chance to enter the material world. As stated in the &lt;em&gt;Prema-vivarta:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;kṛṣṇa-bahirmukha hañā bhoga vāñchā kare.&lt;/em&gt; This is the reason the pure spirit soul falls down to the material world. Due to his activities under the influence of the three modes of material nature, the living entity takes different positions in different species. Sometimes he is a demigod in the heavenly planets and sometimes a most insignificant creature in the lower planetary systems. In this regard, Śrīla Narottama dāsa Ṭhākura says, &lt;em&gt;nānā yoni sadā phire:&lt;/em&gt; the living entity passes through various species. &lt;em&gt;Kardarya bhakṣaṇa kare:&lt;/em&gt; he is obliged to eat and enjoy abominable things. &lt;em&gt;Tāra janma adhaḥ-pāte yāya:&lt;/em&gt; in this way his whole life is spoiled. Without the protection of an all-merciful Vaiṣṇava, the conditioned soul cannot get out of the clutches of &lt;em&gt;māyā.&lt;/em&gt; As stated in &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad-gītā&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;manaḥ ṣaṣṭhānīndriyāṇi prakṛti-sthāni karṣati&lt;/em&gt;), the living entity begins material life with his mind and the five knowledge-acquiring senses, and with these he struggles for existence within the material world. These senses are compared to rogues and thieves within the forest. They take away a man’s knowledge and place him in a network of nescience. Thus the senses are like rogues and thieves that plunder his spiritual knowledge. Over and above this, there are family members, wife and children, who are exactly like ferocious animals in the forest. The business of such ferocious animals is to eat a man’s flesh. The living entity allows himself to be attacked by jackals and foxes (wife and children), and thus his real spiritual life is finished. In the forest of material life, everyone is envious like mosquitoes, and rats and mice are always creating disturbances. Everyone in this material world is placed in many awkward positions and surrounded by envious people and disturbing animals. The result is that the living entity in the material world is always plundered and bitten by many living entities. Nonetheless, despite these disturbances, he does not want to give up his family life, and he continues his fruitive activities in an attempt to become happy in the future. He thus becomes more and more entangled in the results of &lt;em&gt;karma,&lt;/em&gt; and thus he is forced to act impiously. His witnesses are the sun during the day and the moon during the night. The demigods also witness, but the conditioned soul thinks that his attempts at sense gratification are not being witnessed by anyone. Sometimes, when he is detected, he temporarily renounces everything, but due to his great attachment for the body, his renunciation is given up before he can attain perfection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the descendants of Bharata Mahārāja and many other kings are described. The son of Mahārāja Bharata was named Sumati. He followed the path of liberation given by Ṛṣabhadeva. Some people mistakenly thought Sumati to be the direct incarnation of Lord Buddha. The son of Sumati was Devatājit, and his son was Devadyumna. Devadyumna’s son was Parameṣṭhī, and his son was Pratīha. Pratīha was a very great devotee of Lord Viṣṇu, and he had three sons, named Pratihartā, Prastotā and Udgātā. Pratihartā had two sons, Aja and Bhūmā. The son of Bhūmā was Udgītha, and the son of Udgītha was Prastāva. The son of Prastāva was Vibhu, and the son of Vibhu was Pṛthuṣeṇa, whose son was Nakta. The wife of Nakta, Druti, gave birth to Gaya, who was a very famous and saintly king. Actually King Gaya was a partial incarnation of Lord Viṣṇu, and because of his great devotion to Lord Viṣṇu he received the title Mahāpuruṣa. King Gaya had sons named Citraratha, Sumati and Avarodhana. The son of Citraratha was the emperor Samrāṭ, and his son was Marīci, whose son was Bindu. Bindu’s son was Madhu, and Madhu’s son was Vīravrata. Vīravrata’s two sons were Manthu and Pramanthu, and the son of Manthu was Bhauvana. The son of Bhauvana was Tvaṣṭā, and the son of Tvaṣṭā was Viraja, who glorified the whole dynasty. Viraja had one hundred sons and one daughter. Of these, the son named Śatajit became very famous.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While describing the character of Mahārāja Priyavrata and his descendants, Śukadeva Gosvāmī also described Meru Mountain and the planetary system known as Bhū-maṇḍala. Bhū-maṇḍala is like a lotus flower, and its seven islands are compared to the whorl of the lotus. The place known as Jambūdvīpa is in the middle of that whorl. In Jambūdvīpa there is a mountain known as Sumeru, which is made of solid gold. The height of this mountain is 84,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas,&lt;/em&gt; of which 16,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; are below the earth. Its width is estimated to be 32,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; at its summit and 16,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; at its foot. (One &lt;em&gt;yojana&lt;/em&gt; equals approximately eight miles.) This king of mountains, Sumeru, is the support of the planet earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Seventeenth Chapter describes the origin of the Ganges River and how it flows in and around Ilāvṛta-varṣa. There is also a description of the prayers Lord Śiva offers to Lord Saṅkarṣaṇa, part of the quadruple expansions of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Lord Viṣṇu once approached Bali Mahārāja while the King was performing a sacrifice. The Lord appeared before him as Trivikrama, or Vāmana, and begged alms from the King in the form of three steps of land. With two steps, Lord Vāmana covered all three planetary systems and pierced the covering of the universe with the toes of His left foot. A few drops of water from the Causal Ocean leaked through this hole and fell on the head of Lord Śiva, where they remained for one thousand millenniums. These drops of water are the sacred Ganges River. It first flows onto the heavenly planets, which are located on the soles of Lord Viṣṇu’s feet. The Ganges River is known by many names, such as the Bhāgīrathī and the Jāhnavī. It purifies Dhruvaloka and the planets of the seven sages because both Dhruva and the sages have no other desire than to serve the Lord’s lotus feet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes the different &lt;em&gt;varṣas&lt;/em&gt; of Jambūdvīpa and the incarnation of the Supreme Lord worshiped in each. The predominating ruler of Bhadrāśva-varṣa is Bhadraśravā. He and his many servants always worship the incarnation known as Lord Hayagrīva. At the end of each &lt;em&gt;kalpa,&lt;/em&gt; when the demon Ajñāna steals the Vedic knowledge, Lord Hayagrīva appears and preserves it. Then He delivers it to Lord Brahmā. In the land known as Hari-varṣa, the exalted devotee Prahlāda Mahārāja worships Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva. (The appearance of Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva is described in the Seventh Canto of &lt;em&gt;Śrīmad-Bhāgavatam.&lt;/em&gt;) Following in the footsteps of Prahlāda Mahārāja, the inhabitants of Hari-varṣa always worship Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva to receive from Him the benediction of being engaged in His loving service. In the tract of land known as Ketumāla-varṣa, the Supreme Personality of Godhead (Lord Hṛṣīkeśa) appears in the form of Cupid. The goddess of fortune and the demigods living there engage in His service day and night. Manifesting Himself in sixteen parts, Lord Hṛṣīkeśa is the source of all encouragement, strength and influence. The conditioned living entity has the defect of being always fearful, but simply by the mercy of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, he can rid himself of this defect of material life. Therefore the Lord alone can be addressed as master. In the tract of land known as Ramyaka-varṣa, Manu and all the inhabitants worship Matsyadeva to this very day. Matsyadeva, whose form is pure goodness, is the ruler and maintainer of the whole universe, and as such He is the director of all the demigods, headed by King Indra. In Hiraṇmaya-varṣa Lord Viṣṇu has assumed the form of a tortoise (Kūrma &lt;em&gt;mūrti&lt;/em&gt;) and is worshiped there by Aryamā, along with all the other residents. Similarly, in the tract of land known as Uttarakuru-varṣa, Lord Śrī Hari has assumed the form of a boar, and in that form He accepts service from all the inhabitants living there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the glories of Bhārata-varṣa, and it also describes how Lord Rāmacandra is being worshiped in the tract of land known as Kimpuruṣa-varṣa. The inhabitants of Kimpuruṣa-varṣa are fortunate because they worship Lord Rāmacandra with His faithful servant Hanumān. Lord Rāmacandra exemplifies an incarnation of Godhead who descends for the mission of &lt;em&gt;paritrāṇāya sādhūnāṁ vināśāya ca duṣkṛtām&lt;/em&gt; — protecting the devotees and destroying the miscreants. Lord Rāmacandra exhibits the actual purpose of an incarnation of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, and the devotees take the opportunity to offer loving transcendental service to Him. One should surrender fully to the Lord, forgetting one’s so-called material happiness, opulence and education, which are not at all useful for pleasing the Lord. The Lord is pleased only by the process of surrender unto Him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter there is a description of various islands, beginning with Plakṣadvīpa, and the oceans that surround them. There is also a description of the location and dimensions of the mountain known as Lokāloka. The island of Plakṣadvīpa is twice as broad as Jambūdvīpa, which is surrounded by an ocean of salt water. The master of this island is Idhmajihva, one of the sons of Mahārāja Priyavrata. The island is divided into seven regions, each with a mountain and a large river.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter informs us of the movements of the sun. The sun is not stationary; it is also moving like the other planets. The sun’s movements determine the duration of night and day. When the sun travels north of the equator, it moves slowly during the day and very quickly at night, thus increasing the duration of the daytime and decreasing the duration of night. Similarly, when the sun travels south of the equator, the exact opposite is true — the duration of the day decreases, and the duration of night increases. When the sun enters Karkaṭa-rāśi (Cancer) and then travels to Siṁha-rāśi (Leo) and so on through Dhanuḥ-rāśi (Sagittarius), its course is called Dakṣiṇāyana, the southern way, and when the sun enters Makara-rāśi (Capricorn) and thereafter travels through Kumbharāśi (Aquarius) and so on through Mithuna-rāśi (Gemini), its course is called Uttarāyaṇa, the northern way. When the sun is in Meṣa-rāśi (Aries) and Tulā-rāśi (Libra), the duration of day and night are equal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the orbits of the planets are described. According to the movements of the moon and other planets, all the inhabitants of the universe are prone to auspicious and inauspicious situations. This is referred to as the influence of the stars.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sun-god, who controls the affairs of the entire universe, especially in regard to heat, light, seasonal changes and so on, is considered an expansion of Nārāyaṇa. He represents the three &lt;em&gt;Vedas — Ṛg, Yajur&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sāma&lt;/em&gt; — and therefore he is known as Trayīmaya, the form of Lord Nārāyaṇa. Sometimes the sun-god is also called Sūrya Nārāyaṇa. The sun-god has expanded himself in twelve divisions, and thus he controls the six seasonal changes and causes winter, summer, rain and so on. &lt;em&gt;Yogīs&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;karmīs&lt;/em&gt; following the &lt;em&gt;varṇāśrama&lt;/em&gt; institution, who practice &lt;em&gt;haṭha&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;aṣṭāṅga-yoga&lt;/em&gt; or who perform &lt;em&gt;agnihotra&lt;/em&gt; sacrifices, worship Sūrya Nārāyaṇa for their own benefit. The demigod Sūrya is always in touch with the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Nārāyaṇa. Residing in outer space, which is in the middle of the universe, between Bhūloka and Bhuvarloka, the sun rotates through the time circle of the zodiac, represented by twelve &lt;em&gt;rāśis,&lt;/em&gt; or signs, and assumes different names according to the sign he is in. For the moon, every month is divided into two fortnights. Similarly, according to solar calculations, a month is equal to the time the sun spends in one constellation; two months constitute one season, and there are twelve months in a year. The entire area of the sky is divided into two halves, each representing an &lt;em&gt;ayana,&lt;/em&gt; the course traversed by the sun within a period of six months. The sun travels sometimes slowly, sometimes swiftly and sometimes at a moderate speed. In this way it travels within the three worlds, consisting of the heavenly planets, the earthly planets and outer space. These orbits are referred to by great learned scholars by the names Saṁvatsara, Parivatsara, Iḍāvatsara, Anuvatsara and Vatsara.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how all the planetary systems take shelter of the polestar, Dhruvaloka. It also describes the totality of these planetary systems to be Śiśumāra, another expansion of the external body of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Dhruvaloka, the abode of Lord Viṣṇu within this universe, is situated 1,300,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; from the seven stars. In the planetary system of Dhruvaloka are the planets of the fire-god, Indra, Prajāpati, Kaśyapa and Dharma, all of whom are very respectful to the great devotee Dhruva, who lives on the polestar. Like bulls yoked to a central pivot, all the planetary systems revolve around Dhruvaloka, impelled by eternal time. Those who worship the &lt;em&gt;virāṭ-puruṣa,&lt;/em&gt; the universal form of the Lord, conceive of this entire rotating system of planets as an animal known as &lt;em&gt;śiśumāra.&lt;/em&gt; This imaginary &lt;em&gt;śiśumāra&lt;/em&gt; is another form of the Lord. The head of the &lt;em&gt;śiśumāra&lt;/em&gt; form is downward, and its body appears like that of a coiled snake. On the end of its tail is Dhruvaloka, on the body of the tail are Prajāpati, Agni, Indra and Dharma, and on the root of the tail are Dhātā and Vidhātā. On its waist are the seven great sages. The entire body of the &lt;em&gt;śiśumāra&lt;/em&gt; faces toward its right and appears like a coil of stars. On the right side of this coil are the fourteen prominent stars from Abhijit to Punarvasu, and on the left side are the fourteen prominent stars from Puṣyā to Uttarāṣāḍhā. The stars known as Punarvasu and Puṣyā are on the right and left hips of the &lt;em&gt;śiśumāra,&lt;/em&gt; and the stars known as Ārdrā and Aśleṣā are on the right and left feet of the &lt;em&gt;śiśumāra.&lt;/em&gt; Other stars are also fixed on different sides of the Śiśumāra planetary system according to the calculations of Vedic astronomers. To concentrate their minds, &lt;em&gt;yogīs&lt;/em&gt; worship the Śiśumāra planetary system, which is technically known as the &lt;em&gt;kuṇḍalini-cakra.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the planet Rāhu, which is 10,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; (80,000 miles) below the sun, and it also describes Atala and the other lower planetary systems. Rāhu is situated below the sun and moon. It is between these two planets and the earth. When Rāhu conceals the sun and moon, eclipses occur, either total or partial, depending on whether Rāhu moves in a straight or curving way.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Below Rāhu by another 1,000,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; are the planets of the Siddhas, Cāraṇas and Vidyādharas, and below these are planets such as Yakṣaloka and Rakṣaloka. Below these planets is the earth, and 70,000 &lt;em&gt;yojanas&lt;/em&gt; below the earth are the lower planetary systems — Atala, Vitala, Sutala, Talātala, Mahātala, Rasātala and Pātāla. Demons and Rakṣasas live in these lower planetary systems with their wives and children, always engaged in sense gratification and not fearing their next births. The sunshine does not reach these planets, but they are illuminated by jewels fixed upon the hoods of snakes. Because of these shining gems there is practically no darkness. Those living in these planets do not become old or diseased, and they are not afraid of death from any cause but the time factor, the Supreme Personality of Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes Ananta, the source of Lord Śiva. Lord Ananta, whose body is completely spiritual, resides at the root of the planet Pātāla. He always lives in the core of Lord Śiva’s heart, and He helps him destroy the universe. Ananta instructs Lord Śiva how to destroy the cosmos, and thus He is sometimes called &lt;em&gt;tāmasī,&lt;/em&gt; or “one who is in the mode of darkness.” He is the original Deity of material consciousness, and because He attracts all living entities, He is sometimes known as Saṅkarṣaṇa. The entire material world is situated on the hoods of Lord Saṅkarṣaṇa. From His forehead He transmits to Lord Śiva the power to destroy this material world. Because Lord Saṅkarṣaṇa is an expansion of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, many devotees offer Him prayers, and in the planetary system of Pātāla, all the &lt;em&gt;suras, asuras,&lt;/em&gt; Gandharvas, Vidyādharas and learned sages offer Him their respectful obeisances. The Lord talks with them in a sweet voice. His bodily construction is completely spiritual and very, very beautiful. Anyone who hears about Him from a proper spiritual master becomes free from all material conceptions of life. The entire material energy is working according to the plans of Anantadeva. Therefore we should regard Him as the root cause of the material creation. There is no end to His strength, and no one can fully describe Him, even with countless mouths. Therefore He is called Ananta (unlimited). Being very merciful toward all living entities, He has exhibited His spiritual body. Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes the glories of Anantadeva to Mahārāja Parīkṣit in this way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Twenty-sixth Chapter describes how a sinful man goes to different hells, where he is punished in various ways by the assistants of Yamarāja. As stated in the &lt;em&gt;Bhagavad-gītā&lt;/em&gt; (3.27):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;prakṛteḥ kriyamāṇāni&lt;br&gt;&#xA;guṇaiḥ karmāṇi sarvaśaḥ&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ahaṅkāra-vimūḍhātmā&lt;br&gt;&#xA;kartāham iti manyate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“The bewildered spirit soul, under the influence of the three modes of material nature, thinks himself to be the doer of activities, which are in actuality carried out by nature.” The foolish person thinks he is independent of any law. He thinks there is no God or regulative principle and that he can do whatever he likes. Thus he engages in different sinful activities, and as a result, he is put into different hellish conditions life after life, to be punished by the laws of nature. The basic principle of his suffering is that he foolishly thinks himself independent, although he is strictly under the control of the laws of material nature. These laws act due to the influence of the three modes of nature, and therefore each human being also works under three different types of influence. According to how he acts, he suffers different reactions in his next life or in this life. Religious persons act differently from atheists, and therefore they suffer different reactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/05/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-ten&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eleven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twelve&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fourteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventeen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nineteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
