<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;01 Ancient period on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;01 Ancient period on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 THE SACRED HILL OF TIRUVENGADAM FROM THE ANCIENT TIMES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/01_THE_SACRED_HILL_OF_TIRUVENGADAM_FROM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/01_THE_SACRED_HILL_OF_TIRUVENGADAM_FROM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In ancient Tamil literature the sacred shrine of Tirumala is referred to by the name Vengadam. This is generally understood to refer to the hill, though quite often the reference is as much to the territory surrounding it. The northern Vengadam or Vada Vengadam, is generally spoken of, in ancient Tamil literature as the northern boundary of the Tamil speaking country. Tolkappiyam, the most ancient classical Tamil grammar, which is said to be one of the oldest pieces of Tamil literature extant, defines the area where Tamil speaking people lived, as situated between the hill Vengadam in the north and the Kumari or the Cape Comorin in the south and between the seas in the east and in the west. Thus from very ancient days, the Tirumala hills have been recognised as the landmark through which the Tamil speaking people had to pass, to reach regions where Tamil was not spoken.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 TIRUMALA IN EARLY CLASSICAL TAMIL SANGAM LITERATURE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/02_TIRUMALA_IN_EARLY_CLASSICAL_TAMIL_SAN/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/02_TIRUMALA_IN_EARLY_CLASSICAL_TAMIL_SAN/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ancient classical Tamil literature known as Sangam literature consists of a number of collections of poems, which at one time must have been more generally current in Tamilnadu. Popularly, Sangams are divided into three Sangams, each of which has its own patron poets. These poems, as seen from their nature, seem to exhibit various modes of composition, displaying the poetic skill of the authors. The Sangam poetry, is thus mostly a collection of anthologies, put together from some of the excellent pieces of the composition of these ancient poets, to give typical illustrations of the various modes of composition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 TIRUPATI AND TIRUMALA NOT REFERRED TO AS HOLY SHRINE</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/03_TIRUPATI_AND_TIRUMALA_NOT_REFERRED_TO/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/03_TIRUPATI_AND_TIRUMALA_NOT_REFERRED_TO/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that in these ancient references, a number of authors of eminence, refer to Vengadam and give details of features which were regarded in those days as characteristics of the hill and the region surrounding it, but no specific reference to the great shrine which now dominates the entire area is given. Reference has already been made to poem 61 of Mamulanar, in which the celebration of the festivals is clearly referred to. This leads to the unmistakable inference about the existence of the temple there and the series of festivals connected with it. During the period of the Sangam literature therefore the importance is more to the sanctity of the hill, rather than to the temple, and the temple as such, had not yet taken over the importance which the hill had in this early age.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 ALVARS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/04_ALVARS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/04_ALVARS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;*(Circa 4th **Century A.D. **to Circa **9th Century A. D.) ***&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Prabandha Four Thousand,&amp;rsquo; the ancient Vaishnava piece of literature, is a collection of 4000 stanzas of Tamil poetry celebrating the 108 places of worship sacred to Lord Vishnu. These poems are attributed by tradition to a certain number of devotees, generally counted as twelve and called as Alvars. This literature throws considerable light on the early history of Tirumala. The whole body of this literature can be said to refer roughly to the five centuries from 300 to 800 A.D. Three of these are known as the first Alvars, described as the singers in classical Tamil (Sen Tamil) by Tirumangai Alvar, viz., Poygai alvar, Bhutam alvar and Pey alvar. One other alvar who follows viz., Tirumalisai alvar is also generally counted as one of the early alvars.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 POYGAI ALVAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/05_POYGAI_ALVAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/05_POYGAI_ALVAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first of these early alvars, Poygai Alvar is the author of the first *centum *of the last thousand of the Four Thousand in the prabhanda. He was notably a Vaishnava devotee but one who occupied a high place among the celebrities in Tamil literature. He has as many as twelve to fifteen direct references to Tirumala in the *centum *ascribed to him. He refers to this place as a sacred kshetra where Lord Vishnu had in his infinite grace manifested himself. Stanzas 5 and 74 clearly refer to the Lord and give description of the Lord&amp;rsquo;s features and the weapons that he holds. Stanza 26 refers to Tirumala, the saving grace of which is enjoyed by the Gods themselves. In stanza 37 there is a more explicit reference to Vengadam as a place acceptable to the God who blew the beautiful white conch, which receives constant worship from people of great learning who offer daily worship with incense, lamp, holy water etc., and who came from all directions to offer worship here.&amp;quot; There is a similar reference to Vengadam in stanza 39. Stanza 40 gives reference only to the secular feature of the place, where elephants are referred to as if threatened by the falling stars, in the belief that they were torches held by the Kuravars of that place. There is yet another reference in stanza 68. Stanza 76 refers to Tiruvengadam and, describes the God there as one who measured the earth (Vishnu-Trivikrama). Stanza 77 similarly refers to Vengadam where the Lord standing along with the other three places, Vinnagar, Vehka and Kovalur. The last reference to Tirumala is in stanza 99 where Lord Vishnu is spoken of as Eternal and being in the heart of everyone who is capable of thinking about him, and as habitually residing in the waters and on the hill of Vengadam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 BHUTAM ALVAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/06_BHUTAM_ALVAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/06_BHUTAM_ALVAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bhutam Alvar refers to Vengadam in eight places or stanzas directly. The first reference is in stanza 25 where the Lord is described as standing on the Hill at Tirumala. In stanzas 33, 45 and 46 there are general references to Tirumala and Vishnu. In stanza 70 reference is made to a number of Vishnu shrines, and in stanzas 72 and 75 also similar references are made. Stanza 28 equates the deity presiding in Vengadam to the deity presiding in Srirangam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 PEY ALVAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/07_PEY_ALVAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/07_PEY_ALVAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The next of the early Alvars, namely, Pey Alvar also refers to Vengadam in his verses. The first reference to Vengadam occurs in stanzas 14. In stanzas 26, 30 and 32 there are general references to Vengadam. He takes up the reference to Vengadam in 58 again, and comes up in the last line to the same references that the God in Vengadam is, &amp;ldquo;He who recovered the earth by the use of his acute intelligence,&amp;rdquo; referring to his having outwitted Mahabali and got him to grant the three feet of earth. In stanza 59, the Alvar gives expression to his satisfaction that he has attained to the correct way of gaining salvation, since he attaches himself in devotion to Vishnu. Similarly stanzas 69, 70, 71, 72, 73 and 75 have also general references to Vengadam While 69 and 70 only refer to some general features, 71 repeats almost in the same terms incidents referred to in stanza 68. In 72 there is the specific statement that Vengadam is the residence of the prince among the young&amp;quot; (Ilam-Kumarar-Koman). Stanza 73 has a reference to Vengadam but in general terms; 75 has similarly a general reference to Tirumalai as the hill of Vishnu-Krishna (Ayan, shepherd). Stanza 76 states definitely that, if one should offer flowers and fold his hands in worship before the God at Vehka, no consequences of evil deeds would come to him, and that one need not stand amidst hills, or dip into water, or otherwise perform penance by standing amidst the five fires. Stanzas 77 to 88 recommend single-minded devotion to Vishnu as the sole efficient way of getting rid of evil and attaining to salvation. 89 refers to Vengadam and states clearly &amp;ldquo;it is the hill of the One who applied his lips to the flute emitting sweet music&amp;rsquo; (meaning young Krishna). Stanzas 90 to 93 are general as usual, and 94 states that the Alvar succeeded in recapturing Him, who stands, sits or lies down (in various holy places) and in his own heart by the process of lighting the lamp of contemplation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 TIRUMALA IN SILAPPADHIKARAM</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/08_TIRUMALA_IN_SILAPPADHIKARAM/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/08_TIRUMALA_IN_SILAPPADHIKARAM/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Tamil classic Silappadhikaram, the author of which was not a Hindu refers in his work to Tirumala as a place of Vishnu shrine. Ilango Adigal, the author of this work describes Venkatesa on the Hill in the following terms in Book XI, lines 41 to 51:-&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    *&amp;quot;High on Vengadam&#39;s towering crest,  \&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;with flowing streams in flood,  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;Betwixt the effulgent glory, of shining Sun and Moon,  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;Like unto a blue cloud in lightning dres’st  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;In all the brilliance of rainbow dight,  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;The Red-eyed great One, majestic stands  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;In dress of flowery brilliance with garland bright,  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;One lotus hand with fearsome disc adorned,  &lt;br&gt;&#xA;and milk white conch (the other held).&amp;quot; *&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Tirumalisai Alvar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/09_Tirumalisai_Alvar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/09_Tirumalisai_Alvar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This Alvar had also composed 100 verses in honour of Vishnu. In stanzas 42 and 43 he mentions that both Brahma and Siva were among the worshippers at Vengadam.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first reference is in stanza 31. It is a bare reference to Vengadam along with the other Vaishnava place Kottiyur. There is a simple reference in stanza 39. There is a specific reference in 40 where it says that he was devoted to the God at Vengadam, who was constantly in his thought; “He is the beloved of Her who is described and quite extolled in the sciences, and I am inextricably caught in the net which is His feet.&amp;quot; There is a very interesting reference in 41 where he refers again to the holy One at Vengadam having entered his mind by being in residence at Vengadam. In describing this hill at Vengadam there are two points that are brought out. The first is the mountain streams running down scattering pearls. By implication there is also the rattle of the running stream. Another kind of sound that is referred to as the normal feature of Vengadam is the sound that arises from the celebration of the festivals on Onam days. This asterism is of course sacred to Vishnu, and is, in some form, attached to Vishnu as almost the asterism of his birth (one that has no birth). But the festival on this asterism is, in some respects, peculiar to Tirumala, and is also usual in shrines where the deity installed is Srinivasa, (the abode of the Goddess Lakshmi), which is the ordinary familiar name of the God at Tirumala. The most sacred day in the year at Tirumala is this Sravana in the month of Purva-Bhadra. The next stanza has reference to Vengadam where the Alvar exhorts peoples to go and offer worship at Vengadam as it permanently destroys the evils of Karma, and offers as inducement the fact that the lotus-born Brahma and the three-eyed Siva alike placed lotus flowers at the feet of the God at Tirumala and worshipped Him. The next following stanza has a similar reference to the worship offered by the same two Gods. Stanza 44 is particularly interesting, as, in making a reference to Vengadam, he exhorts younger people particularly to go and offer worship at Vengadam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 TIRUMALA IN NAMMALVAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/10_TIRUMALA_IN_NAMMALVAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/10_TIRUMALA_IN_NAMMALVAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Next after the early Alvars comes Nammalvar who is generally regarded by the Vaishnava Tradition as the best and greatest of them all. His works have come to be regarded as a faithful rendering of all that is of value in the teaching of the Veda. The Tiruvaymoli of Nammalvar is generally regarded as being a rendering of the Veda in Tamil. The earliest Tamils seem to have made a distinction between the Veda and Upanishads by calling the first as Vaymoli and the second as Marai though the latter term has now become more or less fashionable for the entire Vedic literature.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 OTHER ALVARS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/11_OTHER_ALVARS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/03_Temple_history/01_Ancient_period/11_OTHER_ALVARS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From Nammalvar onwards, we have a group of seven Alvars who are later in time and these also make a reference to Tirumala in their literature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Particular mention must be made of Nacchiyar Tirumoli of Andal who is generally worshipped in Vaishnavite temples and also of Alvar Kulasekhara who was a ruler of the Chera country. Coming to Tirumangai Alvar who is probably the latest Alvar, we have a dozen references to the God of Vengadam in his works.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
