<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०३ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०३ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 1: ****Maitreya - ****Kathitaa gurunaa samyak bhoo samudra aadi samsthitih | **&lt;strong&gt;Sooryaadeenaam cha samsthaanam jyotishaam cha ati vistaraat ||&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;em&gt;bhoo mandala&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;samudraas&lt;/em&gt;, how they are located, what is their disposition, were all very clearly taught to me you. &lt;em&gt;Soorya&lt;/em&gt; and others also, their positions, their activities were told. And also the &lt;em&gt;nakshatraas&lt;/em&gt;, in great detail, were taught by you. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Uktah prathama amshe prajaa sargah | Dviteeye tat sheshah priyavrata ****vamshah, prasaktah srushtaanaam aavaasa bhooto loka sanniveshah | Atha ****truteeya chaturthayoh vaidikah manu vyaasa aadi pravartito dharmah, tat ****sthaapako kshatra vamshah cha kramaat uchyate | Tatra amsha dvaya **&lt;strong&gt;ukthaartham anoodya manvantaraani prucchati - kathita iti |&lt;/strong&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Amsha&lt;/em&gt; 1, &lt;em&gt;srushti&lt;/em&gt; was taught. In &lt;em&gt;Amsha&lt;/em&gt; 2, the remaining part of that &lt;em&gt;srushti&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;Priyavrata vamsha&lt;/em&gt;, was taught. Whoever was created, their place of residence was told. What is now to be told is - who are the people living here, what they are doing, all these things are remaining to be told. In &lt;em&gt;Amshas&lt;/em&gt; 3 and 4, &lt;em&gt;Manu, Vyaasa&lt;/em&gt;, and others who spread this &lt;em&gt;vaidika dharma&lt;/em&gt;, and practiced the &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;, that is going to be told. And whatever they taught, those &lt;em&gt;vaidika dharmaas&lt;/em&gt;, those who helped in establishing that, those &lt;em&gt;Kshatra vamshaas&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;vamshaas&lt;/em&gt; of the kings, are also going to be told in order. He tells briefly what was told in the two &lt;em&gt;Amshaas&lt;/em&gt;, and then asks what is it that he wants to know. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 2: ****Devaadeenaam tathaa srushtih rusheenaam cha api varnitaa | **&lt;strong&gt;Chaaturvarnasya cha utpattih tiryak yonigatasya cha ||&lt;/strong&gt; You also told about the creation of &lt;em&gt;deva&lt;/em&gt; and others, all the &lt;em&gt;rishis&lt;/em&gt;, very clearly in detail. And also the four &lt;em&gt;varnaas&lt;/em&gt;, how they were created, *Braahmana, Kshatriya, *&lt;em&gt;Vaishya, Shoodra&lt;/em&gt;, and also the creation of the animals was also told. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 3: **www. [[1]] of 219 Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3 **Dhruva prahlaada charitam vistaraat cha tvaya uditam | ****Manvantaraani asheshaani shrotum icchaami anukramaat || **You taught me &lt;em&gt;Dhruvacharita&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Prahlaada charita&lt;/em&gt; in great detail. Now, I would like to listen to all the &lt;em&gt;Manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt;, in this order. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 4: ****Manvantara adhipaan cha eva shakra deva purogamaan | **&lt;strong&gt;Bhavataa kathitaan etaan shrotum icchaami aham guro ||&lt;/strong&gt; Who are the presiding kings in all these &lt;em&gt;Manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt;, who was the &lt;em&gt;Indra&lt;/em&gt; at that time in each of the &lt;em&gt;Manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt;, who are the &lt;em&gt;devaas&lt;/em&gt;, who are the &lt;em&gt;rishis&lt;/em&gt;, all the details I would like to know. I would like to listen to these, being taught by you, about all these details. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 5: ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Ateeta anaagataani iha yaani manvantaraani vai | ****Taani aham bhavatah samyak kathayaami yathaa kramam || **I will now teach you whatever is past, and whatever is going to come, and also whatever is presently there. All the &lt;em&gt;manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt; which are past, all the &lt;em&gt;manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt; which are going to come in future, all those things I am going to tell you in detail, in order. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Ateeta iti | Ateeta anaagatayoh eva vartamaanasya antarbhaavaat na pruthak ****uktih | Iha - vaaraahe kalpe | **The present one is not told, as it is included in what is past and what is going to come. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 6: ****Svaayambhuvo manuh poorvam parah svarochishah tathaa | ****Uttamah taamasah cha eva raivatah chaakshushah tathaa || **Earlier, the &lt;em&gt;manvantara&lt;/em&gt; was &lt;em&gt;Svaayambhuva&lt;/em&gt;, and after that &lt;em&gt;Svaarochisha&lt;/em&gt;, then &lt;em&gt;Uttama&lt;/em&gt;, then &lt;em&gt;Taamasa&lt;/em&gt;, then &lt;em&gt;Raivata&lt;/em&gt;, then &lt;em&gt;Chaakshusha&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 7: ****Shadete manavo ateetaah saampratam tu raveh sutah | **&lt;strong&gt;Vaivasvato ayam yah tu etat saptamam vartate antaram ||&lt;/strong&gt; These six &lt;em&gt;Manus&lt;/em&gt; were there in the past. Currently, it is &lt;em&gt;Ravi&lt;/em&gt; or *Vivasvaan *- his son, &lt;em&gt;Vaivasvata&lt;/em&gt;. Now, it is &lt;em&gt;Vaivasvata manvantara&lt;/em&gt;, the seventh &lt;em&gt;manvantara&lt;/em&gt; is presently running. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 1, Shloka 8:  ****Svaayambhuvam tu kathitam kalpaadou antaram mayaa | ****Devaah tatra rushayah cha eva yathaavat kathitaa mayaa || **I told you already about the &lt;em&gt;Svaayambhuva Manvantara&lt;/em&gt;. I also told you that in the &lt;em&gt;Svaayambhuva Manu&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; time, who were the &lt;em&gt;devaas, rishis&lt;/em&gt;, and all this. www. [[2]] of 219 Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 2, Shloka 1:  ****Maitreyah - ****Proktaani etaani bhavataa sapta manvantaraani vai | **&lt;strong&gt;Bhavishyaani api viprarshe mamaakhyaatum tvam arhasi ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Maitreya&lt;/em&gt; asks &lt;em&gt;Paraasharar&lt;/em&gt; - You are a &lt;em&gt;Rishi&lt;/em&gt;, you see everything, what happened in the seven &lt;em&gt;Manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt; and what is going to come also. Please tell me what is going to come from now in future, in the future &lt;em&gt;Manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt;. Please do tell me what are the &lt;em&gt;Manvantaraas&lt;/em&gt; which are going to come in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 3, Shloka 1:  ****Maitreyah - ****Jnyaatam etat mayaa tattvo yathaa sarvam idam jagat | **&lt;strong&gt;Vishnuh vishnou vishnutah cha na param vidyate tatah ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Maitreyar *- Now, from you, your good self, I have realized that the whole world is &lt;em&gt;Vishnu&lt;/em&gt; only; everything is established in &lt;em&gt;Vishnu&lt;/em&gt;, and the whole world is created or emanating from &lt;em&gt;Vishnu&lt;/em&gt; only. There is nobody who is superior to Him. I have understood all these things.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 4, Shloka 1:  ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Aadyo vedah chatushpaadah shata sahasra sammitah | ****Tato dasha gunah krutsno yajnyo ayam sarvakaamadhuk || ***Sri Paraasharar *- &lt;em&gt;Veda&lt;/em&gt; which was present as one unit initially, was divided into four; and then hundreds of thousands of branches afterwards. It has &lt;em&gt;dasha guna&lt;/em&gt;. It can bestow any desire of anybody. Whatever you desire, you can get from the &lt;em&gt;Vedaas&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 5, Shloka 1:  ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Yajurveda taroh shaakhaah saptavimshan mahaamunih | **&lt;strong&gt;Vaishampaayana naama asou vyaasashishyah chakaara vai ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[43]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;27 &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;, branches of &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;, were done by &lt;em&gt;Vaishampaayana&lt;/em&gt; who was &lt;em&gt;shishya&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Vyaasa&lt;/em&gt;. There are 27 main branches in &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;. The tree of &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt; was divided into main branches. &lt;em&gt;Vyaasa&amp;rsquo;s shishya, Vaishampaayana&lt;/em&gt;, who was taken as &lt;em&gt;shishya&lt;/em&gt; for promulgation of &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;, created 27 main &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Yajurveda taroh iti | Saptavimshati yajushah pradhaana shaakhaah | ****Brahmaanda uktah shadasheeti pakshah tat pratishaakhaa vivakshayaa | Taah ****cha kaanvaadi shukla yajuh panchadashakam cha samhatya eka shatam **&lt;strong&gt;adhvaryu shaakhaah aapastambha uktaah syuh |&lt;/strong&gt; 27 &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt; told here are the main &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt; of *Yajurveda. Brahmaanda *&lt;em&gt;Puraana&lt;/em&gt; tells about 86 &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;. Among the 27 main &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;, these are the sub-branches. &lt;em&gt;Shukla Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt; which is going to be told now, how &lt;em&gt;Yaajnyavalkya&lt;/em&gt; obtained the &lt;em&gt;Shukla Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;, that is about &lt;em&gt;Kaanva&lt;/em&gt; and other &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;, and this is 15 &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;. 86 and 15 put together, 101 is said to be the &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;. This is how &lt;em&gt;Aapastambha Rishi&lt;/em&gt; says. In the &lt;em&gt;Brahmaanda Puraana&lt;/em&gt;, it is told that 86 branches are there. That means that these main branches have sub branches. &lt;em&gt;Shukla Yujurveda&lt;/em&gt;, has &lt;em&gt;Kaanva&lt;/em&gt; and other branches, totally 15 branches. This becomes 86 + 15 = 101, which is said to be the count of &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;. It has the &lt;em&gt;mantraas&lt;/em&gt; used by the &lt;em&gt;adhvaryu&lt;/em&gt; in any &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt;. Out of these, 27 are the main branches created by &lt;em&gt;Vaishampaayana. Aapastambha rishi&lt;/em&gt; has told that there are 101 branches in the &lt;em&gt;Yajurveda&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 5, Shloka 2:  **&lt;strong&gt;Shishyebhyah pradadou taah cha jagruhuh te api anukramaat |&lt;/strong&gt; He taught it to various students. They all mastered those parts. He taught all those 27 &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt; to various &lt;em&gt;shishyaas&lt;/em&gt;, and they all mastered the &lt;em&gt;Samhitaas&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 6, Shloka 1:  ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Saamavedtaroh shaakhaah vyaasa shishyah sa jaiminih | **&lt;strong&gt;Kramena yena maitreya bibheda shrunu tam mama ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Sri Paraasharar *- O &lt;em&gt;Maitreyar&lt;/em&gt;, I am going to tell you how &lt;em&gt;Vyaasa&amp;rsquo;s shishya Jaimini&lt;/em&gt;, who learnt &lt;em&gt;Saamaveda&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;Vedavyaasa&lt;/em&gt;, how he divided them into various &lt;em&gt;shaakhaas&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 6, Shloka 2:  ****Sumantuh tasya putro abhoot sutvaa tasya api abhoot sutah | ****Adheetavantou cha ekaikaam samhitaam tou mahaamatee || **&lt;em&gt;Jaimini&lt;/em&gt; had a son called &lt;em&gt;Sumantu. Sumantu&lt;/em&gt; had a son called &lt;em&gt;Sutvaa&lt;/em&gt;. They all studied one &lt;em&gt;samhitaa&lt;/em&gt; each.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Sumantuh iti | Taam jaimini samhitaam tat putra poutrou ekaikou **&lt;strong&gt;ayougapadyena sva sva pituh adheetavantou |&lt;/strong&gt; The son and grandson of &lt;em&gt;Jaimini&lt;/em&gt;, studied from their respective fathers, not together, but one after the other. First, &lt;em&gt;Jaimini&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; son learnt, and then &lt;em&gt;Jaimini&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; grandson learnt.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 7, Shloka 1:  ****Maitreyah - ****Yathaavat kathiram sarvam yat prushtho asi mayaa guro | **&lt;strong&gt;Shrotum icchaami aham tu ekam tat bhavaan prabraveetu me ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Maitreyar *- O &lt;em&gt;Paraasharar&lt;/em&gt;, you told me everything that I requested for, as it is. Now, I am interested in one particular thing, which kindly do tell me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Atha shrutyaadi ukto dharmo bhagavad aaraadhanatayaa anushtito ****nishreyasaaya iti etat artham yama bhata samvaadam prastouti yathaavat iti | **&lt;em&gt;Maitreyar&lt;/em&gt; is asking about whatever &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; is told in the &lt;em&gt;Shrutis, Shrutis&lt;/em&gt; and other &lt;em&gt;Upabrahmanaas&lt;/em&gt;, that which is performed with the idea that it is worship of the Lord, &lt;em&gt;Bhagavaan&lt;/em&gt;; and when the &lt;em&gt;anushthaana&lt;/em&gt; is done like this, it leads to &lt;em&gt;Moksha&lt;/em&gt;, and this is what he wants to know. Related to that, the dialogue which happens between &lt;em&gt;Yama&lt;/em&gt; and his &lt;em&gt;bhata&lt;/em&gt;, assistant, is being told here.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 8, Shloka 1: ****Maitreyah - ****Bhagavan bhagavaan devah samsaaravijigeeshubhih | **&lt;strong&gt;Samaakhyaahi jagannaatho vishnuh aaraadhyate yathaa ||&lt;/strong&gt; O &lt;em&gt;Paraasharar, Jagannaatha&lt;/em&gt;, who is &lt;em&gt;Bhagavaan Deva&lt;/em&gt;, by those who want to win over this &lt;em&gt;samsaara&lt;/em&gt;, how is He worshipped? Please do tell me. &lt;em&gt;Paraasharar&lt;/em&gt; told about the &lt;em&gt;Vishnu bhaktaas&lt;/em&gt; who escape from &lt;em&gt;Yama vashyatva&lt;/em&gt;. He told about the &lt;em&gt;lakshanaas&lt;/em&gt; of devotees of &lt;em&gt;Vishnu&lt;/em&gt;. Now, he is asking about how they worship &lt;em&gt;Vishnu&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Poorvam bhagavat aajnyaa roopa shruti smruti ukta varna aashrama dharma ****anushthaanam bhakti lakshanam uktam | Idaaneem tat eva chaturvarga ****saadhanam iti uchyate bhagavan iti adhyaaya navakena | **From here onwards, up to the ninth chapter, &lt;em&gt;varna aashrama aachaaraas&lt;/em&gt; will be told. &lt;em&gt;Bhakti&lt;/em&gt; which is always associated with &lt;em&gt;varna aashrama dharma anushthaana&lt;/em&gt;, are told in the &lt;em&gt;Shrutis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Smrutis&lt;/em&gt;, these &lt;em&gt;Shrutis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Smrutis&lt;/em&gt; which are &amp;quot; *Mama eva *&lt;em&gt;aajnyaa&amp;quot;, Bhagavat aajnyaa roopa&lt;/em&gt;; the &lt;em&gt;varna aashrama dharmaas&lt;/em&gt; have to be done with utmost devotion, which is as told in &lt;em&gt;Shrutis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Smrutis&lt;/em&gt;, which is nothing but &lt;em&gt;Bhagavat aajnynaa&lt;/em&gt;. With that only, one can attain all the four *purushaarthaas, *&lt;em&gt;dharma, artha, kaama, moksha&lt;/em&gt;, is going to be told in nine chapters. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 8, Shloka 2: ****Aaraadhitaat cha govindaat aaraadhana paraih naraih | **&lt;strong&gt;Yat praapyate phalam shrotum tat cha icchaami mahaamune ||&lt;/strong&gt; When &lt;em&gt;Govinda&lt;/em&gt; is worshipped by such devotees, what are the fruits that they get? Please do tell me that also. O &lt;em&gt;Mahaamuni&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Sri Paraasharar&lt;/em&gt; remembers another story and tells it now. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 8, Shloka 3: ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Yat prucchati bhavaan etat sagarena mahaatmanaa | ****Ourvah praaha yathaa prushtah tat me nigaditah shrunu || ***Sri Paraasharar *- Once &lt;em&gt;Sagara&lt;/em&gt; went and asked *Mahaatma Ourva *- Please do tell me how Vishnu is worshipped, how &lt;em&gt;Vishnu aaraadhana&lt;/em&gt; is done. &lt;em&gt;Ourva Rishi&lt;/em&gt; explains how &lt;em&gt;Vishnu&lt;/em&gt; is going to be worshipped. Whatever &lt;em&gt;Ourva&lt;/em&gt; told, I will tell you, please listen to me. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 8, Shloka 4:  ****Sagarah pranipatya enam ourvam papraccha bhaargavam | **&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[86]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 9, Shloka 1: ****Ourva uvaacha - ****Baalah kruta upanayanah vedaaharana tatparah | **&lt;strong&gt;Gurugehe vaset bhoopa brahmachaaree samaahitah ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Oorva *- A boy who has undergone &lt;em&gt;upanayana&lt;/em&gt;, has to be engaged and established in learning the &lt;em&gt;Vedaas&lt;/em&gt;. He has to live in the &lt;em&gt;Guru&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/em&gt; house, &lt;em&gt;aashrama&lt;/em&gt;. Or &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt; will do &lt;em&gt;upanayana&lt;/em&gt; and teach him the &lt;em&gt;Vedaas&lt;/em&gt;. A &lt;em&gt;Brahmachaari&lt;/em&gt; has to be engaged in studying the &lt;em&gt;Vedaas&lt;/em&gt; with a proper mind, in a focussed way. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 9, Shloka 2: ****Shouchaachaaravataa tatra kaaryam shushrooshanam guroh | ****Vrataani charataa graahyo vedah cha krutabuddhinaa || **A &lt;em&gt;Brahmachaari&lt;/em&gt; when he is living with a &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt;, learning the &lt;em&gt;Vedaas&lt;/em&gt;, has to do all kinds of service to the &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt;. He has to follow all the &lt;em&gt;aachaaraas&lt;/em&gt; as told by his &lt;em&gt;varna dharma&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;aashrama dharma&lt;/em&gt; for a &lt;em&gt;Brahmachaari&lt;/em&gt;. He has to be established in pure &lt;em&gt;aachaara&lt;/em&gt;. He has to do &lt;em&gt;seva&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt;. Performing all the vrataas, he has to learn the Vedaas. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Shouchaachaaravataa iti | Vrataani prajaapati aadeeni madhu maamsa aadi ****varjana aadeeni cha | Kruta buddhinaa avahita buddhinaa | **He has to follow &lt;em&gt;Praajaapatya&lt;/em&gt; and other &lt;em&gt;vrataas&lt;/em&gt;; he should not take *madhu, *&lt;em&gt;maamsa&lt;/em&gt;, and others which are not allowed. He has to totally concentrate on learning only. And on serving the Guru with all sincerity. And maintaining all the &lt;em&gt;shoucha&lt;/em&gt; told in the &lt;em&gt;shaastraas&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 9, Shloka 3: ****Ubhe sandhye ravim bhoopa tathaa evaa agnim samaahitah | **&lt;strong&gt;Upatishthet tathaa kuryaat guroh api abhivaadanam ||&lt;/strong&gt; Both the &lt;em&gt;sandhyaa kaalaas&lt;/em&gt;, and also &lt;em&gt;maadhyaahnika&lt;/em&gt;, he has to do &lt;em&gt;sandhyaavandana&lt;/em&gt;. He also has to do &lt;em&gt;agni kaarya&lt;/em&gt; with proper &lt;em&gt;shraddhe&lt;/em&gt;. He has to do &lt;em&gt;abhivaadana&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 9, Shloka 4:  ****Sthite tishthet vrajet yaate neechaih aaseeta chaasati | ****Shishyo guroon nrupa shreshtha pratikoolam na sancharet || **He has to follow his &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt; in every way and serve him. If &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt; stands, he has to stand. He has to follow the &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt;. If &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt; is sitting, he has to sit; he should not sit in a seat which is higher than the &lt;em&gt;Guru. Shishya&lt;/em&gt; should never do anything wrong to a &lt;em&gt;Guru&lt;/em&gt;. ****&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[99]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 10, Shloka 1: ****Sagarah - ****Kathitam chaaturaashramyam chaaturvarnya kriyaah tathaa | **&lt;strong&gt;Pumsah kriyaam aham shrotum icchaami dvijasattama ||&lt;/strong&gt; Sagara - You told me about the &lt;em&gt;dharmaas&lt;/em&gt; of the *Brahmachaari aashrama, *&lt;em&gt;Gruhastha aashrama, Vaanaprastha aashrama, Sannyaasa aashrama&lt;/em&gt;. And also the four &lt;em&gt;varnaas&lt;/em&gt; of *Braahmana, Kshatriya, Vaishya, Shoodra *- about their duties. What are the &lt;em&gt;karmaas&lt;/em&gt; that they do, I want to know about that. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 10, Shloka 2: ****Nitya naimittikaah kaamyaah kriyaah pumsaam asheshatah | ****Samaakhyaahi bhrugu shreshtha sarvajnyo hi asi me matah || **I want to know everything about the &lt;em&gt;nitya naimittika karmaas, kaamya karmaas&lt;/em&gt;. Please tell me, O &lt;em&gt;Bhrugu shreshta&lt;/em&gt;, you know everything. You are &lt;em&gt;sarvajnya&lt;/em&gt;. You are knowledgeable about everything. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Kathitam iti | Pumsah kriyaam shodasha samskaara roopaam | Garbhaadhaana ****pumsavana seemanta unnayana vishnubali jaatakarma naamakarana ****upanishkramana annapraashana choodaa upanayana vedavrata chatushtaya **&lt;strong&gt;samaavartana vivaahaah shodasha samskaaraah |&lt;/strong&gt; There are 16 &lt;em&gt;samskaaraas&lt;/em&gt; told. This is also told to be 40 in other places. These are listed here. Out of them, *Garbhaadhaana, Pumsavana, Seemanta, Unnayana, **Vishnubali *- are all before birth. The others, *Jaatakarma, Naamakarana, **Upanishkramana, Annapraashana, Choodaa, Upanayana, Vedavrata chatushtaya, **Vivaaha *- are after the birth. I want to know about all these &lt;em&gt;samskaaraas&lt;/em&gt; is what &lt;em&gt;Sagara&lt;/em&gt; is asking. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 10, Shloka 3: ****Ourvah - ****Yat etat uktam bhavataa nitya naimittika aashrayam | ****Tat aham kathayishyaami shrunushva ekamanaa mama || ***Ourva *- O &lt;em&gt;Sagara&lt;/em&gt;, you asked me about &lt;em&gt;nitya naimittika karmaas&lt;/em&gt;. I am going to tell you about all that. Do listen to me very attentively. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Yat etat iti | Nitya naimittika aashrayam iti kaamyasya api upalakshanam | **&lt;em&gt;Nitya, naimittika&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;kaamya karmaas&lt;/em&gt; also. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 10, Shloka 4:  ****Jaatasya jaata karmaadi kriyaa kaandam asheshatah | **&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[109]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 11, Shloka 1: ****Sagarah - ****Gruhasthasya sadaachaaram shrotum icchaami aham mune | **&lt;strong&gt;Lokaat asmaat parasmaat cha yam aatishthan na heeyate ||&lt;/strong&gt; King *Sagara *- What are the &lt;em&gt;sadaachaaraas&lt;/em&gt; that a &lt;em&gt;gruhasta&lt;/em&gt; has to follow, I would like to listen from you. By which he will not get into any difficulty in this &lt;em&gt;loka&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;para loka&lt;/em&gt;. By which he will always have a &lt;em&gt;sadgati&lt;/em&gt;, that kind of &lt;em&gt;aachaara&lt;/em&gt;, I would like to listen to. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 11, Shloka 2: ****Ourvah - ****Shrooyataam pruthiveepaala sadaachaarasya lakshanam | **&lt;strong&gt;Sadaachaaravataa pumsaam jitou lokou ubhou api ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Ourva Rishi *- I am going to tell you the signs of &lt;em&gt;sadaachaara&lt;/em&gt;, how they have to be followed. One who follows this kind of &lt;em&gt;sadaachaara&lt;/em&gt;, as told in the &lt;em&gt;shaastraas&lt;/em&gt;, he can win over both the worlds, here as well as elsewhere. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 11, Shloka 3: ****Saadhavah ksheena doshaah tu sat shabdah saadhu vaachakah | **&lt;strong&gt;Teshaam aacharanam yat tu sadaachaarah sa uchyate ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Saadhu&lt;/em&gt; itself means those who have destroyed all their defects. They are very pure. The word sat itself indicates &lt;em&gt;saadhu&lt;/em&gt;. Whatever they follow is said to be &lt;em&gt;sadaachaara&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 11, Shloka 4: ****Saptarshayah atha manavah prajaanam patayah tathaa | **&lt;strong&gt;Sadaachaarasya vaktaarah kartaarah cha maheepate ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Saptarshis, manus&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;prajaapatis&lt;/em&gt; are all people who have taught &lt;em&gt;sadaachaara&lt;/em&gt;, and have done &lt;em&gt;anusthaana&lt;/em&gt;, they performed it, put it into practice, and taught it to others. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 11, Shloka 5:  ****Braahme muhoorte cha utthaaya manasaa matimaan nrupa | **&lt;strong&gt;Prabuddhah chintayet dharmam artham cha api avirodhinam ||&lt;/strong&gt; One has to wake up in &lt;em&gt;Braahma muhoorta&lt;/em&gt;, and has to think at that time, about &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;artha&lt;/em&gt; which are not opposed to each other. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: **&lt;strong&gt;Braahma iti | Braahmah spooryodayaat praak truteeyo muhoortah |&lt;/strong&gt; The third &lt;em&gt;muhoorta&lt;/em&gt; before sunrise is &lt;em&gt;Braahma muhoorta&lt;/em&gt;. ****&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[117]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 12, Shloka 1: ****Ourvah - ****Deva go braahmanaan siddhaan vruddha aachaaryaan tathaa archayet | **&lt;strong&gt;Dvikaalam cha namet sandhyaam agneen upacharet tathaa ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Ourva *- One should worship God ( &lt;em&gt;Deva&lt;/em&gt;), go (cow), *Brahmins, siddhaas, vruddha *&lt;em&gt;aachaaryaas. Sandhyaavandanaa&lt;/em&gt; is to be done - says two times (this includes &lt;em&gt;maadhyaahnika&lt;/em&gt; also); all the &lt;em&gt;agni kaaryaas&lt;/em&gt; have to be done. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 12, Shloka 2: ****Sadaa anupahate vastre prashastaah cha mahoushadheeh | **&lt;strong&gt;Gaarudaani cha ratnaani bibhruyaat prayato narah ||&lt;/strong&gt; One has to wear two clothes always, they should not be torn. One can also take medicinal herbs - *Vishnukraantaa *(morning glory, helps in bone growth, intestinal health) and &lt;em&gt;Doorva&lt;/em&gt;. One can wear all the gemstones which are good. A person should be using all of these. To basically keep good health. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Sadaa iti | Oshadheeh vishnukraantaa doorvaadyaah | Gaarudaani ratnaani na ****vishaghnaani marakata aadeeni | ****Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 12, Shloka 3: ****Prasnigdha amala keshah cha sugandhah chaaru veshadhruk | ****Sitaah sumanaso hrudyaah bibhruyaat cha narah sadaa || **He should groom his hair well. He can have perfumes and wear good clothes. One should wear white flowers all the time. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Prasnigdhaa iti | Prasnigdhaah alamkrutaah amalaah keshaah yasya | ****Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 12, Shloka 4:  ****Kinchit paratvam na haret na alpam api apriyam vadet | ****Priyam cha na anrutam brooyaat na anya doshaan anudeerayet || **One should not steal others belongings. One should not tell something which is not liked by others. Even though it is likeable to others, one should not tell lies. One should not highlight defects of others.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 13, Shloka 1: ****Ourvah - ****Sachelasya pituh snaanam jaate putre vidheeyate | **&lt;strong&gt;Jaata karma tathaa kuryaat shraadham abhyudayam cha yat ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Ourva *- When a person gets a child, (when a child is born), then he should take a bath with the cloth on. He has to do the &lt;em&gt;jaata karma&lt;/em&gt; as ordained. And also has to do &lt;em&gt;abhyudaya shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;, as told earlier. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 13, Shloka 2: ****Yugmaan devaan cha pitryaan cha samyak savyakramaat dvijaan | **&lt;strong&gt;Poojayet bhojayet chaiva tanmanaa na anyamaanasah ||&lt;/strong&gt; In pairs, Gods, &lt;em&gt;Brahmins&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;pitrus&lt;/em&gt;, in the &lt;em&gt;pradakshina krama&lt;/em&gt;, one has to worship; one has to offer food to &lt;em&gt;Brahmins&lt;/em&gt; also, being dedicated and focussing on that. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: **&lt;strong&gt;Yugmaan iti | Savyakramaat pradakshinakramaat |&lt;/strong&gt; **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 13, Shloka 3: ****Dadhi akshataih sabadaraih praangmuka udamgmukho api vaa | ****Devateerthena vai pindaan dadyaat kaayena vaa nrupa || **Either facing east or north, using curd, &lt;em&gt;akshataa&lt;/em&gt;, and fruits, ( *yelachi *&lt;em&gt;hannu&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Kannada&lt;/em&gt;), he has to give *deva teertha *(with the front of the fingers), as per the &lt;em&gt;rishis&lt;/em&gt;, he has to give. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: **&lt;strong&gt;Dadhyakshataih iti | Kaayena praajaapatyena |&lt;/strong&gt; **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 13, Shloka 4: ****Naandeemukhah pitruganah tena shraaddhena paarthiva | ****Preeyate tat tu kartavyam purushaih sarva vruddhishu || **In all the &lt;em&gt;vruddhi kaaryaas&lt;/em&gt;, used for &lt;em&gt;abhivruddhi&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;mangala karmaas&lt;/em&gt;, one has to do &lt;em&gt;naandee mukha shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;, and the &lt;em&gt;pitru ganaas&lt;/em&gt; which are called *naandee *&lt;em&gt;mukhaas&lt;/em&gt;, they will be pleased with this &lt;em&gt;naandee mukha shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;. One has to do these &lt;em&gt;naandee mukha shraaddha&lt;/em&gt; in all the &lt;em&gt;vruddhi karmaas&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 13, Shloka 5:  ****Kanyaa putra vivaaheshu pravesheshu cha veshmanah | **&lt;strong&gt;Naama karmaani baalaanaam choodaa karmaadike tathaa ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[152]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 14, Shloka 1: ****Ourvah - ****Brahmendra rudranaasatya soorya agni vasu maarutaan | **&lt;strong&gt;Vishvedevaan pitru ganaan vayaamsi manujaan pashoon ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Ourva Rishi *- As a part of the &lt;em&gt;uttara kriyaa&lt;/em&gt;, what is done is told here. &lt;em&gt;Shraaddha&lt;/em&gt; is that which is done with a lot of &lt;em&gt;shraddhe&lt;/em&gt;, a lot of devotion. If one does the &lt;em&gt;shraaddha kaaryaas&lt;/em&gt; with such devotion, he is going to please all the beings. They are *Brahma, Indra, Rudra, Ashvini devaas, Soorya, Agni, Vasu, Marudganaas, *&lt;em&gt;Vishve devaas, Pitru ganaas&lt;/em&gt;, all the birds, humans, animals, &amp;hellip; **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 14, Shloka 2: ****Sareesrupaan rushiganaan yat cha anyat bhoota sanjnyitam | **&lt;strong&gt;Shraaddham shraddhaanvitah kurvan preenayati akhilam jagat ||&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;hellip; snakes, all the &lt;em&gt;rishis&lt;/em&gt;, all beings, the whole world will be pleased if one does the &lt;em&gt;shraaddha kaaryaas&lt;/em&gt;. The importance of the &lt;em&gt;shraaddha kaaryaas&lt;/em&gt;, done with great devotion, is told here. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 14, Shloka 3: ****Maasi maasyasite pakshe pancha dashyaam nareshvara | **&lt;strong&gt;Tathaa ashtakaasu kurveeta kaamyaan kaalaan shrunushva me ||&lt;/strong&gt; There are also &lt;em&gt;kaamya shraaddhaas&lt;/em&gt;. Which can be done every month, on *Krushna *&lt;em&gt;Paksha, Amaavaasyaa&lt;/em&gt;. Then also on &lt;em&gt;Ashtakaas&lt;/em&gt;. I will tell you the &lt;em&gt;kaala&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Maasi iti | Atha ukta kriyaanaam kaalah | Ashtakaasu * Hemanta shishirayoh ****chaturnaam aparapakshanaam ashtameeshu asthakaah * iti aashvalaayana ****uktam aasapanchake krushna paksha saptami aadyaah tisrastisroshtakaa iti **&lt;strong&gt;uktaah taasu |&lt;/strong&gt; In the &lt;em&gt;Hemanta&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Shishira maasaas&lt;/em&gt;, there are four *apara pakshaas, Krushna *&lt;em&gt;pakshaas&lt;/em&gt;; in these, the &lt;em&gt;ashtamis&lt;/em&gt; are said to be &lt;em&gt;ashtakaas&lt;/em&gt;. There are three *ashtaka *&lt;em&gt;shraaddhaas&lt;/em&gt;. Each &lt;em&gt;ashtaka shraaddha&lt;/em&gt; has got three *shraaddhaas - saptami, *&lt;em&gt;ashtami, navami&lt;/em&gt;. On these three days, three times is to be done. This is as per &lt;em&gt;Ashvalaayana&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 14, Shloka 4:  ****Shraaddhaarham aagatam dravyam vishishtam atha vaa dvijaan | **&lt;strong&gt;Shraaddham kurveeta vijnyaaya vyateepaate ayane tathaa ||&lt;/strong&gt; These &lt;em&gt;Kaamya shraaddhaas&lt;/em&gt;, when one can do is when he receives the material required good for performing a &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;. It is not easy to get a good material all the time. If one receives good material with which he can perform &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt; well, he can do a &lt;em&gt;kaamya shraaddha&lt;/em&gt; at that time. Or, if he gets a &lt;em&gt;Brahmin&lt;/em&gt; who is very &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[161]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 15, Shloka 1: ****Ourvah - **&lt;strong&gt;Braahmanaan bhojayet shraaddhe yat gunaan taan nibodha me ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Ourva *- What are the expected qualifications of the &lt;em&gt;Brahmins&lt;/em&gt;, who are to be fed during a &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 15, Shloka 2:  ****Trinaachiketah trimadhuh trisuparnah shadangavit | **&lt;strong&gt;Vedavit shrotriyo yogee tathaa vai jyeshtha saamagah ||&lt;/strong&gt; The first eligibility is &lt;em&gt;trinaachiketa&lt;/em&gt;. The next is &lt;em&gt;trimadhu&lt;/em&gt;. Next is &lt;em&gt;trisuparna&lt;/em&gt;. Next is *shadangavit *- one who has knowledge of all the six &lt;em&gt;angaas. Vedavit&lt;/em&gt; is one who has studied the &lt;em&gt;Vedaas&lt;/em&gt; fully. A &lt;em&gt;shrotriya. Vedavit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;shrotriya&lt;/em&gt;. A &lt;em&gt;yogi&lt;/em&gt;. A *jyestha *&lt;em&gt;saamaga&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 16, Shloka 1: ****Ourvah - ****Havishya matsya maamsaih tu shashasya nakulasya cha | **&lt;strong&gt;Soukara cchaagala aineya rouravaih gavayena cha ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Havishya&lt;/em&gt; is the grains used by the sages in the forest, milk, *soma rasa, shuddha **maamsa, saindhava lavana *- these are &lt;em&gt;havishya&lt;/em&gt;. Fish, deer, rabbit, hog, goat, antelope, some kind of deer, some kind of cow, &amp;hellip; Here, it is told that offering &lt;em&gt;maamsa&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt; is supposed to be very good. This is also told in &lt;em&gt;Manu Smruti&lt;/em&gt;. There is a &lt;em&gt;Gita&lt;/em&gt; Press commentary, the &lt;em&gt;Hindi&lt;/em&gt; version, that &lt;em&gt;maamsa&lt;/em&gt; is not allowed in the &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;. Quoting from &lt;em&gt;Manu Smruti&lt;/em&gt; itself, where generally, it is said that &amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Na himsyaat sarva bhootaani&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;, that one should not do &lt;em&gt;himsaa&lt;/em&gt; to any being. But, in &lt;em&gt;yajnya&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;, this is exempted. Nowadays, the grains we use are equivalent for these things. Nowadays, the practice of offering &lt;em&gt;maamsa&lt;/em&gt; is not there. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Havishya iti | Havishyena ekam maasam truptih, matsyena dvou, maamsena ****treen maasaan | Atra maamso haarinaadi * Treen maasaan harinena truptih iti ****manu ukteh | Chaagalah - ajah, ruruh mahaan krushnasaarah | **&lt;em&gt;Havishya&lt;/em&gt; is one month. &lt;em&gt;Matsya&lt;/em&gt;, if offered, it is two months, they get pleased. Deer, it is for three months. &lt;em&gt;Manu smruti&lt;/em&gt; is also quoted here. &lt;em&gt;Chagala&lt;/em&gt; is goat. &lt;em&gt;Ruru&lt;/em&gt; is another kind of deer. Each one of them, if offered, &lt;em&gt;pitrus&lt;/em&gt; will get &lt;em&gt;trupti&lt;/em&gt; for one more month each. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 16, Shloka 2:  ****Ourabhragavyaih cha tathaa maasa vruddhyaa pitaamahaah | **&lt;strong&gt;Prayaanti truptim maamsaih tu nityam vaardhreena saamishaih ||&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;hellip; sheep, by-products of cow (ghee, milk). There is a bird called &lt;em&gt;Vaardhreena&lt;/em&gt;, and if that &lt;em&gt;maamsa&lt;/em&gt; is given, the &lt;em&gt;pitrus&lt;/em&gt; will be always satisfied. **Sri Engal Aalwaan&amp;rsquo;s Commentary: ****Ourabhra iti | Urabhrah oornaayuh | Gavyam payah, paayasam vaa * ****Samvatsaram tu gavyena payasaa paayasena vaa * iti smruteh | Gavyam **&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[181]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 17, Shloka 1: ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Iti aaha bhagavaan ourvah sagaraaya mahaatmane | **&lt;strong&gt;Sadaachaaram puraa samyak maitreya pariprucchate ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Sri Paraasharar -&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Bhagavaan Ourva&lt;/em&gt; told to &lt;em&gt;Sagara&lt;/em&gt; thus - Whatever you asked about &lt;em&gt;Sadaachaara&lt;/em&gt; and all those things, O &lt;em&gt;Maitreya&lt;/em&gt;, this is what &lt;em&gt;Ourva Rishi&lt;/em&gt; has told to &lt;em&gt;Sagara&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 17, Shloka 2: ****Mayaa api etat asheshena kathitam bhavato dvija | **&lt;strong&gt;Samullanghya sadaachaaram kashchit na aapnoti shobhanam ||&lt;/strong&gt; Whatever I knew, I told you everything. Anyone who transgresses this &lt;em&gt;sadaachaara&lt;/em&gt;, will not get anything good. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 17, Shloka 3: ****Maitreyah - ****Shandaapaviddapramukhaa (kathitaa bhagavaan tvayaa) viditaa bhagavanmayaa ****| **&lt;strong&gt;Udakyaadyaah cha me samyak nagnam icchaami veditum ||&lt;/strong&gt; In the previous chapter, we had seen who should not come in sight of &lt;em&gt;Brahmins&lt;/em&gt;, who are having food in a &lt;em&gt;shraaddha&lt;/em&gt;. I understood all these - &lt;em&gt;shanda, apaviddha&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;stree&lt;/em&gt; with *rajas *- I understood all these things well. I would like to know what is &lt;em&gt;nagna&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 17, Shloka 4: ****Ko nagnah kim samaachaaro nagna samnjyaam naro labhet | ****Nagna svaroopam icchaami yathaavat kathitam tvayaa | **&lt;strong&gt;Shrotum dharmabhrutaam shreshtha ha hi asti aviditam tava ||&lt;/strong&gt; Who is called a &lt;em&gt;nagna&lt;/em&gt;. What does he do? What are his actions? I would like to know a &lt;em&gt;nagna svaroopa&lt;/em&gt;, as it is, from you. O, excellent among those who are following the &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;. There is nothing which is not known to you. Please tell me about &lt;em&gt;nagna lakshana&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 17, Shloka 5:  ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Rik yajus saama sanjnyeyam trayee varnaavruti dvija | **&lt;strong&gt;Etaam ujjhati yo mohaat sa nagnah paatakee smrutah ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Sri Paraasharar - Trayee&lt;/em&gt; is called &lt;em&gt;Rig, Yajus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Saama&lt;/em&gt;. This is a covering of &lt;em&gt;varnaas, aksharaas&lt;/em&gt;. It is like a cloth which is covering us, it is a cloth made of &lt;em&gt;varnaas&lt;/em&gt;. One who, out of ignorance or delusion, gives this up, is called a &lt;em&gt;nagna&lt;/em&gt;. He is a great sinner. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[187]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/viShNu-purANam/viShNuchitta-TIkA/en/03/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;**Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 18, Shloka 1: ****Sri Paraasharah - ****Tapasabhirataan sah atha maayaa moho mahaasuraan | **&lt;strong&gt;Maitreya dadrushe gatvaa narmadaa teera samshritaan ||&lt;/strong&gt; All the great &lt;em&gt;asuraas&lt;/em&gt; were residing on the banks of &lt;em&gt;Narmadaa&lt;/em&gt; river, and were engaged in &lt;em&gt;tapas. Maayaamoha&lt;/em&gt; went there and saw all the &lt;em&gt;asuraas&lt;/em&gt; engaged in &lt;em&gt;tapas&lt;/em&gt;. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 18, Shloka 2: ****Tato digambaro mundo barhipicchadharo dvija | ****Maayaamoho asuraan shlakshnam idam vachanam abraveet || **&lt;em&gt;Maayaamoha&lt;/em&gt;, going as a &lt;em&gt;digambara&lt;/em&gt;, not wearing any cloth, and shaving off his head, was wearing a peacock feather. He saw the &lt;em&gt;asuraas&lt;/em&gt; and told them in a soft polished way, thus. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 18, Shloka 3: ****Maayaamohah - ****He daityapatayo broota yadartham tapyate tapah | ****Ehikaartham nu paaratryam tapasah phalamicchatha || ***Maayaamoha *- O great leaders of the &lt;em&gt;daityaas&lt;/em&gt;. Do tell me for what purpose are you doing this tapas. Are you interested in &lt;em&gt;aihika phalaas&lt;/em&gt;, or *aamushmika **phalaas *(benefits of the world, or in liberation)? For what purpose are you doing this &lt;em&gt;tapas&lt;/em&gt;? **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 18, Shloka 4: ****Asuraah - ****Paaratra phala laabhyaaya tapashcharyaa mahaamate | **&lt;strong&gt;Asmaabhiriyamaarabdhaa him vaa te atra vivakshitam ||&lt;/strong&gt; *Asuraas *- We are not interested in this &lt;em&gt;aihika phala&lt;/em&gt;, we are interested in moksha itself. We want to get liberated. That is why we are doing this &lt;em&gt;tapas&lt;/em&gt;. We have started the &lt;em&gt;tapas&lt;/em&gt; for this purpose. What do you have to say in this matter. **Sri Vishnu Puraana, Amsha 3, Chapter 18, Shloka 5:  ****Maayaamoha uvaachaa - ****Kurudhvam mama vaakyaani yadi muktim abheepsatha | **&lt;strong&gt;Arhadhvamenam dharmam cha mukti dvaaram asamvrutam ||&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Maayaamoha&lt;/em&gt; says - If you are desirous of attaining &lt;em&gt;moksha&lt;/em&gt;, follow me, what I am going to say. You become worthy of &lt;em&gt;dharma&lt;/em&gt;, that I am going to teach you. Then, for you the path to liberation will be wide open. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sadagopan.org&#34;&gt;www.sadagopan.org&lt;/a&gt;  [[198]] of 219&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
