<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;टीका on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;टीका on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Nancy nAyar</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/nancy-nAyar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/nancy-nAyar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;[[TODO: परिष्कार्यम्]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PRAISE-POEMS&#xA;TO&#xA;f&#xA;VISNU AND SRI&#xA;The Stotras of Ramanuja&amp;rsquo;s Immediate Disciples&#xA;NANCY ANN NAYAR&#xA;ANANTHACHARYA INDOLOGICAL&#xA;RESEARCH INSTITUTE&#xA;BOMBAY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ananthacharya Indological Research Institute Series&#xA;No. XXIII&#xA;བ་་▪་་ ་ ག h on it quidfærd&#xA;General Editor:&#xA;K.K.A. VENKATACHARI&#xA;PRAISE-POEMS TO VIṢŅU AND ŚRĪ The Stotras of Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s Immediate Disciples&#xA;by&#xA;NANCY ANN NAYAR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;PRAISE-POEMS TO VIṢŅU AND ŚRĪ&#xA;The Stotras of Rāmānuja&amp;rsquo;s Immediate Disciples&#xA;A Translation from the Sanskrit with Introduction and Notes&#xA;NANCY ANN NAYAR&#xA;ANANTHACHARYA INDOLOGICAL RESEARCH INSTITUTE&#xA;G.D. SOMANI SCHOOL BUILDING CUFFE PARADE, BOMBAY 400005&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ShrInivAsa rAghava H</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/shrInivAsa-rAghavaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/shrInivAsa-rAghavaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/srisuktabhashyaofsriranganathamuni1937ocr/page/n73/mode/2up&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[यत्पदाम्भोरुहध्यानविध्वस्ताशेषकल्मषः । वस्तुतामुपयातोऽहं यामुनेयं नमामि तम् ॥]शरणागतिगद्यम् ।&#xA;[Sri Ramanuja was the successor of Sri Yamuna. He popularised the Visishtadvaita System of Philo- sophy and spread it everywhere so that the system came to be known after him. He is the author of nine works. The Vedanta Sara, the Vedanta Dipa and Sri Bhashya are graded com- mentaries on the Brahma Sutras with increasing elaborateness. The fourth is the Bhashya on the Bhagavad Gita ; the fifth, the Vedartha Sangraha, is a digest of the teachings of all Upanishads; the sixth is called Nitya which codifies the daily rites of a devotee of the God; and the last three are devotional songs in prose, the Gadya traya&#xA;-Saranagati Gadya, Sriranga Gadya and Vai- kuntha Gadya. At the beginning of the Sarana- gati Gadya and in one or two other places, he has spoken of Sri, though he has not specially devoted a book to Her greatness.]&#xA;भगवन्नारायणाभिमतानुरूपस्वरूपरूपगुणविभवैश्वर्यशीलाद्यनव- धिकातिशयासंख्येयकल्याणगुणगणां पद्मवनालयां भगवतीं श्रियं देवीं नित्यानपायिनीं निरवद्यां देवदेवदिव्यमहिषीं अखिलजगन्मातरं (अस्म- न्मातरं) अशरण्यशरण्यां अनन्यशरणः शरणमहं प्रपद्ये ||&#xA;१०१&#xA;In Sri do I take refuge, helpless as I am, in Sri-who is the saviour of the helpless; who has got innumerable hosts of qualities,-auspicious and unexcelled-like sovereignty and amiability; who possesses a nature, forms, qualities and Vibhuti (splendour) suited to and loved by Sri Narayana, the Bhagavan (Himself, the possessor of such superb qualities); in Sri, the Goddess (of superb qualities), the denizen of the lotus-ponds who is ever inseparable from Her Consort and unimpeachable and unsullied (by any fault); and who is the queen of the Lord of all Gods and the Mother of the entire Universe (and of myself.)&#xA;[प्रणामं लक्ष्मणमुनिः प्रतिगृह्णातु मामकम् । प्रसाधयति यत्सूक्तिः स्वाधीनपतिकां श्रुतिम् ॥ ]&#xA;श्रीस्तवः ।&#xA;[Sri Vatsanka Misra was the loving disciple of Sri Ramanuja and was much loved and held in great esteem by all, both for his knowledge and saintly qualities. His devotion and saintliness were paralleled only by those of the Alvars- who were called as such, because they sank in the ocean of Bhakti to God-and so he also was called Kurattalvan (i. e., Alvan of Kuram, his birthplace near Conjivaram.) He is the author of a work called Yamakaratnakara and of five devotional psalms which go by the naine of Panca stava-Sri Stava, Varadaraja Stava, Sundarabahu Stava, Atimanusha Stava and Vaikuntha Stava-all in charming and moving and emotional verses.&#xA;His Sri Stava which is given below is in praise of the&#xA;Goddess Lakshmi in eleven verses.&#xA;The first is an invocation to the Goddess, the next four form an introduction to the poem and the next three describe the greatness of Lakshmi. The pra- patti to the Goddess (i.e. seeking shelter in Her) is done in the ninth and the tenth. The last is a prayer to the Goddess, for blessing the poct with Her benevolent glances.]&#xA;स्वस्ति श्रीर्दिशतादशेषजगतां सर्गोपसर्गस्थितीः&#xA;स्वर्गं दुर्गतिमापवर्गिकपदं सर्वं च कुर्वन् हरिः । यस्या वीक्ष्य मुखं तदितिपराधीनो विधत्तेऽखिलं&#xA;क्रीडेयं खलु नान्यथाऽस्य रसदा स्यादैकरस्यात्तया ॥ १ ॥&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>प्रज्ञाचार्यः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/prajNAchAryaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/kAvyam/padyam/shrIvaiShNava-kRtam/kUresha-shrIvatsAnka-mishraH/TIkA/prajNAchAryaH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/srisrivatsankami023991mbp/page/n117/mode/2up&#34;&gt;v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/SriSriVatsankamishraVirachitaPanchastaviPartIi&#34;&gt;v2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;[[TODO: परिष्कार्यम्]]&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्री हयग्रीवाय नमः&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्री श्री वत्साङ्कमिश्रविरचित&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;पञ्चस्त वी 5/1099&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;प्र थ म सम्पु टमु (श्री वैकुण्ठातिमानुष स्तवमुलु)&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;8107&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;कविशेखर - महोपाध्याय, विद्यालंकारि मध्वश्री पळ्लॆपूर्ण प्रज्ञाचार्यकृत भावादर्शनाम कान्ध्र विवरण सहितमु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;दासकु टी&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;प्रकाशितमु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;अङ्गलकुदुरु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;टी&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;4-00&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;मूल्यमु : 200&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;स म र्प ण मु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्री दासशेष बुध सेवित पादपद्मा : मोदादि सद्गुण समूह निवाससद्मा ! कोदण्डराम ! यिदिगो कॊनु काव्यकन्यका&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;1&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;नी दिव्य वैभवमुने कॊनियाडु मान्यज् ॥&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्री हयग्रीवाय नमः&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;लि प लु कु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;पञ्च स्तवी पवित्र कृतिकर्तलु प्रतिभाशालु लगु श्रीवत्साङ्क मिश्रुलु. वीरु कलि 4109 सौम्यसंवत्सर पुष्यमासमुन हस्तानक्षत्रमन्दु श्रीरामुनंशवलन हारीतान्वय सम्भू तुँडगु श्री मदनन्त भट्वार्युन कात्मजुलै यवतरिञ्चिरि. &amp;lsquo;नग रेषु काञ्ची&amp;rsquo; अनि प्रसिद्धि गाञ्चिन काञ्चीपुरमुनकुँ ब्रतीचीदिग्भाग मुनँ ग्रो सॆँडु दव्वुनँगल &amp;lsquo;कूर&amp;rsquo; नगरमु वीरि जन्मभूमि.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;मि. ई कूरनगरमुनकुँ ब्रभुवु लगुट चे वीरिकिँ गू रेशु लनियु द्रविडभाषलो &amp;lsquo;कूरत्ताळ्वा ननियुँ दिरुनाममु लेर्पडिनवि. वीरु ज्ञान भक्ति वैराग्यमुलकु निकषायमानुलु. इन्दुलकु वीरि पञ्चस्तविये निदर्शनमु.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;आगर्भ श्रीमन्तुलु वदान्युलु धर्मनिरतु लगु वीरु तामु कोरि पॆण्ड्लाडिन धर्मपत्नि याण्डाळ्ळु सहकरिम्पँ ब्रतिनित्यमु रवि युदयिञ्चिनदि मॊदलु रात्रि याम द्वयमुवऱकु &amp;lsquo;बधिर पङ्ग्वन्धभिक्षुक ब्रह्मचारि जटिपरि व्राजकातिथि&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;पूजलयन्दु निमग्नुलै युण्डॆडु वारु. अन्न शाला कलकलमुलु सन्नगिल्ल रात्रि पण्ड्रॆण्डु गण्टल वेळ मूयँबडु वीरिकोटगुम्मपुँ दलुपुल घण्टिका निनाद मुलु घल्लु मनि काञ्चीपुरमुनकु विनँबडुडु नेमिदि यनि श्री वरदराज प्रेयसि यगु श्रीमहालक्ष्मि विस्मितुरालै&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;2&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;भर्तृमुखमुनँ दत्कारण मारसि यी महनीयुनि दर्शनमुनकुँ दहतह लाडॆननँ गूरेशुल वैभवमुनु वेते वर्णिम्पवलॆना ?&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;कू रेशु लन्तँ गॊन्नाळ्ळकु निर्विणुलै &amp;lsquo;मदत्रय विही सस्य मुक्ति स्तस्य करे स्थिता&amp;rsquo; विद्याधनाभिजन मदमुलु लेनिवानि के कै वल्यमु करतलामलक मनि यॆञ्चि तन सर्वस्व मुनु सत्पात्रुल कॊसङ्गि सहधर्मिणितो श्रीरङ्गनाथुनि सेविम्प श्रीरङ्गमुनकु बयलु वॆडलिरि. धर्मपत्नि यगु नाण्डाळ्ळुमात्र मागर्भ श्रीमन्तुँ डगु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;तन भर्त क्षीरपान मॊनर्प नवरत्नखचित मगु नॊक बङ्गारु गिन्नॆनु वस्त्रमुलो दाँचि तॆच्चुचुण्डॆनु. अरण्यमार्गमुन भीतुरालै यातल्लि मुन्दु पोवुचुन्न भर्तनु जूचि नाथा ! यी यरण्यमार्गमुन भयमेमियु लेदुगदा ! यनि यडुग, &amp;lsquo;साध्वी! वित्तवन्तुनकु सर्वत्र भयमुगलदु. नीटिलोँ जेँपल चेत, नेलपैँ बुलुल चेत नाकसमुनँ बक्कुल चेत निमिषमु भक्षिम्पँबडुनट्लु धनवन्तुँ डॆल्लर चे भक्षिम्पँबडुनु. प्राणुलनु मृत्युवुवलॆ धनवन्तुलनु भयमु वॆण्टाडु&amp;rsquo; ननि तॆलिपि, तदय काणमु नॆऱिङ्गि, यामॆ दाँचियुञ्चिन रतनाल पैडिगिन्नॆनु नावलँ बाऱ&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;वै चॆनु. इदि श्री कूरेशुल पै राग्यमुनकु गीटुरायि.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;क्रममुगा नाळ्वानु धर्मपत्नितो श्रीरङ्गमुनु जेरु कॊनि, श्रीरङ्गेशुनि सेविञ्चि, यच्चटने वेञ्चेसियुन्न&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;भगवद्रामानुजुलकु साष्टाङ्ग मर्पिम्प गुरुवुलु श्री कूरेशुलु लेव नॆत्ति गाढालिङ्गन मॊनर्चि प्रियशिष्युनि राक कत्यन्त मुप्पॊङ्गिरि. नाँडु मॊदलुकॊनि कूरनाथुलु श्रीहरि गुरुवुल सेविञ्चुकॊनुचु नुञ्छवृत्ति नॊनर्चुचु श्रीरङ्गमुन सद्दोष्ठितोँ गालमु गडुपुचुण्डिरि. इट्लुण्ड नॊकनाँडु जडिवान, यॆड तॆऱपि लेक कुरियुट चेतँ गूरेशुल युञ्छवृत्ति कन्तरायमु गलिगॆनु. नाँडु स्नान मॊनर्चि यनुष्ठानमुल निर्वर्तिञ्चि पॆरुमाळ्ळपूज सलिपि फलमु निवेदन मॊनर्चि तीर्थमुनु मात्रमु ग्रहिञ्चिरि. सायङ्कालमु को वॆललो श्रीरङ्गनाथुनि सेविञ्चि यिण्टि करुदॆञ्चि शठारिसूक्त मुनु जपिञ्चुचु स्वस्थमुगाँ बरुण्डिरि. अन्त रङ्गनाथुनि कोवॆललो सायङ्काल निवेदन समयमु नन्दलि काहळी निनादमुलु चॆविँबडुडु श्री आण्डाळ्लु तनभर्त पस्तुण्डुटकु वगचुचु ‘स्वामि! श्री रङ्गनाथा! नीभक्तुँ डाँकट नलमटिम्प नी वारगिञ्चु चुन्नावा?&amp;rsquo; अनि मनस्सुलो ननुकॊनॆनु. भ क्त वत्सलुँ डगु रङ्गनाथुँ डा साध्वीमणि वाणि नालिञ्चि देवालय धर्माधिकारिकि स्वप्नमुन सा त्करिञ्चि शर्क राज्यादि सम्मिश्रमगु मत्प्रसादमुनु छत्र चामरादि वैभवमुतो श्रीकूरेशुल कर्पिम्पु मन धर्माधि कारियु नट्लु चेय श्रीवत्सचिह्नु लाश्चर्यभरितुलै यिदि येमन भार्य तानु मदिलो ननुकॊन्न माटनु मनवि चेसॆनु. इट्लु भगवानुनि नडुगवच्चुना ? अनि गृहिणिनि&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;4&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;मन्दलिञ्चि या प्रसादमुलो नॊक्किन्त तानु स्वीकरिञ्चि तक्किन प्रसादमु नर्धाङ्गि कीयङ्गा नासाध्वि दानिवलन गर्भमुनु दाल्चि विलक्षणुलगु निर्वुरँ गुमारुलँ ग नॆनु. वारि योग क्षेममुल नॆल्ल श्री रङ्गनाथुँडे चूचुकॊनु चुण्डॆनु. इदि वीरियॆड श्री रङ्गनाथुनकुँ गल वात्सल्याति शयमुनकुँ दार्काण.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ऒकतऱि नुद्दण्ड पण्डितुलगु यादव प्रकाशुलु भगव द्रामानुजस्वामिवारि मठमुनकु वेञ्चेसि &amp;lsquo;स्वामि.! मी रॊनर्चु शङ्खचक्रोर्ध्वपुण्ड्रादि धारणमुनकु सगुण ब्रह्मो पासनमुनकुनु शास्त्रमुलँ ब्रमाणमुलु गानरावु. उन्न चो नुपन्यसिम्पुँ डन श्रीवारु तम शिष्युलगु कूरेशुल नियमिम्प &amp;rsquo; श्रूयता मभिधास्यामि शङ्खचक्रादिधारणे । सगुणब्रह्मसद्भावे&amp;rsquo; अनि श्रीवत्साङ्कुलु गम्भीरोपन्यास मॊसँगि प्रतिपक्षुल नीरु त्तरुलँ जेसिन विषयमु वीरि पाण्डिती प्रतिभलकु श्रुति स्मृतीहासाभिज्ञतकु मञ्चिलक्ष्यमु.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;जूडँ&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;श्री भगवद्रामानुजुलु श्री यामुनमुनुल सङ्कल्पमु नीडेर्प श्रीभाष्यमुनु रचिम्प नॆञ्चि काश्मीरमुन शारदा पीठमुन नुन्न बोधायन वृत्ति ग्रन्थमुनु गूरेशादि शिष्युलतो नट केँगि सौजन्यमुतो वृत्ति ग्रन्थमुन मॊदटि यध्यायमुनु साङ्गमुगाँ जूचिरि. कुशाग्रबुद्धुलगु कूरेशुलु तक्किन यध्यायमुल नवलोकिञ्चिरि. अन्तलोन मतान्तरुल&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ग्रन्थालयाधिकारुल&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;5&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;मायमाटलचे नधिकारु लाग्रन्थमुनु गैकॊनि मऱल नीयक पोवुटचे ना चार्युलवारु तपिञ्चुचुण्ड श्रीकूरे शुलु स्वामी ! विचारमु वलदु. दासुँडु तक्किन यध्या यत्रयिलो नेपङ्क्तियैन नप्पगिम्पँ गलँडनि विन्नविञ्चि गुरुपादुल चेत नोकू रेशा ! नी वुण्डुटवलन श्रीयामुन मुनुलु परमपद मलङ्करिञ्चिनट्लु नेनु भाविञ्चुट लेदनि प्रशंसिम्पँ बडुट वीरि धारणाशक्तिकि गुरुप्रसादलब्धिकिँ ब्रबलदृष्टान्तमु.&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;इट्लु कूरनाथु लाचार्याभिमानमुनु जूऱ गॊनि श्रीरङ्गेशुनि सेविञ्चुकॊनुचु सुखमुगाँ गालमु गडुपु चुण्डँगा जरिगिन विचित्र सङ्घटन मॆट्टिवारि केनियु हृदय विदारकमु काकपोदु, अत्तऱि राजेन्द्र चोळ पुरमु राजधानिगाँ जोळमण्डल मेलुचुन्न कुलोत्तुङ्ग चोळराजु शैवमताभिमानियै विष्णुद्वेषमु पट्टँजालक वैष्णवपण्डितुल चे &amp;lsquo;शिवात् परतरं नास्ति&amp;rsquo; अनु वाक्यमुनु व्रायिञ्चुचुण्ड ‘नालू रान्&amp;rsquo; अनु नॊक वैष्णवुँ डितरु लॆन्द ऱट्लु व्रासिन नेमि प्रयोजनमु. भगवद्रामानु जुलु व्रासिनँगदा याव्रातकु विलुव यनँगा ना पाषण्ड राजु श्री रामानुजुलनु गॊनिरण्डनि यमकिङ्करुलँ बोलु तन किङ्करुलनु बम्प वारु श्रीरङ्गमुनँ गल रामानुज मठमुँ जेरुकॊनि रामानुजुलवा रॆच्चट अनि यडुग वारिनि जूडँग ने सूक्ष्मबुद्धियगु कूरे&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;6&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;शुँडु गुरुलकु रानुन्न यापदनु गुर्तिञ्चि स्नानमु केँगिन गुरुवुल काषाय त्रिदण्डमुलँ रामानुजुलनि वारि वॆण्ट&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;वॆण्ट नु,&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ज&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;धरिञ्चि ताने कूरेशुल वीड लेक&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;वारि कण्डग श्री महापूर्णुलुनु वारितो राजसभ केगिरि, स्नान मॊनर्चि वच्चिन श्री रामानुजमुनु लन्तयु विनि शिष्युल केमि विपत्तु घटिल्लुनो यनि वगचिरि, इङ्क नचट नुण्डुट यनर हेतुवनि यचटिवारु पलुविधमुल विन्न विम्प श्रीरामानुजुलु तक्किन शिष्युलतोँ दिरु&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;Ф&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;नारायण पुरमुनकु वेञ्चेसिरि. अचट चोळराजु तन किङ्करुलु कॊनिवच्चिन वैष्णव पण्डितुलँ जूचि &amp;lsquo;शिवा त्परतरं नास्ति&amp;rsquo; यनि व्रायुँडनि कोर वारु श्रुति स्मृति पुराणादुलनुण्डि प्रमाणमुलँ जूपुचुँ ब्रति पक्षुल निरुत्तरुलँ जेयुचु विष्णुवे परात्परुँडनि चाटिरि. अन्दुलकुँ जोळरा जाग्रहिञ्चि मीरु मी यिष्टमु वच्चिन ट्लेमेमो प्रसङ्गिञ्चुचुन्नारु. मेमु चॆप्पिनट्लु व्रायुदुरा ! कन्नुलँ दीयिम्पमन्दुरा ! अनि गट्टिगा ँ बलुकँ गूरेशुलु व्यङ्ग्यभङ्गिगा विष्णुसर्वोत्त मत्वमु ने चाटुचु &amp;lsquo;शिवात् परतरं नास्ति द्रोण मस्ति ततः परम्&amp;rsquo; अनि व्रायुडुँ बाषण्डभूपति यदि ग्रहिञ्चि वारि ग्रुड्लु दीयिञ्चॆनु. इदि निजमुगा हृदयविदारक मेगदा ! दीनिच्चे वयोधिकुलगु महापूर्णुलु मार्गमध्यमुन ने मरणिञ्चिरि. कू रेशुलु श्रीरङ्गमुनु जेरँबोवु रामा&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;H&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;ด7&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;नुज सम्बन्धु लिं दॆव्वरुनु ब्रवेशिम्परादु. इदि राजु शासन मनि द्वारा पालुरु निरोधिम्प &amp;lsquo;अवुनु. नेनु रामानुजुल सम्बन्धिनि, श्रीरङ्ग सेवनैननु मानुकॊन्दुनु गानि या चार्यसम्बन्धमुनु दॆगँ द्रॆञ्चुकॊनँ जाल’ननि यटनुण्डि सकुटुम्बमुगा सुन्दर भुज&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dt&gt;स्वामिनि सेविम्प वनगिरिकिँ ब्रयाण मॊनर्चिरि. मार्गमध्यमुन सत्वर मुगा सद्गुरुसमागम भाग्यलाभमुनकु नेत्रबाधास्मृति निरोधमुनकु भगवत्कल्याण गुणानुभव मॊनर्चुकॊनुचु महाकवुलगु श्री कूरेशुलु &amp;lsquo;पञ्च स्तवी&amp;rsquo; रचन कुपक्र मिञ्चिरि. पञ्चानां स्तवानां समाहारः&amp;rsquo; अनु विग्रह वाक्यमु चेत नी पदमुन कैदु स्तवमुल कूट मनि यर्थमु. लक्ष्मी कटाक्षमु पुरुष कारमुगा नन्निटिकि न पेक्षणीयमु · गानँ दॊलुदॊल्त &amp;lsquo;श्री स्तव मनु पेर&lt;/dt&gt;&#xA;&lt;dd&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;श्रीस्तव 11 श्लोकमुलतो श्री देविनि वर्णिञ्चिनारु. आवल वैकुण्ठ&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
