<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Articles on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/elephant/articles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Articles on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/elephant/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1940 elephant puNDra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/elephant/articles/1940_elephant_puNDra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/elephant/articles/1940_elephant_puNDra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While deciding on Elephant, it has decided as follows in the last but third paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;“After all the elephant is one forms a part of the paraphernalia of the chief deity and in this temple the chief deity bears admittedly a Vadagalai namam and it has been found that should so wear. It is usual in any temple that the mark on the paraphernalia of any deity should be the same as the marks of the chief deity. Further this elephant is a gift by His Highness of Maharaja of Travancore with a condition that the elephant that the elephant should be painted with a Vadagalai namam Vide XXIV-the letter of the Chief Secretary. Therefore the donor’s wishes that it should be painted only with a Vadagalai namam should be complied with and there is no reason for not doing so. By the elephant being adorned with a Vadagalai namam the fundamental character of the institution or the nature of worship there is not altered. It has been the usage for the temple elephant to bear the Vadagalai namam from at least 1834 or 1893 and donor’s wish is that it should be painted with Vadagalai namam on the face. To order a Thengalai namam for the elephant would be introducing really an innovation. We therefore, direct the elephant now presented by His Highness the Maharaja of Travancore should be painted with a Vadagalai namam. The elephant will have a Vadagalai mark. The aggrieved Thenkalai community filed O.S.7 of 1945 before the District Judge, Chingleput challenging this order. The suit was dismissed on merits. Thereupon the Thenkalai Community filed a Appeal before the High Court of Madras in Appeal against Order No.111 of 1948. They withdrew the same “Adocate for Appellant (Thenklai) representing that the matter had been settled out of court and requesting for permission to withdraw the appeal and also representing that the appellants will not proceed with the suit it is ORDERED that the appeal be hereby is dismissed as withdrawn and it is further ordered that there be no costs to this appeal.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1977 Judgement</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/elephant/articles/1977-judgement-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/kAnchI/varadarAja-mandiram/elephant/articles/1977-judgement-summary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://indiankanoon.org/doc/1666870/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;R. Thathadesika Thathachariar And Anr. vs K.V. Alagia Manavala Jeerswamy (Died) &amp;hellip; on 9 September, 1976&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Madras High Court&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Equivalent citations: AIR1978MAD210, AIR 1978 MADRAS 210, ILR (1978) 1 MAD 125 (1977) 2 MADLJ247, (1977) 2 MADLJ247&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Author: P.S. Kailasam&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Bench: P.S. Kailasam&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;JUDGMENT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;P.S. Kailasam, C.J.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Defendants 2 and 3 in the suit are the appellants in the Letters Patent Appeal. The suit was filed by plaintiffs 1 to 4. They are residents of Kancheepuram and are Thengalai Vaishnavites holding offices in Sri Devaraja Swami Temple. The suit was filed for themselves and as representatives of the entire body of Thengalai Vaishnavites of Kancheepuram, who are office holders and mirasdars of Sri Devaraja Swami Temple. The dispute mainly relates to the namam which the temple elephant should bear. The elephant died on 28-3-1965. According to the planitiffs, the trustees were making an attempt to get an elephant themselves and introduce it with Vadagalai namam. According to the plaintiffs, the established usage of the temple is that the elephant should have only a Thengalai namam. As the plaintiffs apprehended that the trustees would induct an ele-&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;phant with a Vadagalai namam, they offered to present an elephant provided it bore the Thengalai namam. They also apprehended that the trustees, who belonged to the Vadagalai sect, might introduce an elephant with a Vadagalai namam and therefore sought to prevent it. The reliefs they sought in this suit were a direction to the defendants to accept the gift of an elephant to the suit temple by the plaintiffs or their nominees and have it painted with Thengalai namam on all occasions inside and outside the temple and in temple processions with Deities or when connected with the worship and other ceremonies of the temple as per the decree in A. S. No. 13 of 1854 and a permanent injunction restraining the defendants or their agents or servants from putting Vadagalai namam to the living elephant donated, maintained or possessed by the temple and using the same for any festivals, processions, functions or occasions of the temple.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
