<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;१ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;१ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Introductory</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1. May the water of the Puṣkara lake purify you—the water which is clean; which is clear like the moon; in which foam is produced by the commotion of elephants’ trunks and of crocodiles; which is frequented by the chief Brāhmaṇas engaged in the (observance of) vows and restraints for the realisation of Brahman; which is sanctified by the sight of Brahmā adorned by Oṃkāra and the Lord of the three worlds; which is delightful due to (its being fit for) enjoyment; and which removes evil.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Contents of the Section on Creation (Sṛṣṭi-khaṇḍa)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-spoke&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta spoke&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I salute the Lord of all human beings and of the entire world, of the form of Creation and the Knower of Pradhāna (i.e. Sāṃkhya Prakṛti). He creates this disposition in me.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. He, the Creator of the worlds, the Knower of their essential nature, conversant with Yoga (-doctrines), resorting to the concentration of mind created all immobile and mobile beings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Being desirous of knowing the story of the Purāṇa I submit myself to Him—the unborn, the creator of everything, the Lord of souls, the Observer of the worlds, and the Supreme Ruler.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Kinds of Creation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. How is it possible for Brahman, the quality-less, unlimited, pure and great, to be the author of the creation etc.?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. As the potentialities of all objects are inconceivable and inapprehensible, so are those powers of creation of Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. The wise one who is born is only secondarily described to be eternal; and by his own measure his life-span is said to be a hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 The birth of Lakṣmī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I have heard that Lakṣmī was born in the white ocean. How did you say that she was born of Khyāti from Bhṛgu?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. How did the auspicious daughter of Dakṣa give up her body? And how was she conceived by Menā and born as Umā?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Why did the lord of lords take Himālaya’s daughter as his wife? And why did he have hostility with Dakṣa? May the revered one tell this to me.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Destruction of Dakṣa’s Sacrifice</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. How did Satī, Dakṣa’s auspicious daughter, cast off her body? For what reason was Dakṣa’s sacrifice destroyed by Rudra?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. I have also a desire to know why lord Śiva, the destroyer of Tripura and greatly renowned, got angry.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-spoke&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya spoke&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. O Bhīṣma, in olden time, Dakṣa commenced a sacrifice at Haridvāra. There hosts of gods, Pitṛs (manes), and great sages, all gods with Indra, Nāgas, Yakṣas, Suparṇas, creepers and herbs, and revered Kaśyapa, Atri, Pulastya, Pulaha, Kratu, Pracetas, Aṅgiras and Vasiṣṭha of great penance had assembled. Making the altar even, he appointed four priests. Vasiṣṭha was the Hotṛ (reciting the Ṛgvedic prayers at the sacrifice); Aṅgiras was the best Adhvaryu (officiating priest); Bṛhaspati was the Udgātṛ (chanting the hymns of Sāmaveda) and Nārada the Brahmā (-priest). When the sacrifice commenced and oblations were offered into fires, all the Vasus and the twelve Ādityas, the two Aśvins, Maruts and the fourteen Manus arrived there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Birth of Devas, Daityas, Birds and Serpents etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O sire, tell me duly and in detail, about the birth of gods, demons and of the Gandharvas, serpents and goblins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-spoke&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya spoke&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. The creation in ancient times is said to be effected by volition, sight and touch; (but) the creation after Prācetasa Dakṣa is effected by coitus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. Listen, O Kaurava, as to how he created (gods etc.): When he was creating groups of gods, sages and serpents, the world did not grow. So Dakṣa generated thousands of sons on his young maid-servant.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Description of Manu Periods</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. How did Maruts, the sons of Diti; become dear to gods, and how did they have excellent intimacy with gods?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-spoke&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya spoke&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Formerly, in the war between the gods and the demons, when, by Hari and gods, her sons and grandsons were killed, Diti, afflicted with grief, went to the excellent terrestrial globe.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. At the great sacred place in Puṣkara, on the auspicious bank of the Sarasvatī, Diti the mother of the Daityas, intent upon propitiating her husband, practised a severe penance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Description of the Solar Race (Ādityavaṃśa or Sūryavaṃśa)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. It is heard that the earth was formerly enjoyed by many kings. They are (called) Pārthiva on account of their connection with the earth; but on account of (its) connection with whom is the Pṛthvī (earth) so called?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Why is the earth given that technical name? Tell me why it has the name Gau, or why it is (called) Bhū?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Formerly Aṅga by name was the Prajāpati of the &lt;em&gt;Kṛtayuga&lt;/em&gt;. He married Mṛtyu’s extremely ugly daughter named Sunīthā. Her son was Vena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 General Rules of Śrāddha Performance</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O revered one, I wish to learn about the best family of the manes (&lt;em&gt;pitṛs&lt;/em&gt;), and also particularly of Ravi, of the deity of Śrāddha i.e. Soma.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. I shall narrate to you the best family of the manes. In the heaven there are seven groups of the manes. Out of them three are incorporeal.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Of all (the manes) of unlimited lustre four are corporeal. The incorporeal groups of manes are said to belong to Vairāja Prajāpati.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 The Greatness of Pitṛs</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I shall now explain the &lt;em&gt;Ekoddiṣṭa&lt;/em&gt; (a &lt;em&gt;śrāddha&lt;/em&gt; performed for one definite deceased individual, not including other ancestors) described by Brahmā formerly as to how the sons should perform it till the purification from personal defilement caused by the death of the father.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. For a brāhmaṇa the defilement caused by the death is said to be for ten days; for a kṣatriya it is for twelve days, for a Vaiśya it is for a fortnight and for a Śudra it is for one month on the death of a &lt;em&gt;Sapiṇḍa&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 A list of sacred places (tīrtha)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I. During which portion of the day should the performer of a &lt;em&gt;Śrāddha&lt;/em&gt; perform it? O brāhmaṇa, what are the sacred places in which &lt;em&gt;Śrāddha&lt;/em&gt; performed gives abundant fruit?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-spoke&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya spoke&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. The sacred place named Puṣkara, is said to be the greatest. Presents or offerings made there, or muttering done there certainly becomes endless. It is always dear to the manes and is regarded as great by the sages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 The dynasty of Yadu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O learned one, tell me now how the Soma dynasty came up and which kings were born in that family that increased its fame.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. Formerly Atri was ordered by Brahmā to create. Then the lord practised penance for creation. (It was) delightful, removing the trouble of Brahmā, nearest to Brahmā, Rudra, Indra and Sūrya and supra-sensual.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. Having made his mind tranquil Atri then remained restrained. Even the greatness of penance causes great delight. Since the chief of the dynasty then stood out it increased by half and since Soma having seen him reported it he became mighty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 The Deeds of the Avatāra (Incarnation)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O king of kings, listen to (the account) of Kroṣṭṛ’s family (in which) excellent men (were born). In his family was born Viṣṇu, the perpetuator of the Vṛṣṇi family.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. From Kroṣṭṛ was born Vṛjinīvān, of great fame. His son was Svāti, and Kuśaṅku was his (i.e. Svāti’s) son.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Kuśaṅku had a son Citraratha by name; his son named Śaśabindu became a sovereign emperor.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. About him this verse containing the genealogical table was formerly sung. The hundred sons of Śatabindu had a hundred sons. From those hundred intelligent, handsome and important sons resplendent with great wealth were born the very mighty kings having the appellation Pṛthu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 Chopping-off of Brahmā’s head by Rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Tell me how Arjuna, the killer of the brave enemies, was born from Tripuruṣa; how again, Karṇa, the son of an unmarried woman is known as born from a charioteer; how enmity sprang up between the two. I have a great curiosity; so please tell me that.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. Formerly when his face was rent, Brahma, overpowered by great anger, took up the perspiration produced on his forehead and struck it on the ground; from that perspiration a brave hero having rings, arrows and a great bow and having a thousand armours was born and he said: “What shall I do?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Importance of Dwelling at a sacred place (tīrtha)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. What did Brahmā do after having sent (Rudra) to Vārāṇasī? What work did Viṣṇu do? Tell me (also), O sage, what Śaṅkara did, which sacrifice he performed, and at which sacred place (he performed it). Who were the assistant priests and who were the officiating priests? Tell me about them all. I have great curiosity (to know) who were the gods that he gratified.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4. On Meru’s peak there is a city named Śrīnidhāna. It is variegated with jewels; is the abode of many wonders; is full of many trees; is variegated with many minerals and is clear like spotless crystal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 The acquisition of Gāyatrī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O brāhmaṇa, (now) that you have narrated to me the excellent importance of the sacred place, that the sacred place was produced on the surface of the earth by the fall of the lotus, best among the sages, tell me all that revered Viṣṇu and Śaṅkara, who stayed there, did.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. (Tell me) how the sacrifice was performed by the all-powerful god. Who were the members? Who were the priests? Which brāhmaṇas arrived there?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Sāvitrī’s curses and Gāyatrī’s boons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O best brāhmaṇa, then what was the wonder there at the sacrifice? How did Rudra stay there? How also did Viṣṇu, the best of gods, reside there? What did Gāyatrī, who was positioned as (Brahmā’s) wife do there? O sage, what did the cowherds of good conduct do after having come to know (about the seizure of Gāyatrī)? Tell me this story—as to what took place and what was done by the cowherds and Brahmā. I have a great curiosity (to know) it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 The greatness of Nandā-Prācī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Indeed, O brāhmaṇa, I am hearing something very wonderful—the consecration of Gāyatrī performed like that in the (sacrificial) assembly; Sāvitrī’s opposition and curses; Viṣṇu’s glorification of all her places.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. Gāyatrī, of an excellent complexion, also was praised by Rudra. Hearing in detail about the grandsire the very likeness of the soul, my hair has bristled, and my mind has become very tranquil. Having heard it I am very much pleased and have great curiosity (to know what took place later). Revered Nārāyaṇa, having in that way very much praised Brahmā’s wife with devotion, and placed her on the mountain, uttered the words giving satistaction and strength. I heard (about) Śrīmatī, Hrīmatī and (about)the chief goddess—this much only that came out of your mouth (i.e. whatever you said). The revered one may please tell me in order as to what took place afterwards and what was done at that place. There is no doubt that by hearing it my body will be purified.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 Conversation of the Seven Sages</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. I have heard the excellent (account of) the greatness of Puṣkara and Nandā. I have heard all that, viz. that a crore of sages came there and all became handsome on seeing the (reflections of their) faces in (the water of) Puṣkara. Tell me how they divided the portions of land. How did the magnanimous ones divide the sacred place? How did they fashion the other holy hermitages also? Viṣṇu first stepped on the sacrificial mountain. Then serpents of great (i.e. severe) poison fashioned a holy place there. Who first fashioned the well for the offering of balls of rice to the manes? How did Gaṅgā-Sarasvatī, going underground, flow towards the north? (Please) tell me how the brāhmaṇas well-versed in the Vedas should undertake the pilgrimage of the triad of Puṣkara and what fruit accrues from it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 The rules of ablution</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Please narrate in detail and truthfully, to me who am asking you, another charming account (capable of) destroying sins, also of the Madhyama (Puṣkara) glorified by the sages and the fruit of (offering) food, and the importance of restraint (as told by them). And also, O great sage, tell me where Viṣṇu planted his foot, and how the Kaniṣṭha (Puṣkara) came about.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. Formerly in the Rathantara Kalpa, there was a king by name Puṣpavāhana who was well-known among people and like the sun in lustre. Pleased with his penance, the four-faced one (i.e. Brahmā) gave him a golden lotus going at will, O king of the Bharata-family.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 The greatness of Puṣkara and some important vows</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. Formerly in the &lt;em&gt;Bṛhatkalpa&lt;/em&gt;, there was a king by name Dharmamūrti who was a friend of Indra and who had killed thousands of demons. Due to his lustre, the Moon and the Sun had lost their brilliance. He had defeated demons in hundreds, could take any form he liked and was undefeated even among (i.e. by) men.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3b-4. That king had the chief queen Bhānumatī by name, the most beautiful lady in the three worlds, who resembled Lakṣmī in beauty and had vanquished divine beauties (by means of her beauty), and who was greater (i.e. dearer) to the king than his own life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 On vows (vrata)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. &lt;em&gt;Bhūḥ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bhuvaḥ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Svaḥ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mahaḥ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tapas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Satya&lt;/em&gt; are said to be the seven worlds. How can one have the lordship over all these in turn? O brāhmaṇa, who are honoured by gods, how can one have handsome form, (long) life and (good) health, and also ample wealth in this world?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-10. Formerly Indra ordered Agni, along with Vāyu, to destroy the enemies of gods. When he consequently burnt the demons in thousands, (the demons) Tāraka, Kamalākṣa, Kāladaṃṣṭra, Parāvasu, Virocana and Saṃhrāda entered the ocean and remained deep in it. Taking them to be weak, Agni and Vāyu ignored them. Since then they harass gods, men and snakes and all sages and then again enter the ocean. In this way, O king, those heroes have harassed, on the strength of the water (of the ocean) being inaccessible, the three worlds for seven and five (i.e. twelve) thousand yugas. Then again Indra ordered Agni and Vāyu: “Dry up this ocean immediately. Since this abode of Varuṇa (i.e. the ocean) is the shelter of our enemies, therefore you should today only dry it up.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 The vow (vrata) for Prostitutes (veśyā)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O lord of brāhmaṇas, tell me what kind of practices in honour of Viṣṇu are (observed), as Rudra had told them, and. what their fruit is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. Formerly, in the Rathantara Kalpa, Mahādeva (i.e. Śiva), the trident-holder (who was), living on Mandara, was asked by Brahmā, the great-souled one, himself: “How can men always have good health, endless prosperity and salvation by (practising) little penance, O god? O Adhokṣaja&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; what is that knowledge, which (obtained) through your favour even by little penance is said to be very fruitful in this world?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 The vow (vrata) of Aṅgāraka Caturthī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahmā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O revered sir, tell me (about) that (vow) which causes blessing (i.e. divine favour) to a man as well as a woman, and by (the observance of) which there will be no grief, disease, fear or sorrow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaṅkara-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaṅkara said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. On the second day of the dark half of Śrāvaṇa, Madhusūdana always lives with his wife in the milky ocean. A man would get (i.e. fulfil) all his desires by worshipping Govinda on that (day). He should give the present of a cow, gold etc. as was done in seven hundred &lt;em&gt;Kalpas&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 The Vow of Ādityaśayana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Tell me about the vow that is desirable for one who is unable to observe fasts due to lack of practice or ill health.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Hear about that great vow in (the performance of) which meal at night is prescribed for those who are unable to observe fasts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. It is called &lt;em&gt;Ādityaśayana&lt;/em&gt; in which Śaṅkara is to be properly worshipped. (Listen to) the conjunctions of constellations (and planets), which, those who are well-versed in the Purāṇas, prescribe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 The vow of Rohiṇīcandraśayana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I. Tell me properly about the vow of the cool-rayed one (i.e. the Moon), by (the observance of) which a man would be endowed with a long life, good health and his family’s great prosperity, as well as a (handsome) form and (noble) family, in every existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. I shall (now) tell you fully the secret (vow) leading to the unending (residence in) heaven, (and) which those who are well-versed in the Purāṇas know. This vow is here called &lt;em&gt;Rohiṇīcandra-śayana&lt;/em&gt;. A man should perform Nārāyaṇa’s worship with the accompaniment of the epithets of the Moon in (i.e. while observing) that vow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 The rite (vidhi) of installation of Lakes etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. O brāhmaṇa, tell me in detail, about the rite (which is performed) with reference to lakes, gardens, ponds, wells and ponds full of lotuses, and temples of deities. Tell me which brāhmaṇas are employed as the priests there; (tell me) also (about) the fees to be paid to the priests, (about) the offerings, the time, the place and the preceptor. O you of a good vow, tell me also about the components that are prescribed (for the rite).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 The rite (vidhi) of planting of trees (pādapa)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. O brahman, tell me in detail about the rite (which is performed) with reference to (the planting of) trees (&lt;em&gt;pādapa&lt;/em&gt;). Also tell me about the worlds that are said (to exist).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-3. O King, I shall describe to you the rite with reference to the (planting) of trees in gardens and other places. O lord of the worlds, having accomplished everything as in the case of the rite with reference to the lakes, he should worship the priests, parts of the pavilion and also the preceptor like that (i. e. in the same way).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 The vow (vrata) called Saubhāgyaśayana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Similarly I shall tell you about another (vow) fulfilling all desires. Those who are well-versed in the Purāṇas know it to be &lt;em&gt;Saubhāgya-śayana&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Formerly when worlds like &lt;em&gt;Bhūḥ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bhuvaḥ&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Svaḥ&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mahaḥ&lt;/em&gt; were burnt, then the good fortune of all the beings became (concentrated) at one place.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5a. All that, having reached Vaikuṇṭha, remained in the chest of Viṣṇu. O king, then, when, after some time, at the time of creation again, the world was covered over with &lt;em&gt;Ahaṃkāra&lt;/em&gt;, and was linked to &lt;em&gt;Pradhāna&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Puruṣa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and when the rivalry between Brahmā and Viṣṇu had increased, a terrible tawny flame of fire arose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 Origin of Viṣṇu’s steps</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4a. Having reached the sacrificial mountain. the powerful Viṣṇu planted his foot (-steps) there. What is the purpose of this line of the foot (-steps) which the lord of lords planted? O highly intelligent one, tell me (about) that. O great sage, tell me which demon he subdued after having planted his foot (-steps) there. The residence of Viṣṇu is in heaven, the great-souled one lives in Vaikuṇṭha. How is it that he planted his foot (-step) in the human world?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 The account of Śivadūtī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O revered one, the killing of Bāṣkali is a great wonder I have heard (the account) being narrated by best brāhmaṇas (that Viṣṇu) had taken the form of Trivikrama (i.e. Vāmana) when he had formerly subdued Bali, the son of Vairocana who even now stays in &lt;em&gt;Pātāla&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. (Tell me now as to) how Nāgatīrtha came into being, and also (tell me about) the origin of goblins, and how Śivadūti came there and who made her auspicious.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>32 Descent of a Holy Place</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/32/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/32/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you highly intelligent one, tell me, as a result of which deeds the condition of an evil spirit is produced (i.e. as a result of which one turns into an evil spirit after death); and also (tell me) by (doing which) deeds one is freed from here (i.e. this condition of evil spirit).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O best king, I shall entirely tell you all this, hearing which you will not be deluded.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>33 Rāma’s Visit to Mārkaṇḍeya’s Hermitage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/33/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/33/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O sage, how was Rāma enlightened here by Mārkaṇ-ḍeya? How did they meet? When did they meet?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Whose son was Mārkaṇḍeya? How was the one of great penance born? O great sage, tell me the exact explanation of his name.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. I shall tell you about the birth of Mārkaṇḍeya. In the old Kalpa there was a well-known sage by name Mṛkaṇḍu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4. The illustrious (sage), the son of Bhṛgu, practised penance with his wife. When he was living in a forest, a son was born to him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>34 The gift of Brahmāṇḍa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/34/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/34/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Please tell me when revered Brahmā, the creator of the worlds, commenced to perform a sacrifice with the requisites.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Who were the priests that he employed at the sacrifice? What sacrificial fees did the great-souled one pay them?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. (Please) tell me as it happened, as it took place; there is a great curiosity in me to know about the sacrifice of (i.e. performed by) Brahmā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>35 The Killing of a Śūdra Ascetic</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/35/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/35/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The revered one has told (me) everything based on the Purāṇa; and also (has narrated to me) how (king) Śveta presented Brahmāṇḍa to his preceptor.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Hearing this curiosity has arisen (in me) as to how, O brāhmaṇa, he licked (his own) bones in the absence of (i.e. as a result of his non-gifting of) food.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. I desire to hear that; I also desire to hear about other kings on the earth who reached heaven due to (i.e. as a result of) giving food; for sacrifices are based on food.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>36 Conversation between Rāma and Agastya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/36/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/36/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then the gods went by many aeroplanes. Rāma too quickly went to the penance-grove of Agastya.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. (He thought:) ‘The revered one, who had formerly come to see me in my assembly, had told me to go to him again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. So by the order of gods and for their work I shall go and see that great sage, honoured by gods and demons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4. And the best one will advise me so that I shall never again be unhappy in this mortal world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>37 Rāma’s Abstaining from the Performance of Rājasūya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/37/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/37/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The descendant of Raghu, having heard those most wonderful words, asked Agastya again, prompted by the importance of the ornament and through amazement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;rāma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rāma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. (Tell me) O revered sir, (about) the fearful forest where the Vidarbha-king Śveta practised penance. Tell me how the wonderful thing took place there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Tell me how, (when) the fearful forest was desolate and void of beasts the king entered it to practise penance, O great sage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>38 The Installation of the Image of Vāmana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/38/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/38/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O brāhmaṇa-sage, how did Rāma install (the image of) Vāmana at Kānyakubja? Where did he get him (i.e. the image)? Tell me (all this) in detail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O revered one, similarly the sweet words with which you described Rāma, gave pleasure to my ears.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. People look at Rāma with love and affection. Rāma, who knows virtue, who is grateful, who is firm in mind and who is well-composed, rules over the entire world righteously.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>39 The Birth of the Lotus (padma)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/39/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/39/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. You have narrated in detail the importance of Vāmana. Tell me again any other (point of) importance than this, pertaining to Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. How did the lotus arise in the lord’s navel from which the world sprang up? How did the creation of Viṣṇu formerly take place in the lotus?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. How was the world of lotus formed in the great cycle of time (Mahākalpa) called Padma in the navel of Viṣṇu, who had entered the ocean and slept there?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>40 The army of Demons (Asuras)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/40/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/40/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Then the lord, created Brahmā, the best among those endowed with yoga, of a great lustre, the creator of all worlds and having faces in all directions, in that golden lotus, extending over many &lt;em&gt;Yojanas&lt;/em&gt;, having all qualities of lustre and covered over with (i.e. having) earthly characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. The great sages say that that excellent lotus formed in olden times, and of the nature of the earth, sprang from Nārāyaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>41 The Rise of the Lotus and the War between Gods &amp; Demons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/41/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/41/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. The Ādityas, the Vasus, the two mighty Aśvins got ready for battle with their troops and followers in due order.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. The thousand-eyed Indra, the guardian of the worlds and the leader of gods mounted on an excellent elephant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6a. To his right stood the chariot, which had the best bird (i.e. Garuḍa) as its banner; which moved on very fine wheels; which was adorned with a golden umbrella; which was followed by the multitudes of gods, Gandharvas and Yakṣas in thousands; which was eulogised by brahmanic brilliant sages living in heaven; having mounted upon which chariot, furnished with multitudes of clouds having the lustre of lightning and rain-bow risen due to the vibration of the thunderbolt, and resembling mountains moving according to their will, the lord moves in the entire world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>42 Tāraka’s Victory in the War between Gods and Demons</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/42/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/42/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhiṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhiṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O brahman, I have listened to (the account of) the rise of the lotus which you described in detail. O brahman, (now) I desire to hear from you about the greatness of Bhava (i.e. Śiva) and the birth of Guha (i.e. Kārttikeya)—how he was born and what he did; how Tāraka the demon became more powerful and how that great demon was killed (by Kārttikeya); how Rudra sent the sages to the Mandara mountain; how Rudra, the supreme lord, obtained Umā there. O great sage, tell me all this as it took place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>43 Gaurī’s Marriage</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/43/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/43/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. The door-keeper, who had put on a bright silken garment appeared (before the king of demons). Going down to (i.e. touching) the ground on his knees, he, without delay. said the following adorned with (i.e. couched in) few words, to the lord of demons, having a bright body resembling a host of suns.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. “Having brought the gods, after binding them, Kālanemi stands at the door. He respectfully asks: ‘O lord, where should the captives stay?’”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>44 The Birth of Kumāra and the Death of Tārarka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/44/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/44/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śarva-ie-śiva-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śarva (i.e. Śiva) said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O you of slender body, joined with my white body, you will shine like a black female-serpent clung to a white sandal tree or like night covered with reddish garment touched by moonlight.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Thus addressed by him, the Mountain’s daughter, with her eyes red due to anger, and her face changed due to (the knitting of) the eye-brows, loudly spoke.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-goddess-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The goddess said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-5. Every person grieves due to the foolish acts done by him; O you, having the moon as your decoration, a suppliant certainly meets with a rebuff. You are certainly, at every step, insulting me, who sought you by means of penance practised for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>45 The Manifesṭation of Narasiṃha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/45/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/45/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Now I desire to hear about the killing of Hiraṇyakaśipu, about the greatness of Narasiṃha and about the destruction that he brought about.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O king, formerly, in the Kṛta age, Hiraṇyakaśipu, the lord of demons, practised a very great (i.e. severe) penance. He, surrounded by (i.e. observing) tranquility, restraint and celibacy and having taken up the vow of bath and silence lived in water for ten thousand and ten hundred years. Brahmā was pleased with him as a result of his penance and restraint.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>46 Purificatory Rites of a Brāhmaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/46/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/46/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. You have told (me) in detail the greatness of Narasiṃha; in the same way (please) narrate (to me) the greatness of the fearful, Bhava (i.e. Śiva).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4a. Listen also to the excellent deed of that god of gods. There was a demon Andhaka by name, who resembled a heap of collyrium, who had great penance (to his credit), and who could not be killed by gods. Once he saw the lord Mahādeva, sporting with Pārvatī, and proceeded to take her away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>47 The Birth of Garuḍa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/47/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/47/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2a. Due to your favour I have understood who the most meritorious Brāhmaṇa is (i.e. I have understood the characteristics of the most meritorious brāhmaṇa). O best of gods, if you desire (i.e. have) affection for me, quickly tell me, so that I shall understand, O lord of gods, (the characteristics of) a mean brāhmaṇa by his acts.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahmā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2b-4a. That is a mean brāhmaṇa, who has fallen from the ten kinds of baths, and from presenting libations of water&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to the manes of the deceased ancestors; also one who has abandoned the (offering of) prayers and restraint; one who has fallen from worship of gods and from vows, and from learning the Vedas; and from truth, purity etc.; and from the knowledge of abstract meditation and offering oblations into fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>48 Importance of Bull (and Cow)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/48/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/48/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3a. O brāhmaṇic sage (Nārada), and hereafter, that brāhmaṇa who had fallen among the cāṇḍālas, lamented in various ways and went to sage Kaśyapa. Having gone to him, he said: “O best sage, tell me words beneficial to me (i.e. Instruct me in such a way that I would fare well in life). O greatest sage, act in such a way that I would be free from sin.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>49 Good Conduct</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/49/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/49/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. By what conduct, does the brāhmaṇic lustre of a brāhmaṇa increase and by what conduct does that lustre perish?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahmā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. The best brāhmaṇa should get up from his bed when there is still a portion of the night (i.e. early morning), and should certainly remember the meritorious gods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-8. (He should recite the hymns: I salute) ‘Govinda, Mādhava, Kṛṣṇa, Hari, Dāmodara, Nārāyaṇa, Jagannātha, the unborn lord; (I salute) Sarasvatī, Mahālakṣmī, Sāvitrī, the mother of the Vedas, Brahmā, Bhāskara (i.e. the Sun), Candra (i.e. the Moon), the regents of the quarters and planets, Śaṅkara, Śiva, Śambhu, Īśvara and Maheśvara, Gaṇeśa, Skanda, Gaurī and auspicious Bhāgīrathī’. (He should also recite the verses:) ‘King Nala of an auspicious fame, Janāradana of an auspicious fame, Vaidehī (i.e. Sītā) of an auspicious fame and Yudhiṣṭhira of an auspicious fame.’ ‘These seven viz. Aśvatthāman, Bali, Vyāsa, Hanumat and Bibhīṣaṇa, Kṛpa and Paraśurāma are long-lived (i.e. deathless)’. A man, who, having got up in the morning, daily remembers these, is free from the sins like the murder of a brāhmaṇa etc. There is no doubt about this.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 The Account of the Five</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/50/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/50/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhīṣma-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhīṣma said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O brāhmaṇa, tell me if you so desire (about) that which would give a greater religious merit, which is always liked in the world, and which was done by (our) ancient ancestors.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Once all the brāhmaṇas, the disciples of Vyāsa, having respectfully saluted him, asked him about righteousness as you have asked me (now).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇas-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇas said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. Tell (us), which are the best of all pious deeds, and most meritorious in the whole world, by doing which men enjoy heaven eternally. Tell (us) about one sacrifice, which is performed without trouble, which is pure, and which could be done (easily) by the mortals of high and low castes. O Brahman-be well pleased towards us and tell us by doing which, ever (deed) a man becomes adorable to the gods in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>51 The Story of a Faithful Wife</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/51/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/51/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;narottama-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narottama said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Of the thirty-three gods and others the lord is the author. He is the one who snatches them away, who protects them, is their father and originator.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Whatever fatigue we give to our speech (i.e. however hard we try to describe), we are not fit to describe him. Yet I have a kind of curiosity or thirst and hunger.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4a. The dear one should speak when something about what is done is asked. O lord, how does the loyal, chaste wife know the past? (Please) tell me fully as to what her power was.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>52 On Women’s Conduct</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/52/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/52/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Viṣṇu, how was there (i.e. for what reason was there) a wound of the stake on the body of Māṇḍavya (i.e. why was he fixed on the stake)? How (i.e. for what reason) leprosy spread on the body of the husband of the loyal wife?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;hari-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hari said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. As a child, Māṇḍavya inadvertently put (i.e. inserted) a straw into the abdomen of a cricket, and abandoned her through folly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>53 Non-Covetousness of a Śūdra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/53/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/53/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O lord, if you favour me, (please) tell me fully about the life and matchless prowess of the trader.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. A man should give (presents) with truthfulness, without greed, and without jealousy. (It may be said) that he would thus always well-accomplish a hundred sacrifices, in which sumptuous fees are given.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Due to truth (alone), the sun rises; also the wind blows; the ocean would (i.e. does) not cross its boundary nor would (i.e. does) the Tortoise avert (sustaining) the earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>54 The Rape of Ahalyā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/54/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/54/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. (I have) told (you) about Adrohaka’s greatness, unbearable to the people. Having resisted (the temptation of cohabiting with) a woman occupying the same bed, he conquered everything.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. He made convenient (i.e. easy) what was difficult to be accomplished by the wise, and by the celibate sages, and which was difficult for gods, demons and men.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Which man, but Adrohaka, is capable of conquering the sexual desire, which is naturally difficult (to overcome)? O brāhmaṇa, he (i.e. Adrohaka) aloneis a man who has conquered everything.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>55 The Birth of Lauhitya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/55/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/55/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. I shall tell you another (account) of a man overpowered by the passion of love. Formerly on the bank of Bhāgīrathī, there lived a brāhmaṇa, an ascetic of the highest order, who instructed thousands of brāhmaṇas, who gave peace (of mind to others), who was ekadaṇḍadhara,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and like a tortoise living on the earth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. When he was sitting all alone in a secluded temple, he suddenly came across a young beautiful woman going to another’s house from her husband’s house in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>56 The Account of the Five (conclusion)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/56/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/56/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lord said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Formerly, Śarva (i.e. Śaṅkara), having seen youthful and beautiful women of Gandharvas, Kinnaras and human beings, and with his mind set on them, pretended to be intent on practising penance, and with a spell dragged them far away into the sky.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Then the great lord, the conqueror of the god of love, having fashioned a very delightful cottage, sported (there) with them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4. In the meanwhile, Gaurī’s mind became excited. By means of meditation she saw the lord of the world, sporting with women.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>57 In Praise of (Digging a) Tank etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/57/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/57/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇas-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇas said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O best sage, tell us, if you favour us, (how) fame and dharma (can be accomplished) in the worlds, and (tell us about) all the excellent things (in the three worlds).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. He, in whose dug up (portion of) forest, cows are satisfied (by grazing) for a month, or seven days, is purified and is honoured by all gods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Listen to all the fruit that is here (i.e. in this world obtained) by offering water, especially at a pool purified by (the performance of) a sacrificial rite.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>58 In Praise of Planting Trees etc.</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/58/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/58/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I shall (now) tell you what the fruit of (planting) trees is. O illustrious ones, listen to it. And also listen to the fruit derived from planting (trees) singly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. It is not possible to know or to narrate the meritorious fruit earned by that man who plants auspicious trees all round.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. The fruit that a man would get by planting trees near water is a lakh crore times more than the fruit that he would get by planting them somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>59 In Praise of Rudrākṣa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/59/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/59/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-spoke&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa spoke&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Hereafter I shall narrate (to you) the extremely auspicious fruit, leading to fame, of constructing a bridge, as told by Brahmā (himself).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. A man having constructed (i.e. who constructs) a bridge having many pillars in a forest or a muddy place difficult to cross, is purified and would attain godhead.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. If (the breadth of the bridge) is of the measure of a vitasti&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, he would obtain (i.e. live in) heaven for a hundred divine years. If the bridge is done according to this calculation, he is not abandoned (i.e. does not fall) from heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>60 In Praise of Tulasī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/60/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/60/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;skanda-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Skanda said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I am asking about (the importance of) the fruit of another tree also. O lord of the world, tell me about it for the good of all the worlds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lord-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;lord. said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. The dhātrī&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; fruit is very pure and is well-known in all the worlds, by planting which (i.e. it) a man or a woman is free from the bondage of birth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. This fruit of Vāsudeva is pure, is pleasing and auspicious. Merely by eating it a man is free from all sins.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>61 Glorification of Tulasī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/61/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/61/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇas-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇas said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. We have heard from you the greatness of the Tulasī blossom, auspicious to Viṣṇu. We (now) desire to hear the auspicious hymn of praise composed in her (i.e.Tulasī’s) honour.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O brāhmaṇas, I shall tell you that Purāṇa (i.e. old account) which I narrated in the Skanda Purāṇa, for (obtaining) liberation. All the disciples of the sage Śatānanda who had fulfilled their vows, having saluted their preceptor asked him what was helpful to religious merit, O brāhmaṇas. (They said to Śatānanda:) “O lord, O best of brāhmaṇas, we desired to hear from you the glorification of Tulasī, which you had formerly heard from the mouth of Brahmā.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>62 In Praise of the Gaṅgā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/62/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/62/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-brāhmaṇas-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The brāhmaṇas said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3 By a (sacred) bath, all sins, great sins, and also other sins certainly perish. Instruct us about it. Instruct us (as to how) a man, being purified from sin, obtains (i.e. lives in) heaven like Indra, and does not lose his existence as god. He (gets) all enjoyments here; and after death becomes the best god in heaven. It is said that the staircase to heaven is (obtained by) those whose sins due to Kali have perished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>63 A Hymn to Gaṇapati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/63/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/63/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;pulastya-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pulastya said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O Bhīṣma, in the meanwhile, Sañjaya, a great sage and a disciple of Vyāsa, having saluted his preceptor asked him formerly: “(Please) tell (me) the means of worshipping gods and the well-defined order in which they should be worshipped. Which god is most adorable in the beginning? Who should be worshipped in between (the first and the best)? Who should be worshipped last in everyday worship? Whose power is what (i.e. what is the power of each one)? O brāhmaṇa, worshipping whom, what fruit would a man obtain?”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>64 Another Hymn to Gaṇapati</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/64/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/1/64/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. I shall again tell you another hymn of praise in honour of Gaṇeśa, which gives success in all undertakings; which is sacred, and which gives every desired fruit:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. “I salute the chief of the Gaṇas, who has one tusk, whose body is big, who resembles heated gold, who has a large belly, and large eyes, who has put on the muñja (girdle), and the skin of the black antelope, and has the sacred thread of serpents, who has, on his head, the digit of the young moon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
