<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;४ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;४ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>001 Who Are the Devotees of Viṣṇu?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Salutation to Śrī Vedavyāsa&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, now that the Kali age has arrived, tell me, by means of which acts a being would be liberated from that (mundane existence).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. Well (asked), well (asked), O best of sages, you are the best among the righteous people. You constantly desire the wellbeing of all people. O you devotee of Viṣṇu, listen to what Vyāsa, the omniscient brāhmaṇa, revered by all, said, when he was formerly asked by Jaimini. The best sage (Jaimini), having prostrated himself like a staff before preceptor Vyāsa, Satyavatī’s son, who had mastered everything, asked him:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>002 The Importance of Besmearing the Floor of Viṣṇu’s Temple</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Saunaka, listen. I shall tell you (about) the ancient way of life (from) the conversation between Vyāsa and Jaimini, which destroys the sins of the listeners.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O lord, O preceptor, tell me today by (doing) which acts does a sinful man go to the abode of the lord of the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. That man who besmears (the ground) in the temple of Viṣṇu, is freed from all sins, becomes tranquil and goes to the abode of Hari (i.e. Viṣṇu).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>003 The Importance of Offering a Lamp to Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, tell me the significance of (the month of) Kārtika. (Tell me) what the fruit of that vow is, and what the blemish of one who does not do it, is.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. On a former occasion, O best of sages, Jaimini asked (about) this to Vyāsa, Satyavatī’s son. (Then) the sage (Vyāsa) commenced this narration:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-15. He who would give up sesamum-oil and copulation in the auspicious (month of) Kārtika, becomes free from sins committed during many (previous) existences and goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. He, a fool, who does not give up (eating) fish and copulation in Kārtika, would certainly be (born as) a pig in every (subsequent) existence. A man who would worship Viṣṇu with the tulasī-leaves in Kārtika, obtains the fruit (of the performance) of a horse sacrifice for every leaf (that is offered to Viṣṇu). He who would worship Viṣṇu in Kārtika with the flowers of the muni-tree, obtains through Viṣṇu’s grace salvation difficult to be obtained (even) by gods. The best man who eats the muni-vegetable in Kārtika, has all the sin committed during the year destroyed by (just) one vegetable (viz. muni). He who after offering to Viṣṇu eats the fruit of that (tree) in the month of Kārtika dear to Viṣṇu, (has all) his sin (committed) during crores of existences (destroyed). He who gives (an article of food), which is tasty and with ghee, to Viṣṇu, is freed from all sins and would go to Viṣṇu’s abode. A man, who offers even one lotus to Viṣṇu in Kārtika, in the end goes, free from all (his) sins, to Viṣṇu’s position. He who would (everyday) bathe in the morning in (the month of) Kārtika dear to Viṣṇu, would obtain the fruit which (he would get) on bathing at all the sacred places. That brāhmaṇa, who would offer a lamp into water in Kārtika, is free from sins like the murder of a brāhmaṇa, and would go to the abode ofViṣṇu. O best brāhmaṇa, he who would offer a lamp even for a short time in Kārtika to please Viṣṇu, has Viṣṇu always pleased with him. Everyday the brāhmaṇa who would offer a lamp with ghee to Viṣṇu in his (own) house in Kārtika, obtains the fruit of a horse sacrifice. I (shall) tell you the special significance (of the offering) of a lamp. O best ofbrāhmaṇas, being attentive, listen to it (as I tell it) with its tradition.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>004 The Importance of Fasting on the Jayantī Day</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, tell (me about) the importance of Jayantī (birth day anniversary). When is it celebrated by the people? You are a boat in the ocean of the mundane existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O brāhmaṇa, O best sage, listen; since I am asked, I shall tell you. This was formerly asked by Nārada from Brahma in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. O grandsire, tell me the significance of Jayantī (i.e. birth day anniversary), hearing which I shall go to that highest position of Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>005 The Deeds for Which One Becomes Sonless</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you very intelligent one, tell me, due to which act (of a man) he becomes sonless (i.e. does not have a son), and due to (i.e. by doing) which (act) he would have a son.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Formerly this was asked by the magnanimous Nārada from Brahmā. O best sage, listen to what he said (then).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;nārada-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nārada said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. O grandsire, O very wise one, O you who have mastered all the truth, O you lotus-born, tell me by (i.e. doing) which deed a mortal would become sonless; due to what sin a woman would be barren. O you who are intent on the well-being of all creatures, tell me, who am listening. Due to which deed a daugther is born, or an import ant son is born; due to what a child is stillborn. A woman bringing forth a stillborn child is extremely unhappy. O Brahman, tell me due to which religious merit a son would be born.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>006 Acts Leading to Vaikuṇṭha</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, tell me who am listening, due to which (acts of) religious merit Vaikuṇṭha is obtained (by a man), for you are a boat in the ocean of the worldly existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. O best sage doing auspicious (things) for all, (you have asked) well. I shall tell you in brief (the rite) destroying all sins. Listen, O best brāhmaṇa, bear about the merit of him who would give a house made of clay to a brāhmaṇa devoted to Viṣṇu. That brāhmaṇa, free from all sins, would always live in a palatial building in Viṣṇu’s heaven. He is honoured in Viṣṇu’s heaven. He who would present a palatial building to a brāhmaṇa devotee of Viṣṇu, would, on reaching Viṣṇu’s abode, certainly be a resident of heaven. O brahmaṇa, he, with a crore of (members of) his family ultimately goes to Viṣṇu’s city, and staying in a palatial golden building, he would enjoy pleasures as he pleases. (Even) the Creator, the cause of all, is unable to measure the religious merit that one would get by causing a brāhmaṇa to settle well (in his life), O sage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>007 The Greatness of Rādhāṣṭamī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O very wise one, O you very intelligent one, tell me due to which act a man goes to the world of cows from the ocean of the mundane existence which is difficult to cross and, O Sūta, about Rādhāṣṭamī and its excellent importance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O brāhmaṇa, O great sage, formerly Nārada had asked this from Brahmā. Listen, in brief, to what he had asked him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>008 Prelude to the Churning of Ocean</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;saunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, O preceptor, why was the ocean churned by the gods in ancient days? Curiosity is produced in my mind to hear it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O brāhmaṇa, I shall tell you in brief the reason for the churning of the ocean. Listen also to the account of the dialogue between Durvāsas and Indra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3. Once, the brāhmaṇic sage Durvāsas who had practised great (i.e. severe) penance, who was very lustrous, who was born of a portion of the Lord, went to heaven to see Indra.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>009 The Churning Starts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Then the hosts of gods with gandharvas and demons uprooted the Mandara mountain and put it into the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7a. Then the glorious, kind, ancient lord of the world supported on his back the bottom of the mountain. (Then the gods) putting Ananta (the lord of serpents) round it churned the milky ocean. When it was being churned on the Ekādaśī day, all of them ran away seeing the Kālakūṭa poison that had come up. Seeing them running away Śaṅkara said these (words): “O hosts of gods, hand over the poison to me. I shall quickly inactivate the great (i.e. severe) poison, viz. Kālakūṭa”. Saying so, that lord of Pārvatī, meditating upon Viṣṇu in his heart and uttering the great hymn, took that fearful poison. By the power of the great hymn, that great (deadly) poison was digested.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>010 The Birth of Lakṣmī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. Then Airāvata sprang up (from the ocean), so also the horse Uccaiḥśravas. Then (sprang up) Dhanvantari, and the fragrant Pārijāta. So also there was the rise of the celestial nymphs. Then on the twelfth day in the morning, when the sun had risen, the great Lakṣmī, graced with all (auspicious) characteristics, sprang up. All the religious deities saw that great mother of all creatures having her abode in the heart of Viṣṇu, and were delighted. Then, the cool-rayed one (i.e. the Moon), the brother of Lakṣmī, sprang up with nectar. (So also) Tulasī, Viṣṇu’s wife, purifying the world, came up.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>011 The Importance of Observing a Vow in Honour of Lakṣmī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. Now I desire to hear, O you who were actually instructed by Veda Vyāsa, of the nature of Viṣṇu. O you who have no pride, O you who favour the world, tell me properly as to how (i. e. by doing what) a sinful and very miserable woman would be fortunate. By (doing) what would she be dear to her husband, would she be beautiful, and nectar to (his) eyes? O you, rich in penance, tell me by which (means) wealth is produced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>012 Merit Earned by Protecting a Brāhmaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, kindly tell (me) due to which other religious merit a man with his sins gone (away) goes to the place of Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. That man, O best brāhmaṇa, who protects a brāhmaṇa with his (own) wealth or his (own) life, goes to Viṣṇu’s world. Formerly, in the yuga called Dvāpara, there was a king (named) Dīnānātha who was sonless (but who was) a devotee of Viṣṇu and a sacrificer. Once that king politely asked Gālava: “O best sage, O ocean of compassion, tell me due to which religious merit a son is born. I shall practise it by your order. The life of those men who do not have a son is useless.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>013 The Importance of the Vow of Janmāṣṭamī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, O you very wise one, tell me (about) Kṛṣṇāṣṭamī, and its excellent importance, (and) emancipate me from the great ocean (of the mundance [mundane?] existene).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8. O brāhmaṇa, he who devoutly observes the (vow) Kṛṣṇāṣṭamī, ultimately goes to Viṣṇu’s city along with a crore (members) of his family. O best brāhmaṇa, when Aṣṭamī falls on a Wednesday or Monday in conjunction with Rohiṇī, it gives salvation to a crore (members) of his family. Even if a great sinner observes (this) excellent vow, he is freed from all sins and in the end goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. O brāhmaṇa, that mean man who does not observe (the vow of) Kṛṣṇajanmāṣṭamī, meets with misery here (i.e. in this world) and after death he would go to hell. That foolish woman who does not observe the vow of Kṛṣṇajanmāṣṭamī goes to a terrible hell year after year. That foolish man who eats (food) on the day of Janmāṣṭamī, attains to a great hell. I am telling (you) the truth and truth (only). Formerly Dilīpa asked the best sage Vasiṣṭha. Listen to that (conversation), destroying all sins, O you very intelligent one.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>014 The Greatness of a Brāhmaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you very wise one, O you ocean of compassion, kindly tell me the import ance of a brāhmaṇa, the best of all the castes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8. O best brāhmaṇa, a brāhmaṇa is the preceptor of all the castes. He should be known to be the resort of all gods, and he is actually Viṣṇu, the lord. O best brāhmaṇa, the wealth etc. of him who devoutly salutes a brāhmaṇa, looking upon him as Viṣṇu, enhances. Viṣṇu would always desire to cut off the head of him who, being proud, does not even casually salute a brāhmaṇa. Those of sinful minds, who hate a brāhmaṇa who has committed an offence, should be known to be hating Viṣṇu. They go to a terrible hell. Yama torments with a heated needle the eyes of him who would look angrily at a brāhmaṇa who has come to make a request. The messengers (i.e. servants) of Yama put (a piece of) heated iron into the mouth of the foolish mean man who threatens a brāhmaṇa. Kṛṣṇa himself along with gods eats in the house of those in whose house a brāhmaṇa with penance as his wealth eats.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>015 The Importance of Ekādaśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O illustrious one, tell me the importance of Ekādaśī, and also what its fruit is and the sin (that accrues) to him who does not observe it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-40. Now why should I tell the importance of (the vow of) Ekādaśī? The messengers of Yama, who cause fear to all beings, are frightened on hearing the name of Ekādaśī. There is no doubt about this. A man should observe a fast on the auspicious (day of) Ekādaśī which is the best of all vows, should keep awake and highly decorate Viṣṇu. O brāhmaṇa, the man who worships Viṣṇu with Tulasī-leaves, obtains the fruit of a crore of sacrifices. That sin which is said to be due to illicit intercourse, perishes due to a fast on the (day of) Ekādaśī. O brāhmaṇa, he who would offer a lamp full of ghee (to Viṣṇu) on the Viṣṇu-day (i.e. Ekādaśī), in the end goes to Viṣṇu’s place. “Do not bring to me these meritorious beings who observe a fast on (the day of) Viṣṇu’s going to bed or his turning aside, and especially on the Prabodhinī (Ekādaśī).” Thus orders Yama to his messengers day and night. Ekādaśī is dear to the lord of the world (i.e. Viṣṇu) and enhances religious merit. Viṣṇu does burn the body (of a man) on (his) eating food on that (day). Fie upon the life, wealth, handsomeness and conduct of those, the most sinful ones, who eat food on (the day of) Ekādaśī! They are the eaters of feces. O best brāhmaṇa, on merely eating food on Ekādaśī(-day), many and various sins attend upon the eater. As a great sin would accrue by having coitus with women on the new moon day, in the same way sin would be there (i.e. would be committed by a man) on eating on an Ekādaśī (-day). Beings (i.e. men) become diseased, crippled, and suffer from cough, and congenital leprosy on eating food on that (day). They become (i.e. are born as) village-pigs and are reduced to poverty. O best brāhmaṇa, people are bound by the king on eating (i.e. if they eat) on that (day), O brāhmaṇa; (all) the sins that are there in the worldly existence resort to food. There would be escape from hell of those who commit all sins (but) drink water (on that, day only) through the order (ofa superior person etc.). There is no escape (from hell) for those men who eat on Viṣṇu’s day. Sin due to crores of brāhmaṇa-murders would accrue to those men for each kind of food that they eat. O men, listen, listen, I tell again, I tell again: On the day of Viṣṇu, (food) should not be eaten, food should not be eaten, food should not be eaten. That fruit is obtained by him who fasts on an (Ekādaśi-) day which is obtained by bathing in Gaṅgā etc. and at holy places or at the (time of) lunar or solar eclipse. He having worshipped (i.e. who worships) with lotus-garlands lord Viṣṇu after having properly broken the fast, does not have a place in mother’s womb (i.e. is not reborn). O brāhmaṇa, he who makes a decoration in Viṣṇu’s abode (i.e. temple) on an Ekādaśī(-day), gets the highest status and would stay in Viṣṇu’s house. Those who having waited for the Ekādaśī-(day) observe a fast on that day, undoubtedly stay in Viṣṇu’s city. There is no doubt that those whose minds are clung to the devotion of Viṣṇu, go to the highest place of Viṣṇu. Those too who have no longing for others’ wealth and whose minds are contented, certainly have (i.e. go to) Viṣṇu’s city. Those best men, who having encountered famine give food to creatures, undoubtedly get (i.e. go to) Viṣṇu’s abode. Those, who cast their life for protecting cows, brāhmaṇas, (their) master, and a woman, certainly get (i.e. go to) Viṣṇu’s city. Creatures (i.e. men) should never observe a fast on (an Ekādasī day) joined with Daśamī (i.e. the tenth day). O best brāhmaṇa, it should be avoided like the proximity of a wicked man. Having fasted on that day, if the Ekādaśī-day is joined with Daśamī at the break of day, having fasted on that day, there would be Dvādaśī, and breaking of the fast would be on the thirteenth day. A devotee of Viṣṇu should not observe the Ekādaśī-vow on that day if the day-break is said to be the four ghaṭikās of the morning. This is the time of the bath for the ascetics, and is said to be like the water of Gaṅgā. If at the time of day-break Daśamī is seen (to continue), then on that day Ekādaśī destroying religious merit, worldly prosperity and sensual enjoyments, should not be observed. A wise man should avoid the Ekādaśī joined even a little with Daśamī, as he would abandon a pitcher full of ghee spoiled by the contact of a drop of liquor. When there is the full Ekādaśī (i.e. it falls on the eleventh day) and again continues (in part) on the twelfth-day also, then the latter should be observed by ascetics and a householder should observe a fast on the former day. When a part of Ekādaśī does not go beyond Dvādaśī, the merit there is of a hundred sacrifices; and the breaking of the fast (should be done) on the thirteenth day. If the Ekādaśī is omitted and is further united with Dvādaśī, then a man should fast for the entire twelfth day if he desires the highest place. If it is the entire Ekādaśī (day) and if it is there in the morning also, then, if Dvādaśī is after it (commencing on that day) all should observe the (fast of Ekādaśī) on the latter day. Those men whose mind clings to the Ekādaśī-vow, live in heaven and go to Viṣṇu’s house. There is no greater means than Ekādaśī for (going to) the next world. He who, full of many sins, observes (a fast on) the day of Viṣṇu, is freed from all sins and goes to Viṣṇu’s abode.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>016 How to Win Favour of Viṣṇu</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, kindly tell (me) that due to which act the sins would perish and grace of Viṣṇu would follow.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4. O Śaunaka, I shall tell you what destroys the sins of the listeners, by which Viṣṇus grace, destroying sins, would take place. O sage, the sin of him, earned during crores of existences disappears, who, with devotion and in many ways, offers on a full moon day worship to the lord of the world, O sage. Certainly the favour of the lord of Śrī would come to him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>017 The Importance of Water Flowing from Viṣṇu’s Feet</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you ocean of compassion, O you very wise one, tell me from the beginning the greatness of the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet, which destroys sins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-11. The water (flowing) from the feet of Viṣṇu destroys all sins and is auspicious. He who would carry (even) a drop of it, would obtain the fruit of (visiting) all the holy places. O brāhmaṇa, the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet destroys the sin of him who touches it; he does not meet with an untimely death and would obtain the fruit of a bath in Gaṅgā. O brāhmaṇa, there is no doubt that the sin in the body of the sinner who would drink the water (flowing) from the feet of Viṣṇu, would perish. That man who would devoutly carry on his head the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet along with a Tulasī-leaf in the end goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. Men obtain that fruit by touching the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet, which is obtained by giving (pieces of) gold resembling Meru. That fruit is surely obtained by offering water to Viṣṇu’s feet and touching the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet, which is obtained by (offering) thousands of crores of cows. The fruit that is obtained by touching the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet, is crores of times greater than the fruit which is obtained by performing thousands of crores of sacrifices. O brāhmaṇa, the fruit (obtained) by touching the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet is greater than the fruit got by men by giving a crore of virgins (in marriage to worthy grooms). That fruit which a man obtains by giving a crore of elephants or by giving a crore of horses is obtained by a man by touching the water (flowing) from the feet of Viṣṇu. O brāhmaṇa, a man would get a larger fruit by touching the water (flowing) from Viṣṇu’s feet, than that which he would obtain by giving (the earth) with the seven islands along with crops (growing on it).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>018 Purificatory Acts for One Guilty of Illegitimate Intercourse</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, tell me fully, with what can a man who having through delusion h ad illegitimate intercourse, be purified?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-8a. The best brāhmaṇa, who cohabits with a cāṇḍāla woman or an outcaste woman, should observe three fasts, then should observe the Prājāpatya vow, get clean-shaved with (even) the tuft of hair on the crown of his head (removed), and should give a couple of cows (to a brāhmaṇa). The brāhmaṇa becomes purified after giving proper present (to a brāhmaṇa). If a kṣatriya or a vaiśya cohabits with a cāṇḍālī, he should (observe) the Kṛcchra Prājāpatya (vow) and should give two pairs of cows to (a brāhmaṇa). O you ascetic, if a śūdra cohabits with an outcaste woman, he should give four pairs of cows (to a brāhmaṇa) and observe the Prājāpatya vow. If a man being infatuated, cohabits with his mother or sister or daughter, or his daughter-in-law, he should observe three Kṛcchra (-vows). Having observed three Cāndrāyaṇa (-vows), he should give three pairs of cows. Getting clean-shaved with (even) the tuft of hair on the crown of the head (removed), he should drink the mixture of the five products of a cow. O ascetic, in this case he becomes purified even after making offerings into fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>019 Purificatory Acts for Other Sins</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O brāhmaṇa, listen, I shall tell you, how those who, through ignorance, have eaten feces (or drunk) urine or have sipped liquor, are purified.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-4a. O sage, he should observe two Prājāpatya (-vows); he should go to a holy place. He should give a bull and eleven cows, and then should get himself clean-shaved with the tuft of hair on the crown of the head (removed). Having gone to all crossways he should observe the Prājāpatya (-vow). Then he should give a pair of cows and drink the mixture of the five products of a cow. There is no doubt that he is purified after having fed brāhmaṇas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>020 The Greatness of the Worship of Rādhā-Dāmodara</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, (tell me which) you said to be the (deeds of) merit, doing which, the frogs (men) in the blinding well due to darkness, will cross the ocean of mundane existence.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-10. That woman who, bathing (every) morning in Kārtika, being dear to Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa, being composed and devoutly worshipping Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa, gives up eating meat etc. and is engaged in serving her husband, goes to Viṣṇu’s place called &lt;em&gt;Goloka&lt;/em&gt; which is very difficult to obtain (i.e. to reach). She who would offer incense and lamp to Rādhā and Dāmodara (i.e. Kṛṣṇa) in Kārtika, goes, with her sin abandoned (i.e. removed), to Viṣṇu’s abode. O brāhmaṇa, that woman who would offer a garment to Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa would, for a long time, live in the abode to Sri Viṣṇu. She who offers to Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa fragrant flowers and garlands in the month of Kārtika, goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. Also she who would offer sandal and make an offering like sugar to Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa, would go to Viṣṇu’s abode. O brāhmaṇa, the merit of that woman who gives something to a brāhmaṇa in the month of Kārtika to please Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa, becomes inexhaustible. O brāhmaṇa, that woman who devoutly worships Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa in the month of Kārtika goes (to Viṣṇu’s abode); she would not live in hell for long, even if she was a widow in a previous existence or was not dear to her husband.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>021 Restrictions While Observing the Kārtika Vow</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, O sage, please tell me properly the rites and restrictions (to be observed) in the best month Kārtika.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-7. O best brāhmaṇa, a man, being pure, should (begin to) observe the vow of the Kārtika month on (i.e. from) the full moon of Āśvina (and should continue it) till the Udbodhinī (i.e. the eleventh day of the bright fortnight of Kārtika). O brāhmana, a man should excrete or pass urine by facing the north during the day time. He should observe silence (while excreting or passing urine); and O you omniscient one, he should excrete or pass urine by facing the south during the night. O brāhmaṇa, he who has undertaken the vow (of Kārtika) should not excrete or pass urine on a path, in water, in a cow-pen, in a crematory or an anthill. He should not excrete or pass urine at excellent places. Taking pure clay he should first wash his left hand with clay and water for cleansing it twenty times. He should apply it (i.e. the clay) once to his generative organ and five times to his anus, ten times to his left hand, and then ten times to both (his hands), and three times to (each of) his feet. Then he should cleanse his face and then resolve to bathe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>022 The Greatness of Tulasī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you omniscient one, kindly tell me, for the good of all creatures, the greatness of Tulasī which destroys the sins of those who listen to it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-13. The servants of Yama do not come to his house in the vicinity of which there is a grove of Tulasī, due to the house having the nature of a holy place, O brāhmaṇa. O brāhmaṇa, the Tulasī-grove is auspicious and removes all sins. Those excellent men who plant it do not see the Sun’s son (i.e. Yama). O best brāhmaṇa, all the sin of him who plants it, nourishes it, attends upon it, looks at it and touches it, perishes. O brāhmaṇa, those high-souled ones who worship Viṣṇu with tender Tulasī-leaves do not go to Yama’s abode. The best rivers like Gaṅgā, the best (gods) Viṣṇu, Brahmā and Śiva, along with deities and holy places like Puṣkara, remain in a Tulasī-leaf. A sinner who, endowed with Tulasī-leaves, casts his life, goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. I have told (you) the truth. The man who, besmeared with the clay of Tulasī (i.e. in which Tulasī is growing), casts his life, goes, though full of hundreds of sins, to Viṣṇu’s abode. O brāhmaṇa, sin does not touch the body of the man’ who would wear the sandal-like Tulasī-wood. He goes to the highest position. He, who, though impure and of bad conduct, wears the rosary of (the beads made of) Tulasī-wood round his neck, goes, due to his devotion, to Viṣṇu’s house. That man on whose body is seen the rosary made of Dhātrī-fruits or (beads of) Tulasī-wood, is a devotee of Viṣṇu. He again who, putting round his neck the garland (of the leaves) of Tulasī, would worship Viṣṇu, obtains, for each flower, a myriad of cows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>023 The Importance of Viṣṇupañcaka</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O Sūta, O sage, kindly tell me the importance of the remaining five days of Kārtika, which destroys sins.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-16. O Śaunaka, listen. I shall narrate (to you) the importance, which destroys sins, of the remaining five days of Kārtika. O best sage, of the five vows Viṣṇupañcaka (i.e. the vow observed for the remaining five days of Kārtika), is the best. He who, during that (period) worships Śrī Hari (i.e. Kṛṣṇa) with Rādhā, by means of sandal, flowers, incense, clothes and various kinds of fruits, goes, freed from all sins, to Viṣṇu’s abode. Without doing the vow of Viṣṇupañcaka, a religious student, (or) a householder, (or) an anchorite, (or) an ascetic does not obtain the highest position. Viṣṇupañcaka removes all sins, is meritorious and well-known. He who would bathe during that (period), would obtain the fruit of (having bathed at) all holy places. He who, to propitiate Viṣṇu, devoutly offers a lamp full of ghee in front of (the image of) Viṣṇu, or near Tulasī, in water, goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. A sinner goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. I have told the truth. A man should bathe with devotion (the image of) Viṣṇu with honey, milk, ghee etc. What would Viṣṇu being pleased not give to that good man? He should present excellent cooked food to the god of gods. (Even Brahmā) having four faces is not able to measure his religious merit. Being pure, he worships Viṣṇu on Ekādaśī day. Having secured cow-dung he duly waits upon (the god) with the sacred hymns. He who observes the vow, should similarly again diink cow urine (reciting) the sacred hymns on the twelfth day. Similarly he should drink milk on the fourteenth day. Having got (these) for the purification of his sins, and having passed the four days, he should, on the fifth day, having bathed and duly worshipped Viṣṇu, devoutly feed brāhmaṇas and should give them presents. Then at night he should eat the mixture of the five products of a cow, which is well consecrated with sacred hymns. He who is unable to do this, should eat fruits, roots and food; O brāhmaṇa, he should offer an oblation according to the rite that is laid down. Lord Viṣṇu who is fit to be known, would himself honour him who would observe (the vow of) Pañcaka with Tulasī-leaves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>024 In Praise of Giving Gifts</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O sage, O best among the learned, O you who know the essential nature (of things), tell me in order the importance of vows.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. O best sage, giving (a piece of) land is regarded as the best gift. He who made that gift (has given) a gift having the fruit of all gifts. O best brāhmaṇa, he who would give a gift of land with a crop (growing in it) to a brāhmaṇa, enjoys happiness in Viṣṇu’s heaven as long as (the regimes of) fourteen Indras (last). Then, O king, he, having obtained a birth on the earth, (becomes) a sovereign emperor. Having enjoyed the earth for a long time, he would go to the abode of Viṣṇu. He who gives land of the measure of a cow’s hide to a brāhmaṇa, is freed from all sins and goes to Viṣṇu’s abode. The sages described that land to be of the measure of a cow’s hide (&lt;em&gt;gocarmamātra&lt;/em&gt;) where a hundred cows and a bull remain uncontrolled.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>025 The Importance of Uttering Viṣṇu’s Name</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4a. That man who devoutly listens to the account of Viṣṇu, which is the abode of glory, which removes all harms, which destroys all sins, which wards off all evil planets, which gives proximity with Viṣṇu, which gives the fruit of the four goals of human life, goes to Viṣṇu’s abode in the end. The importance of the utterance of (Viṣṇu’s) names is said to be very wonderful; merely by uttering it a man would go to the highest position. Therefore, O Sūta, now tell me the manner of the utterance of (Viṣṇu’s) names.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>026 The Importance of Keeping Promise</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śaunaka-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śaunaka said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O wise one, I desire to hear, (therefore) tell me fully what the religious merit there is in keeping a promise, and what the sin is in breaking it. O you ocean of compassion, (tell me) what would happen if one takes a false oath or a true one, and by one&amp;rsquo;s offering one’s right hand or favouring (someone).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-13. O best sage, listen, I am telling it from the beginning. You are the foremost among Viṣṇu’s devotees and are engaged in the good of all people. O brāhmaṇa, the merit in (i.e. due to) keeping a promise is a crore times greater than the fruit which a man obtains by giving a hundred cows. There is no doubt that a fool by breaking his promise goes to a terrible hell and is roasted there for a hundred periods of Manu. Then due to his own deeds he obtains birth (i.e. is born) on the earth in the house of a poor person, and bereft of food and garments he is afflicted. One should take an oath truthfully in the vicinity of a deity, fire, or one’s preceptor. Till that time the body is burnt; but the family of Viṣṇu is not lost (i.e. continues). O brāhmaṇa, what should I now say about a false oath? O brāhmaṇa, a man (lives) in hell for a hundred periods of Manu due to a false promise. O best sage, he who touches the flowers taken off after Viṣṇu’s worship and takes a truthful oath (but does not keep it), is roasted, taking with him seven members (of his family), in hell for a long time. If by chance he gets a birth, then in every existence (he becomes) a leper. This would never happen due to truthful promise. What can be said about (what would happen) due to a false oath? The man who offer his right hand (to give a promise) and keeps it, would obtain Kṛṣṇa. I am telling the truth, (and) the truth (only). The dead ancestors of him who, having offered his hand (to make a promise), does not keep it, are tormented in hell; and undoubtedly the dead one (i.e. he, after death) goes to a terrible hell, and is emancipated by crores of men (of his family, i.e. after a very long time).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>027 Section 5 - Pātāla-Khaṇḍa (Section on the Nether World)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/027/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/4/027/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
