<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०९ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०९ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Sudyumna became a woman and how the dynasty of Vaivasvata Manu was amalgamated with the Soma-vaṁśa, the dynasty coming from the moon.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the desire of Mahārāja Parīkṣit, Śukadeva Gosvāmī told about the dynasty of Vaivasvata Manu, who was formerly King Satyavrata, the ruler of Draviḍa. While describing this dynasty, he also described how the Supreme Personality of Godhead, while lying down in the waters of devastation, gave birth to Lord Brahmā from a lotus generated from His navel. From the mind of Lord Brahmā, Marīci was generated, and his son was Kaśyapa. From Kaśyapa, through Aditi, Vivasvān was generated, and from Vivasvān came Śrāddhadeva Manu, who was born from the womb of Saṁjñā. Śrāddhadeva’s wife, Śraddhā, gave birth to ten sons, such as Ikṣvāku and Nṛga.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Second Chapter describes the dynasties of the sons of Manu, headed by Karūṣa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Sudyumna accepted the order of &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; and departed for the forest, Vaivasvata Manu, being desirous of sons, worshiped the Supreme Personality of Godhead and consequently begot ten sons like Mahārāja Ikṣvāku, all of whom were like their father. One of these sons, Pṛṣadhra, was engaged in the duty of protecting cows at night with a sword in his hand. Following the order of his spiritual master, he would stand in this way for the entire night. Once, in the darkness of night, a tiger seized a cow from the cowshed, and when Pṛṣadhra came to know this, he took a sword in his hand and followed the tiger. Unfortunately, when he finally approached the tiger, he could not distinguish between the cow and the tiger in the dark, and thus he killed the cow. Because of this, his spiritual master cursed him to take birth in a &lt;em&gt;śūdra&lt;/em&gt; family, but Pṛṣadhra practiced mystic &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; and in &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga&lt;/em&gt; he worshiped the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Then he voluntarily entered a blazing forest fire, thus relinquishing his material body and going back home, back to Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the dynasty of Śaryāti, another son of Manu, and also tells about Sukanyā and Revatī.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Devajña Śaryāti gave instructions about what to do in the ritualistic ceremony observed on the second day of the &lt;em&gt;yajña&lt;/em&gt; of the Aṅgirasas. One day, Śaryāti, along with his daughter, known as Sukanyā, went to the &lt;em&gt;āśrama&lt;/em&gt; of Cyavana Muni. There Sukanyā saw two glowing substances within a hole of earthworms, and by chance she pierced those two glowing substances. As soon as she did this, blood began to ooze from that hole. Consequently, King Śaryāti and his companions suffered from constipation and inability to pass urine. When the King asked why circumstances had suddenly changed, he found that Sukanyā was the cause of this misfortune. Then they all offered prayers to Cyavana Muni just to satisfy him according to his own desire, and Devajña Śaryāti offered his daughter to Cyavana Muni, who was a very old man.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the history of Mahārāja Nabhaga, of his son Nābhāga, and of Mahārāja Ambarīṣa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The son of Manu was Nabhaga, and his son Nābhāga lived for many years in the &lt;em&gt;gurukula.&lt;/em&gt; In Nābhāga’s absence, his brothers did not consider his share of the kingdom, but instead divided the property among themselves. When Nābhāga returned home, his brothers bestowed upon him their father as his share, but when Nābhāga went to his father and told him about the dealings of the brothers, his father informed him that this was cheating and advised him that for his livelihood he should go to the sacrificial arena and describe two &lt;em&gt;mantras&lt;/em&gt; to be chanted there. Nābhāga executed the order of his father, and thus Aṅgirā and other great saintly persons gave him all the money collected in that sacrifice. To test Nābhāga, Lord Śiva challenged his claim to the wealth, but when Lord Śiva was satisfied by Nābhāga’s behavior, Lord Śiva offered him all the riches.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter we find Mahārāja Ambarīṣa offering prayers to the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; and we find how the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; became merciful to Durvāsā Muni.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the order of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Viṣṇu, Durvāsā Muni immediately went to Mahārāja Ambarīṣa and fell at his lotus feet. Mahārāja Ambarīṣa, being naturally very humble and meek, felt shy and ashamed because Durvāsā Muni had fallen at his feet, and thus he began to offer prayers to the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; just to save Durvāsā. What is this Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt;? The Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; is the glance of the Supreme Personality of Godhead by which He creates the entire material world. &lt;em&gt;Sa aikṣata, sa asṛjata.&lt;/em&gt; This is the Vedic version. The Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra,&lt;/em&gt; which is the origin of creation and is most dear to the Lord, has thousands of spokes. This Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; is the killer of the prowess of all other weapons, the killer of darkness, and the manifester of the prowess of devotional service; it is the means of establishing religious principles, and it is the killer of all irreligious activities. Without his mercy, the universe cannot be maintained, and therefore the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; is employed by the Supreme Personality of Godhead. When Mahārāja Ambarīṣa thus prayed that the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra&lt;/em&gt; be merciful, the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra,&lt;/em&gt; being appeased, refrained from killing Durvāsā Muni, who thus achieved the Sudarśana &lt;em&gt;cakra’s&lt;/em&gt; mercy. Durvāsā Muni thus learned to give up the nasty idea of considering a Vaiṣṇava an ordinary person (&lt;em&gt;vaiṣṇave jāti-buddhi&lt;/em&gt;). Mahārāja Ambarīṣa belonged to the &lt;em&gt;kṣatriya&lt;/em&gt; group, and therefore Durvāsā Muni considered him lower than the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; and wanted to exercise brahminical power against him. By this incident, everyone should learn how to stop mischievous ideas of neglecting Vaiṣṇavas. After this incident, Mahārāja Ambarīṣa gave Durvāsā Muni sumptuous food to eat, and then the King, who had been standing in the same place for one year without eating anything, also took &lt;em&gt;prasāda.&lt;/em&gt; Mahārāja Ambarīṣa later divided his property among his sons and went to the bank of the Mānasa-sarovara to execute devotional meditation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After describing the descendants of Mahārāja Ambarīṣa, Śukadeva Gosvāmī described all the kings from Śaśāda to Māndhātā, and in this connection he also described how the great sage Saubhari married the daughters of Māndhātā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Mahārāja Ambarīṣa had three sons, named Virūpa, Ketumān and Śambhu. The son of Virūpa was Pṛṣadaśva, and his son was Rathītara. Rathītara had no sons, but when he requested the favor of the great sage Aṅgirā, the sage begot several sons in the womb of Rathītara’s wife. When the sons were born, they became the dynasty of Aṅgirā Ṛṣi and of Rathītara.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the descendants of King Māndhātā are described, and in this connection the histories of Purukutsa and Hariścandra are also given.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The most prominent son of Māndhātā was Ambarīṣa, his son was Yauvanāśva, and Yauvanāśva’s son was Hārīta. These three personalities were the best in the dynasty of Māndhātā. Purukutsa, another son of Māndhātā, married the sister of the snakes (&lt;em&gt;sarpa-gaṇa&lt;/em&gt;) named Narmadā. The son of Purukutsa was Trasaddasyu, whose son was Anaraṇya. Anaraṇya’s son was Haryaśva, Haryaśva’s son was Prāruṇa, Prāruṇa’s son was Tribandhana, and Tribandhana’s son was Satyavrata, also known as Triśaṅku. When Triśaṅku kidnapped the daughter of a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa,&lt;/em&gt; his father cursed him for this sinful act, and Triśaṅku became a &lt;em&gt;caṇḍāla,&lt;/em&gt; worse than a &lt;em&gt;śūdra.&lt;/em&gt; Later, by the influence of Viśvāmitra, he was brought to the heavenly planets, but by the influence of the demigods he fell back downward. He was stopped in his fall, however, by the influence of Viśvāmitra. The son of Triśaṅku was Hariścandra. Hariścandra once performed a Rājasūya-yajña, but Viśvāmitra cunningly took all of Hariścandra’s possessions as a &lt;em&gt;dakṣiṇa&lt;/em&gt; contribution and chastised Hariścandra in various ways. Because of this, a quarrel arose between Viśvāmitra and Vasiṣṭha. Hariścandra had no sons, but on the advice of Nārada he worshiped Varuṇa and in this way got a son named Rohita. Hariścandra promised that Rohita would be used to perform a Varuṇa-yajña. Varuṇa reminded Hariścandra repeatedly about this &lt;em&gt;yajña,&lt;/em&gt; but the King, because of affection for his son, gave various arguments to avoid sacrificing him. Thus time passed, and gradually the son grew up. To safeguard his life, the boy then took bow and arrows in hand and went to the forest. Meanwhile, at home, Hariścandra suffered from dropsy because of an attack from Varuṇa. When Rohita received the news that his father was suffering, he wanted to return to the capital, but King Indra prevented him from doing so. Following the instructions of Indra, Rohita lived in the forest for six years and then returned home. Rohita purchased Śunaḥśepha, the second son of Ajīgarta, and gave him to his father, Hariścandra, as the sacrificial animal. In this way, the sacrifice was performed, Varuṇa and the other demigods were pacified, and Hariścandra was freed from disease. In this sacrifice, Viśvāmitra was the &lt;em&gt;hotā&lt;/em&gt; priest, Jamadagni was the &lt;em&gt;adhvaryu,&lt;/em&gt; Vasiṣṭha was the &lt;em&gt;brahmā,&lt;/em&gt; and Ayāsya was the &lt;em&gt;udgātā.&lt;/em&gt; King Indra, being very satisfied by the sacrifice, gave Hariścandra a golden chariot, and Viśvāmitra gave him transcendental knowledge. Thus Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes how Hariścandra achieved perfection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this Eighth Chapter the descendants of Rohita are described. In the dynasty of Rohita there was a king named Sagara, whose history is described in relation to Kapiladeva and the destruction of the sons of Sagara.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The son of Rohita was known as Harita, and the son of Harita was Campa, who constructed a township known as Campāpurī. The son of Campa was Sudeva, the son of Sudeva was Vijaya, the son of Vijaya was Bharuka, and the son of Bharuka was Vṛka. Bāhuka, the son of Vṛka, was greatly disturbed by his enemies, and therefore he left home with his wife and went to the forest. When he died there, his wife wanted to accept the principles of &lt;em&gt;satī,&lt;/em&gt; dying with her husband, but when she was about to die a sage named Aurva found that she was pregnant and forbade her to do so. The co-wives of this wife of Bāhuka gave her poison with her food, but still her son was born with the poison. The son was therefore named Sagara (&lt;em&gt;sa&lt;/em&gt; means “with,” and &lt;em&gt;gara&lt;/em&gt; means “poison”). Following the instructions of the great sage Aurva, King Sagara reformed many clans, including the Yavanas, Śakas, Haihayas and Barbaras. The king did not kill them, but reformed them. Then, again following the instructions of Aurva, King Sagara performed &lt;em&gt;aśvamedha&lt;/em&gt; sacrifices, but the horse needed for such a sacrifice was stolen by Indra, the King of heaven. King Sagara had two wives, named Sumati and Keśinī. While searching for the horse, the sons of Sumati extensively dug up the surface of the earth and in this way dug a trench, which later became known as the Sāgara Ocean. In the course of this search, they came upon the great personality Kapiladeva and thought Him to have stolen the horse. With this offensive understanding, they attacked Him and were all burned to ashes. Keśinī, the second wife of King Sagara, had a son named Asamañjasa, whose son Aṁśumān later searched for the horse and delivered his uncles. Upon approaching Kapiladeva, Aṁśumān saw both the horse meant for sacrifice and a pile of ashes. Aṁśumān offered prayers to Kapiladeva, who was very pleased by his prayers and who returned the horse. After getting back the horse, however, Aṁśumān still stood before Kapiladeva, and Kapiladeva could understand that Aṁśumān was praying for the deliverance of his forefathers. Thus Kapiladeva offered the instruction that they could be delivered by water from the Ganges. Aṁśumān then offered respectful obeisances to Kapiladeva, circumambulated Him, and left that place with the horse for sacrifice. When King Sagara finished his &lt;em&gt;yajña,&lt;/em&gt; he handed over the kingdom to Aṁśumān and, following the advice of Aurva, attained salvation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the history of the dynasty of Aṁśumān, up to Khaṭvāṅga, and it also describes how Bhagīratha brought the water of the Ganges to this earth.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The son of Mahārāja Aṁśumān was Dilīpa, who tried to bring the Ganges to this world but who died without success. Bhagīratha, the son of Dilīpa, was determined to bring the Ganges to the material world, and for this purpose he underwent severe austerities. Mother Ganges, being fully satisfied by his austerities, made herself visible to him, wanting to give him a benediction. Bhagīratha then asked her to deliver his forefathers. Although mother Ganges agreed to come down to earth, she made two conditions: first, she wanted some suitable male to be able to control her waves; second, although all sinful men would be freed from sinful reactions by bathing in the Ganges, mother Ganges did not want to keep all these sinful reactions. These two conditions were subject matters for consideration. Bhagīratha replied to mother Ganges, “The Personality of Godhead Lord Śiva will be completely able to control the waves of your water, and when pure devotees bathe in your water, the sinful reactions left by sinful men will be counteracted.” Bhagīratha then performed austerities to satisfy Lord Śiva, who is called Āśutoṣa because he is naturally satisfied very easily. Lord Śiva agreed to Bhagīratha’s proposal to check the force of the Ganges. In this way, simply by the touch of the Ganges, Bhagīratha’s forefathers were delivered and allowed to go to the heavenly planets.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Tenth Chapter describes how Lord Rāmacandra appeared in the dynasty of Mahārāja Khaṭvāṅga. It also describes the Lord’s activities, telling how He killed Rāvaṇa and returned to Ayodhyā, the capital of His kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The son of Mahārāja Khaṭvāṅga was Dīrghabāhu, and his son was Raghu. The son of Raghu was Aja, the son of Aja was Daśaratha, and the son of Daśaratha was Lord Rāmacandra, the Supreme Personality of Godhead. When the Lord descended into this world in His full quadruple expansion — as Lord Rāmacandra, Lakṣmaṇa, Bharata and Śatrughna — great sages like Vālmīki who were actually in knowledge of the Absolute Truth described His transcendental pastimes. Śrīla Śukadeva Gosvāmī describes these pastimes in brief.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Lord Rāmacandra resided in Ayodhyā with His younger brothers and performed various sacrifices.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Rāmacandra, the Supreme Personality of Godhead, performed various sacrifices by which to worship Himself, and at the end of these sacrifices He gave land to the &lt;em&gt;hotā, adhvaryu, udgātā&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;brahmā&lt;/em&gt; priests. He gave them the eastern, western, northern and southern directions respectively, and the balance He gave to the &lt;em&gt;ācārya.&lt;/em&gt; Lord Rāmacandra’s faith in the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; and affection for His servants was observed by all the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas,&lt;/em&gt; who then offered their prayers to the Lord and returned whatever they had taken from Him. They regarded the enlightenment given to them by the Lord within the core of their hearts as a sufficient contribution. Lord Rāmacandra subsequently dressed Himself like an ordinary person and began wandering within the capital to understand what impression the citizens had of Him. By chance, one night He heard a man talking to his wife, who had gone to another man’s house. In the course of rebuking his wife, the man spoke suspiciously of the character of Sītādevī. The Lord immediately returned home, and, fearing such rumors, He superficially decided to give up Sītādevī’s company. Thus He banished Sītādevī, who was pregnant, to the shelter of Vālmīki Muni, where she gave birth to twin sons, named Lava and Kuśa. In Ayodhyā, Lakṣmaṇa begot two sons named Aṅgada and Citraketu, Bharata begot two sons named Takṣa and Puṣkala, and Śatrughna begot two sons named Subāhu and Śrutasena. When Bharata went out to conquer various lands on behalf of the emperor, Lord Rāmacandra, He fought many millions of Gandharvas. By killing them in the fight, He acquired immense wealth, which He then brought home. Śatrughna killed a demon named Lavaṇa at Madhuvana and thus established the capital of Mathurā. Meanwhile, Sītādevī placed her two sons in the care of Vālmīki Muni and then entered into the earth. Upon hearing of this, Lord Rāmacandra was very much aggrieved, and thus He performed sacrifices for thirteen thousand years. After describing the pastimes of Lord Rāmacandra’s disappearance and establishing that the Lord appears for His pastimes only, Śukadeva Gosvāmī ends this chapter by describing the results of hearing about the activities of Lord Rāmacandra and by describing how the Lord protected His citizens and displayed affection for His brothers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the dynasty of Kuśa, the son of Lord Rāmacandra. The members of this dynasty are descendants of Śaśāda, the son of Mahārāja Ikṣvāku.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Following in the genealogical table of Lord Rāmacandra’s dynasty, Kuśa, the Lord’s son, was followed consecutively by Atithi, Niṣadha, Nabha, Puṇḍarīka, Kṣemadhanvā, Devānīka, Anīha, Pāriyātra, Balasthala, Vajranābha, Sagaṇa and Vidhṛti. These personalities ruled the world. From Vidhṛti came Hiraṇyanābha, who later became the disciple of Jaimini and propounded the system of mystic &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt; in which Yājñavalkya was initiated. Following in this dynasty were Puṣpa, Dhruvasandhi, Sudarśana, Agnivarṇa, Śīghra and Maru. Maru attained full perfection in the practice of &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; and he still lives in the village of Kalāpa. At the end of this Age of Kali, he will revive the dynasty of the sun-god. Next in the dynasty were Prasuśruta, Sandhi, Amarṣaṇa, Mahasvān, Viśvabāhu, Prasenajit, Takṣaka and Bṛhadbala, who was later killed by Abhimanyu. Śukadeva Gosvāmī said that these were all kings who had passed away. The future descendants of Bṛhadbala will be Bṛhadraṇa, Ūrukriya, Vatsavṛddha, Prativyoma, Bhānu, Divāka, Sahadeva, Bṛhadaśva, Bhānumān, Pratīkāśva, Supratīka, Marudeva, Sunakṣatra, Puṣkara, Antarikṣa, Sutapā, Amitrajit, Bṛhadrāja, Barhi, Kṛtañjaya, Raṇañjaya, Sañjaya, Śākya, Śuddhoda, Lāṅgala, Prasenajit, Kṣudraka, Raṇaka, Suratha and Sumitra. All of them will become kings one after another. Sumitra, coming in this Age of Kali, will be the last king in the Ikṣvāku dynasty; after him, the dynasty will be extinguished.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the dynasty in which the great and learned scholar Janaka was born. This is the dynasty of Mahārāja Nimi, who is said to have been the son of Ikṣvāku.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Mahārāja Nimi began performing great sacrifices, he appointed Vasiṣṭha to be chief priest, but Vasiṣṭha refused, for he had already agreed to be priest in performing a &lt;em&gt;yajña&lt;/em&gt; for Lord Indra. Vasiṣṭha therefore requested Mahārāja Nimi to wait until Lord Indra’s sacrifice was finished, but Mahārāja Nimi did not wait. He thought, “Life is very short, so there is no need to wait.” He therefore appointed another priest to perform the &lt;em&gt;yajña.&lt;/em&gt; Vasiṣṭha was very angry at King Nimi and cursed him, saying, “May your body fall down.” Cursed in that way, Mahārāja Nimi also became very angry and retaliated by saying, “May your body also fall down.” As a result of this cursing and countercursing, both of them died. After this incident, Vasiṣṭha took birth again, begotten by Mitra and Varuṇa, who were agitated by Urvaśī.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The summary of this Fourteenth Chapter is given as follows. This chapter describes Soma and how he kidnapped the wife of Bṛhaspati and begot in her womb a son named Budha. Budha begot Purūravā, who begot six sons, headed by Āyu, in the womb of Urvaśī.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Brahmā was born from the lotus that sprouted from the navel of Garbhodakaśāyī Viṣṇu. Brahmā had a son named Atri, and Atri’s son was Soma, the king of all drugs and stars. Soma became the conqueror of the entire universe, and, being inflated with pride, he kidnapped Tārā, who was the wife of Bṛhaspati, the spiritual master of the demigods. A great fight ensued between the demigods and the &lt;em&gt;asuras,&lt;/em&gt; but Brahmā rescued Bṛhaspati’s wife from the clutches of Soma and returned her to her husband, thus stopping the fighting. In the womb of Tārā, Soma begot a son named Budha, who later begot in the womb of Ilā a son named Aila, or Purūravā. Urvaśī was captivated by Purūravā’s beauty, and therefore she lived with him for some time, but when she left his company he became almost like a madman. While traveling all over the world, he met Urvaśī again at Kurukṣetra, but she agreed to join with him for only one night in a year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the history of Gādhi in the dynasty of Aila.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the womb of Urvaśī came six sons, named Āyu, Śrutāyu, Satyāyu, Raya, Jaya and Vijaya. The son of Śrutāyu was Vasumān, the son of Satyāyu was Śrutañjaya, the son of Raya was Eka, the son of Jaya was Amita, and the son of Vijaya was Bhīma. Bhīma’s son was named Kāñcana, the son of Kāñcana was Hotraka, and the son of Hotraka was Jahnu, who was celebrated for having drunk all the water of the Ganges in one sip. The descendants of Jahnu, one after another, were Puru, Balāka, Ajaka and Kuśa. The sons of Kuśa were Kuśāmbu, Tanaya, Vasu and Kuśanābha. From Kuśāmbu came Gādhi, who had a daughter named Satyavatī. Satyavatī married Ṛcīka Muni after the &lt;em&gt;muni&lt;/em&gt; contributed a substantial dowry, and from the womb of Satyavatī by Ṛcīka Muni, Jamadagni was born. The son of Jamadagni was Rāma, or Paraśurāma. When a king named Kārtavīryārjuna stole Jamadagni’s desire cow, Paraśurāma, who is ascertained by learned experts to be a &lt;em&gt;saktyāveśa&lt;/em&gt; incarnation of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, killed Kārtavīryārjuna. Later, he annihilated the &lt;em&gt;kṣatriya&lt;/em&gt; dynasty twenty-one times. After Paraśurāma killed Kārtavīryārjuna, Jamadagni told him that killing a king is sinful and that as a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; he should have tolerated the offense. Therefore Jamadagni advised Paraśurāma to atone for his sin by traveling to various holy places.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Jamadagni was killed by the sons of Kārtavīryārjuna, as described in this chapter, Paraśurāma rid the entire world of &lt;em&gt;kṣatriyas&lt;/em&gt; twenty-one times. This chapter also describes the descendants of Viśvāmitra.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Jamadagni’s wife, Reṇukā, went to bring water from the Ganges and saw the King of the Gandharvas enjoying the company of Apsarās, she was captivated, and she slightly desired to associate with him. Because of this sinful desire, she was punished by her husband. Paraśurāma killed his mother and brothers, but later, by dint of the austerities of Jamadagni, they were revived. The sons of Kārtavīryārjuna, however, remembering the death of their father, wanted to take revenge against Lord Paraśurāma, and therefore when Paraśurāma was absent from the &lt;em&gt;āśrama,&lt;/em&gt; they killed Jamadagni, who was meditating on the Supreme Personality of Godhead. When Paraśurāma returned to the &lt;em&gt;āśrama&lt;/em&gt; and saw his father killed, he was very sorry, and after asking his brothers to take care of the dead body, he went out with determination to kill all the &lt;em&gt;kṣatriyas&lt;/em&gt; on the surface of the world. Taking up his axe, he went to Māhiṣmatī-pura, the capital of Kārtavīryārjuna, and killed all of Kārtavīryārjuna’s sons, whose blood became a great river. Paraśurāma, however, was not satisfied with killing only the sons of Kārtavīryārjuna; later, when the &lt;em&gt;kṣatriyas&lt;/em&gt; became disturbing, he killed them twenty-one times, so that there were no &lt;em&gt;kṣatriyas&lt;/em&gt; on the surface of the earth. Thereafter, Paraśurāma joined the head of his father to the dead body and performed various sacrifices to please the Supreme Lord. Thus Jamadagni got life again in his body, and later he was promoted to the higher planetary system known as Saptarṣi-maṇḍala. Paraśurāma, the son of Jamadagni, still lives in Mahendra-parvata. In the next &lt;em&gt;manvantara,&lt;/em&gt; he will become a preacher of Vedic knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Āyu, the eldest son of Purūravā, had five sons. This chapter describes the dynasties of four of them, beginning with Kṣatravṛddha.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Āyu, the son of Purūravā, had five sons — Nahuṣa, Kṣatravṛddha, Rajī, Rābha and Anenā. The son of Kṣatravṛddha was Suhotra, who had three sons, named Kāśya, Kuśa and Gṛtsamada. The son of Gṛtsamada was Śunaka, and his son was Śaunaka. The son of Kāśya was Kāśi. From Kāśi came the sons and grandsons known as Rāṣṭra, Dīrghatama and then Dhanvantari, who was the inaugurator of medical science and was a &lt;em&gt;śaktyāveśa&lt;/em&gt; incarnation of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Vāsudeva. The descendants of Dhanvantari were Ketumān, Bhīmaratha, Divodāsa and Dyumān, who was also known as Pratardana, Śatrujit, Vatsa, Ṛtadhvaja and Kuvalayāśva. The son of Dyumān was Alarka, who reigned over the kingdom for many, many years. Following in the dynasty of Alarka were Santati, Sunītha, Niketana, Dharmaketu, Satyaketu, Dhṛṣṭaketu, Sukumāra, Vītihotra, Bharga and Bhārgabhūmi. All of them belonged to the dynasty of Kāśi, the descendant of Kṣatravṛddha.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter gives the history of King Yayāti, the son of Nahuṣa. Among Yayāti’s five sons, the youngest son, Pūru, accepted Yayāti’s invalidity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Nahuṣa, who had six sons, was cursed to become a python, his eldest son, Yati, took &lt;em&gt;sannyāsa,&lt;/em&gt; and therefore the next son, Yayāti, was enthroned as king. By providence, Yayāti married the daughter of Śukrācārya. Śukrācārya was a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; and Yayāti a &lt;em&gt;kṣatriya,&lt;/em&gt; but Yayāti married her nonetheless. Śukrācārya’s daughter, named Devayānī, had a girlfriend named Śarmiṣṭhā, who was the daughter of Vṛṣaparvā. King Yayāti married Śarmiṣṭhā also. The history of this marriage is as follows. Once Śarmiṣṭhā was sporting in the water with thousands of her girlfriends, and Devayānī was also there. When the young girls saw Lord Śiva, seated on his bull with Umā, they immediately dressed themselves, but Śarmiṣṭhā mistakenly put on Devayānī’s clothes. Devayānī, being very angry, rebuked Śarmiṣṭhā, who also became very angry and responded by rebuking Devayānī and throwing her into a well. By chance, King Yayāti came to that well to drink water, and he found Devayānī and rescued her. Thus Devayānī accepted Mahārāja Yayāti as her husband. Thereafter, Devayānī, crying loudly, told her father about Śarmiṣṭhā’s behavior. Upon hearing of this incident, Śukrācārya was very angry and wanted to chastise Vṛṣaparvā, Śarmiṣṭhā’s father. Vṛṣaparvā, however, satisfied Śukrācārya by offering Śarmiṣṭhā as Devayānī’s maidservant. Thus Śarmiṣṭhā, as the maidservant of Devayānī, also went to the house of Devayānī’s husband. When Śarmiṣṭhā found her friend Devayānī with a son she also desired to have a son. Therefore, at the proper time for conception, she also requested Mahārāja Yayāti for sex. When Śarmiṣṭhā became pregnant also, Devayānī was very envious. In great anger, she immediately left for her father’s house and told her father everything. Śukrācārya again became angry and cursed Mahārāja Yayāti to become old, but when Yayāti begged Śukrācārya to be merciful to him, Śukrācārya gave him the benediction that he could transfer his old age and invalidity to some young man. Yayāti exchanged his old age for the youth of his youngest son, Pūru, and thus he was able to enjoy with young girls.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Nineteenth Chapter describes how Mahārāja Yayāti achieved liberation after he recounted the figurative story of the he-goat and she-goat.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After many, many years of sexual relationships and enjoyment in the material world, King Yayāti finally became disgusted with such materialistic happiness. When satiated with material enjoyment, he devised a story of a he-goat and she-goat, corresponding to his own life, and narrated the story before his beloved Devayānī. The story is as follows. Once upon a time, while a goat was searching in a forest for different types of vegetables to eat, by chance he came to a well, in which he saw a she-goat. He became attracted to this she-goat and somehow or other delivered her from the well, and thus they were united. One day thereafter, when the she-goat saw the he-goat enjoying sex with another she-goat, she became angry, abandoned the he-goat, and returned to her &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; owner, to whom she described her husband’s behavior. The &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; became very angry and cursed the he-goat to lose his sexual power. Thereupon, the he-goat begged the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa’s&lt;/em&gt; pardon and was given back the power for sex. Then the he-goat enjoyed sex with the she-goat for many years, but still he was not satisfied. If one is lusty and greedy, even the total stock of gold in this world cannot satisfy one’s lusty desires. These desires are like a fire. One may pour clarified butter on a blazing fire, but one cannot expect the fire to be extinguished. To extinguish such a fire, one must adopt a different process. The &lt;em&gt;śāstra&lt;/em&gt; therefore advises that by intelligence one renounce the life of enjoyment. Without great endeavor, those with a poor fund of knowledge cannot give up sense enjoyment, especially in relation to sex, because a beautiful woman bewilders even the most learned man. King Yayāti, however, renounced worldly life and divided his property among his sons. He personally adopted the life of a mendicant, or &lt;em&gt;sannyāsī,&lt;/em&gt; giving up all attraction to material enjoyment, and engaged himself fully in devotional service to the Lord. Thus he attained perfection. Later, when his beloved wife, Devayānī, was freed from her mistaken way of life, she also engaged herself in the devotional service of the Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the history of Pūru and his descendant Duṣmanta. The son of Pūru was Janamejaya, and his son was Pracinvān. The sons and grandsons in the line of Pracinvān, one after another, were Pravīra, Manusyu, Cārupada, Sudyu, Bahugava, Saṁyāti, Ahaṁyāti and Raudrāśva. Raudrāśva had ten sons — Ṛteyu, Kakṣeyu, Sthaṇḍileyu, Kṛteyuka, Jaleyu, Sannateyu, Dharmeyu, Satyeyu, Vrateyu and Vaneyu. The son of Ṛteyu was Rantināva, who had three sons — Sumati, Dhruva and Apratiratha. The son of Apratiratha was Kaṇva, and Kaṇva’s son was Medhātithi. The sons of Medhātithi, headed by Praskanna, were all &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas.&lt;/em&gt; The son of Rantināva named Sumati had a son named Rebhi, and his son was Duṣmanta.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Twenty-first Chapter describes the dynasty born from Mahārāja Bharata, the son of Mahārāja Duṣmanta, and it also describes the glories of Rantideva, Ajamīḍha and others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The son of Bharadvāja was Manyu, and Manyu’s sons were Bṛhatkṣatra, Jaya, Mahāvīrya, Nara and Garga. Of these five, Nara had a son named Saṅkṛti, who had two sons, named Guru and Rantideva. As an exalted devotee, Rantideva saw every living entity in relationship with the Supreme Personality of Godhead, and therefore he completely engaged his mind, his words and his very self in the service of the Supreme Lord and His devotees. Rantideva was so exalted that he would sometimes give away his own food in charity, and he and his family would fast. Once, after Rantideva spent forty-eight days fasting, not even drinking water, excellent food made with ghee was brought to him, but when he was about to eat it a &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; guest appeared. Rantideva, therefore, did not eat the food, but instead immediately offered a portion of it to the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa.&lt;/em&gt; When the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; left and Rantideva was just about to eat the remnants of the food, a &lt;em&gt;śūdra&lt;/em&gt; appeared. Rantideva therefore divided the remnants between the &lt;em&gt;śūdra&lt;/em&gt; and himself. Again, when he was just about to eat the remnants of the food, another guest appeared. Rantideva therefore gave the rest of the food to the new guest and was about to content himself with drinking the water to quench his thirst, but this also was precluded, for a thirsty guest came and Rantideva gave him the water. This was all ordained by the Supreme Personality of Godhead just to glorify His devotee and show how tolerant a devotee is in rendering service to the Lord. The Supreme Personality of Godhead, being extremely pleased with Rantideva, entrusted him with very confidential service. The special power to render the most confidential service is entrusted by the Supreme Personality of Godhead to a pure devotee, not to ordinary devotees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the descendants of Divodāsa. It also describes Jarāsandha, who belonged to the Ṛkṣa dynasty, as well as Duryodhana, Arjuna and others.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The son of Divodāsa was Mitrāyu, who had four sons, one after another — Cyavana, Sudāsa, Sahadeva and Somaka. Somaka had one hundred sons, of whom the youngest was Pṛṣata, from whom Drupada was born. Drupada’s daughter was Draupadī, and his sons were headed by Dhṛṣṭadyumna. Dhṛṣṭadyumna’s son was Dhṛṣṭaketu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this Twenty-third Chapter the dynasties of Anu, Druhyu, Turvasu and Yadu, as well as the story of Jyāmagha, are described.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sons of Yayāti’s fourth son, Anu, were Sabhānara, Cakṣu and Pareṣṇu. Of these three, the sons and grandsons of Sabhānara were, in succession, Kālanara, Sṛñjaya, Janamejaya, Mahāśāla and Mahāmanā. The sons of Mahāmanā were Uśīnara and Titikṣu. Uśīnara had four sons, namely Śibi, Vara, Kṛmi and Dakṣa. Śibi also had four sons — Vṛṣādarbha, Sudhīra, Madra and Kekaya. The son of Titikṣu was Ruṣadratha, who begot a son named Homa. From Homa came Sutapā and from Sutapā, Bali. In this way the dynasty continued. Begotten by Dīrghatamā in the womb of the wife of Bali were Aṅga, Vaṅga, Kaliṅga, Suhma, Puṇḍra and Oḍra, all of whom became kings.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Vidarbha had three sons, named Kuśa, Kratha and Romapāda. Of these three, Romapāda expanded his dynasty by the sons and grandsons named Babhru, Kṛti, Uśika, Cedi and Caidya, all of whom later became kings. From the son of Vidarbha named Kratha came a son named Kunti, from whose dynasty came the descendants named Vṛṣṇi, Nirvṛti, Daśārha, Vyoma, Jīmūta, Vikṛti, Bhīmaratha, Navaratha, Daśaratha, Śakuni, Karambhi, Devarāta, Devakṣatra, Madhu, Kuruvaśa, Anu, Puruhotra, Ayu and Sātvata. Sātvata had seven sons. One of them was Devāvṛdha, whose son was Babhru. Another son of Sātvata was Mahābhoja, by whom the Bhoja dynasty was inaugurated. Another was Vṛṣṇi, who had a son named Yudhājit. From Yudhājit came Anamitra and Śini, and from Anamitra came Nighna and another Śini. The descendants in succession from Śini were Satyaka, Yuyudhāna, Jaya, Kuṇi and Yugandhara. Another son of Anamitra was Vṛṣṇi. From Vṛṣṇi came Śvaphalka, by whom Akrūra and twelve other sons were generated. From Akrūra came two sons, named Devavān and Upadeva. The son of Andhaka named Kukura was the origin of the descendants known as Vahni, Vilomā, Kapotaromā, Anu, Andhaka, Dundubhi, Avidyota, Punarvasu and Āhuka. Āhuka had two sons, named Devaka and Ugrasena. The four sons of Devaka were known as Devavān, Upadeva, Sudeva and Devavardhana, and his seven daughters were Dhṛtadevā, Śāntidevā, Upadevā, Śrīdevā, Devarakṣitā, Sahadevā and Devakī. Vasudeva married all seven daughters of Devaka. Ugrasena had nine sons named Kaṁsa, Sunāmā, Nyagrodha, Kaṅka, Śaṅku, Suhū, Rāṣṭrapāla, Dhṛṣṭi and Tuṣṭimān, and he had five daughters named Kaṁsā, Kaṁsavatī, Kaṅkā, Śūrabhū and Rāṣṭrapālikā. The younger brothers of Vasudeva married all the daughters of Ugrasena.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>२५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/09/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-ten&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eleven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twelve&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fourteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventeen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nineteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-forty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FORTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventy-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighty-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTY-NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-ninety&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINETY&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
