<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;११ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;११ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 The Curse upon the Yadu Dynasty</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter gives a hint of the destruction of the Yadu dynasty, which took place owing to the appearance of an iron club. Hearing this narration is a great impetus for becoming detached from the material world.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa expertly arranged the great Kurukṣetra battle between the Kurus and the Pāṇḍavas and thus removed to a great extent the earth’s burden. But the Supreme Lord, whose influence is inconceivable, was not yet satisfied, because of the continued presence of the undefeatable Yadu family. The Lord desired to bring about the destruction of the Yadu dynasty so that He could completely wind up His pastimes on the earth and go back to His own abode. Using the pretense of a curse by an assembly of &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas,&lt;/em&gt; He withdrew His entire dynasty from the surface of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Mahārāja Nimi Meets the Nine Yogendras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Nārada gives instructions in &lt;em&gt;bhāgavata-dharma&lt;/em&gt; to the faithful and inquisitive Vasudeva by recounting a conversation between Mahārāja Nimi and the nine Yogendras.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Greatly eager to see Lord Kṛṣṇa, Devarṣi Nārada resided almost exclusively in Dvārakā. Vasudeva, bewildered by the Lord’s illusory potency, had previously offered worship to the Supreme Lord Ananta for the purpose of getting a son, but had failed to worship Him for liberation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Liberation from the Illusory Energy</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In answer to four questions spoken by Mahārāja Nimi, this chapter describes the nature and activities of the illusory potency (&lt;em&gt;māyā&lt;/em&gt;), the method of becoming free from &lt;em&gt;māyā’s&lt;/em&gt; insurmountable grip, the transcendental situation of the Supreme Lord Nārāyaṇa, and the process of &lt;em&gt;karma-yoga,&lt;/em&gt; by which one becomes free from all material activities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Personality of Godhead, the original cause of all causes, created the five material elements, from which the material bodies of the conditioned souls are created so that the conditioned souls may cultivate either sense gratification or ultimate liberation. Appearing as the Supersoul, the Supreme Lord enters the material bodies of the created beings and activates the eleven senses of the conditioned souls. The conditioned soul misidentifies the created material body with his actual self and thus engages in various fruitive activities. Impelled by the reactions of his own activities, he repeatedly takes birth in various species of life and thus suffers greatly until the time of the cosmic annihilation. When the annihilation is imminent, the soul of the universal form withdraws the entire material creation within Himself, and then He Himself enters into the original cause of all causes. In this way the Lord empowers His illusory potency, consisting of the three modes of material nature, for the creation, maintenance and annihilation of the material universe.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Drumila Explains the Incarnations of Godhead to King Nimi</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The various forms of the past, present and future incarnations of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Śrī Hari, and the various transcendental characteristics of each of these &lt;em&gt;avatāras&lt;/em&gt; constitute the subject matter of this chapter.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even if it were ever possible to count all the particles of dust on the face of the earth, any attempt to count all the innumerable transcendental qualities of the unlimited Lord Hari, the foundation of all potencies, would be simply madness. The Personality of Godhead Nārāyaṇa created the universe out of the five elements manufactured by His own &lt;em&gt;māyā,&lt;/em&gt; entered into that universe in the form of the Supersoul and became known as the Puruṣa-avatāra. He effects the work of creation in the mode of passion through the personal form of Brahmā, of protection in the mode of goodness through the form of the Lord of sacrifice, Viṣṇu, and of annihilation in the mode of ignorance through the form of Rudra. Incarnating in the form of Nara-Nārāyaṇa, the greatest of sages, from the womb of Mūrti, the daughter of Dakṣa and wife of Dharma, He preached by His own practical demonstration the science of &lt;em&gt;naiṣkarmyam.&lt;/em&gt; When Cupid (Kandarpa) and his hosts were sent to Badarikāśrama by King Indra, who had become fearful and envious at seeing the austerities of Lord Nara-Nārāyaṇa, that best of sages welcomed Cupid as an honored guest. The pacified Cupid then offered prayers to the Supreme Personality Nara-Nārāyaṇa Ṛṣi. By the order of the sage, Cupid returned from there with Urvaśī and upon presenting himself before Indra related to him everything that had taken place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Nārada Concludes His Teachings to Vasudeva</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the destination of persons who are inimical to the worship of Lord Hari, who are unable to control their own senses and who are not peaceful is examined, along with the different names, forms and modes of worship of the Personality of Godhead in each &lt;em&gt;yuga.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the face, arms, thighs and feet of the primeval person Lord Viṣṇu are born (correspondingly and in order of the modes of goodness, passion and ignorance) the four &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; — &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; and so on — and also the four different &lt;em&gt;āśramas.&lt;/em&gt; If the members of the four &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; and four &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt; do not worship Lord Śrī Hari, who is Himself directly the origin of their own creation, they will simply fall down. Among these classes, women and &lt;em&gt;śūdras,&lt;/em&gt; who generally have no contact with the hearing and chanting of &lt;em&gt;hari-kathā,&lt;/em&gt; are on account of their very ignorance special candidates for the mercy of great souls. The members of the other three &lt;em&gt;varṇas,&lt;/em&gt; becoming fit for achieving the lotus feet of Hari by second birth through Vedic initiation (&lt;em&gt;śrauta-janma&lt;/em&gt;), nevertheless become confused by concocted interpretations of the &lt;em&gt;Vedas.&lt;/em&gt; Presuming themselves to be great scholars, although not understanding the essential meaning of &lt;em&gt;karma,&lt;/em&gt; they become flatterers of other deities in their greed for fruitive results and ridicule the devotees of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. They are fixed in family life, attached to mundane gossip and indifferent to the devotional service of Viṣṇu and the Vaiṣṇavas. They are maddened by material opulences and pleasures, devoid of real discrimination and intelligence and always function on the mental platform. But such attachment to family life and so on is most natural for the mass of people, even though it is against the best advice of &lt;em&gt;śāstra.&lt;/em&gt; To become disentangled from such life in all respects is the principal teaching of the &lt;em&gt;Vedas.&lt;/em&gt; Real wealth is that conducive to the faithful execution of the duty of the soul, not that which exists simply for selfish sense gratification. As a consequence of the desire to indulge the senses, men and women couple together to produce children. Engaging in animal slaughter apart from that necessary for performance of sacrifice, these human animals themselves suffer violence in the next life. If because of excessive greed for one’s own pleasure one commits violence against living beings, he is also attacking Lord Śrī Hari, who is present in the bodies of all living entities as the Supersoul. Opposed to Lord Vāsudeva, ignorant self-cheaters completely carry out their own ruination and enter into hell.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 The Yadu Dynasty Retires to Prabhāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Brahmā and other demigods, after offering prayers to Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, requested the Lord to return to His own abode and how Uddhava, anticipating separation from the Supreme Personality of Godhead, was very distressed and prayed to Śrī Kṛṣṇa that he might accompany Him on His return to that abode.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Desiring to see Śrī Kṛṣṇa in His humanlike form, which enchants all the worlds, the Gandharvas, Apsarās, Nāgas, Ṛṣis, Pitās, Vidyādharas, Kinnaras and other demigods, all headed by Brahmā, Śiva and Indra, arrived at the city of Dvārakā. Covering the body of Kṛṣṇa with flower garlands from the Nandana gardens of heaven, they praised Him with statements about His transcendental power and qualities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Lord Kṛṣṇa Instructs Uddhava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As described in this chapter, the Supreme Lord, Kṛṣṇa, replied to Uddhava’s prayerful entreaty that he be allowed to return with Him to His abode. Kṛṣṇa advised Uddhava to take to the renounced order of &lt;em&gt;sannyāsa,&lt;/em&gt; and when Uddhava showed interest in more elaborate instructions, the Lord further described the &lt;em&gt;avadhūta’s&lt;/em&gt; account of his twenty-four spiritual masters.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After hearing Uddhava’s prayerful request to be taken back with Him to the spiritual world, Lord Kṛṣṇa informed him that He was indeed desirous of returning to His own personal abode because the purpose of His descent had been successfully fulfilled and the misfortunes of Kali-yuga would soon beset the earth. He thus advised Uddhava to take up &lt;em&gt;sannyāsa&lt;/em&gt; by fixing his mind upon Him and establishing himself in theoretical and realized transcendental knowledge. The Lord further instructed Uddhava that while remaining untouched by contamination and compassionately disposed to all beings, he should begin wandering throughout this temporary world, which is simply the combined manifestation of the Lord’s illusory energy and the imaginations of the living entities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 The Story of Piṅgalā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Kṛṣṇa told Uddhava how the &lt;em&gt;avadhūta brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; explained to Mahārāja Yadu the instructions he had received from nine of his &lt;em&gt;gurus,&lt;/em&gt; beginning with the python.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The instruction the &lt;em&gt;avadhūta brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; received from the python is that an intelligent person should cultivate a mentality of detachment and should maintain his body by accepting whatever comes of its own accord or is easily obtained. In this way, he should remain always engaged in the worship of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Even if no food is available, the person who wants to engage fully in the Lord’s worship should not beg; rather, he should understand this to be the arrangement of providence, thinking, “Whatever enjoyment is destined for me will automatically come, and thus I should not uselessly waste the remaining duration of my life in worrying about such things.” If he does not get any food, he should simply remain lying like the python and patiently fix his mind in meditation upon the Supreme Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Detachment from All that Is Material</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;avadhūta brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; describes his seven remaining &lt;em&gt;gurus,&lt;/em&gt; beginning with the &lt;em&gt;kurara&lt;/em&gt; bird. He also describes an additional &lt;em&gt;guru,&lt;/em&gt; one’s own body.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The instruction received from the &lt;em&gt;kurara&lt;/em&gt; bird is that attachment creates misery, but the person who is unattached and has no material possessions is qualified to achieve unlimited happiness.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;avadhūta brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; learned from the foolish, lazy child that by becoming free from anxiety a person becomes capable of worshiping the Supreme Personality of Godhead and experiencing supreme ecstasy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 The Nature of Fruitive Activity</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa refutes the philosophy of the followers of Jaimini and describes to Uddhava how the spirit soul bound within the material body can develop pure transcendental knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vaiṣṇava, or one who has taken shelter of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Viṣṇu, should observe the rules and regulations found in the &lt;em&gt;Pañcarātra&lt;/em&gt; and other revealed scriptures. According to his own natural qualities and work, he should follow the code of &lt;em&gt;varṇāśrama&lt;/em&gt; in a spirit free from motivation. The so-called knowledge received through one’s material senses, mind and intelligence is as useless as the dreams experienced by a sleeping person attached to sense gratification. Therefore, one should give up work performed for sense gratification and accept work as a matter of duty. When one has come to understand something of the truth of the self, he should give up material work performed out of duty and simply engage himself in the service of the bona fide spiritual master, who is the manifest representative of the Personality of Godhead. The servant of the spiritual master should have very firm affection for his &lt;em&gt;guru,&lt;/em&gt; should be anxious to receive from him knowledge of the Absolute Truth, and should be devoid of envy and the tendency to talk nonsense. The soul is distinct from the gross and subtle material bodies. The spirit soul who has entered into the material body accepts bodily functions according to the reactions of his own past activities. Therefore, only the bona fide, transcendental spiritual master is capable of demonstrating pure knowledge of the self.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 The Symptoms of Conditioned and Liberated Living Entities</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa describes to Uddhava the difference between conditioned and liberated living entities, the characteristics of a saintly person and the different aspects of the practice of devotional service.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the previous chapter Uddhava had presented questions regarding conditioned and liberated souls. In His replies, the almighty Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa states that although the spirit soul is part and parcel of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, on account of his infinitesimal nature, he falls into contact with the material energy, which causes him to accept the covering designations of the modes of goodness, passion and ignorance. Thus the soul has been bound up since time immemorial. But when he achieves the shelter of pure devotional service, he becomes designated as eternally liberated. Transcendental knowledge is therefore the cause of the living entity’s liberation, and ignorance is the cause of his bondage. Both knowledge and ignorance are produced by the &lt;em&gt;māyā&lt;/em&gt; energy of Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa and are His eternal potencies. The living entities who become attracted to the modes of nature are bewildered by false ego, which causes them to see themselves as the enjoyers of misery, confusion, happiness, distress, danger, and so on. In this way, they meditate upon such states of being, although in the real, or spiritual, world these things do not exist. Both the &lt;em&gt;jīva&lt;/em&gt; (individual soul) and the Supersoul reside within the same body. The difference between them is that the almighty Supersoul, being fully cognizant, does not indulge in enjoying the fruits of material work but remains simply as a witness, whereas the infinitesimal conditioned &lt;em&gt;jīva,&lt;/em&gt; being ignorant, suffers the consequences of his own work. The liberated &lt;em&gt;jīva,&lt;/em&gt; in spite of being within a material body because of the remaining reactions of his past activities, does not become disturbed by the happiness and suffering of the body. He sees such bodily experiences in the same way that a person who has just awakened from a dream sees his dream experiences. On the other hand, although the conditioned living entity is by nature not the enjoyer of the happiness and misery of the body, he imagines himself to be the enjoyer of his bodily experiences, just as a person in a dream imagines his dream experiences to be real. Just as the sun reflected upon water is not actually bound up in the water, and just as the air is not confined to some particular segment of the sky, similarly a detached person takes advantage of his broad outlook on the world to cut off all his doubts with the sword of appropriate renunciation, &lt;em&gt;yukta-vairāgya.&lt;/em&gt; Since his life force, senses, mind and intelligence have no tendency to fix themselves on sense objects, he remains liberated even while situated within the material body. Regardless of whether he is harassed or worshiped, he remains equipoised. He is therefore considered liberated even in this life. A liberated person has nothing to do with the piety and sin of this world, but rather sees everything equally. A self-satisfied sage does not praise or condemn anyone. He does not speak uselessly to anyone and does not fix his mind on material things. Rather, he is always merged in meditation upon the Supreme Personality of Godhead, so in the eyes of fools he seems to be a speechless, crazy person.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Beyond Renunciation and Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the glories of holy association and the superexcellence of the pure love of the residents of Vṛndāvana are described.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The association of saintly devotees destroys the soul’s attachment to material life and is capable of bringing even the Supreme Lord, Kṛṣṇa, under one’s control. Neither &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; Sāṅkhya philosophy, ordinary religious duties, study of scriptures, austerities, renunciation, works of &lt;em&gt;iṣṭā&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pūrtam,&lt;/em&gt; charity, vows of fasting, worship of the Deity, secret &lt;em&gt;mantras,&lt;/em&gt; visiting of holy places, nor adherence to any major or minor regulative principles can effect the same result. In every age there are demons, monsters, birds and animals who are in the modes of passion and ignorance, and there are also human beings in the categories of businessmen, women, workers, outcastes, and so on, who cannot study the Vedic scriptures. Nevertheless, by the purifying effect of the association of devotees they may all achieve the supreme abode of the Personality of Godhead, whereas without such saintly association, even those very seriously endeavoring in &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; Sāṅkhya study, charity, vows and practice of the renounced order of life may remain incapable of attaining the Supreme Personality of Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 The Haṁsa-avatāra Answers the Questions of the Sons of Brahmā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa explains to Uddhava how human beings, overwhelmed by sense gratification, become bound by the three modes of nature, and how to renounce these modes. The Lord then describes how He appeared in His form of Haṁsa before Brahmā and the four sages headed by Sanaka and revealed to them various confidential truths.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The three modes — goodness, passion and ignorance — are related to material intelligence, not to the soul. One should conquer the lower modes of passion and ignorance by the mode of goodness, and then one must surpass the mode of goodness by acting in the transcendental mode of pure goodness. By associating with things in the mode of goodness, one becomes more fully situated in that mode. The three modes increase their different influences through various types of scripture, water, place, time, beneficiaries of activity, natures of activity, birth, meditation, &lt;em&gt;mantras,&lt;/em&gt; purificatory rituals, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 Lord Kṛṣṇa Explains the Yoga System to Śrī Uddhava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, Kṛṣṇa explains that devotional service to the Supreme Lord is the most excellent method of spiritual practice. He also speaks about the process of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Śrī Uddhava wanted to know which process of spiritual advancement is the best. He also desired to hear about the superexcellence of devotional service free from ulterior motives. The Supreme Personality of Godhead replied to him that the original process of religion revealed in the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; had become lost during the time of annihilation. At the beginning of the new creation, therefore, the Supreme Lord spoke it again to Brahmā. Brahmā repeated it to Manu, Manu spoke it to the sages headed by Bhṛgu Muni, and these sages in turn instructed this eternal religion to the demigods and demons. Because of the living entities’ multitude of diverse desires, this system of religion was elaborately explained in different ways. Thus different philosophies arose, including various atheistic doctrines. Because the living entity, bewildered by illusion, is incapable of ascertaining his eternal benefit, he mistakenly identifies ordinary vows of penance, austerity, etc., to be the topmost spiritual practice. But the only true means of achieving happiness is to meditate on offering everything to the Supreme Lord. In this way one becomes free from all desires for selfish gratification through enjoyment of mundane sense objects, and he becomes released from all hankering for either enjoyment or liberation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 Lord Kṛṣṇa’s Description of Mystic Yoga Perfections</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the eight primary and ten minor mystic perfections. They are developed by fixing one’s mind in &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; but they are ultimately obstructions to achieving the spiritual abode of Lord Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Being questioned by Uddhava, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa describes the characteristics of the eighteen mystic perfections and the particular kind of meditation by which each is achieved. In conclusion, Kṛṣṇa states that for one who desires to perform pure devotional service to the Personality of Godhead, the achievement of these mystic perfections is a waste of time, because they distract one from proper worship. All these perfections are automatically offered to a pure devotee, but he does not accept them. Unless used in the &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt; of devotional service, these perfections are valueless. A devotee simply sees that the Personality of Godhead is always present everywhere, both externally and internally, and depends completely upon Him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 The Lord’s Opulence</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the Personality of Godhead, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, describes His manifest opulences in terms of His specific potencies of knowledge, strength, influence, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Śrī Uddhava offered glorification to Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, the Supreme Personality of Godhead and ultimate shelter of all holy places, saying, “The Supreme Lord has no beginning and no end. He is the cause of the birth, maintenance and destruction of all living entities. He is the soul of all beings, and by secretly taking up residence within all living bodies He sees everything. The conditioned souls, on the other hand, are bewildered by His external energy and thus are unable to see Him.” After offering such prayers at the lotus feet of Lord Kṛṣṇa, Śrī Uddhava revealed his desire to know about the Lord’s various opulences in heaven, on earth, in hell and in all directions. Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa then described all these opulences, after which He commented that all power, beauty, fame, opulence, humility, charity, charm, good fortune, valor, tolerance and wisdom — wherever they are manifest — are simply expansions from Himself. It therefore cannot be truthfully said that a material object actually possesses these opulences. Such conceptions are the results of mentally combining two ideas to produce an object that exists only in the imagination, such as a sky flower. Material opulences are not substantially true, and therefore one should not become too involved in meditating upon them. The pure devotees of the Supreme Lord utilize their intelligence to properly regulate the activities of their speech, mind and vital force and thus perfect their existence in Kṛṣṇa consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 Lord Kṛṣṇa’s Description of the Varṇāśrama System</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/17/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Previously, the Supreme Lord, Śrī Kṛṣṇa, had assumed the form of Haṁsa and glorified the duties of the &lt;em&gt;brahmacārī&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;gṛhastha&lt;/em&gt; orders. In this present chapter Lord Kṛṣṇa further describes these matters to Uddhava.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Uddhava inquires from Śrī Kṛṣṇa about the duties of the social and religious orders of the &lt;em&gt;varṇāśrama&lt;/em&gt; society, the Lord replies that in the first age, Satya-yuga, there was only one social order, called &lt;em&gt;haṁsa.&lt;/em&gt; In that age men were automatically dedicated to pure devotional service from their very birth, and since everyone was perfect in all respects, the age was called Kṛta-yuga. The &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; were then manifest in the form of the sacred syllable &lt;em&gt;om,&lt;/em&gt; and the Supreme Lord was perceived within the mind in the form of the four-legged bull of religion. There were no formalized processes of sacrifice, and the sinless people, who were naturally inclined to austerity, simply engaged in meditation on the personal form of the Lord. In the following age, Tretā-yuga, there became manifest from the heart of the Supreme Personality of Godhead the three &lt;em&gt;Vedas,&lt;/em&gt; and from them the three forms of the sacrificial fire. At that time the system of four &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; and four &lt;em&gt;āśramas,&lt;/em&gt; which prescribes material and spiritual duties for the different members of society, appeared from the bodily limbs of the Lord. According to how the social divisions took birth from higher and lower features of the Lord’s body, they became endowed with higher and lower qualities. After this description, Lord Kṛṣṇa explains the natures of persons in each of the four &lt;em&gt;varṇas&lt;/em&gt; and of those who are outside the limits of the &lt;em&gt;varṇas.&lt;/em&gt; He also describes those qualities that pertain to humanity in general.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>18 Description of Varṇāśrama-dharma</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/18/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As related in this chapter, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa explained to Uddhava the duties of the &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sannyāsa&lt;/em&gt; orders and the religious practices proper to each of these levels of advancement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One who is taking to the &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; stage of life should leave his wife at home in the care of his sons, or else take her along, and with a peaceful mind spend the third quarter of his life in the forest. He should accept as his food whatever bulbs, fruits, roots and so on that grow in the forest, taking sometimes grains cooked by fire and sometimes fruits ripened by time. Furthermore, he should take as his garments tree bark, grass, leaves or the skin of a deer. It is prescribed that he should perform austerities by not cutting his hair, beard, or nails. Nor should he make any special attempt to remove dirt from his limbs. He should bathe three times daily in cold water and sleep upon the ground. During the hot season he should stand beneath the fearsome heat of the sun with fires blazing on four sides. During the rainy season he should stand in the midst of the downpour of rain, and during the cold winter he should submerge himself in water up to his neck. He is absolutely forbidden to clean his teeth, to store food that he has collected at one time to eat at another time, and to worship the Supreme Lord with the flesh of animals. If he can maintain those severe practices for the remainder of his life, the &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; will achieve the Tapoloka planet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>19 The Perfection of Spiritual Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how those who practice speculative knowledge eventually give up their method, whereas the pure devotees remain engaged in devotional service eternally. Also described are the different practices of the &lt;em&gt;yogīs,&lt;/em&gt; beginning with &lt;em&gt;yama.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Lord, Śrī Kṛṣṇa, stated to Uddhava, “One who is actually wise, who knows the truth of the self and possesses transcendental insight, rejects this world of dualities and the so-called knowledge meant for facilitating enjoyment of it. He instead engages himself in trying to satisfy the Supreme Personality of Godhead, the master of all. This is pure &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga.&lt;/em&gt; Transcendental knowledge is greater than such ordinary pious activities as chanting of &lt;em&gt;mantras,&lt;/em&gt; but pure devotional service is greater than even knowledge.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>20 Pure Devotional Service Surpasses Knowledge and Detachment</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The processes of &lt;em&gt;karma-yoga, jñāna-yoga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga&lt;/em&gt; are explained in this chapter, in terms of the presence of different good and bad qualities in particular candidates.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Vedic &lt;em&gt;śāstras&lt;/em&gt; are the words expressing the order of the Supreme Personality of Godhead. In these Vedic literatures is found an outlook of duality, based on such concepts as the &lt;em&gt;varṇāśrama&lt;/em&gt; system, and at the same time the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; reject this dualistic vision. Uddhava, desiring to understand the reason why the scriptures contain such conflicting ideas, and how these might be reconciled, inquired from Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa about this matter. In response the Supreme Lord replied that the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; describe the processes of &lt;em&gt;karma-yoga, jñāna-yoga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga&lt;/em&gt; for facilitating the attainment of liberation. &lt;em&gt;Karma-yoga&lt;/em&gt; is designated for those persons who are not detached and who are full of gross desires; &lt;em&gt;jñāna-yoga&lt;/em&gt; is for those who are detached from the fruits of activity and have given up material endeavors; and &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga&lt;/em&gt; is for those persons who have taken to the principle of &lt;em&gt;yukta-vairāgya,&lt;/em&gt; appropriate renunciation. As long as one has not become uninterested in enjoying the fruits of one’s work, or as long as one’s faith in the topics of discussion of the Supreme Personality of Godhead on the path of devotional service has not awakened, then one must continue to fulfill all the prescribed duties of his &lt;em&gt;karma.&lt;/em&gt; But neither the renunciant nor the devotee of the Supreme Lord need carry out ritualistic duties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21 Lord Kṛṣṇa’s Explanation of the Vedic Path</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/21/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are persons who are unfit for all three of the forms of &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt; — &lt;em&gt;karma, jñāna&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;bhakti.&lt;/em&gt; They are inimical to Lord Kṛṣṇa, attached to sense gratification, and are dominated by fruitive activities aimed at fulfillment of material desires. This chapter describes their faults in terms of place, time, substance and beneficiary of actions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For those who are perfect in knowledge and devotion to the Lord, there are no materially good qualities or faults. But for a candidate endeavoring on the platform of &lt;em&gt;karma&lt;/em&gt; to achieve cessation of material life, execution of regular and special fruitive duties is good and the failure to execute such is evil. That which counteracts sinful reaction is also good for him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>22 Enumeration of the Elements of Material Creation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/22/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter enumerates and categorizes the natural elements, explains the difference between the male and female natures and describes birth and death.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many opinions concerning the number of material elements. But this difference of opinions, brought about by the influence of the illusory energy, is not illogical. All the elements of nature exist everywhere; so authorities who have accepted the illusory potency of the Supreme Personality may propose a variety of theories. The insurmountable illusory energy of God is the root cause of their mutually contradictory arguments.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>23 The Song of the Avantī Brāhmaṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/23/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/23/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter tells the story of a mendicant &lt;em&gt;sannyāsī&lt;/em&gt; from the Avantī country as an example of how one should tolerate the disturbances and offenses created by evil persons.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The harsh words of uncouth persons pierce the heart even more severely than arrows. Yet a mendicant &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; from the city of Avantī, even while being attacked by wicked men, considered this trouble to be simply the consequence of his own past deeds and tolerated it with utmost sobriety. Previously the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; had been an agriculturalist and merchant. He had been extremely greedy, miserly and prone to anger. As a result, his wife, sons, daughters, relatives and servants were all deprived of every kind of enjoyment and gradually came to behave unaffectionately toward him. In due course of time, thieves, family members and providence took away the sum total of his wealth. Finding himself without any property and abandoned by everyone, the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; developed a deep sense of renunciation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>24 The Philosophy of Sāṅkhya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter Lord Kṛṣṇa gives instruction how bewilderment of the mind can be dispelled by the science of Sāṅkhya. Herein the Supreme Lord again imparts to Uddhava instruction about the analysis of material nature. By assimilating this knowledge the spirit soul can drive away his confusion based on false dualities.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of creation, the seer and seen are one and indistinguishable. This Supreme Absolute Truth, one without a second and inaccessible to words and mind, then separates into two — the seer, which means consciousness or personality, and the seen, which means substance or nature. The material nature, which comprises the three modes of matter, is agitated by the controlling male factor. The &lt;em&gt;mahat-tattva&lt;/em&gt; then becomes manifest together with the energies of consciousness and activity. From these come the principle of false ego in its three aspects of goodness, passion and ignorance. From false ego in the mode of ignorance arise fifteen subtle forms of sense perception, followed by the fifteen physical elements. From false ego in the mode of passion come the ten senses, and from false ego in the mode of goodness come the mind and the eleven demigods who preside over the senses. By the conglomeration of all of these elements grows the universal egg, in the midst of which the Supreme Personality of Godhead as the creating Lord of the universe takes up residence in the role of indwelling Supersoul. From the navel of this ultimate creator comes a lotus, upon which Brahmā takes birth. Lord Brahmā, invested with the mode of passion, executes austerities by the grace of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, and on the strength of these penances he is able to create all the planets of the universe. The region of heaven is meant for the demigods, that of inner space for ghostly spirits and that of the earth for human beings and others. In the region above these three planetary systems are the places of advanced sages, and in the lower worlds are those of the demons, Nāga serpents and so forth. The goals achieved by activities based on the three modes of material nature are all within the three mortal worlds. The destinations of &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; severe austerity and the renounced order of life are the worlds known as Mahar, Janas, Tapas and Satya. The goal of devotional service to the Supreme Lord, on the other hand, is the lotus feet of the Personality of Godhead in His abode, Vaikuṇṭha. This universe of material action and reaction is constituted under the control of time and the three modes of material nature. Moreover, whatever exists in this universe is simply the product of the combination of material nature and her Lord. In the same way that creation proceeds gradually from the one and supremely subtle to the multitudinous and very gross, the process of annihilation proceeds from the grossest to the subtlest manifestation of nature, leaving only the eternal spiritual substance. This ultimate Soul remains situated within Himself, alone and without end. The mind of a person who meditates on these ideas does not become bewildered by material dualities. This science of Sāṅkhya, narrated in alternating sequences of creation and annihilation, serves to cut off all doubts and bondage.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>25 The Three Modes of Nature and Beyond</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To establish the transcendental nature of the Supreme Personality of Godhead, this chapter describes the various functional manifestations of the three modes (goodness, passion and ignorance), which arise in the mind.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Control of the mind, control of the senses, tolerance and so forth are manifestations of the unmixed mode of goodness. Desire, endeavor, false pride and so on are manifestations of the unmixed mode of passion. And anger, greed and bewilderment are among the functions of the unmixed mode of ignorance. In the admixture of the three modes we find the concept of “I” and “my,” behavior in accordance with this mentality by body, mind and words, adherence to the principles of religiosity, economic development and sense gratification, and the fixed pursuit of one’s occupational duty for material interest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>26 The Aila-gītā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/26/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter explains how unfavorable association is a threat to one’s position in devotional service and how by associating with saintly persons one can attain the highest platform of devotion.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;jīva&lt;/em&gt; who has received a human body, which is in itself most conducive toward achieving the Supreme Personality of Godhead, and who has situated himself in the duties of devotional service to the Lord becomes capable of realizing Him, the very identity of spiritual bliss. Such a person, fully dedicated to the Supreme Personality, is liberated from the influence of Māyā*;* even while continuing to reside in this world created by illusion he is totally untouched by it. Those souls, on the other hand, who are bound up by Māyā are devoted only to their bellies and genitals. They are impure, and by associating with them one will fall down into the dark pit of ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>27 Lord Kṛṣṇa’s Instructions on the Process of Deity Worship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/27/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/27/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter the Supreme Personality of Godhead explains the process of &lt;em&gt;kriyā-yoga,&lt;/em&gt; or Deity worship.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Worshiping the Deity form of the Supreme Lord automatically brings purity and satisfaction to the mind. Thus it is the source of all desirable gains. If a person has no engagement in Deity service he will simply remain attracted to material sense gratification, and he will have no hope of giving up bad association. The Personality of Godhead has given instruction, among the regulations of the &lt;em&gt;Sātvata&lt;/em&gt; scriptures, on the process of worshiping Him as the bona fide Deity. Brahmā, Śiva, Nārada, Vyāsa and all other sages have recommended this process described by the Lord as most perfectly beneficial for all the occupational classes and spiritual orders of human society, including even the women and &lt;em&gt;śūdras.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>28 Jñāna-yoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/28/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter briefly summarizes the process of &lt;em&gt;jñāna-yoga,&lt;/em&gt; which previous chapters described in detail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Every created thing in this universe is a material product of the three modes of nature, is subject to sensory perception, and is essentially unreal. Actually, the designations of “good” and “bad” that we assign to the various objects and activities of this world are all superficial. It is better to avoid condemning or praising anything of this world, because doing so simply entangles one in matter and deprives one of the higher goals of spiritual life. Hidden within every object of the material universe is the spirit soul, who underlies both the causes and products of manifest existence. One should see things in this light and thus move about the material world in a mood of detachment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>29 Bhakti-yoga</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/29/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/29/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thinking that the previously described spiritual practice, based on detachment, is too difficult, Uddhava inquired about an easier method. In reply, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa gave brief instructions on devotional service.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The fruitive workers and mystic &lt;em&gt;yogīs,&lt;/em&gt; who are bewildered by the illusory energy of the Supreme Personality of Godhead and puffed up by their false identifications, refuse to take shelter of the lotus feet of the Supreme Lord. But the swanlike men, those who know how to discriminate between the essential and nonessential, always take shelter at the lotus feet of the Personality of Godhead. The Supreme Lord Himself — within the living entity as the &lt;em&gt;caittya-guru&lt;/em&gt; and without as the spiritual master who teaches by example — eradicates all the misfortune of the spirit soul and reveals His own personal form.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>30 The Disappearance of the Yadu Dynasty</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/30/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/30/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter discusses the destruction of the Yadu dynasty in connection with the winding up of the pastimes of the Supreme Personality of Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Śrī Uddhava left for Badarikāśrama, Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa, taking note of many bad omens, advised the Yādavas to abandon Dvārakā and go to Prabhāsa, on the bank of the Sarasvatī, to perform &lt;em&gt;svasty-ayana&lt;/em&gt; and other rituals for counteracting bad fortune. They followed His advice and went to Prabhāsa. There they became absorbed in festivity, and by the illusory power of Lord Kṛṣṇa they became intoxicated from drinking liquor. Thus losing their intelligence, they quarreled among themselves and began killing one another, until not a man was left alive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>31 The Disappearance of Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/31/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/11/31/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTY-ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the return of the Supreme Personality of Godhead to His own abode, along with all the Yadus.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Upon learning from Dāruka that Lord Śrī Kṛṣṇa had returned to His abode, Vasudeva and all the others remaining in Dvārakā became very much agitated by lamentation and went out from the city to find Him. All the demigods who, in pursuance of the desire of Lord Kṛṣṇa, had taken birth in the Yadu dynasty to render assistance in His pastimes followed Lord Kṛṣṇa and returned to their respective abodes. The Lord’s activities of creating a life for Himself and then dismantling it are simply tricks of Māyā, like an actor’s performance. Actually, He creates the entire universe, and then He enters within it as the Supersoul. In the end, He again winds up the entire universe within Himself and, remaining in His private glory, desists from external pastimes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
