<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;05 mUrtis on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;05 mUrtis on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 GENERAL THEMES</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/01_GENERAL_THEMES/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/01_GENERAL_THEMES/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION-I   &lt;br&gt;&#xA;GENERAL THEMES OF THE TEMPLE SCULPTURES AND VAISHNAVITE TRADITIONS.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A Hindu temple is always conceived as a miniature universe revolving around the creator who is represented by the presiding deity within the garbhagriha. Hence the temple precincts normally display all the various facets of the universe like the animals, trees and planets, human beings and their various forms, demi gods, kinnaras, gandharvas, the nadi devatas, the vana devatas etc. etc. Hence in a Hindu temple almost all the aspects of the panorama of life with its variegated changing patterns are represented in the sculptured panels.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Other Garbha Griha idols</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/03_Other_Garbha_Griha_idols/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/05_mUrtis/03_Other_Garbha_Griha_idols/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SECTION -III The Other idols in the Garbha Griha of the Tirumala Temple.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhoga-srinivasa-the-kautuka-bera&#34;&gt;Bhoga Srinivasa-The Kautuka Bera.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This idol is made of silver and was consecrated by the donor, the Pallava queen, Samavai in 966 A.D. The donor&amp;rsquo;s consecration is recorded in an epigraph on the northern wall of the temple prakaram which is perhaps the earliest inscription in the temple. This mentions that Queen Samavai also called as Kadavan-Perundevi and queen of Sakti-Vitankan arranged in the 14th regnal year of her lord and king Koppatra-Mahendra-Panmar for a daily offering of 4 nali of tiruvamudu, (cooked rice) and a perpetual lamp, (mandavilakku) for tirumanjanam on the two ayana-sankrantis and the two vishu sankrantis, and for celebrating the purattasi festival commencing from the two days before the main festival and to conduct the festival for nine days and also installed in the Tiruvilankoyil (by which name the garbha griha of the temple was then known), this idol after performing special worship of the God of the sacred Venkata Hill. She also presented gold ornaments worth 47 kalanjus. Lands were also endowed to the new Kautuka Bhera, named Manavalapperumal and the managers of the temple (called as madapatyan) were enjoined to conduct the services and the sabhaiyar were ordered to protect the endowed lands from being taxed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
