<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;०७ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;०७ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/01/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, in response to a question by Mahārāja Parīkṣit, Śukadeva Gosvāmī gives his conclusions concerning how the Supreme Personality of Godhead, although the Supersoul, friend and protector of everyone, killed the Daityas, the demons, for the sake of Indra, the King of heaven. In his statements, he totally refutes the arguments of people in general who accuse the Supreme Lord of partiality. Śukadeva Gosvāmī proves that because the body of the conditioned soul is infected by the three qualities of nature, dualities arise such as enmity and friendship, attachment and detachment. For the Supreme Personality of Godhead, however, there are no such dualities. Even eternal time cannot control the activities of the Lord. Eternal time is created by the Lord, and it acts under His control. The Supreme Personality of Godhead, therefore, is always transcendental to the influence of the modes of nature, &lt;em&gt;māyā,&lt;/em&gt; the Lord’s external energy, which acts in creation and annihilation. Thus all the demons killed by the Supreme Lord attain salvation immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/02/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As described in this chapter, after the annihilation of Hiraṇyākṣa, Hiraṇyākṣa’s sons and his brother Hiraṇyakaśipu were very much aggrieved. Hiraṇyakaśipu reacted very sinfully by trying to diminish the religious activities of people in general. However, he instructed his nephews about a history just to diminish their aggrievement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When the Supreme Personality of Godhead appeared as the boar and killed Hiraṇyakaśipu’s brother Hiraṇyākṣa, Hiraṇyakaśipu was very much aggrieved. In anger, he accused the Supreme Personality of Godhead of being partial to His devotees and derided the Lord’s appearance as Varāha to kill his brother. He began to agitate all the demons and Rākṣasas and disturb the ritualistic ceremonies of the peaceful sages and other inhabitants of earth. For want of the performance of &lt;em&gt;yajña,&lt;/em&gt; sacrifice, the demigods began wandering unseen on earth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/03/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how Hiraṇyakaśipu performed a severe type of austerity for material benefit, thus causing great distress throughout the universe. Even Lord Brahmā, the chief personality within this universe, became somewhat disturbed and personally went to see why Hiraṇyakaśipu was engaged in such a severe austerity.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hiraṇyakaśipu wanted to become immortal. He wanted not to be conquered by anyone, not to be attacked by old age and disease, and not to be harassed by any opponent. Thus he wanted to become the absolute ruler of the entire universe. With this desire, he entered the valley of Mandara Mountain and began practicing a severe type of austerity and meditation. Seeing Hiraṇyakaśipu engaged in this austerity, the demigods returned to their respective homes, but while Hiraṇyakaśipu was thus engaged, a kind of fire began blazing from his head, disturbing the entire universe and its inhabitants, including the birds, beasts and demigods. When all the higher and lower planets became too hot to live on, the demigods, being disturbed, left their abodes in the higher planets and went to see Lord Brahmā, praying to him that he curtail this unnecessary heat. The demigods disclosed to Lord Brahmā Hiraṇyakaśipu’s ambition to become immortal, overcoming his short duration of life, and to be the master of all the planetary systems, even Dhruvaloka.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/04/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter fully describes how Hiraṇyakaśipu obtained power from Lord Brahmā and misused it by harassing all the living entities within this universe.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By severe austerities, Hiraṇyakaśipu satisfied Lord Brahmā and obtained the benedictions he desired. After he received these benedictions, his body, which had been almost entirely consumed, was revived with full beauty and a luster like gold. Nonetheless, he continued to be envious of Lord Viṣṇu, unable to forget Lord Viṣṇu’s having killed his brother. Hiraṇyakaśipu conquered everyone in the ten directions and the three worlds and brought all living entities, both demigods and &lt;em&gt;asuras,&lt;/em&gt; under his control. Becoming the master of all places, including the residence of Indra, whom he had driven out, he began enjoying life in great luxury and thus became mad. All the demigods but Lord Viṣṇu, Lord Brahmā and Lord Śiva came under his control and began serving him, but despite all his material power he was dissatisfied because he was always puffed up, proud of transgressing the Vedic regulations. All the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; were dissatisfied with him, and they cursed him with determination. Eventually, all the living entities within the universe, represented by the demigods and sages, prayed to the Supreme Lord for relief from Hiraṇyakaśipu’s rule.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/05/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prahlāda Mahārāja did not carry out the orders of his teachers, for he was always engaged in worshiping Lord Viṣṇu. As described in this chapter, Hiraṇyakaśipu tried to kill Prahlāda Mahārāja, even by having a snake bite him and by putting him under the feet of elephants, yet he was unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hiraṇyakaśipu’s spiritual master, Śukrācārya, had two sons named Ṣaṇḍa and Amarka, to whom Prahlāda Mahārāja was entrusted for education. Although the teachers tried to educate the boy Prahlāda in politics, economics and other material activities, he did not care for their instructions. Instead, he continued to be a pure devotee. Prahlāda Mahārāja never liked the idea of discriminating between one’s friends and enemies. Because he was spiritually inclined, he was equal toward everyone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/06/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes Prahlāda Mahārāja’s instructions to his class friends. In speaking to his friends, who were all sons of demons, Prahlāda Mahārāja stressed that every living entity, especially in human society, must be interested in spiritual realization from the very beginning of life. When human beings are children, they should be taught that the Supreme Personality of Godhead is the worshipable Deity for everyone. One should not be very much interested in material enjoyment; instead, one should be satisfied with whatever material profits are easily obtainable, and because the duration of one’s life is very short, one should utilize every moment for spiritual advancement. One may wrongly think, “In the beginning of our lives let us enjoy material facilities, and in old age we may become Kṛṣṇa conscious.” Such materialistic thoughts are always useless because in old age one cannot be trained in the spiritual way of life. Therefore, from the very beginning of life, one should engage in devotional service (&lt;em&gt;śravaṇaṁ kīrtanaṁ viṣṇoḥ&lt;/em&gt;). This is the duty of all living entities. Material education is infected by the three modes of nature, but spiritual education, for which there is a great need in human society, is transcendental. Prahlāda Mahārāja disclosed the secret of how he had received instructions from Nārada Muni. By accepting the lotus feet of Prahlāda Mahārāja, who is in the &lt;em&gt;paramparā&lt;/em&gt; succession, one will be able to understand the mode of spiritual life. In accepting this mode of activity, there is no need for material qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/07/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, to dissipate the doubts of his class friends, the sons of the demons, Prahlāda Mahārāja states how, within the womb of his mother, he had heard from the mouth of Nārada Muni, who had instructed him in &lt;em&gt;bhāgavata-dharma.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When Hiraṇyakaśipu left his kingdom and went to the mountain known as Mandarācala to execute severe austerities, all the demons scattered. Hiraṇyakaśipu’s wife, Kayādhu, was pregnant at that time, and the demigods, mistakenly thinking that she carried another demon in her womb, arrested her. Their plan was that as soon as the child took birth they would kill him. While they were taking Kayādhu to the heavenly planets, they met Nārada Muni, who stopped them from taking her away and took her to his &lt;em&gt;āśrama&lt;/em&gt; until Hiraṇyakaśipu’s return. In Nārada Muni’s &lt;em&gt;āśrama,&lt;/em&gt; Kayādhu prayed for the protection of the baby in her womb, and Nārada Muni reassured her and gave her instructions on spiritual knowledge. Taking advantage of those instructions, Prahlāda Mahārāja, although a small baby within the womb, listened very carefully. The spirit soul is always apart from the material body. There is no change in the spiritual form of the living entity. Any person above the bodily conception of life is pure and can receive transcendental knowledge. This transcendental knowledge is devotional service, and Prahlāda Mahārāja, while living in the womb of his mother, received instructions in devotional service from Nārada Muni. Any person engaged in the service of the Lord through the instructions of a bona fide spiritual master is immediately liberated, and being free from the clutches of &lt;em&gt;māyā,&lt;/em&gt; he is relieved of all ignorance and material desires. The duty of everyone is to take shelter of the Supreme Lord and thus become free from all material desires. Regardless of the material condition in which one is situated, one can achieve this perfection. Devotional service is not dependent on the material activities of austerity, penance, mystic &lt;em&gt;yoga&lt;/em&gt; or piety. Even without such assets, one can achieve devotional service through the mercy of a pure devotee.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/08/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As described in this chapter, Hiraṇyakaśipu was ready to kill his own son Prahlāda Mahārāja, but the Supreme Personality of Godhead appeared in front of the demon as Śrī Nṛkeśarī, half lion and half man, and killed him.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Following the instructions of Prahlāda Mahārāja, all the sons of the demons became attached to Lord Viṣṇu, the Supreme Personality of Godhead. When this attachment became pronounced, their teachers, Ṣaṇḍa and Amarka, were very much afraid that the boys would become more and more devoted to the Lord. In a helpless condition, they approached Hiraṇyakaśipu and described in detail the effect of Prahlāda’s preaching. After hearing of this, Hiraṇyakaśipu decided to kill his son Prahlāda. Hiraṇyakaśipu was so angry that Prahlāda Mahārāja fell down at his feet and said many things just to pacify him, but he was unsuccessful in satisfying his demoniac father. Hiraṇyakaśipu, as a typical demon, began to advertise himself as being greater than the Supreme Personality of Godhead, but Prahlāda Mahārāja challenged him, saying that Hiraṇyakaśipu was not God, and began to glorify the Supreme Personality of Godhead, declaring that the Lord is all-pervading, that everything is under Him, and that no one is equal to or greater than Him. Thus he requested his father to be submissive to the omnipotent Supreme Lord.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>०९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/09/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As related in this chapter, Prahlāda Mahārāja, following the order of Lord Brahmā, pacified the Lord when the Lord was extremely angry after having killed Hiraṇyakaśipu.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After Hiraṇyakaśipu was killed, the Lord continued to be very angry, and the demigods, headed by Lord Brahmā, could not pacify Him. Even mother Lakṣmī, the goddess of fortune, the constant companion of Nārāyaṇa, could not dare come before Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva. Then Lord Brahmā asked Prahlāda Mahārāja to go forward and pacify the Lord’s anger. Prahlāda Mahārāja, being confident of the affection of his master, Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva, was not afraid at all. He very gravely appeared before the Lord’s lotus feet and offered Him respectful obeisances. Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva, being very much affectionate toward Prahlāda Mahārāja, put His hand on Prahlāda’s head, and because of being personally touched by the Lord, Prahlāda Mahārāja immediately achieved &lt;em&gt;brahma-jñāna,&lt;/em&gt; spiritual knowledge. Thus he offered his prayers to the Lord in full spiritual knowledge and full devotional ecstasy. The instructions given by Prahlāda Mahārāja in the form of his prayers are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/10/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes how the Supreme Personality of Godhead Nṛsiṁhadeva disappeared, after pleasing Prahlāda Mahārāja. It also describes a benediction given by Lord Śiva.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Lord Nṛsiṁhadeva wanted to bestow benedictions upon Prahlāda Mahārāja, one after another, but Prahlāda Mahārāja, thinking them impediments on the path of spiritual progress, did not accept any of them. Instead, he fully surrendered at the Lord’s lotus feet. He said: “If anyone engaged in the devotional service of the Lord prays for personal sense gratification, he cannot be called a pure devotee or even a devotee. He may be called only a merchant engaged in the business of give and take. Similarly, a master who wants to please his servant after taking service from him is also not a real master.” Prahlāda Mahārāja, therefore, did not ask anything from the Supreme Personality of Godhead. Rather, he said that if the Lord wanted to give him a benediction, he wanted the Lord to assure him that he would never be induced to take any benedictions for the sake of material desires. Exchanges of devotional service for lusty desires are always very prominent. As soon as lusty desires awaken, one’s senses, mind, life, soul, religious principles, patience, intelligence, shyness, beauty, strength, memory and truthfulness are all vanquished. One can render unalloyed devotional service only when there are no material desires in one’s mind.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/11/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the general principles by following which a human being, and specifically one who is interested in advancing in spiritual life, can become perfect.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By hearing about the characteristics of Prahlāda Mahārāja, Mahārāja Yudhiṣṭhira became extremely pleased. Now he inquired from Nārada Muni about the actual religion of a human being and about special characteristics of &lt;em&gt;varṇāśrama-dharma,&lt;/em&gt; which marks the highest status of human civilization. When Mahārāja Yudhiṣṭhira asked Nārada Muni about these matters, Nārada Muni stopped giving his own statements and quoted statements by Lord Nārāyaṇa, for He is the supreme authority for giving religious codes (&lt;em&gt;dharmaṁ tu sākṣād bhagavat-praṇītam&lt;/em&gt;). Every human being is expected to acquire thirty qualities, such as truthfulness, mercy and austerity. The process of following the principles of religion is known as &lt;em&gt;sanātana-dharma,&lt;/em&gt; the eternal religious system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/12/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter particularly describes the &lt;em&gt;brahmacārī&lt;/em&gt; and the person in the &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; stage, and it also gives a general description of the four &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt; — &lt;em&gt;brahmacarya, gṛhastha, vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sannyāsa.&lt;/em&gt; In the previous chapter, the great saint Nārada Muni has described the &lt;em&gt;varṇa&lt;/em&gt; institution of society, and now, in this chapter, he will describe the stages of spiritual advancement in the four &lt;em&gt;āśramas,&lt;/em&gt; which are known as &lt;em&gt;brahmacarya, gṛhastha, vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sannyāsa.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/13/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This Thirteenth Chapter describes the regulative principles for &lt;em&gt;sannyāsīs&lt;/em&gt; and also describes the history of an &lt;em&gt;avadhūta.&lt;/em&gt; It concludes with a description of perfection for the student in spiritual advancement.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Śrī Nārada Muni has been describing the symptoms of various &lt;em&gt;āśramas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;varṇas.&lt;/em&gt; Now, in this chapter, he specifically describes the regulative principles to be followed by &lt;em&gt;sannyāsīs.&lt;/em&gt; After retiring from family life, one should accept the status of &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha,&lt;/em&gt; in which he must formally accept the body as his means of existence but gradually forget the bodily necessities of life. After &lt;em&gt;vānaprastha&lt;/em&gt; life, having left home, one should travel to different places as a &lt;em&gt;sannyāsī.&lt;/em&gt; Without bodily comforts and free from dependence on anyone with respect to bodily necessities, one should travel everywhere, wearing almost nothing or actually walking naked. Without association with ordinary human society, one should beg alms and always be satisfied in himself. One should be a friend to every living entity and be very peaceful in Kṛṣṇa consciousness. A &lt;em&gt;sannyāsī&lt;/em&gt; should travel alone in this way, not caring for life or death, waiting for the time when he will leave his material body. He should not indulge in unnecessary books or adopt professions like astrology, nor should he try to become a great orator. He should also give up the path of unnecessary argument and should not depend on anyone under any circumstances. He should not try to allure people into becoming his disciples just so that the number of his disciples may increase. He should give up the habit of reading many books as a means of livelihood, and he should not attempt to increase the number of temples and &lt;em&gt;maṭhas,&lt;/em&gt; or monasteries. When a &lt;em&gt;sannyāsī&lt;/em&gt; thus becomes completely independent, peaceful and equipoised, he can select the destination he desires after death and follow the principles by which to reach that destination. Although fully learned, he should always remain silent, like a dumb person, and travel like a restless child.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/14/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This chapter describes the occupational duties of the householder according to the time, the country and the performer. When Yudhiṣṭhira Mahārāja became very much inquisitive about the occupational duties for the householder, Nārada Muni advised him that a &lt;em&gt;gṛhastha’s&lt;/em&gt; first duty is to be fully dependent on Vāsudeva, Kṛṣṇa, and to try to satisfy Him in all respects by executing one’s prescribed devotional service. This devotional service will depend on the instructions of authorities and the association of devotees who are actually engaged in devotional service. The beginning of devotional service is &lt;em&gt;śravaṇam,&lt;/em&gt; or hearing. One must hear from the mouths of realized souls. In this way the &lt;em&gt;gṛhastha’s&lt;/em&gt; attraction to his wife and children will gradually be reduced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/15/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The summary of the Fifteenth Chapter is as follows. In the previous chapter, Śrī Nārada Muni proved the importance of the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇa&lt;/em&gt; in society. Now, in this chapter, he will show the differences between different grades of &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas.&lt;/em&gt; Among the &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas,&lt;/em&gt; some are householders and are mostly attached to fruitive activities or the betterment of social conditions. Above them, however, are &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; who are very much attracted by austerities and penances and who retire from family life. They are known as &lt;em&gt;vānaprasthas.&lt;/em&gt; Other &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; are very much interested in studying the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; and explaining the purport of the &lt;em&gt;Vedas&lt;/em&gt; to others. Such &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; are called &lt;em&gt;brahmacārīs.&lt;/em&gt; And still other &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; are interested in different types of &lt;em&gt;yoga,&lt;/em&gt; especially &lt;em&gt;bhakti-yoga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;jñāna-yoga.&lt;/em&gt; Such &lt;em&gt;brāhmaṇas&lt;/em&gt; are mostly &lt;em&gt;sannyāsīs,&lt;/em&gt; members of the renounced order of life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/bhAgavatam/gauDIyo_abhaya-charaNaH/07/16/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-five&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-six&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIX&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eight&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nine&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-ten&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eleven&#34;&gt;CHAPTER ELEVEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twelve&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWELVE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-thirteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER THIRTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fourteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FOURTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-fifteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER FIFTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-sixteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SIXTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-seventeen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER SEVENTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-eighteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER EIGHTEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-nineteen&#34;&gt;CHAPTER NINETEEN&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-one&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-ONE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-two&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-TWO&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-three&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-THREE&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;chapter-twenty-four&#34;&gt;CHAPTER TWENTY-FOUR&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
