<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;02 HISTORICAL BACKGROUND on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;02 HISTORICAL BACKGROUND on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 PREHISTORY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/01_PREHISTORY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/01_PREHISTORY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE palaeolithic age, in which man fashioned his tools and weapons  by chipping hard stones of convenient size and shape, is represented by the  highly developed Acheulian handaxes discovered at Tirupati, Sitarampeta,  Ellampalle, Mekalavandlapalle, Piler and Ghattu. The Mesolithic (Middle  Stone) age, which was essentially a continuation of the one mentioned above,  is represented by the quartzite tools found at Agraharam, Arayandlapalle,  Chintaparti, Maratavandlapalle and Tirupati. Remains of the neolithic  age have not yet been unearthed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 ANCIENT PERIOD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/02_ANCIENT_PERIOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/02_ANCIENT_PERIOD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(1. The Mauryas and 2. The Satavahanas:)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Between the prehistoric and the earliest historical period there is a wide  gap. No direct evidence relating to the early history of Tirumala has so  far come to light. However, the political history of the area, like the other  districts, commences with the Mauryas who extended their sway to the south  after overthrowing the Nandas. After the decline of the Mauryan empire,  the territory, constituting the present Chittoor district, came under the control  of the Satavahanas whose rule lasted for more than four centuries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Pallavas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/03_Pallavas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/03_Pallavas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The area then passed under the Pallavas, who are divided into the Pallavas  of the Prakrit charters, the Pallavas of the Sanskrit charters and the Greater Pallavas. In the time of Skandavarman of the Prakrit charters, the kingdom  extended up to the river Krishna in the north and the Arabian Sea in the west. The  territory, comprising the present Chittoor district, passed out of their control  in the middle of the 4th century A.D., when the Gupta ruler, Samudragupta,  invaded the south and defeated the Pallava ruler, Vishnugopa of Kanchi.  Though the Pallava hegemony was re-established, the dominions were once  again lost to Karikala Chola during the time of Trilochana Pallava. The  Pallava overlordship over this region was established by Simhavishnu who  ruled the kingdom between A.D. 560 and A.D. 580. A major portion of  this district, situated in the north west of the Pallava  kingdom bordering  the Chalukyan territories, was poised directly between two rival powers,  the Pallavas and the Chalukyas of Badami. Mahendravarman I (AD 580-630), however, lost much of his northern territory to the Western Chalukya  ruler Pulakesi II. The Pallava rule over this district was, however, resuscitated  by Narasimhavarman I (A.D. 630-668). His successors held sway over this  area till the end. This is evident from a number of inscriptions pertaining  to the Pallava rulers such as Narasimhavarman II (A.D. 700-728), Paramesvara varman II (A,D, 728-731), Nandivarman II (A.D. 731-796), Dantivarman  (A.D. 796-847), Nandivarman III (A.D. 846-869), Nripatungavannan (A.D.  859-899) and Aparajita (A.D. 885-903), found in this district.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Renadu Cholas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/04_Renadu_Cholas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/04_Renadu_Cholas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About the period of the Chalukyas of Badami and the Greater Pallavas  of Kanchi, a portion of this district was under the rule of a branch of the  Cholas claiming descent from the family of the historical or quasi-historical  figure Karikala Chola. These chiefs are called the Renadu Cholas after the  tract Renadu 7000 in Cuddapah district. Of these chiefs, the inscriptions  of Mahendravikrama known by his title &amp;lsquo;Chola Maharaja&amp;rsquo; and his son  Punyakumara are found in this district.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Rashtrakutas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/05_Rashtrakutas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/05_Rashtrakutas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Chalukyas of Badami were overthrown in A.D. 757 by their  feudatories, the Rashtrakutas. Towards the close of the ninth century A.D.,  the Pallavas themselves had to contend with the rising power of the Pandyas.  The Rashtrakutas seem to have actively assisted them, at least for some time,  in their struggle against the Pandyas. Another new power, the Imperial  Cholas, emerged about this period in South India. These dynasties were  destined to exert considerable influence over Chittoor district. Their  feudatories, like the Banas, the Nolambas, the Western Gangas and the  Vaidumbas, were entangled in the wars of these paramount powers and Chittoor  district passed through fairly exciting times with the changing fortunes of the  kingdoms and principalities of all these rulers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 BANAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/06_BANAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/06_BANAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Banas were closely associated with the territory now falling within  the confines of Chittoor and other adjoining districts, including Kolar in  Mysore State. They constituted one of the important feudatory dynasties.  About 32 inscriptions of this dynasty are so far noticed in this district, Of  these as many as 22 inscriptions are concentrated in Punganur taluk. The  information available in these epigraphs is not Yet clear enough to permit  the presentation of any connected account.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Vaidumbas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/07_Vaidumbas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/07_Vaidumbas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A portion of this district was under the control of another local family  known as the Vaidumbas, Their capital  ‘Vaidumbavrolu’ or &amp;rsquo;the city  of the Vaidumbas &amp;rsquo; was situated in this district. Several inscriptions of this  family are found in Chittoor and Cuddapah districts and in Kolar district  of Mysore State. About twenty epigraphs of this dynasty are noticed in this  district and they are assigned on palaeographical grounds to about the 8th,  9th and 10th centuries A.D. They yield scanty information. Many are  merely hero-stones commemorating the death of warriors ,in battles and  cattle-raids Thus it is not possible to give any connected account of this  dynasty.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 WESTERN GANGAS AND NOLAMBA PALLAVAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/08_WESTERN_GANGAS_AND_NOLAMBA_PALLAVAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/08_WESTERN_GANGAS_AND_NOLAMBA_PALLAVAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another dynasty that held sway over a portion of this district was that  of the Western Gangas, the foundation of whose power was assigned to the  second half of the fourth century A.D. They were feudatory to the Pallavas.  A chief of this family, Harivarman (AD. 450-460) was crowned king by  the Pallava ruler Simhavarman I, to crush the Banas in this region. The  Western Ganga kingdom, however, witnessed partition towards the end of  the reign of Sivamara II (A.D. 788-812) between his son and brother Marasimha  and Vijayaditya respectively. A portion of this district appears to have  been included in the share of Marasimha according to the inscriptions which  came to light in Punganur taluk. Four later Ganga chiefs, namely,  (a) Uttamachola-Ganga alias Senbakachchipati Nayanar, (b) Uttamachola  Gangan alias Vira Gangan Vettum Amarabaranam, (c) Uttamachola Ganga  alias Selva Ganga and (d) Selva Ganga, son of Uttamachola Ganga Padmadeva,  are referred to in the epigraphs found in Punganur taluk. Their relationship  with either the main line or with the collateral line is not ascertainable. The  rule of the Western Gangas, however, gradually came to an end after the  capture of their capital Talakad in A.D. 1004 by the Cholas.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 CHALUKYAS OF KALYANI AND THE IMPERIAL CHOLAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/09_CHALUKYAS_OF_KALYANI_AND_THE_IMPERIAL/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/09_CHALUKYAS_OF_KALYANI_AND_THE_IMPERIAL/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Rashtrakutas were replaced by the Western Chalukyas of Kalyani  in A.D. 973. This district, however, continued to be under the rule of the  Cholas. The rulers who held sway subsequently were Rajaraja I (A.D. 985-1016), Rajendra I (A.D. 1012-1044), Rajadhiraja I (A.D 1052-1063), Vira  rajendra (A.D. 1063-1069) and Adhirajendra (A.D. 1067/68-I070). Of  them, the thirty years of Rajaraja&amp;rsquo;s rule constituted the formative period  of Chola imperialism. A relatively small state at his accession, hardly  recovering from the effects of the Rashtrakuta invasion, the Chola kingdom  grew under him into an extensive and well knit empire The rule of this  as well as the other Chola kings over this area is attested by a number of  inscriptions which register gifts to temples at various places in the district.  The income from the lands thus gifted was spent for the maintenance of  worship in the temple The cattle and sheep endowed to the shrine were  entrusted to shepherds whose main task was to provide ghee for the perpetual  lamps in the temples. A few other inscriptions refer to the digging of tanks,  construction of temples, and levy and remission of taxes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 SUBSEQUENT IMPERIAL CHOLAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/10_SUBSEQUENT_IMPERIAL_CHOLAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/10_SUBSEQUENT_IMPERIAL_CHOLAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The association of the Cholas with the district of Chittoor continued  for some decades. The rule of Kulottunga III (A.D. 1178-1218) was by no  means weak and he succeeded, in the midst of many troubles, in maintaining  the integrity of the kingdom. The Sambuvarayas, the Kadavarayas, the  Chedirayas and the Yadavarayas constituted the four clans of powerful  feudatories in the region comprising portions of Chittoor and Chcngleput  and the two Arcot districts. The number of feudatories, mentioned in the  inscriptions of Kulottunga&amp;rsquo;s reign, shows how rapidly conditions were changing  for the worse. The reign of his successor, Rajaraja III (A.D. 1216-1260)  was a period of continuous trouble. His inscriptions dated up to the twenty ninth regnal year are found in Chittoor and other neighbouring districts.  This implies that the hegemony of the Cholas continued to be recognised  over the whole of Chittoor in his time. During the reign of the last Chola  ruler, Rajendra III (A.D. 1246-1279), the hold of the Cholas over this district  appears to have weakened, for a number of inscriptions of the Telugu-Pallava  chief Vijayagandagopala come to light. It is generally presumed that  Vijayagandagopala and Kopperunjinga, an ally of the Pandyas shared  Tondamandalam between themselves, the former taking the northern half  and the latter the southern half.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 PANDYAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/11_PANDYAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/11_PANDYAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The kingdoms that rose subsequently were the Pandya and the Hoysala  in the south, and the Kakatiya and the Yadava in the north. Minor powers  like the Telugu-Cholas of Nellore played their part as auxiliaries to the chief  powers. The accession to the Pandya throne of  Jatavarman Sundara Pandya I  in A.D. 1251 was an important event. He was a famous warrior and a  conqueror under whom the Pandyan power attained its greatest splendour.  In the early years of his reign Jatavarman Sundara Pandya I fought many  wars and rapidly extended his sway to Nellore and beyond. He also came  into conflict with Kakatiya Ganapati whose inscription is noticed on a stone  in front of the Manikantesvara temple at Srikalahasti. Five inscriptions  of Jatavaraman Sundara Pandya I are found in this district. The other Pandya  ruler mentioned in the epigraphs of the district was Maravarman Kulasekhara I  (A.D. 1268-1308/1309). He fought against Hoysala Ramanatha who had  allied himself with the Chola ruler Rajendra III, defeated both and occupied  their territory. After this loss, Ramanatha started a war against his brother  Narasimha III and succeeded in capturing some territory. An inscription  dated in his 38th regnal year, corresponding to A.D. 1293, 1s found at Punganur.  It records the grant of four dandaka of land for offerings in the temple of  Karumanikkattalvar at the place by a certain Vamanavanan Kuttapperumal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 YADAVARAYAS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/12_YADAVARAYAS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/12_YADAVARAYAS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Yadavarayas were a local dynasty exercising authority over the  northern and eastern portion of Tondamandalam. Tirukkalattideva Yadava raya was the first chief of the family. He assumed high sounding titles such as  Chalukyanarayana &amp;rsquo; which indicate their connection with the Eastern  Chalukyas from whom they appear to have acquired a portion of the V engi  kingdom. His inscriptions are noticed in Chittoor, Nellorc and North Arcot  districts. He strengthened his power by entering into matrimonial alliance  with the Telugu Cholas. He was succeeded by his son Virarakshasa Yadava&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>13 TIRUMALA IN THE TRANSITORY PERIOD 1260-1360 A D</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/13_TIRUMALA_IN_THE_TRANSITORY_PERIOD_126/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/13_TIRUMALA_IN_THE_TRANSITORY_PERIOD_126/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tondamandalam was included in the Vijayanagara empire from the very  time of its foundation in 1336 A.D. Still, the earliest Vijayanagara record  found in the Tirumala-Tirupati region is dated 1359 A.D. The period intervening between the time of Sundara Pandya and this Vijayanagara record  is a period of transition. During this time various Chola subordinates took  advantage of the weakness of the Cholas and assumed independence. They  ligure in this region without acknowledging the suzerainty of anybody.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14 RAYAS OF VIJAYANAGAR</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/14_RAYAS_OF_VIJAYANAGAR/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/14_RAYAS_OF_VIJAYANAGAR/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The district then passed under the Rayas of Vijayanagar. Four dynasties, namely, Sangama, Saluva, Tuluva and Aravidu, ruled over the Vijayanagar  kingdom from A.D.1336 to the last quarter of the 17th century A.D. Harihara  founded the Sangama dynasty in A.D. 1336 and the kingdom during this  period extended from Nellore in the south-east to Dharwar and Badami in northern Karnataka. Harihara I was followed on the throne by his  brother .Hulli I. To unify the kingdom and strengthen his position, Bukka I  appointed his own sons as the governors of the provinces and made them  responsible for the maintenance of the royal authority. Bhaskara Bhavadura  was thus made governor of Udayagiri and Kumara Kampana of Mulbagal  and Padaividu which included a portion of this district. There are a few  inscriptions of Bulli I and his son Kumara Kampana in this district. The  earliest of these, which is undated, pertaining to Bukka I, registers the grant&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>15 TIRUMALA IN VIJAYANAGARA PERIOD</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/15_TIRUMALA_IN_VIJAYANAGARA_PERIOD/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/15_TIRUMALA_IN_VIJAYANAGARA_PERIOD/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tondamandalam was included in the kingdom of Vijayanagara from  the time of its foundation and continued as part of it till the time of its fall.  The period of the rule of the Sangama, Saluva, Tuluva and Aravidu dynasties  of Vijayanagara constitutes the most brilliant epoch in the history of the  Tirumala-Tirupati region and of its temples.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sangama Dynasty&lt;/em&gt;:-The earliest record of this dynasty found in  this region belongs to the time of Harihara I, the second ruler (1355-1377).  One important event of the time which is not known from the inscriptions  but is mentioned in the Koyil-Olugu is the removal of the processional image  of Ranganatha from Triumala to Srirangam. Kumara Kamparaya, a  Vijayanagara prince, led an expedition against the Muslim Sultan of Madura  and put an end to his rule. Gopanna, a brahman general of this prince,  got this image re-installed at Srirangam in 1371 A.D. The idol was taken  to Ginjee and kept there for some time and then finally restored to the Ranganatha temple. In all probability, it was removed from Tirumala in or about  1368 A.D. The next ruler, Harihara II, is mentioned in an inscription from  Tirumala.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>16 MATLIS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/16_MATLIS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/16_MATLIS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Matli chiefs were among the most important of the feudatory  dynasties connected with this district. They belonged to the Devachoda  family. They ruled from Madi in Rayachoti taluk (Cuddapah) and came  to the forefront when the Vijayanagar empire was at its zenith. They had  acquired sufficient status to enter into matrimonial alliances with the imperial  house itself. They stood firmly by the rulers of the fourth or the Aravidu  dynasty and helped to continue the great traditions of the Vijayanagar  empire in diverse spheres.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>17 MUSLIM RULE 1650-1800 A D</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/17_MUSLIM_RULE_1650-1800_A_D/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/02_HISTORICAL_BACKGROUND/17_MUSLIM_RULE_1650-1800_A_D/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Tirumala-Tirupati region came to be conquered by the Sultans of  Golconda by about the middle of the 17th century and remained under Muslim  rule for about a century and half. This was a period of confusion, chaos  and disorder and there was practically no government worth the name in  this region. The Hindu empire of Vijayanagara had vanished and various  interested parties like the Qutub Shah, the Mughals, the Nizam, the Marathas,  the Nawabs of Arcot, Hyder Ali, the English and the French entered the  arena and added to the confusion and misery of this area.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
