<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;N ramesha on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;N ramesha on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>00</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/00/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/00/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;publishers-note&#34;&gt;Publisher&amp;rsquo;s Note&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indian culture and spiritualism was enshrined in its temples which were exactly designed to remind people of their rich and varied heritage Thus the ideals and aspirations of the nation as a whole are centred in the temples where, we are given to understand the visible and tangible form of the Lord of the creation is established for the specious purpose of sincere worship of the devotees at large in gratitude to enable them to have a worthy and useful life in society&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Temple description</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/04_Temple_description/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/04_Temple_description/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE DESCRIPTION OF THE TIRUMALA TEMPLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;general&#34;&gt;General&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sri Venkatesvara temple of Tirumala has been undergoing several additions and changes during the centuries. Perhaps at the time it was originally constructed, it must have been a simple structure with a Garbhagriha and a Mukhamandapa together with an antarala and pradakshina surrounding it. Inscriptions found in the temple give plenty of references to its renovation and rebuilding and addition of later structures. Curiously the earliest mention of Sri Venkatesvara in the epigraphs is found in Tiruchokinur or modern Tiruchanur and not in association with the Tirumala temple on top of the Venkatadri hill, till we reach the date of the consecration of the Manavalapperumal in the Tiruvengadam temple itself. This earliest inscription found in Tiruchchokinur was made in the 51st regnal year of Ko-Vijaya Dantivikraman (826 A.D.) and tells in distinct terms that a proxy or Tiruvengadatupperumanadigal existed in Tiruvilan Koil of Tiruchokinur. The phraseology of the inscription makes it clear that he was another Lord in Tiruchokinur representing the Lord at Tiruvengadam, as we have now a number of Venkatesvara temples in various places. The renovation made in the 13th century at Tirumala was so done, as to overlap the walls of the original sanctum. It is therefore not possible now to examine the outer side of the original walls of the garbhagriha and determine how the temple might have stood originally.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 DAILY RITUALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/06_DAILY_RITUALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/06_DAILY_RITUALS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;DETAILS OF DAILY RITUALS IN TIRUMALA TEMPLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;I. Introduction.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE dominant Hindu ritualistic thinking is that an idol of God is really only a limited expression of the one inexpressible Supreme Brahman. The &lt;em&gt;Purusha Sukta&lt;/em&gt; declares that God has a thousand heads (Sahasra Sirsha Purusha). There is therefore no limit to the many different varieties or forms used to represent different aspects of that Higher Infinite which is ultimately formless. It is to focus, concentrate and lead the devotee&amp;rsquo;s mind, by slow stages to the realisation of the infinite, that, in many sanctuaries and temples, worship and prayers are done, through well laid down principles of puja. Puja and temple worship act as powerful spiritual forces to raise a limited individual slowly to the realisation of the Godhead that is in him.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 FESTIVALS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/07_FESTIVALS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/07_FESTIVALS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;FESTIVALS IN TIRUMALA TEMPLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;(i) Introduction.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE Tirumala temple is famous from earliest times for the festivals conducted on the hill. Those festivals continue with increasing popularity even up to the present day.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In ancient days under royal patronage the temple had received gifts and endowments primarily for the worship of the Lord and secondarily for augmenting the grandeur and attraction of the temple and increasing its popularity by means of elaborate festivals and profuse food offerings. Even the construction of spacious and artistic mantapams and imposing prakarams and gopurams were intended only for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 STHALAPURANA, LEGENDS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/08_STHALAPURANA_LEGENDS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/08_STHALAPURANA_LEGENDS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE STHALAPURANA OF TIRUMALA AND OTHER LEGENDS&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;(i) Introduction.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;THE sthala mahatmyam of the temple of Sri Venkatesvara is called &amp;ldquo;Sri Venkatachala Mahatmyam.&amp;rsquo; This is mentioned in several puranas like Varaha purana, Padma purana, Garuda purana, Brahma purana, Markandeya purana, Vamana purana, Brahmottara purana, Khanda purana, Aditya purana, Bhavishyottara purana and Harivamsa. Of these, the most important are the Varaha purana and Bhavishyottara purana.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are other innumerable collections of legends and stories about Tirumala and about the presiding God Sri Venkatesvara or Srinivasa. An inscription from Tirumala mentions a Venkatachala Mahatmyam that was being recited in the temple before the Lord. It is not possible to say if this work is the same as Sri Venkatachala Mahatmyam which is now available in print as the stala purana of the temple.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 LITERATURE AND SONG</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/09_LITERATURE_AND_SONG/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/09_LITERATURE_AND_SONG/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TIRUMALA IN LITERATURE AND SONG&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;section-i-tamil-literature&#34;&gt;Section I: Tamil Literature.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-general&#34;&gt;(i) General.&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The shrine of Lord Sri Venkatesvara on the Tirumala Hills is generally known as Vengadam or Triuvengadam (Tiru-beautiful) and the Lord Sri Venkatesvara as &amp;lsquo;Vengadathan&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;Tiruvengadathan.&amp;rsquo; From the earliest days of Tamil Literature up to the present day Vengadam and its Lord occupy a prominent place in Tamil literary works and His praises are sung. Further, the Tirupati Hills formed a land-mark in the topography of South India and are mentioned as the limit upto which Tamil was spoken, the place where all cultural streams of India met.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 SEVEN PHASES CONSTRUCTION</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/10_SEVEN_PHASES_CONSTRUCTION/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/10_SEVEN_PHASES_CONSTRUCTION/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;SEVEN PHASES IN THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE TIRUMALA TEMPLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-introduction&#34;&gt;1. Introduction.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;lsquo;Tirumala&amp;rsquo; means only the holy hill. Thus any hill may be called &amp;lsquo;Tirumala&amp;rsquo; and the temple on it could also be known as &amp;lsquo;Tirumala Temple. But in normal practice, the most sacred of all hill temples viz., the temple of Lord Venkatesvara on the Vengadam hills is only known as Tirumala Temple.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is impossible to determine the date of construction of this temple. There is no direct evidence to help us in this connection, and any attempt must therefore be based wholly upon inference from circumstantial evidence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>11 ARCHITECTURE, ICONOGRAPHY</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/11_ARCHITECTURE_ICONOGRAPHY/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/11_ARCHITECTURE_ICONOGRAPHY/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE ARCHITECTURE SCULPTURE AND ICONOGRAPHY OF TIRUMALA TEMPLE&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I. General.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;study of the architecture of the Tirumala temple is interesting and throws light on some of the distinctive architectural features prevalent during the Vijayanagar period over a fairly long span of two or three centuries. Architecturally speaking, Tirumala temple does not present that variegated pattern or a mixture of different styles of architecture which we meet with in several other temples of South India. Except probably the sanctum complexes in the temple, when the walls of the Garbha Griha were thickened and a new Vimanam was built and gold-gilted in the 13th Century A.D. under the patronage of the Yadavaraya rulers, and possibly a few other minor shrines, the major part of the temple is built completely in the Vijayanagar style.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 EPIGRAPHS</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/12_EPIGRAPHS/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/tirupati-mandiram/N-ramesha/12_EPIGRAPHS/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;THE EPIGRAPHS OF TIRUMALA TEMPLE.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-introduction&#34;&gt;I. Introduction.&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Tirumala temple like others in our country bears on its walls several epigraphs of various kings, queens, generals, other royal benefactors and common men who made gifts and endowments to the temple. These are of considerable interest, not only to scholars of history, to rebuild the political, social and economic history of the area, but also to those, who desire to know something of the ancient and time honoured institutions, endowments, administrative arrangement for management etc.,of the temples of our country. These inscriptions of the Tirumala temple, along with others from the neighbouring and ancilliary temples in lower Tirupathi and Tiruchanur, making a total of well over a thousand, furnish a continuous and authentic record of the transactions of the temple and the neighbouring area for the last seven or eight centuries.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
