<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;७ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;७ on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>001 A Dialogue between Jaimini and Vyāsa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/001/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/001/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Salutation to Śrī Gaṇeśa. Now is commenced the Kriyāyogasārakhaṇḍa.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. We devoutly, constantly salute the pair of the lotus-like feet of Lakṣmī’s lord, which is crowned with the bees of the heads that are bowing down, of the line of the gods like Brahmā, which very much nourishes the mass of the exquisite beauty of the lakes of the minds of the meditating saints, which has the mass of the drops of the honey of the water of Gaṅgā, and which removes the afflictions of the mundane existence.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>002 Characteristic Marks of a Vaiṣṇava</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/002/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/002/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-7. At the beginning of the creation great Viṣṇu (Mahāviṣṇu), desiring to create the entire world, turned himself into three forms—creator, protector and destroyer. The Supreme Being produced from the right side of his body, himself, called Brahmā, for creating this world. O sage, then the lord of the world produced from the left portion (of his body), his portion viz. Viṣṇu, for the protection of the world. The lord who had taken his abode in a lotus, produced from the middle part of his body the imperishable Rudra for the destruction of the world. Some describe the god having the three qualities rajas, sattva and tamas as Brahmā, some as Viṣṇu and some as Śaṅkara. Viṣṇu (who is) one (only), dividing himself into three, creates, devours and protects (the world). Therefore, the best people should not differentiate among the three in the worlds. The original Prakṛti (Nature) of the great Viṣṇu, the highest soul, which is the cause of the universe of beings is described as (consisting of) Vidyā (knowledge) and Avidyā (ignorance).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>003 The Story of King Manobhadra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/003/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/003/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O very intelligent Vyāsa, tell me the truth about the yoga of devout deeds. From you I desire to know this yoga of devout deeds.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyiāa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyiāa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. It is difficult to obtain the human body (i.e. existence) on this earth, O brāhmaṇa. A wise man, after having got a body, should practise yoga for salvation. There are said to be two kinds of yoga: of acts and of meditation. The first of the two viz. that of acts, gives all desired objects to those who practise it. Worship of Gaṅgā, of Śrī Viṣṇu, (giving) presents, so also devotion to brāhmaṇas and to the Ekādaśī-vow, similarly devotion to Dhātrī and Tulasī and honouring guests are in brief said to be the constituents of the yoga of acts, O best brāhmaṇa. O brāhmaṇa, without the yoga of acts the yoga of meditation does not succeed. One engaged in the yoga of acts goes to the highest position of Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>004 Praṇidhi, Padmāvatī and Dhanurdhvaja</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/004/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/004/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Through your grace I have heard about the greatness of Gaṅgādvāra. Now I desire to listen to the greatness of Prayāga. O sage, also tell me about the greatness of the union of Gaṅgā and the ocean. On the earth none except you is able to tell it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-9. O dear, I cannot thoroughly tell about the fruit of (the bath at) Prayāga or at the place where Gaṅgā joins the ocean. O Brāhmaṇa, listen to it in brief. O sage, do all those crores of holy places in the universe attain similarity with Prayāga? All gods like Brahmā, Viṣṇu, Śiva praise (the bath) at the confluence of Gaṅgā, Yamunā and Sarasvatī. Those who bathe there in (the month of) Māgha, when the Sun is in (the Zodiacal sign) Capricornus, never return (to his world) from the world of Viṣṇu. The fruit, O brāhmaṇa, due to bathing at Prayāga in (the month of) Māgha would be a crore-fold more than that obtained by the wise by (offering) thousands of crores of cows, (performing) sacrifices like the horse-sacrifice, (giving) gifts of gold of the measure of Meru mountain and other gifts, offering oblations into fire and giving gifts to brāhmaṇas at Kurukṣetra, Puṣkara, Prabhāsa and Gayā. Therefore, Prayāga is the best of all holy places.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>005 The Story of Mādhava and Sulocanā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/005/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/005/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. There was a city named Tāladhvaja. It resembled the city of gods. It was well-known in all the worlds and was crowded with the hosts of meritorious (persons). There was a king named Vikrama, born of a pure family. He was religious, truthful and devoted to the protection of his subjects. His wife named Hārāvatī was excellent in the world, who had vanquished the moon’s lustre by means of her face. In a host of his wives she alone was dear to him, as Gaṅgā is to the Ocean in the host of rivers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>006 Happy End of the Story of Mādhava and Sulocanā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/006/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-king-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The king said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O you of large arms, stay here only, in my very auspicious kingdom. I shall undoubtedly look after your livelihood.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. Then, O brāhmaṇa, Vīravara, with his mind set upon serving him, constantly stayed there, in the vicinity of the king. Once in his city, a rhinoceros, named Bhīmanāda, continuously agitated all his subjects, O Jaimini. To kill him, the king angrily sent him. Then Vīravara, with people, went to kill that rhinoceros. That powerful (Vīravara) saw that rhinoceros, of the size of a mountain, with his mouth fearful due to the fangs, sleeping on the ground. Making his horse move in the atmosphere that Vīravara angrily spoke to the rhinoceros with a voice deep like that of a cloud:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>007 Kālakalpa is Liberated by the Touch of Gaṅgā-water</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/007/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/007/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;śrī-vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Śrī Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. I shall just again tell you the excellent importance of Gaṅgā; having heard it all men would obtain all their desired objects. On seeing the face of him who has not bathed in Gaṅga, the mother of the world, a man should instantly look at the Sun. The sins of him who, in the morning, would devoutly remember the couple of letters ‘Gaṅ-gā’, perish, as darkness perishes at dawn. All the food, water etc. of (i.e. offered by) him who has not seen the best among rivers, are unfit to be accepted.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>008 The Love Story of Indra and Padmagandhā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/008/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/008/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-6. O chief among brāhmaṇas, I shall again narrate the excellent greatness of Gaṅgā. If you desire liberation, drink the nectar in the form of an account of Gaṅgā. He who has-devotion for the mother of Bhīṣma, has given all gifts, has performed all sacrifices, and has worshipped Viṣṇu. O Jaimini, whatever religious rites are performed in Gaṅgā, all those become inexhaustible for him. Seeing flowing water he who gets up and goes to the water of Gaṅgā with devotion, is the performer of a thousand horse-sacrifices. He who does not show devotion (i.e. does not become devoted) when Gaṅgā-water has come (to him), will perpetually have beast-hood in every existence. The religious merit earned during crores of existences of him who, having come across the Gaṅgā-water, does not devoutly take it, perishes just in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>009 The Greatness of Gaṅgā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/009/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/009/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O preceptor, tell me again the excellent greatness of Gaṅgā. Due to its sweetness I again desire to drink the nectar of the account of Gaṅgā.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-9a. That too I shall tell you since you are a devotee of Gaṅgā. Those feet of men (alone) are fruitful (i.e. meritorious) that go to the bank of Gaṅgā. Those (alone) are (fruitful) ears that hear the sound of the waves of Gaṅgā. That (alone) is the (fruitful) tongue which knows the various (kinds of) sweetness of her water. Those (alone) are the (fruitful) eyes that see the charming ripples of Gaṅgā. That is said to be the (fruitful) forehead which bears a vertical mark of the clay of Gaṅgā. Those (alone) are the (fruitful) hands that are intent on worshipping Gaṅgā. That (alone) is the (fruitful) body, giving the fruit of the four goals of human life, which has fallen into the pure water of Gaṅgā. O best brāhmaṇa. All the manes of the dead ancestors, living in heaven, (seeing their son) going to the bank of Gaṅgā, and seeing her water are delighted, and praise it, O Jaimini, saying: “Formerly we have done religious merit for obtaining a good position; and it will be inexhaustible, since we have such a son. He has now gratified us with the water of Gaṅgā. We shall go to the highest abode which is difficult to be had even by gods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>010 The Efficacy of Campaka Flower</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/010/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/010/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O preceptor, through your grace I have heard this (description of the) greatness of Gaṅgā. Now, I desire to listen to the fruit of Viṣṇu’s worship.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. O dear, listen to the excellent fruit of the worship of the lord of Lakṣmī, hearing whicḥ all men obtain excellent knowledge. O brāhmaṇa, listen to the rules according to which the Eternal One should be worshipped in the twelve months like Māgha. I shall (now) tell them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>011 The Rules of Viṣṇu Worship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-8. O Jaimini, O brāhmaṇa sage, I (shall) tell you the mode in which Viṣṇu should always be worshipped. Listen to it attentively. A wise man, having got up from his bed in the morning and taking a pot (full) of water, and covering his head with (a piece of) cloth, should go to a place outside (the town). There, the wise man, keeping mum, putting the sacred thread on his ear, should sit in the northern direction and urinate and excrete. He should not urinate or excrete in a temple of a deity, on the way, in cowpens, places where four roads meet, on the main road, in a ploughed soil, at the root of darbhas, in a courtyard, on the sandy bank of a river, at the root of a fig tree standing on a sacred spot, so also in a forest, in lakes and wells. A wise man should urinate and excrete till he does not see the sun, the moon, brāhmaṇas and the ten quarters. To cleanse himself he should not take the clay from inside the holes dug by mice etc. or (from) ploughed soil. A wise man should purify himself with water after bringing it from (a place of) water. A wise man does not purify himself by keeping his foot in water.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>012 The Greatness of the Holy Fig Tree</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/012/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O best brāhmaṇa, a devotee of Viṣṇu should everyday in (the month of) Phalguna devoutly worship Śrī Kṛṣṇa saluted by gods. Listen properly to the fruit which I shall tell, of (i.e. obtained by) him who would bathe Devakī’s son with clarified butter in Phālguna.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6. He, having received the fruit of all sacrifices and of all gifts, and freed from all sins goes in the end to Viṣṇu’s place. Having enjoyed pleasures in Viṣṇu’s abode for thousands of crores of yugas, he, having obtained excellent knowledge, obtains liberation there only. He who offers, in winter, sweet-meat made of sesamum-seeds to Kṛṣṇa, of the form of a cowherd, would go to Viṣṇu’s abode. He who would offer sweet balls made with ghee to Viṣṇu, the highest soul, would drink nectar in heaven for a period of hundreds of Manu’s ages.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>013 Viṣṇu’s Worship with Lotuses: The Story of Prajā</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/013/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-4. O best brāhmaṇa, in the month of Jyeṣṭha (a man) should devoutly worship lord Viṣṇu after having bathed him (i.e. his image) with cold water. Everyday in summer unguents, fragrant āmalaka, fragrant oil should be offered to Viṣṇu. In a pavilion (having free access) to people he should everyday install (the image of) the lord of Lakṣmī in a temple which is made very fragrant, which is cool and very charming. One should not install (the image of) the lord of Lakṣmī in a hot place, in a place full of smoke or fuel, or in a lying-in chamber.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>014 Prohibition regarding and Fruit of Viṣṇu Worship</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-10. A devotee of Viṣṇu should devoutly worship the immutable Viṣṇu along with the great Lakṣmī in Mārgaśīrṣa, O best brāhmaṇa. So also he should not worship Viṣṇu in a Mleccha region, in the house of a fallen person, or at a place full of bad odour, O best brāhmaṇa. He should not worship Viṣṇu near the heretics or great sinners, so also near those who tell lies. He should not worship Viṣṇu near those who are crying, who are quarrelling or at the place of those who are ridiculing. He should not worship Viṣṇu at the place of those who are engaged in accepting gifts, so also in the house of misers and of those who are greedy of others’ wealth. So also he should not worship Viṣṇu in the house of those whose nature is deceitful. O brāhmaṇa, being highly devoted, he should, giving up attention to any other thing, be intent on meditating upon Viṣṇu at the time of worshipping Viṣṇu. He should not worship Viṣṇu, when there is loud wailing, when there are sighs, when there is a doubt, or a talk with the heretics, O best brāhmaṇa. Viṣṇu receives that flower which is offered even into ash by him whose mind is concentrated, to the god of gods, the lord of the world. O brāhmaṇa, the lord does not receive that flower which a man fatigued due to hundreds of thoughts, offers even on the discs of the (śālagrāma) stones. With an undivided mind a wise man should worship Viṣṇu.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>015 The Efficacy of Rāma’s Name</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-3. O brāhmaṇa, listen. I (shall) again tell you about the greatness of Viṣṇu, having heard which a man becomes free from all sins. O best brāhmaṇa, this entire world is a portion of Viṣṇu. Therefore, those wise men who desire the highest knowledge, look upon it as full of Viṣṇu. All gods like Brahmā, Śaṅkara, Rudra are Viṣṇu’s portions. Therefore, worship offered to all gods, goes to Viṣṇu alone.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>016 Cakrika’s Story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O greatest brāhmaṇa, I am again describing the greatness of Viṣṇu, the highest soul, which destroys all unhappiness. (Please) listen.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. Those brāhmaṇas, kṣatriyas, vaiśyas, śūdras and. others belonging to the lowest castes, who resort to Viṣṇu’s devotion, are fortunate. There is no doubt about this. A brāhmaṇa who is not a devotee of Viṣṇu, should be known to be inferior to a cāṇḍāla, while a cāṇḍāla who is devoted to Viṣṇu, should be known to be superior to a brāhmaṇa.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>017 Bhadratanu’s Story</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/017/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O preceptor, again tell me the greatness of Lakṣmī’s lord. Who is satisfied after drinking the nectar of Viṣṇu’s account?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. There is no one pious like you in the mundane existence, since you desire to listen to Viṣṇu’s greatness with devotion. O best brāhmaṇa, the charming tale of Viṣṇu does purify the three worlds—(it purifies) the listener, the questioner and the speaker.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;4-6. O dear, listen to the greatness of Lakṣmī’s lord, which destroys sins. I shall narrate it, giving the four goals of human life, in brief. Viṣṇu would instantly remove the sin, committed during crores of births, of him who would worshipViṣṇu very devoutly even one day. How can he be (called) pious who has not worshipped Viṣṇu? How can he be (called) a sinner who has devotion for lord Viṣṇu?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>018 The Greatness of Puruṣottama</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O preceptor, if you favour me, then tell me about the greatness of Puruṣottama which you said to be the greatest holy place.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-6. O brāhmaṇa, listen to the greatness of Puruṣottama (told by me) in brief. Who else but Viṣṇu is able to tell it in the world? O best brāhmaṇa, the city called Puruṣottama is (situated) on the shore of the Lavaṇa sea (the Salt-sea), and it is more difficult to be reached than even heaven. Since Śrī Puruṣottama (i.e. Viṣṇu) lives in that city, therefore those who are conversant with the name have called it Puruṣottama. O brāhmaṇa, that rare holy place is ten yojanas (in area) on all sides. The men living there are seen to have four arms by gods. Whileentering the holy place, all would have the form of Viṣṇu. Therefore, the wise should raise no doubt about it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>019 What Pleases Viṣṇu; What Makes Him Angry?</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O best brāhmaṇa, those men who, full of devotion, resort to Viṣṇu, never face a disaster. I will once more narrate the greatness of Lakṣmī’s lord, hearing which all men obtain the highest position.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. Devotees of Viṣṇu are satisfied with listening to the greatness of Kṛṣṇa. Heretics, suffering from trouble in a hell, are not satisfied. O best brāhmaṇa, the excellent greatness of Viṣṇu should not be narrated in the presence of heretics. It should be told in the presence of Viṣṇu’s devotees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>020 The Great Efficacy of Giving (Charity)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O brāhmaṇa, I have told you in brief the fruit of Viṣṇu’s worship. Now I shall tell (you about) the presents. Listen attentively.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-3. Of giving presents and penance, giving presents is said to be superior. Due to penance, it is said, there is sin. In the act of giving presents there is no sin. Penance is (said to be) the best in Kṛtayuga. And meditation is (said to be) the best in Tretā (yuga). Worship is (said to be) the best in Dvāpara (yuga). Giving presents is (said to be) the best in Kali (yuga).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>021 Brāhmaṇas; Gift of Food and Water</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. Having heard Brahmā’s words, that best brāhmaṇa, Hariśarman, again saluted him devoutly, and spoke, O Jaimini:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;hariśarman-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hariśarman said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. O lord, please tell me as to whom the many gifts that you narrated should be given.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;brahmā-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brahmā said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. Of all the castes brāhmaṇa is the most venerable person. Gifts should be given to him by men having devotion and faith. A brāhmaṇa is the resort of all deities. He is actually a god on the earth. He saves a giver in this ocean of the universe, which is difficult to cross.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>022 The Greatness of Ekādaśī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/022/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. O preceptor, by your grace I have heard the sin-destroying greatness along with its history, of the water flowing from a brāhmaṇa’s feet, the auspicious greatness of Gaṅgā, so also the fruit of the worship of Viṣṇu, the excellent (account of the) greatness of the gift of food and of water.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-5. O best sage, now I desire to hear carefully the entire fruit of (the vow of) Ekādaśī, which destroys all sins., Why is the Ekādaśī(-vow) the greatest? What is declared to be the mode of (its observance)? When is it observed? What is its fruit? Tell me. O you ocean of virtues, who is the most adorable deity there? Please tell me what fault (accrues) to him who does not observe it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>023 Queen Suprajñā on the Efficacy of Ekādaśī Vow</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Formerly on the earth there was a king named Kocaraśa. He was calm. He knew the excellent ways of life. He was the best among those who know statesmanship. He, the great one, spoke the truth. He had conquered his anger. He had vanquished the multitude of his enemies. He was very much devoted to Nārāyaṇa’s worship. He was engrossed in the service of Hari.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. His queen was Suprajñā by name, who spoke pleasing words, was endowed with all (good) characteristics, and was absorbed in serving her husband. She was engaged in (observing) the Ekādaśī vow, and desired the good of all living beings. She remembered her (past) births. She was noble and of an excellent complexion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>024 The Greatness of Tulasī and Dhātrī</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/024/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1-2. Jaimini, being very much pleased on hearing the fruit of the Ekādaśī (vow), spoke, with the palms of his hands joined, these (words) to lord Kṛṣṇa Dvaipāyana (i.e. Vyāsa): “Through your grace I have heard the greatness of god Viṣṇu. (Now) tell me about the greatness of tulasī which destroys the sins of the listeners.”&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-6. O brāhmaṇa, this revered tulasī should always be worshipped by all deities like Indra. It gives the fruit of the four goals of human life. To the good tulasī is difficult to be obtained in heaven, in the mortal world and in the nether world. Devotion to it secures the four goals of human life. O best one, at that place only where one tulasī-plant stands, all gods like Brahmā, Viṣṇu and Śiva dwell. Always Keśava dwells in the middle of the leaf, Prajāpati at the tip of the leaf, and Śiva at the foot-stalk of the leaf of tulasī.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>025 The Importance of Honouring a Guest</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O glorious one, tell me in detail again about tulasī’s greatness destroying sins, so also about the importance of honouring a guest.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;sūta-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sūta said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2. Then, O best brāhmaṇa, that very lustrous Vyāsa, started telling the greatness of tulasī, destroying the sins of the listeners.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;3-4. This tulasī, dear to the lord, is actually great Lakṣmī. Therefore, O Jaimini they do not recognise it as a tree. As a mortal always worships tulasī on the earth, so gods along with Indra worship it in heaven.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>026 Conduct in the Four Yugas</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/padma-purANam/deshpANDe/7/026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;jaimini-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jaimini said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;1. O glorious one, tell me how will all people be(i.e. behave) when the very fierce Kali age has come.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;vyāsa-said&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vyāsa said&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;2-5. The first (age) is called Satya-yuga. In it the people—brāhmaṇas and others—were devoted to worshipping Viṣṇu, and were free from grief and diseases. All of them spoke the truth, all were kind, and all lived long. They were rich in wealth and grains. They were free from (doing) harm (to others) and from religious hypocrisy. All obliged others. All knew sacred treatises. O best brāhmaṇa, in Satya-yuga all people were like this. And the kings followed royal duties and protected people. Oh! Who can relate the merit and the glory of Satya-yuga?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
