<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>गोश्रीपुरम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/</link>
    <description>Recent content in गोश्रीपुरम् on पुराणे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Architecture</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/architecture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-of-the-largest-bell-in-asia&#34;&gt;One of the Largest Bell In Asia&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Parsvamantapam is the next hall in front of the main temple inside the periphery. At the Southern end of Parswamantapam is erected Twelve Pillar Silver Mantapam for Kalyana Utsavam. The Chandeliers and Electric Globes and Domes add to the decor of the Parsvamantapam. The Exquisite Carvings on the inner ceilings depicting episodes from the Ramayana, Mahabharata, Bhagavatham etc, make Namaskara Mantapam and its flanks more attractive. In the centre of Vimana Shaped Sreekovil, the sanctum sanctorum, is seen the beautiful throne artistically finished on a single stone and coated with sandal paste.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Festivals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/festivals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/festivals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;aratt&#34;&gt;Aratt&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The two main temple festivals popularly known as ‘Aratt’ are the most important events of the year. Two eight day long festivals (Ratholsavam and Maholsavam) are celebrated in the temple annually. Maholsavam is in commemoration of the first Pratistha and it ends on the full moon day of the month Chaitra (March-April). Ratholsavam performed in the month of (November-December) is similar to Maholsavam in all respects except on the afternoon of the seventh day of festival, the Lord is taken round the temple in a special chariot known as Pushpaka Vimanam. The festival commences with the formal hoisting of the sacred Garuda ensign. The two processions that are held one each in morning and evening which involves taking the representative image of the Lord in procession, draws huge crowd. Palanquin pooja is conducted at noon and night when the fully decked up idol will be taken in procession. One of the Important item during the temple festival is Vishnu Yagam, which starts from first day night onwards and concludes with Poornahuthi on the 8th day of the temple festival. It is the only temple in Kerala where this Vishnu Yagam is held.On the 4th 5th and 8th days of the temple festival, the image is carried in a golden palanquin along the Southern, Northern and Western streets respectively. On the seventh day evening the image of the Lord will be taken around in a horse carriage with all the paraphernalia along the corridors of the temple for the palli vettai (the symbolic wild animal hunt) and meets the Siva of Udyansewara in the temple. On the 8th day, the deity is taken for bathing ( avabritha snanam) at the lake mandapam. Before this ceremony, there will be a procession of the community members who carry two country boats on their shoulders to the accompaniment of two caparisoned elephants, drum beats and nadaswaram, which start from the sasati area of Cherai to commemorate the fact that the forefathers had come to Cochin from the sasathi Pradesh of Goa to escape the forcible religious conversion of the Portuguese. The procession ends at the Papanasam Lake where the country boats are lowered. Soon after the Holy bath of the deity, there will be a sumptuous feast for all the devotees. After the bath, the idol of Venkateswara is seated on the throne at the Mantapam in the middle of the temple tank and after the performance of aarathi, the deity is taken on Golden palanquin in a procession oomprising of decorated elephants and panchavadya along the outer pathway of the Lake mandapam and enters the temple through the Eastern gopuram. The idol is then placed on a golden Garuda vahanam and pooja and aarthi is performed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ravilochana - history</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/ravilochana-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/ravilochana-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The murti and shaThAri are from achyuta raya temple of hampi. The temple claims that the murti was installed by saluva narasimha. It is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The murti is from achyuta raya temple only, which is indeed near cakratirtha as well.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The temple was not lost due to accidental fire but post talikota. Vijayindra tirtha found the murti after that in the well of achyuta raya temple.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Routine</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/routine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/routine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-day-at-gosripuram&#34;&gt;A Day at Gosripuram&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.30 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;The temple opens. The whole of Gosripuram wakes up to the recorded &lt;strong&gt;Venkatesha Suprabhatam&lt;/strong&gt; and other devotional songs rendered by the renowned artists.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5.45 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Singing of &lt;strong&gt;Gosripuresha Suprabhatam&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Saranagata Prarthana&lt;/strong&gt; by the devotees.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6.00 AM to 6.15 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nirmalya Darshanam&lt;/strong&gt; or Opening of the sanctum sanctorum and first glimpse of the Lord, to be followed by the chanting of &lt;strong&gt;Narayana Atharvasirsha&lt;/strong&gt; and distribution of Prasadam to the devotees.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8.00 AM to 8.30 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usha Pooja&lt;/strong&gt; or Morning Pooja also known as &lt;strong&gt;Payasa Pooja&lt;/strong&gt;. During this the Lord is escorted around the temple in a wooden palanquin. This is followed by the distribution of &lt;strong&gt;Tirtham&lt;/strong&gt; and Prasadam to the devotees. Milk Payasam is distributed to children.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.00 AM to 10.30 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;The daily &lt;strong&gt;Abishekam&lt;/strong&gt; to the Lord.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10.30 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Pooja to the Lord by chanting &lt;strong&gt;1000&lt;/strong&gt; names of &lt;strong&gt;Vishnu Sahasranamam&lt;/strong&gt; also known as &lt;strong&gt;Sahasranamarchana&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11.00 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;Afternoon Pooja. Offering of &lt;strong&gt;Mahanaivedyam&lt;/strong&gt; for lunch followed by the &lt;strong&gt;Maha Arati&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11.30 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadagopam&lt;/strong&gt;: The chief priest visits all the sub shrines inside with the &lt;strong&gt;Paduka&lt;/strong&gt; (sandals) of the Lord and performs Pooja there and also touches these paduka onto the head of those idols as a gesture of god’s blessing to them.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11.45 AM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gopujanam&lt;/strong&gt;: The ritual of offering pooja to the cow and offering the Lord’s prasadam to her, followed by the Arati.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12.00 PM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noon Palanquin pooja&lt;/strong&gt;: The Lord is taken in pradakshina in a silver Palanquin.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12.30 PM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brahmana Santarpanam&lt;/strong&gt;: The ritual of taking lunch by the priests together after offering to the Lord.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1.00 PM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: left&#34;&gt;The temple closes for the afternoon.&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This is the schedule of events of a normal day. The timings will vary on days of fortnightly, monthly, yearly or specially conducted functions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Website history</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/website-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/purANam_vaiShNavam/history/go-shrI-puram/website-history/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gosripuram.org/the-deity/&#34;&gt;TW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-deity&#34;&gt;The Deity&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Sri Venkateswara, the main presiding deity of the Cochin Thirumala Devaswom temple is known by the popular name Gosripurusha Thirumala Devar. Held in the highest veneration by all classes of Hindus, this temple is a religious institution of the Gowda Saraswath Brahmin community of Cochin and is the mother of all institutions of the Gowda saraswath community members of Goan origin living in different parts of the State of Kerala. According to the legend, the idol of Lord Venkateswara installed in this temple belonged originally to the Vijayanagar Ruler Saluva Narasmiha Raya of 1472 AD. An ardent devotee of Lord Venkateswara, of Thirumala Hills, he was a frequent visitor to the hill top shrine. But when he became physically weak and incapable of visiting the Lord, he got a revelation that the Lord himself will come over to his capital city to enable him to pray to the Lord daily. The king was also told that a sculptor will call on him for casting the idol, which in turn would be a replica of the image of the Lord at the Thirumali hills. As per the dream, a sculptor appeared before the king the next day. After sourcing all the requisite materials , the sculptor shut himself up in a room. However, when the sculptor failed to come out even after a fairly long period of time, the king decided to get the room broken open. To his disbelief he saw a replica image of the Lord of the Seven hills in the room and the king understood that the sculptor was none other than the Lord Himself. Hence the image came to be known as swayamboo or an idol that emerged on its own and not made by man.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
